<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE bms SYSTEM "bms.dtd">

<bms>
	<volume vnum="023">
		<issue inum="01" month="02" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Sol–gel processing of carbidic glasses</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0001-0004</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Carbon incorporation into the silicate network results in the formation of rigid carbidic glasses with improved physical, mechanical and thermal properties. This generated great interest in the development of these heteroatom structured materials through different processing routes. In the present studies, sol–gel processing has been used to prepare silicon based glasses, especially oxycarbides through organic–inorganic hybrid gels by hydrolysis–condensation reactions in silicon alkoxides, 1,4-butanediol and furfuryl alcohol with an aim to introduce Si–C linkages in the precursors at sol level. The incorporation of these linkages has been studied using IR and NMR spectroscopy. These bonds, so introduced, are maintained throughout the processing, especially during pyrolysis to high temperatures. In FFA–TEOS system, copolymerization with optimized mol ratio of the two results in resinous mass. This precursor on pyrolysis to $1000^\circ $C results in Si–O–C type amorphous solid black mass. XRD studies on the materials heated to $1400^\circ $C exhibit presence of crystalline Si–C and cristobalites in amorphous Si–O–C mass. In organic–inorganic gel system, the pyrolysed mass exhibits phase stability up to much higher temperatures. The carbidic materials so produced have been found to exhibit good resistance against oxidation at $1000^\circ $C.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sol–gel; silicon oxycarbide; organically modified inorganic gels; hydrolysis; pyrolysis; silicon carbide; cristoballites.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Manocha" fname="L. M." isfellow="0">Manocha, L. M.</author>
					<author lname="Yasuda" fname="E." isfellow="0">Yasuda, E.</author>
					<author lname="Tanabe" fname="Y." isfellow="0">Tanabe, Y.</author>
					<author lname="Manocha" fname="S." isfellow="0">Manocha, S.</author>
					<author lname="Vashistha" fname="D." isfellow="0">Vashistha, D.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Collective modes in Ca$_{70}$Mg$_{30}$ glass</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0005-0009</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The self-consistent phonon scheme given by Takeno and Goda, involving multiple scattering and phonon eigen frequencies which are expressed in terms of many-body correlation functions of atoms as well as of interatomic potential in the solids, has been used to generate the collective modes in the Ca$_{70}$Mg$_{30}$ glass. A model potential is proposed to describe the effective interaction in the glass. Three different forms of the local field correction functions viz. Hartree, Taylor and Ichimaru and Utsumi are used to examine relative influence of exchange and correlation effects. The phonon frequencies of the longitudinal and transverse modes are computed employing the theoretical formulation of Hubbard and Beeby. The elastic property of the glassy system is then studied using the long wavelength limits of the phonon modes. The theoretical computations reproduce much better dispersion curves (both for the longitudinal and transverse phonons) compared to earlier reports and are found to be in good agreement with the available experimental results due to neutron scattering.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Metallic glass; pair correlation function; phonon frequencies; sound velocities; elastic properties.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Thakore" fname="B. Y." isfellow="0">Thakore, B. Y.</author>
					<author lname="Gajjar" fname="P. N." isfellow="0">Gajjar, P. N.</author>
					<author lname="Jani" fname="A. R." isfellow="0">Jani, A. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and magnetic properties of one-dimensional metal oxalate networks as molecular-based magnets</title>
				<feature>Molecular Magnets</feature>
				<page>0011-0016</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The homo- and heteropolymetallic assemblies of MM $(OX)_2(H_2O)_4$ , where MM represents MnMn, CoMn, NiMn, CuMn, CoCo, NiCo, CuCo, NiNi, CuNi, and CuCu; and the respective complexes, numbered 1–10, have been prepared by reacting metal(II) salts—i.e. of Mn, Co, Ni, and Cu—and potassium oxalate monohydrate in hot water (90–100$^\circ $C). The magnetic susceptibility data of the complexes 8 and 9 in the 300 K–20 K temperature range obeys the Curie–Weiss law and exhibits Weiss constants – 50 K and – 100 K, respectively. On lowering the temperature, the effective magnetic moment decreases gradually and is indicative of antiferromagnetic phase transition. The complexes have also been characterized by ES mass spectrometry, infrared (IR), electronic, and electron spin resonance (ESR) spectra.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Molecular-based magnets; magnetic properties; one-dimensional metal oxalate; synthesis and structure of metal-oxalates.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="B. P." isfellow="0">Singh, B. P.</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="B." isfellow="0">Singh, B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Dielectric properties of solution-grown-undoped and acrylic-acid-doped ethyl cellulose</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0017-0021</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Dielectric capacities and losses were measured, in the temperature (50–170$^\circ $C) and frequency (01–100 kHz range), for undoped and acrylic acid (AA) doped ethyl cellulose (EC) films (thickness about 20 $\mu$m) with progressive increase in the concentration of dopant in the polymer matrix. The variation of capacity with temperature is attributed to thermal expansion in the lower temperature region to the orientation of dipolar molecules in the neighbourhood of glass transition temperature ($T_g$) and random thermal motion of molecules above $T_g$. The dielectric losses exhibit a broad peak. Doping with AA is found to affect the magnitude and position of the peak. AA is found to have a two-fold action. Firstly, it enhances the chain mobility and secondly, it increases the dielectric loss by forming charge transfer complexes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Dielectric capacity; losses; ethyl cellulose; acrylic acid; charge transfer complexes.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Khare" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Khare, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Jain" fname="Sandeep K." isfellow="0">Jain, Sandeep K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>An instrument for online measurement of structural orientation in translucent polymer sheets</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0023-0026</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>In many applications of polymer materials, a high tensile strength is required. There is a definite correlation between the degree of orientation of molecular chains achieved in the orientation process and the tensile strength obtained. In this work, we describe design and fabrication details of a device, ‘Laser based polymer orientation grader’, for online measurement of the degree of orientation to obtain a high consistent tensile strength as output. This instrument has been designed making skilful use of the optical anisotropic property of the oriented polymer strip. The principle is based on the fact that the spatial distribution of laser light passing through the translucent polymer sheet depends on the degree of orientation of long chain molecules in the sheet. The method has potential online application in monitoring and controlling of anisotropy in manufacturing processes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Online measurement; tensile strength; molecular orientation of long chains; anisotropy; scattering; diffraction.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Palanisamy" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Palanisamy, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Mangaiyarkarasi" fname="D." isfellow="0">Mangaiyarkarasi, D.</author>
					<author lname="Ramalingam" fname="A." isfellow="0">Ramalingam, A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Characterization of plasticized PMMA–LiBF$_4$ based solid polymer electrolytes</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0027-0029</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Polymer electrolyte films prepared from poly(methyl methacrylate) and LiBF$_4$  with different concentrations of plasticizer (DBP) are described. The formation of polymer–salt complex has been confirmed by FTIR spectral studies. The temperature dependence of conductivity of polymer films seems to obey the VTF relation. Values of conductivities of the polymer complexes are presented and discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Polymer electrolyte; PMMA–LiBF$_4$–DBP; FTIR; impedance studies.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rajendran" fname="S." isfellow="0">Rajendran, S.</author>
					<author lname="Uma" fname="T." isfellow="0">Uma, T.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of ZrO$_2$ on conductivity of PVC–PMMA–LiBF$_4$–DBP polymer electrolytes</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0031-0034</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rajendran" fname="S." isfellow="0">Rajendran, S.</author>
					<author lname="Uma" fname="T." isfellow="0">Uma, T.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Impact toughness of ternary Al–Zn–Mg alloys in as cast and homogenized condition measured in the temperature range 263–673 K</title>
				<feature>Metallic Materials</feature>
				<page>0035-0038</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kundar" fname="Harish" isfellow="0">Kundar, Harish</author>
					<author lname="Krishna" fname="" isfellow="0">Krishna</author>
					<author lname="Srinivasan" fname="K." isfellow="0">Srinivasan, K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Role of diffusional coherency strain theory in the discontinuous precipitation in Mg–Al alloy</title>
				<feature>Metallic Materials</feature>
				<page>0039-0045</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Discontinuous precipitation (DP) occurs in many alloy systems under certain conditions. It is called discontinuous precipitation because precipitation occurs on prior matrix grain boundaries followed by grain boundary movement. The DP nodule consists of alternate lamellae of the precipitate and the matrix respectively. The chemical driving force for DP is one of solute supersaturation. Although solute supersaturation is responsible for precipitation, it has to be coupled with another driving force to explain grain boundary migration. This coupling driving force has been identified to be diffusional coherency strain which has been verified to be active in diffusion induced grain boundary migration and liquid film migration. To test diffusional coherency strain theory for discontinuous precipitation Mg–7Al and Mg–7Al–1Pb alloys were studied. While the fraction transformed was high at 6% in Mg–7Al alloy, it was significantly low at 2% in Mg–7Al–1Pb alloy. The velocity of DP nodules decreased by half in alloy with Pb as compared to the alloy without Pb. Theoretical calculations also predict that the misfit parameter $d_{th}$ decreases with the addition of Pb. These observations are an evidence to the fact that diffusional coherency strain is the most active driving force for the movement of the grain boundaries of the DP nodules during discontinuous precipitation in Mg–Al alloy.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>DP; Mg–Al alloy; Mg–7Al–1Pb alloy; DIGM; LFM.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kashyap" fname="K. T." isfellow="0">Kashyap, K. T.</author>
					<author lname="Ramachandra" fname="C." isfellow="0">Ramachandra, C.</author>
					<author lname="Sujatha" fname="M." isfellow="0">Sujatha, M.</author>
					<author lname="Chatterji" fname="B." isfellow="0">Chatterji, B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Role of work hardening characteristics of matrix alloys in the strengthening of metal matrix composites</title>
				<feature>Composites</feature>
				<page>0047-0049</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The strengthening of particulate reinforced metal–matrix composites is associated with a high dislocation density in the matrix due to the difference in coefficient of thermal expansion between the reinforcement and the matrix. While this is valid, the role of work hardening characteristics of the matrix alloys in strengthening of these composites is addressed in the present paper. It is found that commercial purity aluminium which has the lowest work hardening rate exhibits the highest strength increment. This effect is due to increased prismatic punching of dislocations. This relationship of decreasing work hardening rate associated with increasing prismatic punching of dislocations in the order 7075, 2014, 7010, 2024, 6061 and commercial purity aluminium leading to increased strength increments is noted.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Metal matrix composites; strengthening; work hardening rate; dislocation density.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kashyap" fname="K. T." isfellow="0">Kashyap, K. T.</author>
					<author lname="Ramachandra" fname="C." isfellow="0">Ramachandra, C.</author>
					<author lname="Dutta" fname="C." isfellow="0">Dutta, C.</author>
					<author lname="Chatterji" fname="B." isfellow="0">Chatterji, B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Electrochemical processing of high-$T_c$ Bi(Pb)–Sr–Ca–CuO thin films</title>
				<feature>High $T_c$ superconductors</feature>
				<page>0051-0054</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Superconducting thin films of Bi(Pb)–Sr–Ca–CuO system were prepared by depositing the film onto silver substrate by d.c. electrodeposition technique with dimethyl sulphoxide bath in order to examine the effect of Pb addition to the BSCCO system. The films were deposited at the potential of – 0 8 V vs saturated calomel electrode (SCE) onto the silver substrate. The different preparative parameters such as deposition potential, deposition time were studied and optimized. These films were then oxidized electrochemically at room temperature in an alkaline (1 N KOH) solution, and also at 600$^\circ $C temperature in an oxygen atmosphere. The films showed the superconducting behaviour, with $T_c$  values ranging between 85 K and 96 K, respectively.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Superconductor; electrochemical deposition; thin films.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Desai" fname="N. V." isfellow="0">Desai, N. V.</author>
					<author lname="Ekal" fname="L. A." isfellow="0">Ekal, L. A.</author>
					<author lname="Shivagan" fname="D. D." isfellow="0">Shivagan, D. D.</author>
					<author lname="Pawar" fname="S. H." isfellow="0">Pawar, S. H.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Fe-ion implantation in pulse laser deposited La$_{0·75}$Ca$_{0·25}$MnO$_3$ films: Conversion electron Mössbauer spectroscopy and X-ray diffraction studies</title>
				<feature>Magnetic Materials</feature>
				<page>0055-0060</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lanke" fname="U. D." isfellow="0">Lanke, U. D.</author>
					<author lname="Pal" fname="J. Prabhjyot" isfellow="0">Pal, J. Prabhjyot</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Dehydration transformation in Ca-montmorillonite</title>
				<feature>Clay Materials</feature>
				<page>0061-0067</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The present work deals with the dehydration transformation of Ca-montmorillonite in the temperature range 30$^\circ $–500$^\circ $C. Thermal, infrared (IR), and X-ray diffraction (XRD) analyses were used to describe the thermal transformation. The microstructural and layer disorder parameters like crystallite size, r.m.s. strain ($e^{2\ 1/2}$), variation of interlayer spacing (g), and proportion of planes which were affected by the defect (g), have all been calculated from the (001) basal reflection using the method of variance and Fourier line shape analysis. These investigations revealed that sample underwent transformation from hydrated phase to dehydrated phase at 200$^\circ $C, and as a consequence, its basal spacing collapsed from 16 02 Å (30$^\circ $C) to around 10 Å (200$^\circ $C). This transformation occurred through a wide range of temperature, i.e. within the range 120$^\circ $–200$^\circ $C. The crystallite size was maximum at room temperature (30$^\circ $C), however, the size decreased with increasing temperature in the hydrated phase, whereas the size increased with increasing temperature for the dehydrated phase. The g, $g$ and e$^{2\ 1/2}$ of the hydrated and the dehydrated phase increased and decreased, respectively with increase of heating temperature.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Montmorillonite; layer disorder; microstructure parameters.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bala" fname="P." isfellow="0">Bala, P.</author>
					<author lname="Samantaray" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Samantaray, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Srivastava" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Srivastava, S. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of aluminium phosphate as admixture on oxychloride cement</title>
				<feature>Cements</feature>
				<page>0069-0072</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The effect of admixing of aluminium phosphate on oxychloride cement in the matrix has been investigated. It is shown that aluminium phosphate retards the setting process of the cement and improves water-tightness.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Aluminium phosphate; oxychloride cement.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chandrawat" fname="M. P. S." isfellow="0">Chandrawat, M. P. S.</author>
					<author lname="Yadav" fname="R. N." isfellow="0">Yadav, R. N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
        </issue>
        <issue inum="02" month="04" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Microstructural features induced by spray forming of a ternary Pb–Sn–Sb alloy</title>
				<feature>Materials Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0073-0078</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>An alloy containing Pb–12% Sn–12% Sb with small addition of copper and arsenic was spray deposited employing two different atomization gas pressure and nozzle to substrate distances. The temperature of the spray-deposit was measured during deposition at a distance of 2 and 10 mm above the substrate-deposit interface. Thermal profile data indicated small variation in temperature with time during deposition stage whereas during post deposition stage an exponential decrease in temperature was recorded. Second phase particle size along the thickness of the deposit varied from 4 to 8 $\mu$m compared to 70 to 80 $\mu$m size of these particles in the as cast alloy. Maximum porosity occurred in the section of the deposit near the contact surface of the substrate and also in its peripheral regions. X-ray diffraction analysis exhibited the formation of additional Cu$_2$Sb phase in the spray-deposit and CuSn and Cu$_{3.3}$Sb phases in atomized powders compared to that of the as cast alloy. The microstructural evolution during spray deposition of this alloy is discussed.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Spray forming; thermal profile; microstructure; second phase; porosity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Srivastava" fname="V. C." isfellow="0">Srivastava, V. C.</author>
					<author lname="Upadhyaya" fname="Anish" isfellow="0">Upadhyaya, Anish</author>
					<author lname="Ojha" fname="S. N." isfellow="0">Ojha, S. N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Investigations on nucleation thermodynamical parameters of NdBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7–\delta}$ (Nd123) crystallization by high temperature solution growth</title>
				<feature>Materials Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0079-0082</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Investigations on nucleation thermodynamical parameters are very essential for the successful growth of good quality single crystals from high temperature solution. A theoretical estimation of the nucleation thermodynamical parameters like interfacial energy between the solid Nd123 and its flux BaO–CuO, metastable zone-width, Gibbs free energy, critical energy barrier for nucleation and critical nucleation radius have been calculated from the knowledge of solubility data and by applying the classical nucleation theory. Results are discussed to understand the growth kinetics of Nd123 crystals.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>High temperature solution; nucleation parameters; interfacial energy; metastable zone width.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Paul" fname="D. P." isfellow="0">Paul, D. P.</author>
					<author lname="Jayavel" fname="R." isfellow="0">Jayavel, R.</author>
					<author lname="Subramanian" fname="C." isfellow="0">Subramanian, C.</author>
					<author lname="Ramasamy" fname="P." isfellow="0">Ramasamy, P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Cadmium substituted high permeability lithium ferrite</title>
				<feature>Magnetic Materials</feature>
				<page>0083-0085</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Polycrystalline Li$_{0.5 – x/2}$Cd$_x$Fe$_{2.5 – x/2}$O$_4$ ferrites where $x =$ 0, 0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, 0.5 and 0.6 were prepared by a double sintering ceramic technique and characterized by X-ray diffraction and scanning electron microscopy (SEM). The lattice parameter is found to increase monotonically with the cadmium content. It is explained in terms of the sizes of component ions. The grain size of the samples increases up to $x =$ 0.3 and then it decreases for higher values of $x$. A similar trend is observed in the variation of Ms with Cd$^2+$ content. The initial permeability ($\mu_i$) is however found to increase continuously with $x$. The increase in $\mu_i$ is attributed to decrease of anisotropy constant K$_1$ and higher grain size of the samples.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Lithium ferrites; initial permeability; grain size; microstructure; magnetic properties.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bellad" fname="S. S." isfellow="0">Bellad, S. S.</author>
					<author lname="Watawe" fname="S. C." isfellow="0">Watawe, S. C.</author>
					<author lname="Shaikh" fname="A. M." isfellow="0">Shaikh, A. M.</author>
					<author lname="Chougule" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Chougule, B. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Influence of Nd$^{3+}$ substitution on thermoelectric power of Zn–Mg ferrite system</title>
				<feature>Magnetic Materials</feature>
				<page>0087-0090</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Polycrystalline ferrites, Zn$_x$Mg$_{1 – x}$Fe$_{2 – y}$Nd$_y$O$_4$ ($x =$ 0.00, 0.20, 0.40, 0.60, 0.80 and 1.00; $y =$ 0.00, 0.05 and 0.10) were prepared by standard ceramic method. X-ray diffraction study of these compositions revealed the formation of single phase spinels. Seebeck coefficient was obtained from thermo emf measurement by keeping constant temperature difference of 10 K across the pellet. The values of Seebeck coefficient were found to be negative showing majority charge carriers of $n$-type, suggesting the mechanism of conduction to be predominantly by electron hopping. The substitution of Nd$^{3+}$ ion, which perhaps resides at the B-site, resulting in a decrease in the Seebeck coefficient. This decrease was assigned to the decrease of population of Fe$^{3+}$ ion at the B-site. The activation energies calculated both from mobility plots and from dc resistivity plots were found comparable. The Fermi energy, $E_F$(0), which was estimated by intrapolation of $E_F–T$ curves to $T$ $=$ 0 K, was found less than the activation energy. This difference was attributed to electron hopping energy.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Polycrystalline ferrite; rare-earth; Seebeck coefficient; electron hopping; Fermi energy.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ladgaonkar" fname="B. P." isfellow="0">Ladgaonkar, B. P.</author>
					<author lname="Vasambekar" fname="P. N." isfellow="0">Vasambekar, P. N.</author>
					<author lname="Vaingankar" fname="A. S." isfellow="0">Vaingankar, A. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Magnetocaloric effect in temperature-sensitive magnetic fluids</title>
				<feature>Magnetic Materials</feature>
				<page>0091-0095</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The magnetocaloric properties of three different temperature-sensitive magnetic fluids were studied. The pyromagnetic coefficient for all the materials were obtained and it was found that this property depends on physical and magnetic properties like size, magnetization and Curie temperature. A theoretical model was developed to explain the behaviour of change in entropy with temperature.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Magnetic fluid; pyromagnetic coefficient; Curie temperature.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Parekh" fname="Kinnari" isfellow="0">Parekh, Kinnari</author>
					<author lname="Upadhyay" fname="R. V." isfellow="0">Upadhyay, R. V.</author>
					<author lname="Mehta" fname="R. V." isfellow="0">Mehta, R. V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Comparison of the irreversible thermomagnetic behaviour of some ferro- and ferrimagnetic systems</title>
				<feature>Magnetic Materials</feature>
				<page>0097-0101</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The magnetic behaviour of two ferromagnetic oxides and two ferrimagnetic oxides (ferrites) are compared to study the effect of magnetocrystalline anisotropy on thermal-history-dependence of magnetization of these ordered magnetic systems. All four compounds show thermomagnetic irreversibility ($M_{FC}$ &gt; $M_{ZFC}$) below a certain temperature, $T_{irr}$. The highly anisotropic ferromagnetic oxide, SrRuO$_3$ and the hard ferrite, SrFe$_{12}$O$_{19}$ show sharp peaks below $T_c$ in their $M_{ZFC}(T)$ curves, whereas for the soft ferrite Ni$_{0.8}$Zn$_{0.2}$Fe$_2$O$_4$ and the low anisotropic ferromagnetic oxide La$_{0.7}$Ca$_{0.3}$MnO$_3$ only a broad maximum is observed in $M_{ZFC}$, when measured in small magnetic fields. The shapes of the $M_{ZFC}(T)$ curves are inversely-related to the magnitude of the coercivities $(H_c)$ of the compounds in relation to the applied field, and the temperature dependence of $H_c$. $M_{FC}$ and $M_{ZFC}$ are related through the coercivity for all four magnetic systems.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Ferromagnet; ferrimagnet; thermomagnetic irreversibility; magnetocrystalline anisotropy; coercivity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="P. S. Anil" isfellow="0">Kumar, P. S. Anil</author>
					<author lname="Joy" fname="P. A." isfellow="0">Joy, P. A.</author>
					<author lname="Date" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Date, S. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Development, structure and strength properties of PP/PMMA/FA blends</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0103-0107</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A new type of flyash filled PP/PMMA blend has been developed. Structural and thermal properties of flyash (FA) filled polypropylene (PP)/polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) blend system have been determined and analysed. Filled polymer blends were developed on a single screw extruder. Strength and thermal properties of FA filled and unfilled PP/PMMA blends were determined. Addition of flyash imparted dimensional and thermal stability, which has been observed in scanning electron micrographs and in TGA plot. Increase of flyash concentration increased the initial degradation temperature of PP/PMMA blend. The increase of thermal stability has been explained based on increased mechanical interlocking of PP/PMMA chains inside the hollow structure of flyash.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Flyash polymer composite; morphology; particulate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chand" fname="Navin" isfellow="0">Chand, Navin</author>
					<author lname="Vashishtha" fname="S. R." isfellow="0">Vashishtha, S. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Optimization of processing parameters for making alumina–partially stabilized zirconia laminated composites</title>
				<feature>Composites</feature>
				<page>0109-0117</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The aim of the work was to optimize the processing parameters for fabricating laminated ceramic composites of Al$_2$O$_3$–Y–PSZ. Composites of different layer thicknesses, starting from 2 mm and going down up to 0.3 mm, were made by hot-pressing. The different types of cracks originating in the composite were studied in detail and the reason behind their formation analysed. The observed main reasons for crack formation were: (i) differential shrinkage in between the co-sintering layers due to their different sintering kinetics, (ii) thermal expansion mismatch, and (iii) a tensile component of the residual stress in the layer under residual compressive stress. After this defect analysis, suitable remedial measures were taken to avoid the crack formation. And finally a laminated composite with fifteen layers of 0.3 mm thickness was made successfully.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Al$_2$O$_3$–Y–PSZ laminated composites; hot pressing; residual stress; transverse cracks; longitudinal cracks.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Deb" fname="S." isfellow="0">Deb, S.</author>
					<author lname="Bhat" fname="B. V. Radhakrishna" isfellow="0">Bhat, B. V. Radhakrishna</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>An algorithm for generating quasiperiodic patterns and their approximants</title>
				<feature>Quasicrystals</feature>
				<page>0119-0123</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>An algorithm for projecting the interior of a hypercube in $N$-dimensions on to an $m$-dimensional subspace has been developed and incorporated into a computer program for generating quasiperiodic and periodic patterns in an $n$-dimensional subspace. Some aspects of the resulting orthorhombic approximants to Penrose tiling patterns are discussed and illustrated.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Projection method; quasiperiodic; tiling patterns; approximants.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lord" fname="E. A." isfellow="0">Lord, E. A.</author>
					<author lname="Ramakrishnan" fname="K." isfellow="0">Ramakrishnan, K.</author>
					<author lname="Ranganathan" fname="S." isfellow="0">Ranganathan, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Application of design of experiment on electrophoretic deposition of glass-ceramic coating materials from an aqueous bath</title>
				<feature>Glass Ceramics</feature>
				<page>0125-0129</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A process for application of abrasion- or corrosion-resistant glass-ceramic coating materials on metal substrate by electrophoretic deposition technique in an aqueous medium has been described. The effects of various process parameters, e.g. coating material concentration, time of deposition, applied current, pH of the suspension and concentration of the polymeric dispersant on the deposition efficiency have been studied. The process has been studied using a 2$^3$-factorial design technique of three independent variables; i.e. coating material concentration, applied current, and the time taken to achieve the best combination. The regression equation obtained explains the experimental results satisfactorily.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Coating; electrophoretic deposition; glass-ceramic; design of experiment.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Datta" fname="Someswar" isfellow="0">Datta, Someswar</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A combined optical, SEM and STM study of growth spirals on the polytypic cadmium iodide crystals</title>
				<feature>Polytypic Materials</feature>
				<page>0131-0133</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Some novel results of a combined sequential study of growth spirals on the basal surface of the richly polytypic CdI$_2$ crystals by optical microscopy, scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) are presented and discussed. In confirmation of the known structural data, the STM pictures clearly reveal the value of unit cell $a(=\ b)$ dimension to be equal to 0.428 nm a and the value of the interaxial angle $\gamma $ to be equal to 120$^\circ $. Under the high resolution and magnification achieved in the scanning electron microscope, the growth steps of large heights seen in the optical micrographs are found to have a large number of additional steps of smaller heights existing between any two adjacent large height growth steps. When further seen by a scanning tunneling microscope, which provides still higher resolution, several unit substeps are seen to exist between two consecutive additional steps. The height of each substep is found to be equal to the unit cell height of the underlying polytype. The height of the larger additional steps are found to be integral multiple of the unit cell height. The horizontal distance between two consecutive growth steps is found to be an integral multiple of the lattice parameter $a$. The interspacing of the growth steps of same step height is found to vary at different positions on the same crystal face.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>CdI$_2$; polytypism; scanning tunneling microscopy (STM), spiral step height; dislocation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="Rajendra" isfellow="0">Singh, Rajendra</author>
					<author lname="Samanta" fname="S. B." isfellow="0">Samanta, S. B.</author>
					<author lname="Narlikar" fname="A. V." isfellow="0">Narlikar, A. V.</author>
					<author lname="Trigunayat" fname="G. C." isfellow="0">Trigunayat, G. C.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>On the development of an apatitic calcium phosphate bone cement</title>
				<feature>Biomaterials</feature>
				<page>0135-0140</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Development of an apatitic calcium phosphate bone cement is reported. 100 $\mu$ Particles of tetracalcium phosphate (TTCP) and dicalcium phosphate dihydrate (DCPD) were mixed in equimolar ratio to form the cement powder. The wetting medium used was distilled water with Na$_2$HPO$_4$ as accelerator to manipulate the setting time. The cement powder, on wetting with the medium, formed a workable putty. The setting times of the putty were measured using a Vicat type apparatus and the compressive strength was determined with a Universal Testing Machine. The nature of the precipitated cement was analyzed through X-ray diffraction (XRD), fourier transform infrared spectrometry (FTIR) and energy dispersive electron microprobe (EDAX). The results showed the phase to be apatitic with a calcium–to–phosphorous ratio close to that of hydroxyapatite. The microstructure analysis using scanning electron microscopy (SEM) showed hydroxyapatite nanocrystallite growth over particulate matrix surface. The structure has an apparent porosity of $\sim$ 52%. There were no appreciable dimensional or thermal changes during setting. The cement passed the $in\ vitro$ toxicological screening (cytotoxicity and haemolysis) tests. Optimization of the cement was done by manipulating the accelerator concentration so that the setting time, hardening time and the compressive strength had clinically relevant values.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Calcium phosphate cements; tetracalcium phosphate; hydroxyapatite; bioceramics; bone substitute.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Komath" fname="Manoj" isfellow="0">Komath, Manoj</author>
					<author lname="Varma" fname="H. K." isfellow="0">Varma, H. K.</author>
					<author lname="Sivakumar" fname="R." isfellow="0">Sivakumar, R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Thermal behaviour of hydroxides, hydroxysalts and hydrotalcites</title>
				<feature>Thermal Properties</feature>
				<page>0141-0145</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Mass spectrometric analysis of gases evolved during thermal decomposition of divalent metal hydroxides, hydroxysalts and hydrotalcites show that all these compounds undergo dehydration in the temperature range 30 &lt; T &lt; 220$^\circ $C followed by decomposition at temperatures above 250$^\circ $C. The latter step involves simultaneous deanation and dehydroxylation of the layers. Our observations conclusively prove that alternative mechanisms which envisage CO$_2$ evolution due to deanation at lower temperatures proposed by Kanezaki to be wrong.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Hydroxides; hydrotalcites; temperature programmed decomposition (TPD).</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bera" fname="Parthasarathi" isfellow="0">Bera, Parthasarathi</author>
					<author lname="Rajamathi" fname="Michael" isfellow="0">Rajamathi, Michael</author>
					<author lname="Hegde" fname="M. S." isfellow="0">Hegde, M. S.</author>
					<author lname="Kamath" fname="P. Vishnu" isfellow="0">Kamath, P. Vishnu</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Systematic hardness studies on lithium niobate crystals</title>
				<feature>Mechanical Properties</feature>
				<page>0147-0150</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>In view of discrepancies in the available information on the hardness of lithium niobate, a systematic study of the hardness has been carried out. Measurements have been made on two pure lithium niobate crystals with different growth origins, and a Fe-doped sample. The problem of load variation of hardness is examined in detail. The true hardness of LiNbO$_3$ is found to be 630 $\pm$ 30 kg/mm$^2$. The Fe-doped crystal has a larger hardness of 750 $\pm$ 50 kg/mm$^2$.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Microhardness; lithium niobate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Subhadra" fname="K. G." isfellow="0">Subhadra, K. G.</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="K. Kishan" isfellow="0">Rao, K. Kishan</author>
					<author lname="Sirdeshmukh" fname="D. B." isfellow="0">Sirdeshmukh, D. B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A CCD area detector for X-ray diffraction under high pressure for rotating anode source</title>
				<feature>Instrumentation</feature>
				<page>0151-0154</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Details of a two-dimensional X-ray area detector developed using a charge coupled device, a image intensifier and a fibre optic taper are given. The detector system is especially optimized for angle dispersive X-ray diffraction set up using rotating anode generator as X-ray source. The performance of this detector was tested by successfully carrying out powder X-ray diffraction measurements on various materials such as intermetallics AuIn$_2$, AuGa$_2$, high $Z$ material Pd and low $Z$ scatterer adamantane (C$_{10}$H$_{16}$) at ambient conditions. Its utility for quick detection of phase transitions at high pressures with diamond anvil cell is demonstrated by reproducing the known pressure induced structural transitions in RbI, KI and a new structural phase transition in AuGa$_2$ above 10 GPa. Various softwares have also been developed to analyze data from this detector.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>CCD X-ray detector; X-ray diffraction; high pressure studies.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sinha" fname="Amar" isfellow="0">Sinha, Amar</author>
					<author lname="Garg" fname="Alka B." isfellow="0">Garg, Alka B.</author>
					<author lname="Vijayakumar" fname="V." isfellow="0">Vijayakumar, V.</author>
					<author lname="Godwal" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Godwal, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Sikka" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Sikka, S. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Radiation dosimetry by potassium feldspar</title>
				<feature>Instrumentation</feature>
				<page>0155-0158</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The thermoluminescence (TL) properties of raw and annealed feldspar have been studied for their use in gamma dosimetry. The raw gamma exposed feldspar shows glow peaks at 120$^\circ $C and 319$^\circ $C. Gamma dose beyond 500 cGy can be measured without any significant fading even after 40 days of termination of exposure. The annealed feldspar shows a glow peak at 120$^\circ $C after gamma exposure. This peak can be used to measure gamma doses beyond 25 cGy when the TL is measured after 24 h from termination of exposure.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Potassium feldspar; thermoluminescence; fading; glow curve.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Pandya" fname="Arun" isfellow="0">Pandya, Arun</author>
					<author lname="Vaijapurkar" fname="S. G." isfellow="0">Vaijapurkar, S. G.</author>
					<author lname="Bhatnagar" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Bhatnagar, P. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
        </issue>
        <issue inum="03" month="06" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				 <title>A note on the use of ellipsometry for studying the kinetics of formation of self-assembled monolayers</title>
				<feature>Nanomaterials</feature>
				<page>0159-0163</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Ellipsometry is currently one of the most important techniques for characterization of the deposition and growth mode of ultra thin organic films. However, it is well known that for thicknesses normally encountered in organic monolayer films, as would occur for example in self-assembled monolayers, ellipsometry cannot be used to simultaneously determine the thickness and refractive index of the monolayer film. Current practice is to assume a reasonable value for the film refractive index and calculate an effective ‘ellipsometric thickness’. This communication seeks to show that the alternative approach of assuming a thickness for the monolayer (determined by the length of the molecule) and calculating the effective film refractive index lends itself to easier and more meaningful physical interpretation. The Lorentz–Lorenz formula is then used to transform the effective refractive index into a surface coverage and hence to an effective mass coverage. The methodology advanced is applied to the kinetics of formation of a self-assembled monolayer of a well-studied molecule, octadecanethiol on Au.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Ellipsometry; self-assembled monolayers; organic thin films; Lorentz–Lorenz formula.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sastry" fname="Murali" isfellow="0">Sastry, Murali</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Study of interaction of ethylene glycol/PVP phase on noble metal powders prepared by polyol process</title>
				<feature>Nanomaterials</feature>
				<page>0165-0168</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Noble metal powders (Au, Ag, Pt, Pd and Ru) have been synthesized by the polyol process in both the nanometer and submicron scales ($sans$ Pd, Pt and Ru). They have been characterized by both microscopic (TEM and SEM) as well as spectroscopic techniques (FT-IR and XPS). Infrared spectroscopy was employed to study the colloid particles in the presence of ethylene glycol and PVP and the results show that the interaction between the organic phase and the metal particles vary according to the particle size. The role of the solvent, ethylene glycol, during the reduction process was also investigated and we observe formation of &gt;C$=$O vibration band after the reduction process implying that the solvent reduces the metal ions thereby getting oxidized. XPS measurements carried out on the colloidal sols have shown the presence of the organic phase adsorbed onto the metal particles.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Metal nanoparticles; infrared spectroscopy.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bonet" fname="F." isfellow="0">Bonet, F.</author>
					<author lname="Tekaia-Elhsissen" fname="K." isfellow="0">Tekaia-Elhsissen, K.</author>
					<author lname="Sarathy" fname="K. Vijaya" isfellow="0">Sarathy, K. Vijaya</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>La$_{0.9}$Sr$_{0.1}$Ga$_{0.8}$M$_{0.2}$O$_{3–\delta}$ (M = Mn, Co, Ni, Cu or Zn): Transition metal-substituted derivatives of lanthanum–strontium–gallium–magnesium (LSGM) perovskite oxide ion conductor</title>
				<feature>Ionic Conductors</feature>
				<page>0169-0173</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Perovskite oxides of the general formula, La$_{0.9}$Sr$_{0.1}$Ga$_{0.8}$M$_{0.2}$O$_{3–\delta}$ for M = Mn, Co, Ni, Cu and Zn, have been prepared and investigated. All the oxides exhibit high electrical conductivities ($\sigma \sim$ 10$^{–2}$ S/cm at 800$^\circ $C) comparable to that of the best perovskite oxide ion conductor, La$_{0.9}$Sr$_{0.1}$Ga$_{0.8}$Mg$_{0.2}$O$_{2.85}$ (LSGM) ($\sigma \sim$ 8 $\times$ 10$^{–2}$ S/cm at 800$^\circ $C). While M = Mn, Co, Ni, Cu members appear to be mixed conductors with a variable electronic contribution to the conductivity, especially at high oxygen partial pressures ($pO_2 \geq$ 1 atm), arising from mixed-valency of the transition metals, the M $=$ Zn(II) phase is a pure oxide ion conductor exhibiting a conductivity ($\sigma \sim$ 1.5 $\times$ 10$^{–2}$ S/cm at 800$^\circ $C) that is slightly lower than that of LSGM. The lower conductivity of the M $=$ Zn(II) derivative could be due to the preference of Zn(II) for a tetrahedral oxygen coordination.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>LSGM substitution; mixed ionic–electronic conductors; oxide ion conductor.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sebastian" fname="Litty" isfellow="0">Sebastian, Litty</author>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Shukla, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Gopalakrishnan" fname="J." isfellow="0">Gopalakrishnan, J.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and structural characterization of Na$_2$MnP$_2$O$_7$ crystal</title>
				<feature>Ionic Conductors</feature>
				<page>0175-0178</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Na$_2$MnP$_2$O$_7$ crystals were synthesized by hydrothermal technique. Crystals obtained are in the form of single crystals of rhombohedral morphology with lattice parameters as follows: triclinic, $P \bar{1}$, $\lambda$ = 0.71069 Å, a = 6.657(3) Å, b = 6.714(6) Å, c = 6.518(4) Å, $\alpha$ = 112.31(6)$^\circ $, $\beta$ = 92.14(4)$^\circ $, $\gamma$ = 83.89(5)$^\circ $, $V$ = 268.0(3) Å${}^3$, $Z$ = 2, $\rho_{cal}$ = 2, 3.121 g/cm$^3$, $\mu$ = 3.121 mm$^{–1}$, $F_{000}$ = 244, goodness-of-fit on $F$ = 1.348, final $R$ indices with $[I &gt; 3\sigma(I)]$ $R$ = 0.051 and $\omega R$ = 0.065.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>NASICON; hydrothermal; crystal structure.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lokanath" fname="N. K." isfellow="0">Lokanath, N. K.</author>
					<author lname="Sridhar" fname="M. A." isfellow="0">Sridhar, M. A.</author>
					<author lname="Prasad" fname="J. Shashidhara" isfellow="0">Prasad, J. Shashidhara</author>
					<author lname="Gopalakrishna" fname="G. S." isfellow="0">Gopalakrishna, G. S.</author>
					<author lname="Ashamanjari" fname="K. G." isfellow="0">Ashamanjari, K. G.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Study of lithium glassy solid electrolyte/electrode interface by impedance analysis</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0179-0183</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Cells of lithium ion conducting glassy electrolyte Li$_2$SO$_4$–Li$_2$O–B$_2$O$_3$ with different combinations of electrodes (stainless steel blocking electrode, lithium non-blocking electrode and TiS$_2$ electrode) have been prepared. The a.c. impedance measurements of the cells have been studied at elevated temperature as a function of time. The circuit elements such as bulk resistance, double layer capacitance and charge transfer resistance have been inferred and their time dependence studied. The results show that the electrolyte and the interface are chemically very stable with the different types of electrodes studied here.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Solid electrolyte; lithium ion conducting glass; microbattery; electrode–electrolyte compatibility; impedance spectroscopy.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Karthikeyan" fname="A." isfellow="0">Karthikeyan, A.</author>
					<author lname="Vinatier" fname="P." isfellow="0">Vinatier, P.</author>
					<author lname="Levasseur" fname="A." isfellow="0">Levasseur, A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Nucleation and growth of a multicomponent metallic glass</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0185-0188</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The metallic glass samples of Fe$_{67}$Co$_{18}$B$_{14}$Si$_1$ (2605CO), prepared by the melt spinning technique were procured from the Allied Corporation. The kinetics of crystallization of this multicomponent glassy alloy is studied using differential scanning calorimetry (DSC). The crystallization data have been examined in terms of modified Kissinger and Matusita equations for the non-isothermal crystallization. The results show enhanced bulk nucleation in general. At high heating rates added to it is surface induced abnormal grain growth resulting in fractal dimensionality.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Activation energy; isothermal annealing; abnormal grain growth; fractal dimensionality.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Pratap" fname="Arun" isfellow="0">Pratap, Arun</author>
					<author lname="Raval" fname="K. G." isfellow="0">Raval, K. G.</author>
					<author lname="Gupta" fname="Ajay" isfellow="0">Gupta, Ajay</author>
					<author lname="Kulkarni" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Kulkarni, S. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of alloy elements on the anti-corrosion properties of low alloy steel</title>
				<feature>Alloys and Steels</feature>
				<page>0189-0192</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Effect of alloy elements on corrosion of low alloy steel was studied under simulated offshore conditions. The results showed that the elements Cu, P, Mo, W, V had evident effect on corrosion resistance in the atmosphere zone; Cu, P, V, Mo in the splash zone and Cr, Al, Mo in the submerged zone.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Low alloy steel; anti-corrosion; electric connection.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Hou" fname="Baorong" isfellow="0">Hou, Baorong</author>
					<author lname="Li" fname="Yantao" isfellow="0">Li, Yantao</author>
					<author lname="Li" fname="Yanxu" isfellow="0">Li, Yanxu</author>
					<author lname="Zhang" fname="Jinglei" isfellow="0">Zhang, Jinglei</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A study on fatigue crack growth in dual phase martensitic steel in air environment</title>
				<feature>Alloys and Steels</feature>
				<page>0193-0199</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Dual phase (DP) steel was intercritically annealed at different temperatures from fully martensitic state to achieve martensite plus ferrite, microstructures with martensite contents in the range of 32 to 76%. Fatigue crack growth (FCG) and fracture toughness tests were carried out as per ASTM standards E 647 and E 399, respectively to evaluate the potential of DP steels. The crack growth rates $(da/dN)$ at different stress intensity ranges ($\Delta K$) were determined to obtain the threshold value of stress intensity range ($\Delta K_{th}$). Crack path morphology was studied to determine the influence of microstructure on crack growth characteristics. After the examination of crack tortuosity, the compact tension (CT) specimens were pulled in static mode to determine fracture toughness values. FCG rates decreased and threshold values increased with increase in vol.% martensite in the DP steel. This is attributed to the lower carbon content in the martensite formed at higher intercritical annealing (ICA) temperatures, causing retardation of crack growth rate by crack tip blunting and/or deflection. Roughness induced crack closure was also found to contribute to the improved crack growth resistance at higher levels of martensite content. Scanning electron fractography of DP steel in the near threshold region revealed transgranular cleavage fracture with secondary cracking. Results indicate the possibility that the DP steels may be treated to obtain an excellent combination of strength and fatigue properties.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Dual phase (DP) steel; fatigue crack growth; fracture toughness; stress intensity range; intercritical annealing; crack closure.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sudhakar" fname="K. V." isfellow="0">Sudhakar, K. V.</author>
					<author lname="Dwarakadasa" fname="E. S." isfellow="0">Dwarakadasa, E. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Helium implanted $\rm\underline{Al}$Hf as studied by ${}^{181}$Ta TDPAC</title>
				<feature>Defect Studies</feature>
				<page>0201-0206</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Time differential perturbed angular correlation (TDPAC) measurement on $\rm\underline{Al}$Hf reference sample has shown that a fraction 0.88 of probe nuclei are defect free and are occupying the substitutional sites in fcc Al matrix, and the remaining are associated with Hf solute clusters. Measurements on helium implanted sample indicate the binding of helium associated defects by Hf solute clusters. Isochronal annealing measurements indicate the dissociation of the helium implantation induced defects from Hf solute clusters for annealing treatments beyond 650 K. On comparison of the present results with that reported in $\rm\underline{Cu}$Hf subjected to identical helium implantation, it is inferred that the Hf solute clusters in $\rm\underline{Al}$Hf bind less strongly the helium associated defects than in $\rm\underline{Cu}$Hf.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>TDPAC; electric field gradient; Hf solute clusters; helium-vacancy complex; defect recovery.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Govindaraj" fname="R." isfellow="0">Govindaraj, R.</author>
					<author lname="Gopinathan" fname="K. P." isfellow="0">Gopinathan, K. P.</author>
					<author lname="Viswanathan" fname="B." isfellow="0">Viswanathan, B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Optimization of growth of InGaAs/InP quantum wells using photoluminescence and secondary ion mass spectrometry</title>
				<feature>Semiconducting Materials</feature>
				<page>0207-0210</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p></p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bhunia" fname="S." isfellow="0">Bhunia, S.</author>
					<author lname="Banerji" fname="P." isfellow="0">Banerji, P.</author>
					<author lname="Chaudhuri" fname="T. K." isfellow="0">Chaudhuri, T. K.</author>
					<author lname="Haldar" fname="A. R." isfellow="0">Haldar, A. R.</author>
					<author lname="Bose" fname="D. N." isfellow="0">Bose, D. N.</author>
					<author lname="Aparna" fname="Y." isfellow="0">Aparna, Y.</author>
					<author lname="Chettri" fname="M. B." isfellow="0">Chettri, M. B.</author>
					<author lname="Chakraborty" fname="B. R." isfellow="0">Chakraborty, B. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of penetrants on the aramid Nomex</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0211-0214</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The response of Nomex sheets to some penetrants has been analyzed. The process of moisture uptake depends on the relative humidity (RH) of the ambient atmosphere and the initial characteristics of the polymer. In the case of common laboratory solvents, the uptake by the polymer shows an inverse dependence on the molar volume of the former. Although the calendered and the uncalendered Nomex sheets exhibit an overall similarity in their response to various penetrants, quantitative comparison reveals distinct differences.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Nomex; relative humidity; penetrants.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Jain" fname="Anjana" isfellow="0">Jain, Anjana</author>
					<author lname="Vijayan" fname="Kalyani" isfellow="0">Vijayan, Kalyani</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Studies on poly (hydroxy alkanoates)/(ethylcellulose) blends</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0215-0219</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Biodegradable polymers represent one of the most significant area of research today. Among these polymers, poly ($\beta$-hydroxy butyrate co $\beta'$-hydroxy valerate) i.e. PHBV have received special attention because of their unique combination of properties. They are perfectly biocompatible, biodegradable polymers and can be processed by any conventional technique. In the present study an attempt has been made to develop the biodegradable blends of PHBV by blending them with ethyl cellulose (EC). Ethyl cellulose has been selected to monitor the biodegradation rate of PHBV and also for making the blends cost effective. The blends are thoroughly characterized for their compatibility, by the measurement of viscosity of blends and through FT-IR. Various applications of PHBV/EC blend in agriculture and pharmaceutical industries are being explored.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Polymer blends; viscosity; ethyl cellulose; PHBV; compatibility.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Suthar" fname="Vaishali" isfellow="0">Suthar, Vaishali</author>
					<author lname="Pratap" fname="Arun" isfellow="0">Pratap, Arun</author>
					<author lname="Raval" fname="Heta" isfellow="0">Raval, Heta</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Sintering of ultra high molecular weight polyethylene</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0221-0226</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Ultra high molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) is a high performance polymer having low coefficient of friction, good abrasion resistance, good chemical resistance etc. It is used in shipbuilding, textile industries and also in biomedical applications. UHMWPE is processed by powder processing technique because of its high melt viscosity at the processing temperature. Powder processing technique involves compaction of polymeric powder under pressure and sintering of the preforms at temperature above its melting point. In this study, we report our results on compaction and sintering behaviour of two grades of UHMWPE with reference to the powder morphology, sintering temperatures and strength development.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>UHMWPE; powder compaction; sintering; coalescence; strength development.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Hambir" fname="Sangeeta" isfellow="0">Hambir, Sangeeta</author>
					<author lname="Jog" fname="J. P." isfellow="0">Jog, J. P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Low frequency ac conduction and dielectric relaxation in poly(N-methyl pyrrole)</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0227-0232</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The ac conductivity and dielectric constant of poly(N-methyl pyrrole) thin films have been investigated in the temperature range 77–350 K and in the frequency range 10$^2$–10$^6$ Hz. The well defined loss peaks have been observed in the temperature region where measured ac conductivity approaches dc conductivity. These loss peaks are associated with the hopping of the charge carriers. The frequency and temperature dependence of ac conductivity have been qualitatively explained by considering the contribution from two mechanisms; one giving a linear dependence of conductivity on frequency and other having distribution of relaxation times giving rise to broad dielectric loss peak.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Poly(N-methyl pyrrole); dielectric relaxation; ac conduction.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Narula" fname="Amarjeet K." isfellow="0">Narula, Amarjeet K.</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="Ramadhar" isfellow="0">Singh, Ramadhar</author>
					<author lname="Chandra" fname="Subhas" isfellow="0">Chandra, Subhas</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of pressure on the phonon properties of europium chalcogenides</title>
				<feature>High Pressure Studies</feature>
				<page>0233-0235</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Lattice vibrational properties of europium chalcogenides have been investigated at high pressure by using a simple lattice dynamical model theory viz. the three-body force rigid ion model (TRIM) which includes long range three-body interaction arising due to charge transfer effects. The dispersion curves for the four Eu-chalcogenides agree reasonably well with the available experimental data. Variation of LO, TO, LA and TA phonons with pressure have also been studied at the symmetry points of the brillouin zone (BZ) for Euchalcogenides for the first time by using a lattice dynamical model theory. We have also calculated the one phonon density of states and compared them with the first order Raman scattering results. The calculation of one phonon density of states for Eu-chalcogenides has also been extended up to the phase transition pressure. We observed a pronounced shift in phonon spectrum as pressure is increased.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Phonons; high pressure; phase transition.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sakalle" fname="U. K." isfellow="0">Sakalle, U. K.</author>
					<author lname="Jha" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Jha, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Sanyal" fname="S. P." isfellow="0">Sanyal, S. P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Azomesogens with a heterocyclic moiety</title>
				<feature>Liquid Crystals</feature>
				<page>0237-0238</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Azobenzene derivatives were among the first ten liquid crystalline compounds. But there have been no detailed investigations on azomesogens consisting of a heterocyclic moiety. Twelve different azo compounds have been condensed with nicotinic acid to evaluate the effect of variation of terminal group on the monosubstituted pyridine system. The relative thermal stabilities and the variation in the mesomorphic characteristics have also been studied.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Azomesogens; heterocyclic; terminal; polarizable; group efficiency order.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Dave" fname="Jayrang S." isfellow="0">Dave, Jayrang S.</author>
					<author lname="Menon" fname="Meera" isfellow="0">Menon, Meera</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
        </issue>
        <issue inum="04" month="08" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Phase transitions in Na$_2$TeO$_4$ ceramics</title>
				<feature>Phase Transitions</feature>
				<page>0239-0241</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Polycrystalline samples of NaTeO$_4$ were prepared by conventional solid-state reaction technique at low temperature (600$^\circ $C). X-ray powder diffraction (XRD) technique was used to check the formation of single phase NaTeO$_4$ compound with cell parameters $a =$ 10·602(1) Å; $b =$ 70·622(1) Å and $c =$ 8·506(1) Å in orthorhombic crystal system. Detailed studies of dielectric constant ($\varepsilon$) (and loss tangent (tan $\delta$) as a function of frequency (400 Hz–10 kHz) and temperature (– 120$^\circ $C–260$^\circ $C) show that the compound has two phase transitions in the ferroelectric phase.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Polycrystalline; phase transition; ceramics; dielectric constant.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="N. K." isfellow="0">Singh, N. K.</author>
					<author lname="Choudhary" fname="R. N. P." isfellow="0">Choudhary, R. N. P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Ceramic joining through reactive wetting of alumina with calcium aluminate refractory cements</title>
				<feature>Refractory Cements</feature>
				<page>0243-0248</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Compositions in CaO–Al$_2$O$_3$ system have been prepared by gel–to–crystallite conversion method. Reactive powders of 1 : 2, 1 : 1, 2 : 1 and 3 : 1 of CaO and Al$_2$O$_3$ compositions were obtained by calcining the product at 800–1200$^\circ $C. Fine grained powders were used as refractory cement for joining alumina ceramics. An optimum temperature of 1450$^\circ $C for 4 h produced joints of satisfactory strength. The microstructure and X-ray phase analysis of the fractured joint surface clearly indicate reactive wetting of the alumina ceramics. This wetting enhances the joining of alumina substrates and can be attributed to the formation of Ca$_{12}$Al$_{14}O$_{33}$ liquid phase. The results are explained by using CaO–Al$_2$O$_3$ phase diagram.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>G $\rightarrow$ C conversion; reaction bonding; alumina ceramics; calcium aluminate; high temperature cements.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Geetha" fname="K." isfellow="0">Geetha, K.</author>
					<author lname="Umarji" fname="A. M." isfellow="0">Umarji, A. M.</author>
					<author lname="Kutty" fname="T. R. N." isfellow="0">Kutty, T. R. N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Optimization of time–temperature schedule for nitridation of silicon compact on the basis of silicon and nitrogen reaction kinetics</title>
				<feature>Nitride Ceramics</feature>
				<page>0249-0253</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A time–temperature schedule for formation of silicon–nitride by direct nitridation of silicon compact was optimized by kinetic study of the reaction, 3Si + 2N$_2$ = Si$_3$N$_4$ at four different temperatures (1250$^\circ $C, 1300$^\circ $C, 1350$^\circ $C and 1400$^\circ $C). From kinetic study, three different temperature schedules were selected each of duration 20 h in the temperature range 1250$^\circ $–1450$^\circ $C, for complete nitridation. Theoretically full nitridation (100% i.e. 66·7% weight gain) was not achieved in the product having no unreacted silicon in the matrix, because impurities in Si powder and loss of material during nitridation would result in 5–10% reduction of weight gain.</p>
                    <p>Green compact of density &lt; 66&#37; was fully nitrided by any one of the three schedules. For compact of density &gt; 66&#37;, the nitridation schedule was maneuvered for complete nitridation. Iron promotes nitridation reaction. Higher weight loss during nitridation of iron doped compact is the main cause of lower nitridation gain compared to undoped compact in the same firing schedule. Iron also enhances the amount of $\beta$-Si$_3$N$_4$ phase by formation of low melting FeSi$_x$ phase.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Reaction sintered silicon nitride; nitridation; reaction kinetics.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rakshit" fname="J." isfellow="0">Rakshit, J.</author>
					<author lname="Das" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Das, P. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Phase analysis and dielectric properties of ceramics in PbO–MgO–ZnO–Nb$_2$O$_5$ system: A comparative study of materials obtained by ceramic and molten salt synthesis routes</title>
				<feature>Ceramics</feature>
				<page>0255-0261</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Compositions of the type 3PbO–MgO/ZnO–Nb$_2$O$_5$ were synthesized by the ceramic route at 1000$^\circ $C and sintered at 1200$^\circ $C. Powder X-ray diffraction studies of the 1000$^\circ $C heated products show the presence of the cubic pyrochlore and the columbite (Mg/ZnNb$_2$O$_6$) type phase in the ratio of 3 : 1 for all possible combinations of MgO and ZnO. Further heating at 1200$^\circ $C led to a decrease in the cubic pyrochlore phase and an increase in the columbite phase by around 10&#37;. Compacted pellets sintered further showed the appearance of the perovskite phase. Similar compositions synthesized using the KCl–NaCl molten salt method at 900$^\circ $C for 6 h gave a significant amount of the cubic perovskite related phase of the type Pb(Mg/Zn)$_{1/3}$Nb$_{2/3}$O$_3$ for all compositions containing MgO. The amount of the perovskite phase was nearly 55&#37; for the Mg rich compositions and decreased with increase in Zn content, the pure Zn composition yielding mainly the cubic pyrochlore phase. On sintering these phases at 1000$^\circ $C the perovskite phase content decreased. The dielectric constant of the composite materials formed by the ceramic route was in the region of 14 to 20 and varied little with frequency. The composites obtained by the molten salt method, however, showed much larger dielectric constants in the region 40–150 at 500 kHz for various compositions. The dielectric loss tangent of these composites were lower by an order (0·005–0·03 at 500 kHz) compared to the ceramic route.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Ceramics; dielectrics; X-ray diffraction.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Thirumal" fname="M." isfellow="0">Thirumal, M.</author>
					<author lname="Ganguli" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Ganguli, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Incorporation of cobalt and nickel metal nano-particles in nano-grain zirconia film matrix by solution route$^#$</title>
				<feature>Nanomaterials</feature>
				<page>0263-0266</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Precursor solutions of cobalt/nickel incorporated nano-grain zirconia films were prepared from aquo-organic solutions of zirconium oxychloride octahydrate and corresponding transition metal nitrate. The films were deposited onto silica glass substrate by the dipping technique. Annealing was made at different temperatures from 450$^\circ $C to 1200$^\circ $C $\pm$ 5$^\circ $C in air atmosphere. The range of thickness of the films baked at 450$^\circ $C was 1800–1870 Å. For cobalt system Co$_3$O$_4$ was formed initially at 450$^\circ $C which gradually transformed to alpha cobalt and next to cubic cobalt along with a non-stoichiometric compound (Zr$_{0·71}$Co$_{0·23}$O$_{0·06}$) with increasing annealing temperature. On the other hand, for nickel system nickel metal of nano-size was observed in the nano-grain zirconia film matrix at 450$^\circ $C. By increasing annealing temperature to 1200$^\circ $C, a compound, ZrNi$_4$O, was formed which was found to be stable for $\sim$ 30 days.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Nano-grain zirconia; nano particles of cobalt and nickel metals; sol-gel.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Jana" fname="S." isfellow="0">Jana, S.</author>
					<author lname="Biswas" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Biswas, P. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Specific heat studies in Ho–Ba–CuO superconductors: Fermionic and bosonic contributions</title>
				<feature>Superconductors</feature>
				<page>0267-0272</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The specific heats of superconducting HoBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7–\delta}$ (T$_c \cong $ 92 K) have been theoretically investigated in the temperature domain 70 $\leq$ T $\leq$ 110 K. The bosonic (phonons) contribution to the specific heat is estimated from Debye model in the harmonic approximation for high temperature expansion (T &gt; $\theta_D$/2$pi$) using the moments of the phonon density of states. The fermionic constituent as the electronic specific heat is deduced using a suitable trial function above and below T$_c$. As a next step the contribution of specific heat by charge oscillations (plasmons) are obtained. The theoretical results from bosonic and fermionic terms are then compared with the experimental results. We find that the specific heats from electronic as well as plasmon term are only a fraction of lattice specific heat and in particular, plasmons do not influence the thermal conduction significantly. The implications of the above analysis are discussed.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Electronic; phonons; plasmons; specific heat; Ho-based superconductors.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="varshney" fname="Dinesh" isfellow="0">varshney, Dinesh</author>
					<author lname="Shah" fname="Sanjay" isfellow="0">Shah, Sanjay</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="R. K." isfellow="0">Singh, R. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Conductivity, dielectric behaviour and magnetoelectric effect in copper ferrite–barium titanate composites</title>
				<feature>Composite Materials</feature>
				<page>0273-0279</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Composites of CuFe$_2$O$_4$ and BaTiO$_3$ were prepared using a conventional ceramic double sintering process. The presence of both phases was confirmed by X-ray diffraction. The variations of resistivity and thermo emf with temperature in these samples were studied. All the composites showed $n$-type behaviour. The variation of dielectric constant ($\varepsilon'$) in the frequency range 100 Hz to 1 MHz and with temperature at constant frequency were studied. The conduction phenomenon was explained on the basis of a small polaronhopping model. Also confirmation of this phenomenon was made with the help of a.c. conductivity measurements. The static value of the magnetoelectric conversion factor, i.e. d.c. (ME)$_H$ was studied as a function of intensity of the magnetic field. The maximum value of ME coefficient was observed for 75&#37; ferroelectric phase composite.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Conductivity; dielectric behaviour; magnetoelectric effect; CuFe$_2$O$_4$; BaTiO$_3$.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mahajan" fname="R. P." isfellow="0">Mahajan, R. P.</author>
					<author lname="Patankar" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">Patankar, K. K.</author>
					<author lname="Kothale" fname="M. B." isfellow="0">Kothale, M. B.</author>
					<author lname="Patil" fname="S. A." isfellow="0">Patil, S. A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>EPR, IR and DC conductivity studies of $x$CuO–(100–$x$) Bi$_2$O$_3$ glasses</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0281-0284</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Glass system $x$CuO–(100–$x$) Bi$_2$O$_3$ in the composition range 30–60 mol&#37; of CuO is prepared by melt-quenching technique. The ESR spectra show no hyperfine splittings in parallel part but the peak to peak field width is found to vary with CuO content. The observed $g$ effective values are found to vary with copper oxide. The absence of hyperfine splittings is due to inhomogeneous broadening. The observed IR spectra suggest the presence of Bi–O bonds. The structure is changing from [BiO$_6$] octahedral to [BiO$_3$] pyramidal units with increasing CuO concentration. D.C. electrical conductivity results indicate that the conduction is electron in nature and arises out of adiabatic hopping of polarons. The activation energy is found to be concentration and temperature dependent.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Preparation of $x$CuO–(100–$x$) Bi$_2$O$_3$ glass system; IR and ESR spectra; d.c. ionic conductivity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sreenivasu" fname="D." isfellow="0">Sreenivasu, D.</author>
					<author lname="Chandramouli" fname="V." isfellow="0">Chandramouli, V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Dielectric properties of NaF–B$_2$O$_3$ glasses doped with certain transition metal ions</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0285-0293</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Dielectric constant $\varepsilon$, loss tan $\delta$, a.c. conductivity $\sigma$ and dielectric breakdown strength of NaF–B$_2$O$_3$ glasses doped with certain transition metal ions (viz. Cu$^{2+}$, VO$^{2+}$, Ti$^{4+}$ and Mn$^{4+}$) are studied in the frequency range 10$^2$–10$^7$ Hz and in the temperature range 30–250$^\circ $C. The values of $^\varepsilon$, tan $\delta$, $\sigma_{a.c.}$ are found to be the highest for Cu$^{2+}$ doped glasses and the lowest for Mn$^{4+}$ doped glasses. Activation energy for a.c. conduction and the value of dielectric breakdown strength are found to be the lowest for Cu$^{2+}$ doped glasses and the highest for Mn$^{4+}$ doped glasses. With the help of infrared spectra, increase in the values of $\varepsilon$ and tan $\delta$ of these glasses with frequency and temperature are identified with space charge polarization. An attempt has been made to explain a.c. conduction phenomenon on the basis of quantum mechanical tunneling model (QMT)/carrier barrier hopping model.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Dielectric properties; NaF–B$_2$O$_3$ glasses; QMT model.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Murthy" fname="M. Krishna" isfellow="0">Murthy, M. Krishna</author>
					<author lname="Murthy" fname="K. S. N." isfellow="0">Murthy, K. S. N.</author>
					<author lname="Veeraiah" fname="N." isfellow="0">Veeraiah, N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A test for diffusional coherency strain hypothesis in the discontinuous precipitation in Mg–Al alloy</title>
				<feature>Alloys</feature>
				<page>0295-0299</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Discontinuous precipitation (DP) occurs in many alloy systems under certain conditions. Although solute supersaturation is the chemical driving force for DP, this has to be coupled with another driving force for grain boundary migration. This was identified to be diffusional coherency strain ahead of the moving boundary in the case of diffusion induced grain boundary migration (DIGM) and liquid film migration (LFM). In the present work, the validity of diffusional coherency strain hypothesis is verified in Mg–Al alloy, which exhibits discontinuous precipitation. Samples were tested with an applied stress simultaneously with discontinuous precipitation and it was found that the velocity of the boundaries both parallel and transverse to the stress axis obeys the model for diffusional coherency strain. This work can be used as a conclusive evidence for diffusional coherency strain hypothesis for the occurrence of discontinuous precipitation in Mg–Al alloys.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Discontinuous precipitation; diffusional coherency strain; Mg–Al alloy; DIGM; LFM; driving force.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kashyap" fname="K. T." isfellow="0">Kashyap, K. T.</author>
					<author lname="Ramachandra" fname="C." isfellow="0">Ramachandra, C.</author>
					<author lname="Bhat" fname="V." isfellow="0">Bhat, V.</author>
					<author lname="Chatterji" fname="B." isfellow="0">Chatterji, B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Thermal formation of corundum from aluminium hydroxides prepared from various aluminium salts</title>
				<feature>Material Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0301-0304</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Aluminium hydroxides have been precipitated from various aluminium salts and the differences in their thermal behaviour have been investigated. Pseudoboehmite derived from the nitrate, sulfate and chloride all form $\gamma$-Al$_2$O$_3$ at $\sim$ 400$^\circ $C but the formation of $\alpha$-Al$_2$O$_3$ at 1200$^\circ $C occurs more readily in the material derived from the sulfate. This contains a higher concentration of anionic impurities related to differences in the solubility of the original aluminium salts. The sulfate is retained in the gel to higher temperatures at which its eventual decomposition may lead to the formation of a reactive pore structure which facilitates the nucleation of $\alpha$-Al$_2$O$_3$.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Aluminium hydroxide; corundum; thermal transformation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Temuujin" fname="J." isfellow="0">Temuujin, J.</author>
					<author lname="Jadambaa" fname="Ts." isfellow="0">Jadambaa, Ts.</author>
					<author lname="Mackenzie" fname="K. J. D." isfellow="0">Mackenzie, K. J. D.</author>
					<author lname="Angerer" fname="P." isfellow="0">Angerer, P.</author>
					<author lname="Porte" fname="F." isfellow="0">Porte, F.</author>
					<author lname="Riley" fname="F." isfellow="0">Riley, F.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Calcium ferrite formation from the thermolysis of calcium tris (maleato) ferrate(III)</title>
				<feature>Material Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0305-0307</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>For preparing calcium ferrite, calcium tris (maleato) ferrate(III) precursor was prepared by mixing aqueous solutions of iron(III) maleate, calcium maleate and maleic acid. Various physico-chemical techniques i.e. TG, DTG, DTA, Mössbauer, XRD, IR etc have been used to study the decomposition behaviour from ambient to 900$^\circ $C and ferrite formation. Three consecutive decomposition steps leading to the formation of $\alpha$-Fe$_2$O$_3$ and calcium carbonate have been observed at various stages of thermolysis. In the final stage the ferrite, Ca$_2$Fe$_2$O$_5$, is obtained as a result of solid state reaction between $\alpha$-Fe$_2$O$_3$ and calcium carbonate at 788$^\circ $C, a temperature much lower than for ceramic method. The results have been compared with those of the oxalate precursor.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Ferrites; thermal decomposition; precursor technique; calcium ferrimaleate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Randhawa" fname="B. S." isfellow="0">Randhawa, B. S.</author>
					<author lname="Sweety" fname="Kamaljeet" isfellow="0">Sweety, Kamaljeet</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Gas-chromism in ultrasonic spray pyrolyzed tungsten oxide thin films</title>
				<feature>Thin Films</feature>
				<page>0309-0312</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A simple and inexpensive ultrasonic spray pyrolysis (USP) technique has been employed to deposit tungsten oxide (WO$_3$) thin films by spraying 2·0 mM aqueous ammonium metatungstate solution onto the amorphous glass substrates kept at 250$^\circ $C. The films were further annealed at 400$^\circ $C for 4 h in air. X-ray diffraction (XRD) technique was used to determine the crystallinity and to identify the WO$_3$ phases. It was found that the films were sub-stoichiometric, WO$_{3–z}$. To study gas-induced properties, a catalyzing layer of platinum (Pt) was sputtered onto it. The gas-induced electrical and optical properties of Pt/WO$_3$/glass samples were studied and results reported. It was found that electrical resistivity decreased by a factor of 10 within 2 min and stabilized after 15 min, after H$_2$ gas exposure. Similarly the optical transmittance of the samples attenuated from 55&#37; to 10&#37; within 15–20 min. The reversible changes in electrical resistivity and optical transmittance were observed when the samples were exposed to oxygen. The response times and sensitivity of the samples were estimated.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Ultrasonic spray pyrolysis; tungsten oxide; thin films; gas-chromism.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Patil" fname="P. S." isfellow="0">Patil, P. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Structural characterization of vacuum evaporated ZnSe thin films</title>
				<feature>Thin Films</feature>
				<page>0313-0317</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Thermally evaporated ZnSe thin films deposited on glass substrates within substrate temperatures ($T_s$) at 303 K–623 K are of polycrystalline nature having f.c.c. zincblende structure. The most preferential orientation is along [111] direction for all deposited films together with other abundant planes [220] and [311]. The lattice parameter, grain size, average internal stress, microstrain, dislocation density and degree of preferred orientation in the film are calculated and correlated with $T_s$.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>ZnSe thin films; X-ray diffraction; average internal stress; microstrain; dislocation density.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kalita" fname="Pradip Kr" isfellow="0">Kalita, Pradip Kr</author>
					<author lname="Sarma" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Sarma, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Das" fname="H. L." isfellow="0">Das, H. L.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>An experimental investigation of electrical conductivities in biopolymers</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0319-0324</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Gum arabica obtained from acacia plant is a conducting biopolymer. Experiments are carried out on this natural gum arabica. In the present study TGA, ion transference number, transient ionic current, thermal analysis, frequency and temperature variation of a.c. conductivity, Arrhenius plot and volt–ampere characteristics of specimens are carried out. The total electrical conductivity of these biopolymers are comparable to that of synthetic polymers doped with inorganic salts. The ion transference number of these biopolymers show their superionic nature of electrical conduction. The overall conduction mechanism seems to be protonic in nature rather than electronic one.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Biopolymer; protonic; gum arabica; ion transference number; electrical conductivity; solid protonic conductor.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mallick" fname="H." isfellow="0">Mallick, H.</author>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="A." isfellow="0">Sarkar, A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Electrical transport in ethyl cellulose–chloranil system</title>
				<feature>Electrical Properties</feature>
				<page>0325-0330</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The charge-transport behaviour in pure and chloranil (Chl) doped ethyl cellulose (EC) system has been studied by measuring the dependence of current on field, temperature, electrode material and dopant concentration. The role of doping molecular concentration in the polymer matrix and modification in the conduction characteristics are studied. Lowering of the activation energy due to doping was observed. The current was found to increase with an increase in the chloranil concentration. An explanation for this has been attempted on the basis of formation of molecular aggregates between chloranil molecules and ethoxy groups of ethyl cellulose. It is suggested that chloranil occupies interstitial positions between the polymer chains and assists in carrier transportation by reducing the hopping barriers. The current–voltage characteristics of different samples are analyzed using space charge limited current theory and quantitative information about the transport parameters is derived. The values of effective drift mobility and trapped charge carrier concentration which result in the build up of space charge have been calculated.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Electrical transport; ethyl cellulose; chloranil; charge transfer complex; molecular aggregates; Richardson–Schottky; Poole–Frenkel; space charge limited current.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Khare" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Khare, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Pandey" fname="R. K." isfellow="0">Pandey, R. K.</author>
					<author lname="Jain" fname="P. L." isfellow="0">Jain, P. L.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Current–voltage studies on $\beta$-FeSi$_2$/Si heterojunction</title>
				<feature>Electrical Properties</feature>
				<page>0331-0334</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>$I–V$ characteristics of both $\beta$-FeSi$_2$/n-Si and $\beta$-FeSi$_2$/p-Si were studied at room temperature. The junctions were formed by depositing Fe on Si selectively followed by thermal annealing and some samples were later treated by pulsed laser. Temperature of thermal annealing and diode area were also varied. $I–V$ studies on all these samples were done and ideality factors were computed. Results obtained were interpreted.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Silicide; semiconducting silicide; heterojunction; pulsed laser; $I–V$ characteristics.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Datta" fname="A." isfellow="0">Datta, A.</author>
					<author lname="Kal" fname="S." isfellow="0">Kal, S.</author>
					<author lname="Basu" fname="S." isfellow="0">Basu, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Electrical conductivity measurements on gel grown KDP crystals added with some ammonium compounds</title>
				<feature>Electrical Properties</feature>
				<page>0335-0340</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Pure and impurity added [with NH$_4$Cl, NH$_4$NO$_3$, NH$_4$H$_2$PO$_4$, $(NH_4)_2CO_3$ and $(NH_4)_2SO_4$] KDP single crystals were grown by the gel method using silica gels. Electrical conductivity measurements were carried out along both the unique axis and perpendicular directions at various temperatures ranging from 28 to 140$^\circ $C by the conventional two-probe method. The present study shows that the conductivity in KDP crystals, for all the five dopants considered, increases with the increase in impurity concentration and temperature. Activation energies were also determined and reported.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Impurity added KDP crystals; gel method; electrical conductivity; activation energy.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Freeda" fname="T. H." isfellow="0">Freeda, T. H.</author>
					<author lname="Mahadevan" fname="C." isfellow="0">Mahadevan, C.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
        </issue>
        <issue inum="05" month="10" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Preparation of Pt–Ru bimetallic catalyst supported on carbon nanotubes</title>
				<feature>Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0341-0344</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The template carbonization of polyphenyl acetylene yields hollow, uniform cylindrical carbon nanotubes with outer diameter almost equal to pore diameter of the template used. High resolution transmission electron microscopic investigation reveals that Pt–Ru nanoparticles are highly dispersed inside the tube with an average particle size of 1 7 nm.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Carbon nanotubes; template synthesis; fuel cell catalyst; nanoparticles.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rajesh" fname="B." isfellow="0">Rajesh, B.</author>
					<author lname="Thampi" fname="K. Ravindranathan" isfellow="0">Thampi, K. Ravindranathan</author>
					<author lname="Bonard" fname="J-M." isfellow="0">Bonard, J-M.</author>
					<author lname="Viswanathan" fname="B." isfellow="0">Viswanathan, B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Solid-state synthesis and characterization of LiCoO$_2$ and LiNi$_y$Co$_{1–y}$O$_2$ solid solutions</title>
				<feature>Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0345-0348</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Solid solutions of compositions LiNi$_y$Co$_{1–y}$O$_2$ ($y$ = 0 0, 0 1 and 0 2) were prepared by solid-state fusion synthesis from carbonate precursors. Material characterization was carried out using XRD. Formation mechanisms of the products are discussed in the light of TG/DTA results. Nickel-containing compositions gave higher discharge capacities and smaller hystereses in their charge–discharge profiles which make them more attractive than pristine LiCoO$_2$  as cathode materials in high-energy lithium cells. The lower loss in capacity per cycle for cells with unsubstituted LiCoO$_2$ , as determined from cycling studies up to 25 cycles, makes it more suitable than the substituted ones for long cycle-life cells with low capacity fade.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Lithium-ion cells; nickel doped LiCoO$_2$ ; lithium cobalt oxide.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Periasamy" fname="P." isfellow="0">Periasamy, P.</author>
					<author lname="Babu" fname="B. Ramesh" isfellow="0">Babu, B. Ramesh</author>
					<author lname="Thirunakaran" fname="R." isfellow="0">Thirunakaran, R.</author>
					<author lname="Kalaiselvi" fname="N." isfellow="0">Kalaiselvi, N.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="T. Prem" isfellow="0">Kumar, T. Prem</author>
					<author lname="Renganathan" fname="N. G." isfellow="0">Renganathan, N. G.</author>
					<author lname="Raghavan" fname="M." isfellow="0">Raghavan, M.</author>
					<author lname="Muniyandi" fname="N." isfellow="0">Muniyandi, N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Characterization of combustion synthesized zirconia powder by UV-vis, IR and other techniques</title>
				<feature>Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0349-0354</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Fine powders of zirconia were prepared by employing combustion method with varying fuel to precursor molar ratios. The zirconia powders contained more amount of monoclinic phase as the fuel content was increased. This aspect was studied using XRD, IR and UV-vis diffuse reflectance techniques. The surface acidbase properties of these samples were also investigated by indicator titration method. The catalytic activity was probed with transfer hydrogenation reaction in liquid phase. It was found that combustion synthesized zirconia did not provide required active sites for transfer hydrogenation reactions in liquid phase unlike hydrous zirconia.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Combustion synthesis; ZrO$_2$ ; UV-vis; XRD; catalysis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sahu" fname="H. Ranjan" isfellow="0">Sahu, H. Ranjan</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="G. Ranga" isfellow="0">Rao, G. Ranga</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Ageing behaviour of unary hydroxides in trivalent metal salt solutions: Formation of layered double hydroxide (LDH)-like phases</title>
				<feature>Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0355-0359</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The hydroxides of Mg, Ni, Cu and Zn transform into layered double hydroxide (LDH)-like phases on ageing in solutions of Al or Cr salts. This reaction is similar to acid leaching and proceeds by a dissolution–reprecipitation mechanism offering a simple method of LDH synthesis, with implications for the accepted theories of formation of LDH minerals in the earth’s crust.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Hydroxides; hydrotalcites; layered double hydroxides.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rajamathi" fname="Michael" isfellow="0">Rajamathi, Michael</author>
					<author lname="Kamath" fname="P. Vishnu" isfellow="0">Kamath, P. Vishnu</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Dielectric properties of nanophase Ag$_2$HgI$_4$ and Ag$_2$HgI$_4$–Al$_2$O$_3$ nanocomposites</title>
				<feature>Nanomaterials</feature>
				<page>0361-0367</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The dielectric properties of nanophase Ag$_2$HgI$_4$  and Ag$_2$HgI$_4$–Al$_2$O$_3$  nanocomposites at different frequencies have been studied over a temperature range covering the stability range of \textbf{\it b} phase of Ag$_2$HgI$_4$  and beyond the \textbf{\it b} to \textbf{\it a} phase transition temperature. \textbf{\it e} , tan \textbf{\it d} and \textbf{\it s_{a.c.}} of nanophase Ag$_2$HgI$_4$  and Ag$_2HgI$_4$–Al$_2$O$_3$ nanocomposites were found to be larger than the reported values for polycrystalline pellets of Ag$_2$HgI$_4$ . The dielectric properties of the nanocomposites were found to be a function of the wt.&#37; of nano alumina. The observed changes are attributed to the grain boundary properties of nanophase materials and to the microsize space charge effects.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Nanophase materials; nanocomposites; dielectric properties.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Potty" fname="S. Sankara Narayanan" isfellow="0">Potty, S. Sankara Narayanan</author>
					<author lname="Khadar" fname="M. Abdul" isfellow="0">Khadar, M. Abdul</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Differential scanning calorimetry studies of Se$_{85}$Te$_{15–x}$Pb$_x$ ($x$ = 4, 6, 8 and 10) glasses</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0369-0375</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Results of differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) studies of Se$_{85}$Te$_{15–x}$Pb$_x$  ($x$ = 4, 6, 8 and 10) glasses have been reported and discussed in this paper. The results have been analyzed on the basis of structural relaxation equation, Matusita’s equation and modified Kissinger’s equation. The activation energies of structural relaxation lie in between 226 and 593 kJ/mol. The crystallization growth is found to be onedimensional for all compositions. The activation energies of crystallization are found to be 100–136 kJ/mol by Matusita’s equation while 102–139 kJ/mol by modified Kissinger’s equation. The Hruby number (indicator of ease of glass forming and higher stability) is the highest for Se$_{85}$Te$_9$Pb$_6$  glass while S factor (indicator of resistance to devitrification) is highest for Se$_{85}$Te$_7$Pb$_8$  glass at all heating rates in our experiment. Further the highest resistance to devitrification has the highest value of structural activation energy and the activation energy of crystallization is maximum for the most stable glass by both Matusita’s equation and the modified Kissinger’s equation.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Stability; devitrification; activation energy; dimension of growth.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Maharajan" fname="N. B." isfellow="0">Maharajan, N. B.</author>
					<author lname="Saxena" fname="N. S." isfellow="0">Saxena, N. S.</author>
					<author lname="Bhandari" fname="Deepika" isfellow="0">Bhandari, Deepika</author>
					<author lname="Imran" fname="Mousa M." isfellow="0">Imran, Mousa M.</author>
					<author lname="Paudyal" fname="D. D." isfellow="0">Paudyal, D. D.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Preparation and characterization of magnesium–aluminium–silicate glass ceramics</title>
				<feature>Glass Ceramics</feature>
				<page>0377-0382</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Synthesis of machinable quality magnesium aluminium silicate (MgO–Al$_2$O$_3$–SiO$_2$) for fabrication of insulators/spacers usable in high voltage applications under high vacuum conditions has been carried out following two different routes i.e. (i) sintering route, and (ii) glass route. A three-stage heating schedule involving calcination, nucleation and crystallization, has been evolved for the preparation of magnesium aluminium silicate (MAS) glass ceramic with MgF$_2$  as a nucleating agent. The effect of sintering temperature on the density of compacted material was studied. Microstructure and machinability of samples obtained from both routes were investigated. They were also characterized for microhardness. Initial studies on material obtained by glass route reveal that these samples are superior to those obtained from sintered route in respect of their high voltage breakdown strength and outgassing behaviour. Outgassing rate of 10$^{–9}$ Torr l s$^{–1}$ cm$^{–2}$  and breakdown strength of 160 kV/cm were obtained. Different types of spacers, lugs, nuts and bolts have been prepared by direct machining of the indigenously developed glass ceramic.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Machinable glass ceramic; magnesium aluminium silicate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Goswami" fname="Madhumita" isfellow="0">Goswami, Madhumita</author>
					<author lname="Mirza" fname="T." isfellow="0">Mirza, T.</author>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="A." isfellow="0">Sarkar, A.</author>
					<author lname="Manikandan" fname="Shobha" isfellow="0">Manikandan, Shobha</author>
					<author lname="Sangeeta" fname="" isfellow="0">Sangeeta</author>
					<author lname="Verma" fname="S. L." isfellow="0">Verma, S. L.</author>
					<author lname="Gurumurthy" fname="K. R." isfellow="0">Gurumurthy, K. R.</author>
					<author lname="Shrikhande" fname="V. K." isfellow="0">Shrikhande, V. K.</author>
					<author lname="Kothiyal" fname="G. P." isfellow="0">Kothiyal, G. P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics of hydrogen evolution reaction on Zr$_{0\ 5}$Ti$_{0\ 5}$V$_{0\ 6}$Cr$_{0\ 2}$Ni$_{1\ 2}$ alloy in KOH electrolyte</title>
				<feature>Hydrogen Storage Alloys</feature>
				<page>0383-0391</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A hydrogen-storage alloy of the composition Zr$_{0\ 5}$Ti$_{0\ 5}$V$_{0\ 6}$Cr$_{0\ 2}$Ni$_{1\ 2}$ has been investigated for corrosion resistance and hydrogen-evolution reaction (HER) in KOH electrolyte of varying concentrations. Activation of the electrode by absorption of hydrogen takes place after prolonged cathodic polarization in the potential range of HER. Prior to activation, the open-circuit potential is about – 0 4 V vs Hg/HgO, OH$^–$ , at which the alloy electrode tends to undergo corrosion with oxygen-reduction reaction (ORR) as the conjugate reaction. The corrosion–current density measured from Tafel polarization of ORR is found to be independent of KOH concentration and has an average value of about 30 $\mu$A cm$^{–2}$ . Subsequent to activation, the open circuit potential of the electrode is shifted to about – 0 93 V vs Hg/HgO, OH$^–$ , which is equal to the reversible potential of HER. The exchange current density values measured from Tafel polarization of HER are marginally higher in relation to the values obtained before the electrode is activated. Alternating-current impedance spectra in the Nyquist form contain two overlapped semicircles. The high-frequency semicircle is attributed to the electrode geometry, while the low-frequency semicircle is due to the charge-transfer reaction and double–layer capacitance. The impedance data are analyzed by a non-linear least square curve fitting technique and impedance parameters are evaluated. </p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Hydrogen-storage alloy; hydrogen-evolution reaction; Tafel polarization; a.c. impedance; exchange-current density.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rodrigues" fname="Shalini" isfellow="0">Rodrigues, Shalini</author>
					<author lname="Munichandraiah" fname="N." isfellow="0">Munichandraiah, N.</author>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Shukla, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A study of austenitization of SG iron</title>
				<feature>Steels and Alloys</feature>
				<page>0393-0398</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Austenitization process of three SG irons with varying compositions and as cast matrix microstructure has been studied at three austenitization temperatures of 850, 900 and 950C for different time periods. Microstructure, hardness and X-ray diffraction have been used to reveal the nature of dependence of the process on austenitization temperature, time and as cast structure. The optimum austenitization time is maximum for ferritic and minimum for pearlitic matrix.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Austenitization; austempering; austempered ductile iron.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Batra" fname="Uma" isfellow="0">Batra, Uma</author>
					<author lname="Tandon" fname="Pankaj" isfellow="0">Tandon, Pankaj</author>
					<author lname="Kaur" fname="Kulbir" isfellow="0">Kaur, Kulbir</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Corrosion of carbon-alloyed iron aluminides</title>
				<feature>Steels and Alloys</feature>
				<page>0399-0403</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The corrosion behaviour of two carbon-alloyed intermetallics of composition Fe–28 1Al–2 1C and Fe–27 5Al–3 7C has been studied and compared with that of binary intermetallics. Potentiodynamic polarization studies indicated that the intermetallics exhibited active–passive behaviour in an acidic solution of pH = 1, whereas they exhibited stable passivity in a buffer solution of pH 8 4. Corrosion rates were also obtained by immersion testing. The variation of corrosion rate as a function of time was similar for both the intermetallics. The variation in corrosion rate as a function of time has been explained based on the observed potentiodynamic polarization behaviour. Scanning electron microscopy of corroded surfaces indicated that the carbon-alloyed intermetallics were susceptible to galvanic corrosion, due to the presence of carbides.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Corrosion; iron aluminides; Fe$_3$Al; potentiodynamic polarization.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sen" fname="M." isfellow="0">Sen, M.</author>
					<author lname="Balasubramaniam" fname="R." isfellow="0">Balasubramaniam, R.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="A. V. Ramesh" isfellow="0">Kumar, A. V. Ramesh</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A model for two-step ageing</title>
				<feature>Steels and Alloys</feature>
				<page>0405-0411</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>In commercial practice, two-step ageing is commonly used in Al–Zn–Mg alloys to produce a fine dispersion of $h$ precipitates to accentuate the mechanical properties and resistance to stress corrosion cracking. While this is true in Al–Zn–Mg alloys, two-step ageing leads to inferior properties in Al–Mg–Si alloys. This controversial behaviour in different alloys can be explained by Pashley’s Kinetic model. Pashley’s model addresses the stability of clusters after two-step ageing. In the development of the model, the surface energy term between cluster and matrix is taken into account while the coherency strains between the cluster and matrix are not considered. In the present work, a model is developed which takes into account the coherency strains between cluster and matrix and defines a new stability criterion, inclusive of strain energy term. Experiments were done on AA 7010 aluminium alloy by carrying out a two-step ageing treatment and the results fit the new stability criterion. Thus it is found that the new model for two-step ageing is verified in the case of Al–Zn–Mg alloy.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Two-step ageing; delayed ageing; clusters; coherency strains.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kashyap" fname="K. T." isfellow="0">Kashyap, K. T.</author>
					<author lname="Ramachandra" fname="C." isfellow="0">Ramachandra, C.</author>
					<author lname="Chatterji" fname="B." isfellow="0">Chatterji, B.</author>
					<author lname="Lele" fname="S." isfellow="0">Lele, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and characterization of castor oil based polyurethane–polyacrylonitrile interpenetrating polymer networks</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0413-0418</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A series of interpenetrating polymer networks (IPNs) of castor oil based polyurethane/polyacrylonitrile (PU/PAN: 80/20, 60/40, 50/50, 40/60 and 20/80) were synthesized by condensation reaction of castor oil with methylene diisocyanate and acrylonitrile, employing benzoyl peroxide (BPO) and ethylene glycol dimethylacrylate (EGDM) as initiator and crosslinkers respectively. The physical, chemical, optical and some of the mechanical properties of PU/PAN were studied. Phase stabilization in IPNs was investigated by wide angle X-ray (WAXS) profile analysis. Variation of crystal size distribution was studied in these polymer networks.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords> Castor oil; MDI; interpenetrating; mechanical; crystal size; strain.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mallu" fname="P." isfellow="0">Mallu, P.</author>
					<author lname="Siddaramaiah" fname="" isfellow="0">Siddaramaiah</author>
					<author lname="Somashekar" fname="R." isfellow="0">Somashekar, R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Electric current arising from unpolarized polyvinyl formal</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0419-0423</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>An appreciable electric current is observed in a system consisting of a polyvinyl formal (PVF) film in a sandwich configuration, in the temperature range 30–110$^\circ $C. The maximum value of the current during first heating is found to be of the order of 10$^{–10}$ A and its thermograms exhibit one transition (i.e. current peak) at around 60$^\circ $C. The position of the current peak in thermal spectrum shifts with the heating rate. A temperature dependence of the open circuit voltage is also observed. The activation energy of the process responsible for the current is determined. The magnitude of the current is more in the case of dissimilar electrode systems. It is proposed that the electric current arising from unpolarized metal–polymer–metal system is a water activated phenomenon, which is influenced by the transitional changes of the polymer.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Electric current; open circuit voltage; water activated phenomenon; plasticization effect.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Khare" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Khare, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Jain" fname="P. L." isfellow="0">Jain, P. L.</author>
					<author lname="Pandey" fname="R. K." isfellow="0">Pandey, R. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Aliphatic amine cured PDMS–epoxy interpenetrating network system for high performance engineering applications—Development and characterization</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0425-0429</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A siliconized epoxy interpenetrating network (IPN) was synthesized from commercially available DGEBA epoxy resin GY250 (Ciba-Geigy, epoxy equivalent = 182–192, viscosity = 9000–12000 cP) and hydroxyl terminated polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS). PDMS and GY250 were thoroughly mixed at 30$^\circ $C to get the prepolymer. Stoichiometric amounts of PDMS–epoxy prepolymer, $g$-aminopropyltriethoxysilane, aliphatic amine curing agent (HY951), and dibutyltindilaurate catalyst, were thoroughly mixed and cast in a mould after evacuating the entrapped air. The cured material was then taken out and post cured at 70$^\circ $C for 10 h. IPN was characterized by FTIR spectroscopy, SEM, DSC, TGA and viscosity measurements. Incorporation of PDMS in the epoxy matrix increased the viscosity and lowered the exotherm and pot-life. PDMS in IPN increased $T_g$ , heat-distortion temperature and reduced the percentage weight loss with increase in temperature. Incorporation of PDMS drastically reduced the tensile and flexural strengths and hardness. By reducing the tensile and flexural modulus, the siloxane moiety effectively reduced the internal stress of IPN thereby improving its impact strength and percentage elongation. PDMS increased the electric potential gradient of IPN to withstand without breakdown. An increase in the tracking index and arc resistance of IPN were observed, because of the presence of Si–O–Si, which minimized the possibility of forming carbonized path. Volume and surface resistivities of IPN also increased with the incorporation of PDMS. The siliconized epoxy IPN, with better impact and thermal resistance, may be used in automobile and aerospace applications to withstand high temperature, and mechanical stress. The PDMS–epoxy IPN may be used for encapsulation, high temperature and high voltage application due to their low shrinkage and lesser internal stress. With the improved electrical characteristics, IPN may be used for high performance electrical insulation, insulator housings, and encapsulation to withstand high voltage, moisture, oxidation, chemical attack, biological attack, outdoor weathering, contamination, electrical, mechanical and thermal stress.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>PDMS; siloxane; epoxy; siliconized epoxy matrix; interpenetrating network.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Velan" fname="T. V. Thanikai" isfellow="0">Velan, T. V. Thanikai</author>
					<author lname="Bilal" fname="I. Mohammed" isfellow="0">Bilal, I. Mohammed</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Studies on electrical properties of SrBi$_4$Ti$_{4–3x}$Fe$_{4x}$O$_{15}$</title>
				<feature>High T$_c$ Superconductors</feature>
				<page>0431-0437</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The system SrBi$_4$Ti$_{4–3x}$Fe$_{4x}$O$_{15}$ belonging to bismuth layer structured ferroelectric (BLSF) materials with $x$ = 0, 0 1 and 0 2 has been prepared through solid-state double sintering method. Increase of iron content in SrBi$_4$Ti$_4$O$_{15}$ resulted in densification of the samples. The normal puckering observed in the sample has been found to decrease and the lattice distortion increased. Dielectric measurements indicate the ferroelectric transition temperature of the samples to be 530$^\circ $C, 560$^\circ $C and 606$^\circ $C. The increase of transition temperature with increasing iron content is correlated with lattice distortion. Conductivity measurements show two slopes and the activation energies have been found to increase with the iron content. Impedance spectroscopy measurements confirm insulating behaviour at lower temperatures. With increase in temperature the samples become conducting and show relaxational effects. The Cole–Cole plots at higher temperatures are found to be semicircles. The relaxation times decrease with the increase of iron content.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Layer structure compounds; ferroelectrics; piezoelectrics; impedance; dielectric properties.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ramulu" fname="N. Venkat" isfellow="0">Ramulu, N. Venkat</author>
					<author lname="Prasad" fname="G." isfellow="0">Prasad, G.</author>
					<author lname="Suryanarayana" fname="S. V." isfellow="0">Suryanarayana, S. V.</author>
					<author lname="Sankaram" fname="T. Bhima" isfellow="0">Sankaram, T. Bhima</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Temperature dependence of thermal conductivity of vanadium substituted BPSCCO system between 10 and 150 K</title>
				<feature>High T$_c$ Superconductors</feature>
				<page>0439-0445</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Thermal conductivity of a set of $(Bi_{0 8}Pb_{0 2–y}V_y)_2Sr$_2$Ca$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{10+d}$(0 = $y$ 0 05) pellets in the temperature range between 10 and 150 K is reported. Vanadium substitution influences strongly the magnitude of thermal conductivity ($l$) over the entire temperature range. But the nature of $l(T)$ dependence remains similar to that generally observed for HTSCs. The electronic contribution to the total $l$ in the normal state is estimated to be $\sim$ 25%. We have attempted to examine our data, assuming the role of both electrons and phonons in the origin of the $l(T)$ behaviour below $T_c$ . Observed temperature variation of $l(T)$ for the present set of samples could be explained very well assuming this electron + approach. Some of the microscopic quantities estimated from the best-fit parameters give reasonable values.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Thermal conductivity; high temperature superconductors; vanadium substitution; electron + phonon approach.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Dhami" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Dhami, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Dey" fname="T. K." isfellow="0">Dey, T. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Dielectric behaviour and a.c. conductivity in Cu$_x$Fe$_{3–x}$O$_4$ ferrite</title>
				<feature>Magnetic Materials</feature>
				<page>0447-0452</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The dielectric properties (dielectric constant and loss) for the system Cu$_x$Fe$_{3–x}$O$_4$  with $x$ = 1 0, 0 8, 0 6, 0 4 and 0 2, were studied in the temperature range 300 800 K and also in the frequency range 1 kHz 1 MHz. A.c. conductivity was derived from dielectric constant and loss tangent data. The conduction in this system is interpreted as due to small polaron hopping. The dielectric relaxation was observed for the compositions with tetragonal structure whereas normal behaviour was observed for cubic structure.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Dielectric constant; polaron hopping.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Patil" fname="A. N." isfellow="0">Patil, A. N.</author>
					<author lname="Patil" fname="M. G." isfellow="0">Patil, M. G.</author>
					<author lname="Patankar" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">Patankar, K. K.</author>
					<author lname="Mathe" fname="V. L." isfellow="0">Mathe, V. L.</author>
					<author lname="Mahajan" fname="R. P." isfellow="0">Mahajan, R. P.</author>
					<author lname="Patil" fname="S. A." isfellow="0">Patil, S. A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="06" month="12" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Hydrothermal synthesis of fine oxide powders</title>
				<feature>Material Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0453-0460</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>This is a review and an overview on hydrothermal synthesis of fine oxide powders. The term hydrothermal today includes methods which involve water at pressures (from 1 atm–several kilobars) and high temperatures from 100–10,000$^\circ $C. Hydrothermal is one of the best methods to produce pure fine oxide powders. The authors describe (i) hydrothermal decomposition, (ii) hydrothermal metal oxidation, (iii) hydrothermal reaction, (iv) hydrothermal precipitation and hydrothermal hydrolysis, (v) hydrothermal electrochemical, (vi) reactive electrode submerged arc, (vii) hydrothermal microwave, (viii) hydrothermal sonochemical, etc and also ideal and real powders.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Hydrothermal; synthesis; fine powders; oxide powders.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sōmiya" fname="Shigeyuki" isfellow="0">Sōmiya, Shigeyuki</author>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="Rustom" isfellow="0">Roy, Rustom</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Microwave synthesis of electrode materials for lithium batteries</title>
				<feature>Material Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0461-0466</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A novel microwave method is described for the preparation of electrode materials required for lithium batteries. The method is simple, fast and carried out in most cases with the same starting material as in conventional methods. Good crystallinity has been noted and lower temperatures of reaction has been inferred in cases where low temperature products have been identified.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Novel microwave method; electrode materials; lithium batteries.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bhat" fname="Harish" isfellow="0">Bhat, Harish</author>
					<author lname="Chakravarthy" fname="B. P." isfellow="0">Chakravarthy, B. P.</author>
					<author lname="Ramakrishnan" fname="P. A." isfellow="0">Ramakrishnan, P. A.</author>
					<author lname="Levasseur" fname="A." isfellow="0">Levasseur, A.</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="K. J." isfellow="0">Rao, K. J.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Room temperature synthesis of colloidal platinum nanoparticles</title>
				<feature>Material Synthesis</feature>
				<page>0467-0470</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Efficient preparation of stable dispersions of platinum nanoparticles from platinous chloride (K$_2$PtCl$_4$) was achieved by simultaneous addition of capping polymer material. The size of platinum nanoparticles was controlled by changing the ratio of concentration of capping polymer material to the concentration of platinum cation used. The morphology of colloidal particles were studied by means of UV-visible spectrophotometry and transmission electron microscopy (TEM). Particle size increased with low reagent concentration. The change in absorption spectra with the particle size was observed, i.e. blue shift attributed to decrease in particle size.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Platinous chloride (K$_2$PtCl$_4$); sodium polyacrylic acid; platinum nanoparticles; UV-visible; TEM.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Devi" fname="G. Sarala" isfellow="0">Devi, G. Sarala</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="V. J." isfellow="0">Rao, V. J.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Temperature dependence of current–voltage characteristics of Au/$n$-GaAs epitaxial Schottky diode</title>
				<feature>Semiconductors</feature>
				<page>0471-0474</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The influence of temperature on current–voltage ($I–V$) characteristics of Au/$n$-GaAs Schottky diode formed on $n$-GaAs epitaxial layer grown by metal organic chemical vapour deposition technique has been investigated. The dopant concentration in the epitaxial layer is $1 \times 10^{16}$ cm$^{−3}$ . The change in various parameters of the diode like Schottky barrier height (SBH), ideality factor and reverse breakdown voltage as a function of temperature in the range 80−300 K is presented. The variation of apparent Schottky barrier height and ideality factor with temperature has been explained considering lateral inhomogeneities in the Schottky barrier height in nanometer scale lengths at the metal–semiconductor interface.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Schottky barrier height; metal–semiconductor interface; current–voltage characteristics; thermionic emission; ideality factor; lateral inhomogeneities in SBH.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="R." isfellow="0">Singh, R.</author>
					<author lname="Arora" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Arora, S. K.</author>
					<author lname="Tyagi" fname="Renu" isfellow="0">Tyagi, Renu</author>
					<author lname="Agarwal" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Agarwal, S. K.</author>
					<author lname="Kanjilal" fname="D." isfellow="0">Kanjilal, D.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Investigations on Tl-2223 thin films fabricated through ultrasonic spray pyrolysis under oxygen deficient conditions</title>
				<feature>Superconductors</feature>
				<page>0475-0481</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>In this paper we have shown that polycrystalline films corresponding to Tl-2223 phase can be grown by employing high thalliation temperatures and short thalliation times. Ultrasonically deposited precursor films corresponding to Ba$_2$Ca$_{2\ 2}$Cu$_{3\ 3}$O$_x$(Ag$_y$) have been thalliated under high vacuum ($\sim$ 10$^{–5}$ torr) at 890$^\circ $C to obtain single phase Tl-2223 films. An off-stoichiometric and unreacted pellet of composition Tl$_{2\ 05}$Ba$_2$Ca$_2$Cu$_3$O$_z$  has been used as source of Tl. We have shown that oxygen ambient is not necessary for the growth of Tl-2223 phase. The as-thalliated films have $T_c$’s in the range 123 K $\pm$ 0 70 K. The $T_c$  has been found to be independent of the addition of AgNO$_3$  to the precursor. The zero field transport $J_c$  has been observed to be &gt; 1 2 $\times$ 10$^5$  A/cm$^2$  at 77 K. Near $T_c$  (110 K–122 K), $J_c$  has been observed to follow the power law $J_c$ $(1 – T/T_c)^p , p$ 2. A power law with $p $ 1 4 has been observed for the temperature range 70 K–110 K. An optimum doping of Ag has been observed to induce about 25% increase in $J_c$  and it also leads to uniform and enlarged grain growth. The surface morphology of Ag free samples contains plate like grains having arbitrary shapes. In contrast to this 0 35 Ag doped sample exhibits nearly rectangular plate like grains.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>HTSC; thin films; Tl-2223; ultrasonic spray pyrolysis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="H. K." isfellow="0">Singh, H. K.</author>
					<author lname="Srivastava" fname="O. N." isfellow="0">Srivastava, O. N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of HIPing on conductivity and impedance measurements of DyBi$_5$Fe$_2$Ti$_3$O$_{18}$ ceramics</title>
				<feature>Oxide Ceramics</feature>
				<page>0483-0489</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>X-ray diffraction, a.c. impedance and conductivity (a.c. and d.c.) have been used to characterize DyBi$_5$Fe$_2$Ti$_3$O$_{18}$. Samples were prepared by solid state double sintering method. A few samples were also subjected to hot isostatic pressing (HIP) at 800$^\circ $C for 2 h at 100 MPa pressure. The data on XRD, impedance and conductivity of two sets of samples are compared to understand study of effect of HIPing on the properties of DyBi$_5$Fe$_2$Ti$_3$O$_{18}$.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Hot isostatic pressing (HIP); bismuth layered structure ferroelectrics (BLSF); ferroelectromagnetic materials; relaxor ferroelectrics.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Prasad" fname="N. V." isfellow="0">Prasad, N. V.</author>
					<author lname="Prasad" fname="G." isfellow="0">Prasad, G.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="Mahendra" isfellow="0">Kumar, Mahendra</author>
					<author lname="Suryanarayana" fname="S. V." isfellow="0">Suryanarayana, S. V.</author>
					<author lname="Bhimasankaram" fname="T." isfellow="0">Bhimasankaram, T.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="G. S." isfellow="0">Kumar, G. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Thermal expansion behaviour of barium and strontium zirconium phosphates</title>
				<feature>Oxide Ceramics</feature>
				<page>0491-0494</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Ba$_{1\, 5–x}$Sr$_x$Zr$_4$P$_5$SiO$_{24}$ compounds with $x$ = 0, 0 25, 0 5, 0 75, 1 0, 1 25 and 1 5, belonging to the low thermal expansion NZP family were synthesized by the solid state reaction method. The XRD pattern could be completely indexed with respect to R$\bar{3}$ space group indicating the ordering of vacancy at the divalent cation octahedral sites. The microstructure and bulk thermal expansion coefficient from room temperature to 800$^\circ $C of the sintered samples have been studied. All the samples show very low coefficient of thermal expansion (CTE), with $x = 0$ samples showing negative expansion. A small substitution of strontium in the pure barium compound changes the sign of CTE. Similarly, $x$ = 1 5 sample (pure strontium) shows a positive CTE and a small substitution of barium changes its sign. $X$ = 1 0 and 1 25 samples have almost constant CTE over the entire temperature range. The low thermal expansion of these samples can be attributed to the ordering of the ions in the crystal structure of these materials.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Coefficient of thermal expansion; low thermal expansion; NZP; ceramic; dilatometer; anisotropy.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Tantri" fname="P. Srikari" isfellow="0">Tantri, P. Srikari</author>
					<author lname="Geetha" fname="K." isfellow="0">Geetha, K.</author>
					<author lname="Umarji" fname="A. M." isfellow="0">Umarji, A. M.</author>
					<author lname="Ramasesha" fname="Sheela K." isfellow="0">Ramasesha, Sheela K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Influence of strontium on the cubic to ordered hexagonal phase transformation in barium magnesium niobate</title>
				<feature>Phase Transitions</feature>
				<page>0495-0498</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Oxides of the type Ba$_{3–x}$Sr$_x$MgNb$_2$O$_9$  were synthesized by the solid state route. The $x$ = 0 composition (Ba$_3$MgNb$_2$O$_9$) was found to crystallize in a disordered (cubic) perovskite structure when sintered at 1000C. For higher Sr doping ($x$ 0 5), there was clearly the presence of an ordered hexagonal phase indicated by the growth of superstructure reflections in the powder X-ray diffraction patterns. In all the compositions there was the presence of a minor amount of Ba$_{5–x}$Sr$_x$Nb$_4$O$_{15}$ phase which increased with Sr substitution up to $x$ = 1 and then it remained nearly constant at about 5%. Samples sintered at 1300C showed the hexagonally ordered phase for the entire range of composition (0 $x$ 3). The degree of ordering being considerably greater than in the 1000C heated samples as evidenced by several superstructure reflections.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Oxides; X-ray diffraction; ordering; dielectric materials.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Thirumal" fname="M." isfellow="0">Thirumal, M.</author>
					<author lname="Ganguli" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Ganguli, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Oxynitride glasses$—$An overview</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0499-0507</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The theory and practice of oxynitride glass synthesis and property evaluation came into effect since late 70’s. Its importance lies in the fact of its formation at the grain-boundary of synthesized silicon–nitride ceramics with additives. Earlier, heating an oxide glass with NH$_3$  and/or N$_2$  was the route to obtain oxynitride glass. Later on greater amount of nitrogen retention was made possible using AlN or Si$_3$N$_4$ as batch material. Silicate, borate and phosphate systems were studied in isolation or in conjugation. Melting temperature of such glasses varied from 1500–1800$^\circ $C. Different technological developments regarding furnace atmosphere, temperature, compositions etc have been discussed towards a successful synthesis with a thermodynamic approach. Nitrogen content in glass as high as 36 8 eq% has been reported by the application of an overpressure of 30 atm N$_2$. Different physical and chemical properties have been discussed in relation to nitrogen content in glass. Structural aspects have been considered with respect to XPS and IR spectroscopic studies. Finally some points have been highlighted towards some potential applications. </p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Oxynitride glass; silicon–nitride; network former and modifier; leach resistance; nuclear waste.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Das" fname="T." isfellow="0">Das, T.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Spectroscopic and transport studies of Cu$^{2+}$ ion doped in (40 – $x$)Li$_2$O–$x$LiF–60Bi$_2$O$_3$ glasses</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0509-0513</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The preparation of (40 – $x$)Li$_2$O–$x$LiF–60Bi$_2$O$_3$  glassy system and spectroscopic and transport studies of this system are reported. IR results show that this glass consists of [BiO$_3$] units and indicate formation of Bi–F bonds with the addition of LiF. From the ESR spectra of Cu$^{2+}$ ion, the effective g values are found to vary slightly with increasing concentration of fluorine ion. The optical absorption peak corresponding to Cu$^{2+}$ increased linearly with increasing concentration of LiF between 620 nm and 728 nm except at 2 5 mole% of LiF where its value is 729 nm. This peculiar behaviour is attributed to the varying structural coordination of fluorine as the concentration of lithium fluoride is increased. The ionic conductivity measurements indicate that the conduction is due to adiabatic hopping of polarons and the activation energies are found to be temperature and concentration dependent.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Preparation; (40 – $x$)Li$_2$O–$x$LiF–60Bi$_2$O$_3$ glasses; spectroscopic and transport studies.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sreenivasu" fname="D." isfellow="0">Sreenivasu, D.</author>
					<author lname="Chandramouli" fname="V." isfellow="0">Chandramouli, V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Cation exchange applications of synthetic tobermorite for the immobilization and solidification of cesium and strontium in cement matrix</title>
				<feature>Cements</feature>
				<page>0515-0520</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Immobilization and solidification of hazardous cations like Cs$^{137}$ and Sr$^{90}$ are required while handling the radioactive waste of nuclear power plants. Efforts are on to find a fail proof method of safe disposal of nuclear wastes. In this context, various materials like borosilicate glass, zeolites, cements and synthetic rocks have been tried by several workers. This communication deals with the synthesis, characterization, cesium uptake capacity and leaching behaviour of synthetic alumina-substituted calcium silicate hydroxy hydrate, which are close to that obtained for the natural mineral, 11 Å tobermorite. The synthetic mineral show cation selectivity for Cs${}^+$  in presence of 500–1000 times concentrated solutions of Na$^+$ , K$^+$ , Mg$^{2+}$, Ca$^{2+}$ , Ba$^{2+}$ and Sr$^{2+}$. Although the ordinary portland cement (OPC) which is often used in waste management operations alone holds negligible amounts of Cs$^+$  and Sr$^{2+}$, the addition of alumina-substituted tobermorite to OPC enhances the retention power of cement matrix by drastically lowering the leach rate of cations.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Cesium; strontium; selectivity; alumina substituted tobermorite; cement matrix.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shrivastava" fname="O. P." isfellow="0">Shrivastava, O. P.</author>
					<author lname="Shrivastava" fname="Rashmi" isfellow="0">Shrivastava, Rashmi</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Resistance to freezing and thawing of mortar specimens made from sulphoaluminate–belite cement</title>
				<feature>Cements</feature>
				<page>0521-0527</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Resistance to freezing and thawing of mortar specimens made from sulphoaluminate–belite cement (M–SAB) is compared with that of mortars made from portland cement (M–PC). The results suggest that larger median radius of the pores and total porosity of M–SAB compared to those of M–PC are primarily caused by the rapid setting of the SAB cement. The ‘coarsening’ of pore structure of mortar specimens under action of freezing and thawing is proved by the increase in the macropores portion, median pore radius, and total porosity values. This process is more intense in M–SAB. The effect of the frost attack is confirmed by lower compressive strength and dynamic modulus of elasticity on the one hand and higher absorption capacity, expansion, and crack propagation of M–SAB compared with those of M–PC on the other hand. Besides the decreased frost resistance of M–SAB as compared with that of M–PC, unsatisfactory passivation of steel in M–SAB was found. The reason of this fact is the pH value decrease to less than 11 5 of the M–SAB extract.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Frost resistance; low-energy sulphoaluminate–belite cement; steel reinforcement corrosion.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Janotka" fname="I." isfellow="0">Janotka, I.</author>
					<author lname="Krajèi" fname="L’." isfellow="0">Krajèi, L’.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of doping on TSD relaxation in cellulose acetate films</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0529-0532</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Thermally stimulated depolarization current (TSDC) studies have been performed on solution grown cellulose acetate films doped with different concentrations of acrylic acid (AA) prepared at the poling temperatures (40–75$^\circ $C) with poling fields (10–50 kV/cm). The TSDC spectra of pure and AA doped CA films reveal two relaxation peaks at 80$^\circ $C and 180 $\pm$ 2$^\circ $C, having activation energies centred around 0 25 and 0 55 eV. The phenomena of the existence of these current maxima have been analyzed and discussed in terms of the molecular motion of the polar side groups and release of the remaining part of the frozen dipoles by their cooperative motion with adjoining segments of the main polymer chain. The peak currents, released charge and activation energies associated with the peaks are affected by AA doping. The effect of doping with acrylic acid on the discharge current indicates the formation of molecular aggregates.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>. TSD relaxation; cellulose acetate; acrylic acid; molecular aggregates.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Khare" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Khare, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Jain" fname="P. L." isfellow="0">Jain, P. L.</author>
					<author lname="Pandey" fname="R. K." isfellow="0">Pandey, R. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>50 MeV lithium ion beam irradiation effects in poly vinylidene fluoride (PVDF) polymer</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0533-0538</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Irradiation effects of 50 MeV ${}^7$Li$^{+3}$ ion beam induced in bulk PVDF polymer have been studied with respect to their optical, chemical, structural and electrical behaviour by using UV-visible, FT-IR spectroscopy, XRD technique and electrical frequency response using LCR bridge. The ion fluences ranging from 1 27 $\times$ 10$^{11}$ to 2 15 $\times$ 10$^{13}$ ions cm$^{–2}$ have been used to study dose effects of irradiation in PVDF. The recorded UV-visible spectra clearly shows five characteristic peaks at 315, 325, 360, 425 and 600 nm. Due to irradiation, the optical absorption initially decreases but then increases with higher fluences. In the FT-IR spectra, no appreciable change has been observed after irradiation, indicating that this polymer is chemically stable. There is exponential increase in admittance with log of frequency but the effect of irradiation is not quite appreciable. The value of tan $d$ and relaxation frequency are changed appreciably due to irradiation. The diffraction pattern of PVDF indicates that this polymer is in semi-crystalline form; a decrease in the crystallinity and crystallite size has been observed due to irradiation.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>PVDF polymer; lithium ion irradiation; UV-visible and FT-IR spectroscopy; X-ray diffraction; a.c. frequency response.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shrivastava" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Shrivastava, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Virk" fname="H. S." isfellow="0">Virk, H. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Pure mechanical wear loss measurement in corrosive wear</title>
				<feature>Mechanical Properties</feature>
				<page>0539-0542</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The method for the measurement of the pure mechanical wear loss for 321 stainless steel, 1045 steel and pure iron in the study of the synergy between corrosion and wear was studied. The methods studied included the measurement in distilled water, by cathodic protection and by adding inhibitor KI, and all were compared with the wear loss in air. The experiment showed that the pure mechanical wear losses and friction coefficients obtained by the three methods were close to each other and can be used to calculate the various wear components in the study of the interaction of corrosion and wear, but the measurements in distilled water for pure iron and 1045 steel are not recommended due to their corrosion.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>. Corrosive wear; synergy; pure mechanical wear loss.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Huang" fname="Yanliang" isfellow="0">Huang, Yanliang</author>
					<author lname="Jiang" fname="Xiaoxia" isfellow="0">Jiang, Xiaoxia</author>
					<author lname="Li" fname="Sizuo" isfellow="0">Li, Sizuo</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Subject index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0543-0552</page>
				<abstract />
                 <keywords />
				<allauthors />
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Author index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0553-0558</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<allauthors />
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Volume Contents</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>i-vii</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<allauthors />
			</entry>
		</issue>
    </volume>
    <volume vnum="024">
		<issue inum="01" month="02" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics of pressure induced structural phase transitions—A review</title>
				<feature>Review---Phase Transitions</feature>
				<page>0001-0021</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The current status of experimental as well as theoretical advances in the understanding of kinetics of structural phase transitions is reviewed. A brief outline of the classification of phase transitions and classical ideas in the theory of kinetics of phase change is presented first. High pressure experimental techniques developed for studying the kinetics of structural transitions are reviewed and the salient features of each technique is brought out. The experimental technique using the diamond anvil cell (DAC) and image processing gets special mention as it promises to impart a new direction to this field. The usefulness of kinetic parameters in understanding the mechanism of a phase transition is examined. Typical examples from the literature are provided to give a flavour for these kind of studies. In conclusion, several open questions are raised which could pave way for future work in this area.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>High pressure; structural transitions; kinetics.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shekar" fname="N. V. Chandra" isfellow="0">Shekar, N. V. Chandra</author>
					<author lname="Rajan" fname="K. Govinda" isfellow="0">Rajan, K. Govinda</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>On the origin of recrystallization textures</title>
				<feature>Review---Phase Transitions</feature>
				<page>0023-0026</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The development of recrystallization textures has been debated for the past 50 years. Essentially the rival theories of evolution of recrystallization textures i.e. oriented nucleation (ON) and oriented growth (OG) has been under dispute. In the ON model, it has been argued that a higher frequency of the special orientation (grains) than random occur, thus accounting for the texture. In the OG model, it has been argued that the specially oriented grains have a high mobility boundary and thus can migrate faster and grow to a larger size as compared to random orientations thus contributing to the final recrystallization texture.</p>
                    <p>In FCC metals and alloys like aluminium, cube orientation [(001) 100 ] is the recrystallization texture component. In the classic OG model, cube orientation is supposed to be misoriented from $S$-orientation [(123) 63$\bar{4}$ ] which is a deformation texture component by a 40$^\circ $ about 111 relationship which is supposed to be a high mobility boundary leading to faster growth of cube grains. Stereographic calculations and analytical calculations are presented in this paper to the effect that the $S$-orientation (123) 63$\bar{4}$ is not misoriented from cube (100) 001 by 40$^\circ $ (111) whereas another deformation texture component (123) 41$\bar{2}$ which is termed the $R$-component is misoriented from cube component by 40$^\circ $ 111 . $R$-component is also seen in deformation textures of aluminium and hence the classic OG model remains valid with respect to the $R$-component.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Recrystallization; oriented nucleation; oriented growth; cube orientation</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kashyap" fname="K. T." isfellow="0">Kashyap, K. T.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of high-energy heavy ion irradiation on the crystallization kinetics of Co-based metallic glasses</title>
				<feature>Review---Phase Transitions</feature>
				<page>0027-0033</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Differential scanning calorimeter (DSC) is employed to study the crystallization kinetics of irradiated (at three different fluences with high-energy heavy ion; Ni$^{11+}$ of 150 MeV) specimens of two Co-based metallic glasses. It is found that the crystallization process in both the glasses is completed in two phases. The DSC data have been analysed in terms of kinetic parameters viz. activation energy ($E_c$), Avrami exponent ($n$), dimensionality of growth ($m$), using two different theoretical models. The results obtained have been compared with that of virgin samples. The lower activation energy in case of second crystallization occurring at higher temperature indicates the easier nucleation of second phase. The abnormally high value of Avrami exponent in Co–Ni glass indicates very high nucleation rate during first crystallization.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Crystallization kinetics; high-energy heavy ion irradiation; morphology.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Jain" fname="Rohit" isfellow="0">Jain, Rohit</author>
					<author lname="Bhandari" fname="Deepika" isfellow="0">Bhandari, Deepika</author>
					<author lname="Saxena" fname="N. S." isfellow="0">Saxena, N. S.</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Sharma, S. K.</author>
					<author lname="Tripathi" fname="A." isfellow="0">Tripathi, A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of 80 keV Ar$^+$  implantation on the properties of pulse laser deposited magnetite (Fe$_3$O$_4$) thin films</title>
				<feature>Review---Phase Transitions</feature>
				<page>0035-0038</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Highly oriented thin films of Fe$_3$O$_4$ were deposited on (100) LaAlO$_3$ substrates by pulsed laser ablation. The structural quality of the films was confirmed by X-ray diffraction (XRD). The films showed a Verwey transition near 120 K. The films were subjected to 80 keV Ar$^+$ implantation at different ion doses up to a maximum of $6 \times 10^{14}$ ions/cm$^2$. Ion beam induced modifications in the films were investigated using XRD and resistance vs temperature measurements. Implantation decreases the change in resistance at 120 K and this effect saturates beyond $3 \times 10^{14}$ ions/cm$^2$. The Verwey transition temperature, $T_V$, shifts towards lower temperatures with increase in ion dose.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Implantation; magnetite; thin films; pulsed laser ablation; Verwey transition.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lanke" fname="U. D." isfellow="0">Lanke, U. D.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis of ferrite grade $\mathbf{g}$-Fe$_2$O$_3$</title>
				<feature>Magnetic Materials</feature>
				<page>0039-0045</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Iron(II) carboxylato–hydrazinates: Ferrous fumarato–hydrazinate (FFH), FeC$_4H$_2$O$_4$ 2N$_2$H$_4$; ferrous succinato–hydrazinate (FSH), FeC$_4$H$_4$O$_4$ 2N$_2$H$_4$; ferrous maleato–hydrazinate (FEH), FeC$_4$H$_2$O$_4$ 2N$_2$H$_4$; ferrous malato–hydrazinate (FLH), FeC$_4$H$_4$O$_5$ 2N$_2$H$_4$; ferrous malonato–hydrazinate (FMH), FeC$_3$H$_2$O$_4$ 1 5N$_2$H$_4$ H$_2$O; and ferrous tartrato–hydrazinate (FTH), FeC$_4$H$_4$O$_6$ N$_2$H$_4$ H$_2$O are being synthesized for the first time. These decompose (autocatalytically) in an ordinary atmosphere to mainly $\mathbf{g}$-Fe$_2$O$_3$, while the unhydrazinated iron(II) carboxylates in air yield $\mathbf{a}$-Fe$_2$O$_3$, but the controlled atmosphere of moisture requires for the oxalates to stabilize the metastable $\mathbf{g}$-Fe$_2$O$_3$. The hydrazine released during heating reacts with atmospheric oxygen liberating enormous energy, $$N_2H_4 + O_2 \quad N_2 + H_2O; H_2O = – 621 kJ/mol,$$ which enables to oxidatively decompose the dehydrazinated complex to $\mathbf{g}$-Fe$_2$O$_3$. The reaction products N$_2$ + H$_2$O provide the necessary atmosphere of moisture needed for the stabilization of the metastable oxide.</p>
					<p>The synthesis, characterization and thermal decomposition (DTA/TG) of the iron(II) carboxylato–hydrazinates are discussed to explain the suitability of $\mathbf{g}$-Fe$_2$O$_3$  in the ferrite synthesis.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Carboxylate; hydrazine; metastable oxide; ferrite.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rane" fname="K. S." isfellow="0">Rane, K. S.</author>
					<author lname="Verenkar" fname="V. M. S." isfellow="0">Verenkar, V. M. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Structural and magnetic properties of CaMg$_2$Fe$_{16}$O$_{27}$</title>
				<feature>Magnetic Materials</feature>
				<page>0047-0050</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>A new compound, CaMg$_2$Fe$_{16}$O$_{27}$, is synthesized for the first time, in polycrystalline form, using stoichiometric mixture of oxides with standard ceramic technique and characterized by X-ray diffraction. It is found to have a hexagonal W-type structure with lattice parameters $a$ = 5 850 Å and $c$ = 33 156 Å. Electrical studies show that the compound is a semiconductor with energy of activation, $E$ = 0 56 eV. Electrical conductivity results show a transition in the conductivity vs temperature plot near the Curie temperature. The activation energy value obtained for the paramagnetic phase is found to be higher than that of the ferrimagnetic phase. The molar magnetic susceptibility was measured in the temperature range 300–850 K and the results show that the compound is ferrimagnetic at room temperature. The compound also shows hysteresis at 300 K. Paramagnetic nature of the sample above Curie temperature is also studied. The Curie molar constant $C_M$ calculated from the plot of 1/$c_M$ vs $T(K)$ is found to be nearly in agreement with the expected value.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>W-type ferrite; electrical conductivity; paramagnetic susceptibility; Curie molar constant.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sawadh" fname="P. S." isfellow="0">Sawadh, P. S.</author>
					<author lname="Kulkarni" fname="D. K." isfellow="0">Kulkarni, D. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Electrochemical behaviour of LiM$_y$Mn$_{2–y}$O$_4$(M = Cu, Cr; 0 $y$ 0 4)</title>
				<feature>Electrode Materials</feature>
				<page>0051-0055</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Spinel lithium manganese oxide, LiMn$_2$O$_4$, is beset with problems of capacity fade upon repeated cycling. The loss in capacity upon cycling is attributable to Jahn–Teller distortion and manganese dissolution in the electrolyte in the charged state. One way to circumvent this capacity fade is to introduce other $3d$ transition metal ions in the LiMn$_2$O$_4$ lattice. In this paper, we report on the effect of partial substitution of manganese in the LiMn$_2$O$_4$ phase with copper (II) and chromium (III) ions. It has been shown that the higher octahedral stabilization energy of trivalent chromium imparts greater structural stability to chromium-doped LiMn$_2$O$_4$ spinels. Both copper and chromium reduce the capacity of the spinel in the 4 V region. In terms of its good reversible capacity and ability to sustain cycling with minimal capacity fade, LiCr$_{0\ 1}$Mn$_{1\ 9}$O$_4$  may be considered as a potential cathode material for lithium rechargeable cells.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Chromium doped LiMn$_2$O$_4$; copper doped LiMn$_2$O$_4$; reversible capacity; cyclability; spinel structure.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Thirunakaran" fname="R." isfellow="0">Thirunakaran, R.</author>
					<author lname="Babu" fname="B. Ramesh" isfellow="0">Babu, B. Ramesh</author>
					<author lname="Kalaiselvi" fname="N." isfellow="0">Kalaiselvi, N.</author>
					<author lname="Periasamy" fname="P." isfellow="0">Periasamy, P.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="T. Prem" isfellow="0">Kumar, T. Prem</author>
					<author lname="Renganathan" fname="N. G." isfellow="0">Renganathan, N. G.</author>
					<author lname="Raghavan" fname="M." isfellow="0">Raghavan, M.</author>
					<author lname="Muniyandi" fname="N." isfellow="0">Muniyandi, N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>pH controlled dispersion and slip casting of Si$_3$N$_4$ in aqueous media</title>
				<feature>Advanced Ceramics</feature>
				<page>0057-0061</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The dispersion characteristics of commercial Si$_3$N$_4$  powder in aqueous media (deionized water) was studied as a function of pH in the range 2–11. The slip was characterized for its dispersion quality by various experimental techniques like particle size analysis, sedimentation phenomena, viscosity and flow behaviour and zeta potential analysis. The optimum dispersion was found to be in the pH region 9–11 wherein the slurry displayed minimum sedimentation height, minimum viscosity, near Newtonian flow behaviour and maximum zeta potential. The slip is highly agglomerated in the pH range 2–8 as manifested by higher sedimentation height, higher viscosity, lower zeta potential and thixotropic non-Newtonian flow behaviour. The 72 wt% (44 vol.%) Si$_3$N$_4$ slips made at pH = 10 resulted in green bodies having 53–59% of theoretical density after casting into plaster molds.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Dispersion; slip casting; Si$_3$N$_4$ slips.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="R. Ramachandra" isfellow="0">Rao, R. Ramachandra</author>
					<author lname="Roopa" fname="H. N." isfellow="0">Roopa, H. N.</author>
					<author lname="Kannan" fname="T. S." isfellow="0">Kannan, T. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Acoustic investigations on PbO–Al$_2$O$_3$–B$_2$O$_3$ glasses doped with certain rare earth ions</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0063-0068</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Elastic moduli (Y, $\mathbf{h}$), Poisson’s ratio ($\mathbf{s}$), microhardness ($H$) and some thermodynamical parameters such as Debye temperature ($\mathbf{q}_D$), diffusion constant ($D_i$), latent heat of melting ( $H_m$) etc of PbO–Al$_2$O$_3$–B$_2$O$_3$ glasses doped with rare earth ions viz. Pr$^{3+}$, Nd$^{3+}$, Sm$^{3+}$, Eu$^{3+}$, Tb$^{3+}$, Dy$^{3+}$, Ho$^{3+}$, Er$^{3+}$ and Yb$^{3+}$, are studied as functions of temperatures (in the temperature range 30–200$^\circ $C) by ultrasonic techniques. All these parameters are found to increase with increasing atomic number $Z$ of the rare earth ions and found to decrease with increasing temperature of measurement. From these results (together with IR spectra of these glasses), an attempt is made to throw some light on the mechanical strength of these glasses.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>PbO–Al$_2$O$_3$–B$_2$O$_3$ glasses; rare earth ions; elastic moduli.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Reddy" fname="Rami" isfellow="0">Reddy, Rami</author>
					<author lname="Raju" fname="S. Bangaru" isfellow="0">Raju, S. Bangaru</author>
					<author lname="Veeraiah" fname="N." isfellow="0">Veeraiah, N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Glass and glass–ceramic coatings, versatile materials for industrial and engineering applications</title>
				<feature>Glasses</feature>
				<page>0069-0077</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Among various coating systems for industrial and engineering applications, glass and glass–ceramic coatings have advantages of chemical inertness, high temperature stability and superior mechanical properties such as abrasion, impact etc as compared to other coating materials applied by thermal spraying in its different forms viz. PVD, CVD, plasma, etc. Besides imparting required functional properties such as heat, abrasion and corrosion resistance to suit particular end use requirements, the glass and glass–ceramic coatings in general also provide good adherence, defect free surface and refractoriness.</p>
                    <p>Systematic studies covering the basic science of glass and glass–ceramic coatings, the functional properties required for a particular end-use along with the various fields of application have been reviewed in this paper.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Wear; glass and glass–ceramic coatings; enamelling; coating properties.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Majumdar" fname="Amitava" isfellow="0">Majumdar, Amitava</author>
					<author lname="Jana" fname="Sunirmal" isfellow="0">Jana, Sunirmal</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Impact fatigue behaviour of carbon fibre-reinforced vinylester resin composites</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0079-0086</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Two types of unidirectional carbon fibre, one of high strength (DHMS) and another of medium strength (VLMS) reinforced vinylester resin composites have been examined for their impact fatigue behaviour over 10$^4$ impact cycles for the first time. The study was conducted using a pendulum type repeated impact apparatus specially designed and constructed for the purpose. A well-defined impact fatigue behaviour (S–N type curve) curve has been demonstrated. It showed a plateau region of 10–10$^2$  cycles immediately below the single cycle impact strength, followed by progressive endurance with decreasing impact loads, culminating in an endurance limit at about 71% and 85% of the single impact strength for DHMS-48 and VLMS-48, respectively. Analysis of the fractured surfaces revealed primary debonding, fibre breakage and pull-out at the tensile zone of the samples and a shear mode of fracture with breakage of fibre bundles at the compressive zone of the samples. The occurrence of a few major macrocracks in the matrix with fibre breakage at the high load–low endurance region and development of multiple microcracks in the matrix, coalescing and fibre breakage at the low-load–high endurance region have been inferred to explain the fatigue behaviour of the composites examined.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Repeated impact; carbon fibre; vinylester resin; residual stress; modulus; toughness; impact energy.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="Rita" isfellow="0">Roy, Rita</author>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Sarkar, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Rana" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Rana, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Bose" fname="N. R." isfellow="0">Bose, N. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effects of moisture on the mechanical properties of glass fibre reinforced vinylester resin composites</title>
				<feature>Polymers</feature>
				<page>0087-0094</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Glass fibre reinforced vinylester resin composites incorporating varying amounts of fibres (63 5, 55 75, 48 48, 38 63 and 27 48 wt%) were characterized for their mechanical properties both as prepared and after treatment with boiling water for 2, 4, 6, 8 and 24 h. Weights of the samples were found to increase to a saturation at about 8 h with boiling water treatment.</p>
                    <p>In keeping with the composite principle, the mechanical properties improved with fibre loading. However, the properties were relatively inferior when treated with boiling water for longer hours attributing to ingress of moisture by capillary action through the interface between the fibre and the resin matrix. Considering the rates of moisture absorption and correlating with the mechanical properties, it was observed that the deteriorating effects were predominant up to 4 h treatment with boiling water. Estimation of defect concentrations for 63 5 wt% of nascent fibre reinforced composites as well as those composites treated with boiling water for 24 h were 56 93% and 64 16% respectively. Similarly, 27 48 wt% nascent fibre reinforced composites and those composites with boiling water treatment showed the estimation of defect concentrations of 39 94% and 50 55% respectively. SEM study of the fractured surfaces showed heavy fibre pull-out in the tensile zone whilst shear fracture of the fibre bundles was predominant at the compressive zone of the samples tested for flexural strength properties.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Nascent glass fibre; vinylester resin; moisture effects; fibre pull-out.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="Rita" isfellow="0">Roy, Rita</author>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Sarkar, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Bose" fname="N. R." isfellow="0">Bose, N. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="04" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Foreword</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0095-0095</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Sarkar, B. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Some numerical approaches of creep, thermal shock, damage and delayed failure of ceramics and refractories</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0097-0100</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Numerical simulation is now very often used to predict the behaviour of components in service conditions. This paper is interested in specific approaches concerning ceramic materials and refractories. Creep can be satisfactorily described by a kinematic hardening, and exhibits different creep rates in tension and compression. Concerning the thermal shock of materials, the numerical approach depends whether or not the material is able to develop a sprayed out damage, leading to micro- or macro-cracking. Finally, delayed failure at high temperature can be considered as a consequence of creep, but the random aspect of failure seriously complicates the numerical models. The lack of experimental data presently limits the calibration and the validation of the numerical models.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Ceramic; refractories; creep; thermal stock; damage; delayed failure; numerical simulation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Boussuge" fname="Michel" isfellow="0">Boussuge, Michel</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of zirconia addition on the fatigue behaviour of fine grained alumina</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0101-0104</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The fatigue behaviour of fine grained Al$_2$O$_3$ and ZrO$_2$ toughened Al$_2$O$_3$ (ZTA) compositions with 15 vol% ZrO$_2$ (3 mol% Y$_2$O$_3$  stabilized: 3Y-TZP) have been investigated by using three different techniques. Primarily 4-point bending load was employed to generate tension–tension fatigue data under both static and cyclic conditions. The results clearly showed that the materials were susceptible to both the static and cyclic fatigue and the time to failure under cyclic loading was considerably shorter than the equivalent static loads. The repeated indentations at the same spot with varying loads showed a typical fatigue behaviour. In addition, both the materials were subjected to the repeated impact cycles at varying subcritical loads simulating impact fatigue. In all the cases typical fatigue curves were obtained having a progressive endurance at subcritical loads having an endurance limit. The fatigue behaviour of Al$_2$O$_3$  was much improved by the addition of 15 vol% 3Y-TZP, having micro-plasticity contributing towards the cyclic fatigue phenomena of these materials.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Fatigue; static/cyclic loading; microplasticity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Basu" fname="D." isfellow="0">Basu, D.</author>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Sarkar, B. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Indentation fatigue in silicon nitride, alumina and silicon carbide ceramics</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0105-0109</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Repeated indentation fatigue (RIF) experiments conducted on the same spot of different structural ceramics viz. a hot pressed silicon nitride (HPSN), sintered alumina of two different grain sizes viz. 1 $\mu$m and 25 $\mu$m, and a sintered silicon carbide (SSiC) are reported. The RIF experiments were conducted using a Vicker’s microhardness tester at various loads in the range 1–20 N. Subsequently, the gradual evolution of the damage was characterized using an optical microscope in conjunction with the image analysing technique. The materials were classified in the order of the decreasing resistance against repeated indentation fatigue at the highest applied load of 20 N. It was further shown that there was a strong influence of grain size on the development of resistance against repeated indentation fatigue on the same spot. Finally, the poor performance of the sintered silicon carbide was found out to be linked to its previous thermal history.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Indentation fatigue; silicon nitride; silicon carbide; grain size.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mukhopadhyay" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Mukhopadhyay, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Fracture resistance of 8 mol% yttria stabilized zirconia</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0111-0116</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>An $in$ $situ$ technique for the assessment of fracture resistance employing double cantilever beam (DCB) specimens was developed in the present study. The side-grooved DCB specimens were loaded with pure bending moments in a specially designed and fabricated test fixture which went inside the specimen chamber of a scanning electron microscope. The study as conducted on a 8 mol% fully stabilized cubic phase yttria (Y$_2$O$_3$) stabilized zirconia (YSZ) ceramic. The powder processed sheets were sintered at 1600$^\circ $C for 2 h in a zirconia tube furnace. The mode I applied energy release rate, $G_I$ was determined for both pure YSZ and treated YSZ. Two sets of experiments were conducted for the complete characterization of the ceramics. Three fracture toughness values were determined for the pure and treated ceramics, viz. (i) at the onset of the crack initiation, $G_{ic}$, (ii) at the arrest of a subcritical crack, $G_{ia}$ and (iii) at the onset of the fast fracture, $G_{if}$. Two analyses of the experimental data were carried out, viz. method of extrapolation and statistical analysis. In case of the pure YSZ, a transgranular mode of the stable crack growth was identified to be predominant. The porous coating treatment appeared to have positive effects as the crack initiation resistance increased due to electrode layers. The stable crack growth behaviours of the ceramics were investigated by monitoring the crack growth velocity as a function of applied $G$ values. The results obtained were of direct significance in designing and fabrication of SOFC stacks.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>YSZ; fracture resistance; fracture energy; fracture toughness; SOFC stacks.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sorensen" fname="B. F." isfellow="0">Sorensen, B. F.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="A. N." isfellow="0">Kumar, A. N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Fracture toughness and reliability in high-temperature structural ceramics and composites: Prospects and challenges for the 21st Century</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0117-0120</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The importance of high fracture toughness and reliability in Si$_3$N$_4$, and SiC-based structural ceramics and ceramic matrix composites is reviewed. The potential of these ceramics and ceramic matrix composites for high temperature applications in defence and aerospace applications such as gas turbine engines, radomes, and other energy conversion hardware have been well recognized. Numerous investigations were pursued to improve fracture toughness and reliability by incorporating various reinforcements such as particulate-, whisker-, and continuous fibre into Si$_3$N$_4$ and SiC matrices. All toughening mechanisms, e.g. crack deflection, crack branching, crack bridging, etc essentially redistribute stresses at the crack tip and increase the energy needed to propagate a crack through the composite material, thereby resulting in improved fracture toughness and reliability. Because of flaw insensitivity, continuous fibre reinforced ceramic composite (CFCC) was found to have the highest potential for higher operating temperature and longer service conditions. However, the ceramic fibres should display sufficient high temperature strength and creep resistance at service temperatures above 1000$^\circ $C. The greatest challenge to date is the development of high quality ceramic fibres with associate coatings able to maintain their high strength in oxidizing environment at high temperature. In the area of processing, critical issues are preparation of optimum matrix precursors, precursor infiltration into fibre array, and matrix densification at a temperature, where grain crystallization and fibre degradation do not occur. A broad scope of effort is required for improved processing and properties with a better understanding of all candidate composite systems.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>CFCC; toughening; fracture toughness; $b$-Si$_3$N$_4$.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Dutta" fname="Sunil" isfellow="0">Dutta, Sunil</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Mechanical characteristics of microwave sintered silicon carbide</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0121-0124</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The present work deals with the sintering of SiC with a low melting additive by microwave technique. The mechanical characteristics of the products were compared with that of conventionally sintered products. The failure stress of the microwave sintered products, in biaxial flexure, was superior to that of the products made by conventional sintering route in ambient condition. In firing of products by conventionally sintered process, SiC grain gets oxidized producing SiO$_2$ ( 32 wt%) and deteriorates the quality of the product substantially. Partially sintered silicon carbide by such a method is a useful material for a varieties of applications ranging from kiln furniture to membrane material.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Microwave sintering; biaxial flexure; silicon carbide.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mandal" fname="S." isfellow="0">Mandal, S.</author>
					<author lname="Seal" fname="A." isfellow="0">Seal, A.</author>
					<author lname="Dalui" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Dalui, S. K.</author>
					<author lname="Dey" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Dey, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Ghatak" fname="S." isfellow="0">Ghatak, S.</author>
					<author lname="Mukhopadhyay" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Mukhopadhyay, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Mechanical characterization of microwave sintered zinc oxide</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0125-0128</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The mechanical characterization of microwave sintered zinc oxide disks is reported. The microwave sintering was done with a specially designed applicator placed in a domestic microwave oven operating at a frequency of 2 45 GHz to a maximum power output of 800 Watt. These samples with a wide variation of density and hence, of open pore volume percentage, were characterized in terms of its elastic modulus determination by ultrasonic time of flight measurement using a 15 MHz transducer. In addition, the load dependence of the microhardness was examined for the range of loads 0 1–20 N. Finally, the fracture toughness data ($K_{IC}$) was obtained using the indentation technique.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Zinc oxide; microwave sintering; microhardness.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mukhopadhyay" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Mukhopadhyay, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Chaudhuri" fname="M. Ray" isfellow="0">Chaudhuri, M. Ray</author>
					<author lname="Seal" fname="A." isfellow="0">Seal, A.</author>
					<author lname="Dalui" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Dalui, S. K.</author>
					<author lname="Banerjee" fname="M." isfellow="0">Banerjee, M.</author>
					<author lname="Phani" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">Phani, K. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of alkali treated jute fibres on composite properties</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0129-0135</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Jute fibres were subjected to a 5% alkali (NaOH) solution treatment for 0, 2, 4, 6 and 8 h at 30$^\circ $C. An improvement in the crystallinity in the jute fibres increased its modulus by 12%, 68% and 79% after 4, 6 and 8 h of treatment respectively. The tenacity of the fibres improved by 46% after 6 and 8 h treatment and the % breaking strain was reduced by 23% after 8 h treatment. For the 35% composites with 4 h treated fibres, the flexural strength improved from 199 1 MPa to 238 9 MPa by 20%, modulus improved from 11 89 GPa to 14 69 GPa by 23% and laminar shear strength increased from 0 238 MPa to 0 2834 MPa by 19%. On plotting the different values of slopes obtained from the rates of improvement of the flexural strength and modulus, against the NaOH treatment time, two different failure modes were apparent before and after 4 h of treatment. In the first region between 0 and 4 h, fibre pull out was predominant whereas in the second region between 6 and 8 h, transverse fracture occurred with a minimum fibre pull out. This observation was well supported by the SEM investigations of the fracture surfaces.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Vinylester resin; jute fibre composite; alkali; mechanical properties; fracture; fibre pull out.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ray" fname="Dipa" isfellow="0">Ray, Dipa</author>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Sarkar, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Rana" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Rana, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Bose" fname="N. R." isfellow="0">Bose, N. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Behaviour of $E$-glass fibre reinforced vinylester resin composites under impact fatigue</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0137-0142</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>An impact fatigue study has been made for the first time on 63 5% glass fibre reinforced vinylester resin notched composites. The study was conducted in a pendulum type repeated impact apparatus especially designed and fabricated for determining single and repeated impact strengths. A well-defined impact fatigue (S–N) behaviour, having a progressive endurance below the threshold single cycle impact fracture stress with decreasing applied stress has been demonstrated. Fractographic analysis revealed fracture by primary debonding having fibre breakage and pullout at the tensile zone, but a shear fracture of fibre bundles at the compressive zone of the specimen. The residual strength, modulus and toughness showed retention of the properties at high impact stress levels up to 1000 impacts followed by a sharp drop. Cumulative residual stresses with each number of impacts not withstanding the static fatigue failure at long endurances have been ascribed for the composite failures under the repeated impact stresses.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Impact fatigue; static fatigue; residual stress; E-glass fibre; vinylester resin.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="Rita" isfellow="0">Roy, Rita</author>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Sarkar, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Bose" fname="N. R." isfellow="0">Bose, N. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Failure analysis of multiple delaminated composite plates due to bending and impact</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0143-0149</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The present work aims at the first ply failure analysis of laminated composite plates with arbitrarily located multiple delaminations subjected to transverse static load as well as impact. The theoretical formulation is based on a simple multiple delamination model. Conventional first order shear deformation is assumed using eight-noded isoparametric quadratic elements to develop the finite element analysis procedure. Composite plates are assumed to contain both single and multiple delaminations. For the case of impact, Newmark time integration algorithm is employed for solving the time dependent multiple equations of the plate and the impactor. Tsai-Wu failure criterion is used to check for failure of the laminate for both the cases. To investigate the first ply failure, parametric studies are made for different cases by varying the size and number of delaminations as well as the stacking sequences and boundary conditions.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Failure analysis; delaminated composite; bending; impact.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Parhi" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Parhi, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Bhattacharyya" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Bhattacharyya, S. K.</author>
					<author lname="Sinha" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Sinha, P. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Mechanical properties of very thin cover slip glass disk</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0151-0155</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The biaxial flexural strength, Young’s modulus, Vicker’s microhardness and fracture toughness data for very thin, commercial, soda-lime-silica cover slip glass (diameter, D-18 mm, thickness, T-0 3 mm; T/D 0 02) are reported here. The ball on ring biaxial flexure tests were conducted at room temperature as a function of the support ring diameter ( 10–20 mm) and cross head speed (0 1–10 mm min$^{–1}$). In addition, the Weibull modulus data were also determined. The Young’s modulus data was measured using a linear variable differential transformer (LVDT) from biaxial flexure tests and was checked out to be comparable to the data obtained independently from the ultrasonic time of flight measurement using a 15 MHz transducer. The microhardness data was obtained for the applied load range of 0 1–20 N. The fracture toughness ($K_{IC}$) data was obtained by the indentation technique at an applied load of 20 N.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Biaxial flexural strength; Young’s modulus; fracture toughness; Weibull modulus.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Seal" fname="A." isfellow="0">Seal, A.</author>
					<author lname="Dalui" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Dalui, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Banerjee" fname="M." isfellow="0">Banerjee, M.</author>
					<author lname="Mukhopadhyay" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Mukhopadhyay, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Phani" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">Phani, K. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Cracking phenomena in lithium-di-silicate glass ceramics</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0157-0160</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Lithium-di-silicate glass ceramic (Li$_2$O, SiO$_2$) with uniformly oriented crystals was placed on a Vickers indentation with extrusion axis horizontally parallel to the base axis. The material was rotated through 0$^\circ $– 90$^\circ $ and at each angle a 20 N load was applied to ascertain the crack path. It was observed that the crack length decreases and the crack deviates from its original path with increasing angle. The deviation of the crack was correlated with the component of the crack driving force and the theoretical strength of the aligned crystals at different angles.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Lithium-di-silicate; crystals; angle of rotation; crack driving force.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Banerjee" fname="Rajat" isfellow="0">Banerjee, Rajat</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Critical fatigue behaviour in brittle glasses</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0161-0164</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The dynamic fatigue fracture behaviour in different glasses under various sub-threshold loading conditions are analysed here employing an anomalous diffusion model. Critical dynamical behaviour in the time-to-fracture and the growth of the micro-crack sizes, similar to that observed in such materials in the case of quasi-static (“instantaneous”) failures for above-threshold conditions, are predicted and compared with some of the experimental observations in different glasses.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Fracture dynamics; critical behaviour; anomalous diffusion.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Banerjee" fname="Rajat" isfellow="0">Banerjee, Rajat</author>
					<author lname="Chakrabarti" fname="Bikas K." isfellow="0">Chakrabarti, Bikas K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Stress relaxation and estimation of activation volume in a commercial hard PZT piezoelectric ceramic</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0165-0167</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The stress relaxation of ferroelectric/piezoelectric material was studied using compression testing. The deformation was produced by the switching of ferroelectric domains. The internal stresses were estimated by decremental stress relaxation during unloading. The results were interpreted in terms of reversible and irreversible switching of the domains.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Ferroelectric/piezoelectric material; deformation; decremental stress relaxation; domains.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Cheng" fname="B. L." isfellow="0">Cheng, B. L.</author>
					<author lname="Reece" fname="M. J." isfellow="0">Reece, M. J.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of stress ratio and frequency on fatigue crack growth rate of 2618 aluminium alloy silicon carbide metal matrix composite</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0169-0171</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Effect of stress ratio and frequency on the fatigue crack propagation of 2618 aluminium alloy–silicon carbide composite were investigated at ambient temperature. With the first set of specimens, the fatigue crack growth rates were studied at three frequencies of 1 Hz, 5 Hz and 10 Hz at a stress ratio of 0 1 whereas the effects of stress ratios of 0 1, 0 25 and 0 50 were studied with the second set of specimens. The study showed that the fatigue crack propagation behaviour of this metal matrix composite was influenced to an appreciable extent by the stress ratio, but not by the fatigue frequencies used in this investigation.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Aluminium alloy–SiC composite; fatigue crack; stress ratio.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="Nirbhay" isfellow="0">Singh, Nirbhay</author>
					<author lname="Khelawan" fname="Ram" isfellow="0">Khelawan, Ram</author>
					<author lname="Mathur" fname="G. N." isfellow="0">Mathur, G. N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Particle fracture and plastic deformation in vanadium pentoxide powders induced by high energy vibrational ball-mill</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0173-0180</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>An X-ray powder profile analysis in vanadium pentoxide powder milled in a high energy vibrational ball-mill for different lengths of time (0–250 h), is presented. The strain and size induced broadening of the Bragg reflection for two different crystallographic directions ([001] and [100]) was determined by Warren–Averbach analysis using a pattern-decomposition method assuming a Pseudo–Voigt function. The deformation process caused a decrease in the crystallite size and a saturation of crystallite size of $\sim$ 10 nm was reached after severe milling. The initial stages of milling indicated a propensity of size-broadening due to fracture of the powder particles caused by repeated ball-to-powder impact whereas with increasing milling time microstrain broadening was predominant. WA analysis indicated significant plastic strain along with spatial confinement of the internal strain fields in the crystallite interfaces. Significant strain anisotropy was noticed in the different crystallographic directions. A near-isotropy in the crystallite size value was noticed for materials milled for 200 h and beyond. The column-length distribution function obtained from the size Fourier coefficients progressively narrowed down with the milling time.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>X-ray diffraction; ball-milling; plastic deformation; microstrain.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chatterjee" fname="Partha" isfellow="0">Chatterjee, Partha</author>
					<author lname="Gupta" fname="S. P. Sen" isfellow="0">Gupta, S. P. Sen</author>
					<author lname="Sen" fname="Suchitra" isfellow="0">Sen, Suchitra</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Study of indentation induced cracks in MoSi$_2$-reaction bonded SiC ceramics</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0181-0184</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>MoSi$_2$–RBSC composite samples were prepared by infiltration of Si–2 at.% Mo melt into a preform of commercial SiC and petroleum coke powder. The infiltrated sample had a density &gt; 92% of the theoretical density (TD) and microstructurally contained SiC, MoSi$_2$, residual Si and unreacted C. The material was tested for indentation fracture toughness at room temperature with a Vicker’s indenter and KIC was found to be 4 42 MPa m which is around 39% higher than the conventional RBSC material. Enhancement in indentation fracture toughness is explained in terms of bowing of propagating cracks through MoSi$_2$/SiC interface which is under high thermal stress arising from the thermal expansion mismatch between MoSi$_2$ and SiC.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Reaction bonded SiC; indentation hardness; fracture toughness.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chakrabarti" fname="O. P." isfellow="0">Chakrabarti, O. P.</author>
					<author lname="Das" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Das, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Mondal" fname="S." isfellow="0">Mondal, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Stereological characterization of crack path transitions in ceramic matrix composites</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0185-0190</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>All ceramic composites involve a mismatch in physical properties the extent of which differs from one composite to another. Mismatch in thermal expansion ( $a$) and elastic modulus ( $E$) is known to produce stresses that influence the path of a propagating crack. Thus, the relative effect of thermal and elastic mismatch on the crack path is expected to change with change in stress intensity. We propose that the crack path in ceramic composites should undergo a transition with the crack being strongly influenced by the thermal mismatch stresses at low stress intensity and elastic mismatch stresses at high stress intensities. Thus, a material in use under different applications each with its own loading conditions is expected to exhibit different crack propagation tendencies which may be reflected in the $v–K$ characteristics of the composite material. In the present work several model composites with different combinations of thermal and elastic mismatch have been considered. Cracks propagating at different sub-critical stress intensities (velocities) were generated by a novel indentation technique. Each indentation was performed at a constant displacement rate and a peak load. A range of displacement rates were used to produce cracks propagating at different velocities. The indentations were made using a Vickers indentor fitted in a universal mechanical testing machine. The crack paths in composites were quantified by stereological technique and the proposed theory was verified.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Elastic mismatch; subcritical stress intensity; Vicker’s indentor; $v–K$ characteristics.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bhargava" fname="Parag" isfellow="0">Bhargava, Parag</author>
					<author lname="Patterson" fname="B. R." isfellow="0">Patterson, B. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Densification and mechanical properties of mullite–SiC nanocomposites synthesized through sol–gel coated precursors</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0191-0195</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Mullite–SiC nanocomposites are synthesized by introducing surface modified sol–gel mullite coated SiC particles in the matrix and densification and associated microstructural features of such precursor are reported. Nanosize SiC (average size 180 nm) surface was first provided with a mullite precursor coating which was characterized by the X-ray analysis and TEM. An average coating thickness of 120 nm was obtained on the SiC particles. The green compacts obtained by cold isostatic pressing were sintered in the range 1500–1700$^\circ $C under pressureless sintering in the N$_2$ atmosphere. The percentage of the theoretical sintered density decreases with increase in SiC content. A maximum sintered density of 97% was achieved for mullite–5 vol.% SiC. The fractograph of the sintered composite showed a highly dense, fine grained microstructure with the SiC particles uniformly distributed along the grains as well as at the grain boundaries inside the mullite. The Vicker’s microhardness of mullite–5 vol.% SiC composite was measured as 1320 kg/mm$^2$ under an applied indentation load of 500 $g$. This value gradually decreased with an increase in SiC content.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>. Mullite–SiC nanocomposites; sol–gel; microstructure; Vicker’s microhardness.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Warrier" fname="K. G. K." isfellow="0">Warrier, K. G. K.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="G. M. Anil" isfellow="0">Kumar, G. M. Anil</author>
					<author lname="Ananthakumar" fname="S." isfellow="0">Ananthakumar, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Mechanical properties of glass polymer multilayer composite</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0197-0201</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The preliminary experimental studies on the comparative behaviour of the deformation processes involved in the failure of a commercial, 0 3 mm thick, 18 mm diameter soda–lime–silica glass disks ($G$) and multilayered glass disk–epoxy (GE) as well as glass disk–epoxy–$E$-glass fabric (GEF) composite structures are reported. The failure tests were conducted in a biaxial flexure at room temperature. The epoxy was a commercial resin and the $E$-glass fabric was also commercially obtained as a two-dimensional weave of $E$-glass fibres to an area density of about 242 g m$^{–2}$. The multilayered structures were developed by alternate placement of the glass and reinforcing layers by a hand lay-up technique followed by lamination at an appropriate temperature and pressure. Depending on the number of layers the volume fraction of reinforcement could be varied from about 0 20 for the GE system to about 0 50 for the GEF system. It was observed that the specific failure load (load per unit thickness) was enhanced from a value of about 60 N/mm obtained for the glass to a maximum value of about 100 N/mm for the GE composites and to a maximum of about 70 N/mm for the GEF composite system. Similarly, the displacements at failure ($d$) measured with a linear variable differential transformer (LVDT) were also found to be a strongly sensitive function of the type of reinforcement (GE or GEF) as well as the number of layers.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Multilayer glass–epoxy material; biaxial flexure; reinforcement.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Seal" fname="A." isfellow="0">Seal, A.</author>
					<author lname="Bose" fname="N. R." isfellow="0">Bose, N. R.</author>
					<author lname="Dalui" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">Dalui, S. K.</author>
					<author lname="Mukhopadhyay" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Mukhopadhyay, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Phani" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">Phani, K. K.</author>
					<author lname="Maiti" fname="H. S." isfellow="0">Maiti, H. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Crack propagation studies and bond coat properties in thermal barrier coatings under bending</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0203-0209</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Ceramic based thermal barrier coatings (TBC) are currently considered as a candidate material for advanced stationary gas turbine components. Crack propagation studies under bending are described that were performed on plasma sprayed ZrO$_2$, bonded by MCrAlY layer to Ni base superalloy. The crack propagation behaviour of the coatings at room temperature in as received and oxidized conditions revealed a linear growth of the cracks on the coating till the yield point of the super alloy was reached. High threshold load at the interface between the ceramic layer and the bond coat was required to propagate the crack further into the bond coat. Once the threshold load was surpassed the crack propagated into the brittle bond coat without an appreciable increase in the load. At temperatures of 800$^\circ $C the crack propagated only in the TBC (ceramic layer), as the ductile bond coat offered an attractive sink for the stress relaxation. Effects of bond coat oxidation on crack propagation in the interface region have been examined and are discussed.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Coating; thermal barrier; bond coat; superalloy; crack propagation; zirconia; plasma spraying; stress; strain; modulus.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ray" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Ray, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="N." isfellow="0">Roy, N.</author>
					<author lname="Godiwalla" fname="K. M." isfellow="0">Godiwalla, K. M.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Macroporous silica–alumina composites with mesoporous walls</title>
				<feature>Composites</feature>
				<page>0211-0214</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Macroporous silica–alumina composites with mesopores have been prepared by employing polymethylmethacrylate beads as templates in the presence of the cationic surfactant, N-cetyl-N,N,N-trimethylammonium bromide. The Si/Al ratio in the composites has been varied between 4 5 and 48 and the occurrence of mesopores has been verified by X-ray diffraction. The surface areas of the samples vary between 676 and 1038 m$^2$ $g^{–1}$, with the highest value in the sample with Si/Al = 48.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Macroporous materials; mesoporous materials; silica–alumina composites.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Gundiah" fname="Gautam" isfellow="0">Gundiah, Gautam</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>High temperature flow behaviour of SiC reinforced lithium aluminosilicate composites</title>
				<feature>Composites</feature>
				<page>0215-0218</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The compressive flow behaviour of lithium aluminosilicate (LAS) glass, with and without SiC particulate reinforcements, was studied. The LAS glass crystallized to $b$ spodumene during high-temperature testing. The flow behaviour of LAS glass changed from Newtonian to non-Newtonian due to the presence of crystalline phase. Further, with the addition of 40 vol.% SiC additions, the strain rate sensitivity of flow stress decreased. While the activation energy for flow in LAS was 300 kJ/mole, it increased to 995 kJ/mole with the addition of 40 vol.% SiC reinforcements.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Lithium aluminosilicate (LAS); SiC particulates; flow behaviour; compression.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Das" fname="Santanu" isfellow="0">Das, Santanu</author>
					<author lname="Murthy" fname="V. S. R." isfellow="0">Murthy, V. S. R.</author>
					<author lname="Murty" fname="G. S." isfellow="0">Murty, G. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of filler addition on the compressive and impact properties of glass fibre reinforced epoxy</title>
				<feature>Composites</feature>
				<page>0219-0223</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Flyash is incorporated in glass fibre reinforced epoxies to study their response to the filler addition. Low cost of flyash can reduce the overall cost of the component. Only very low volume fractions of filler are investigated in the present study. To obtain further clarification of the observed phenomenon, another abundantly available low cost material, calcium carbonate is incorporated in one set of the specimens. Compressive strength of the material is found to decrease, whereas steep increase in impact strength is observed by introduction of very small quantity of fillers. Specimens containing calcium carbonate are tested for impact properties only. Effect of specimen aspect ratio on the compressive strength values is also studied by testing specimens of three different aspect ratios. Scanning electron microscopic observations are taken to develop a better understanding of the phenomena taking place in the material system at microscopic level.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Fillers; flyash; compression test; impact test; fibre reinforced epoxies.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Gupta" fname="Nikhil" isfellow="0">Gupta, Nikhil</author>
					<author lname="Brar" fname="Balraj Singh" isfellow="0">Brar, Balraj Singh</author>
					<author lname="Woldesenbet" fname="Eyassu" isfellow="0">Woldesenbet, Eyassu</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A detailed model for defect concentration and dopant activation in GaAs</title>
				<feature>Semiconductors</feature>
				<page>0225-0229</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Defects in semi-insulating (SI) GaAs are especially critical in determining the properties of devices in which dopants are introduced by ion-implantation. The defects in GaAs are native to the material and their concentrations are subsequently modified after ion-implantation and annealing. In this work, we have extended the existing models in the literature by incorporating a large set of defects and using the most recent values for formation energies of these defects. The model includes eight types of point defects, the vacancy of Ga and As, their antisites and interstitials of Ga and As on both sub-lattices, along with carbon related defects always present in SI–GaAs. We have also included Si and related defects when this element is implanted as an $n$-type dopant. All these defects are considered in several charge states allowed by their stability conditions. The model assumes thermodynamic equilibrium between the point defects at an anneal temperature. Then the GaAs wafer is quenched so that the number of defects remain the same as those at the anneal temperature, but redistribution of charges occurs in various charge states. We find that the defect concentrations are extremely sensitive to the crystal stoichiometry, and good agreement with experimental data is shown. However, when we calculate the dopant activation in implanted GaAs, the quantitative agreement with experiments is not adequate. This discrepancy is explained on the basis of available formation energies for the defects.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Semi-insulating; GaAs; dopant activation; defects.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Deepak" fname="" isfellow="0">Deepak</author>
					<author lname="Lakshminarayana" fname="N." isfellow="0">Lakshminarayana, N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Study of fatigue behaviour of 7475 aluminium alloy</title>
				<feature>Alloys</feature>
				<page>0231-0236</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Fatigue properties of a thermomechanically treated 7475 aluminium alloy have been studied in the present investigation. The alloy exhibited superior fatigue life compared to conventional structural aluminium alloys and comparable stage II crack growth rate. It was also noticed that the fatigue crack initiated from a surface grain and the crack extension was dominated by ductile striations. Analysis also revealed that this alloy possessed fracture toughness and tensile properties superior to that noticed with other structural aluminium alloys. Therefore the use of this alloy can safely reduce the overall weight of the aircraft.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>7475 Aluminium alloy; fatigue life; fatigue crack growth; cyclic cleavage; ductile striations.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Verma" fname="B. B." isfellow="0">Verma, B. B.</author>
					<author lname="Atkinsonm" fname="J. D." isfellow="0">Atkinsonm, J. D.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="M." isfellow="0">Kumar, M.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Catalytic activity of polymer-bound Ru(III)–EDTA complex</title>
				<feature>Catalysts</feature>
				<page>0237-0241</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Chloromethylated styrene–divinylbenzene copolymer was chemically modified with ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid ligand. Catalytically active polymer containing Ru(III) moieties were synthesized from this polymeric ligand. They were characterized using FTIR, UV-vis, SEM, ESR and TGA. Other physico-chemical properties such as bulk density, surface area, moisture content and swelling behaviour in different solvents were also studied. The polymer bound complex was used to study hydrogenation of 1-hexene to $n$-hexane under mild conditions. Influence of [1-hexene], [catalyst], temperature and nature of the solvent on the rate of the reaction was investigated. A rate expression is proposed based on the observed initial rate data. Recycling efficiency of the catalyst has also been studied.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Catalytic hydrogenation; energy of activation for catalytic hydrogenation; kinetics of hydrogenation of 1-hexene; polymer-bound catalyst; polymer-bound Ru(III)–EDTA complex; study of life cycle of polymer-bound catalyst.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Dalal" fname="Mahesh K." isfellow="0">Dalal, Mahesh K.</author>
					<author lname="Ram" fname="R. N." isfellow="0">Ram, R. N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Studies on compensating valency substituted BaTi$_{(1-x)}$Mn$_{x/2}$Nb$_{x/2}$O$_3$ ceramics</title>
				<feature>Ferroelectric Materials</feature>
				<page>0243-0248</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The paper reports investigations of relative permittivity, $e_r$, electrical conductivity, $s$, saturation polarization, $P_s$, infrared absorption and structural properties of compensating valency substituted BaTiO$_3$. The compositions investigated are BaTi$_{(1–x)}$Mn$_{x/2}$Nb$_{x/2}$O$_3$ for $x$ = 0 00; 0 025; 0 05; 0 1; 0 2; 0 4. The compositions for $x$ &lt; 0 1 are observed to be ferroelectric and the transition temperature and value of er are observed to decrease as concentration of substitution is increased. The dielectric investigations are carried out on two sets of samples (i) as sintered and (ii) annealed. Annealing is observed to improve quality factor $‘Q’$ of the materials with a consequent reduction in the $e_r$. The observations on $e_r$ and saturation polarization suggest that additional material engineering efforts are required to improve the material properties.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Valence compensating ceramic; barium titanate; dielectric constant; electron-transport properties; saturation polarization.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kokare" fname="S. R." isfellow="0">Kokare, S. R.</author>
					<author lname="Pawar" fname="S. A." isfellow="0">Pawar, S. A.</author>
					<author lname="Padal" fname="N. T." isfellow="0">Padal, N. T.</author>
					<author lname="Joshi" fname="P. B." isfellow="0">Joshi, P. B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Thermal behaviour of strontium tartrate single crystals grown in gel</title>
				<feature>Crystal Growth</feature>
				<page>0249-0252</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>Thermal behaviour of strontium tartrate crystals grown with the aid of sodium metasilicate gel is investigated using thermogravimetry (TG) and differential thermal analysis (DTA). Effect of magnetic field and dopant $(Pb)^{2+}$ on the crystal stability is also studied using thermal analysis. This study reveals that water molecules are locked up in the lattice with different strengths in the grown crystals.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Strontium tartrate; dopant; effect of magnetic field; thermal behaviour.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rahimkutty" fname="M. H." isfellow="0">Rahimkutty, M. H.</author>
					<author lname="Babu" fname="K. Rajendra" isfellow="0">Babu, K. Rajendra</author>
					<author lname="Pillai" fname="K. Sreedharan" isfellow="0">Pillai, K. Sreedharan</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="M. R. Sudarsana" isfellow="0">Kumar, M. R. Sudarsana</author>
					<author lname="Nair" fname="C. M. K." isfellow="0">Nair, C. M. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Analysis of corrosive environmental factors of seabed sediment</title>
				<feature>Corrosion of Materials</feature>
				<page>0253-0255</page>
				<abstract>
                    <p>The corrosivity of seabed sediment at spots at different distances from seashore was studied based on $in$ $situ$ investigations in the northern sea area of the Yellow River mouth. The results show that there is close relation between distance from seashore and corrosivity of seabed sediment.</p>
                </abstract>
				<keywords>Seabed sediment; corrosion; environmental factors.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Baorong" fname="Hou" isfellow="0">Baorong, Hou</author>
					<author lname="Huyuan" fname="Sun" isfellow="0">Huyuan, Sun</author>
					<author lname="Jinglei" fname="Zhang" isfellow="0">Jinglei, Zhang</author>
					<author lname="Gongyu" fname="Guo" isfellow="0">Gongyu, Guo</author>
					<author lname="Jinming" fname="Song" isfellow="0">Jinming, Song</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
</bms>
