<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cs SYSTEM "journal.dtd">

<journal title="Journal of Astrophysics and Astronomy" short="J. Astrophys. Astr." mnemonic="jaa">
	<volume vnum="021">
		<issue inum="01-02" month="06" year="2000">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A Measurement of the Cosmic Microwave Background Temperature at 1280MHz</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0017</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The absolute temperature of the cosmic microwave back-ground (CMB) has been measured at a frequency of 1280 MHz. The observation was made with a modified version of the L-band receiver used in the Giant Metre wavelength Radio Telescope (GMRT): the feed horn was replaced by a corrugated plate and the receiver was placed on the ground, directed at zenith, and shielded from ground radiation by an aluminium screen with corrugated edges. Novel techniques have been adopted for</p>
					<ul>
						<li>reducing and cancelling unwanted contributions to the system temperature of the receiver and</li>
						<li>calibrating the contributions from the feed assembly and receiver.</li>
					</ul>
					<p>The thermodynamic temperature of the CMB is estimated to be $3.45 \pm 0.78$ K.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmic microwave background;cosmology: observations.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Raghunathan">A. Raghunathan</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, C. V. Raman Avenue, Bangalore - 560080, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ravi" last="Subrahmanyan">Ravi Subrahmanyan</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, C. V. Raman Avenue, Bangalore - 560080, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Present address: Australia Telescope National Facility, CSIRO, Locked bag 194, Narrabri, NSW, Australia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-04-18</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-05-11</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Nature of the Background Ultraviolet Radiation Field at High Redshifts</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0019-0027</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have tried to determine the flux of the ultraviolet background radiation field from the column density ratios of various ions in several absorption systems observed in the spectra of QSOs. We find that in most cases the flux is considerably higher than what has been estimated to be contributed by the AGNs. The excess flux could originate locally in hot stars. In a few cases we have been able to show that such galactic flux can only contribute a part of the total required flux. The results suggest that the background gets a significant contribution from an unseen QSO population.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Quasars: absorption lines;diffuse radiation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Archana" last="Samantaray">Archana Samantaray</name>
						<affiliation>Physics Department, Utkal University, Bhubaneswar, 751 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Pushpa" last="Khare">Pushpa Khare</name>
						<affiliation>Physics Department, Utkal University, Bhubaneswar, 751 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1999-20-09</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-02-09</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>X-ray Observation of XTE J2012+381 during the 1998 Outburst</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0029-0038</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The outburst of X-ray transient source XTE J2012+381 was detected by the RXTE All-Sky Monitor on 1998 May 24th. Following the outburst, X-ray observations of the source were made in the 2-18keV energy band with the Pointed Proportional Counters of the Indian X-ray Astronomy Experiment (IXAE) on-board the Indian satellite IRS-P3 during 1998 June 2nd-10th. The X-ray flux of the source in the main outburst decreased exponentially during the period of observation. No large amplitude short-term variability in the intensity is detected from the source. The power density spectrum obtained from the timing analysis of the data shows no indication of any quasi-periodic oscillations in 0.002-0.5 Hz band. The hardness ratio i.e. the ratio of counts in 6-18 keV to 2-6 keV band, indicates that the X-ray spectrum is soft with spectral index $\gt$ 2. From the similarities of the X-ray properties with those of other black hole transients, we conclude that the X-ray transient XTE J2012+381 is likely to be a black hole.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Accretion, accretion disks;black hole physics;X-rays: stars—stars: individual;XTE J2012+381.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Naik">S. Naik</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P. C." last="Agrawal">P. C. Agrawal</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B." last="Paul">B. Paul</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Present Address: Institute of Space and Astronautical Science, 3-1-1 Yoshinodai, Sagamihara, Kanagawa 229-8510, Japan.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. R." last="Rao">A. R. Rao</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Seetha">S. Seetha</name>
						<affiliation>ISRO Satellite Center, Airport Road, Vimanapura P.O., Bangalore 560017, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Κ." last="Kasturirangan">Κ. Kasturirangan</name>
						<affiliation>ISRO Satellite Center, Airport Road, Vimanapura P.O., Bangalore 560017, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1999-10-22</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-02-09</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>X-ray Measurements of Black Hole X-ray Binary Source GRS 1915+105 and the Evolution of Hard X-ray Spectrum</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0039-0052</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report the spectral measurement of GRS 1915+105 in the hard X-ray energy band of 20-140keV. The observations were made on March 30th, 1997 during a quiescent phase of the source. We discuss the mechanism of emission of hard X-ray photons and the evolution of the spectrum by comparing the data with earlier measurements and an axiomatic model for the X-ray source.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Accretion, accretion disks;X-rays: stars—Black hole candidates, binary sources: individual;GRS 1915+105.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Manchanda">R. K. Manchanda</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1999-12-28</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-02-09</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Scale Length of the Galactic Thin Disk</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0053-0059</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This paper presents an analysis of the first 2MASS (The Two Micron All Sky Survey) sampler data as observed at lower Galactic latitude in our Galaxy. These new near-infrared data provide insight into the structure of the thin disk of our Galaxy, The interpretation of star counts and color distributions of stars in the near-infrared with the synthetic stellar population model, gives strong evidence that the Galactic thin disk density scale length, $h_{R}$, is rather short ($2.7 \pm 0.1$ kpc).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxy: stellar content;Galaxy: structure.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D. Κ." last="Ojha">D. Κ. Ojha</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Dr. Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1999-09-14</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-02-09</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Stellar Sources in the ISOGAL Inner Galactic Bulge Field $(l=0^{0},b=-1^{0})$</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0077-0090</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>ISOGAL is a survey at 7 and 15 μm with ISOCAM of the inner galactic disk and bulge of our Galaxy. The survey covers $\sim 22$ deg$^{2}$ in selected areas of the central $l=\pm 30$ degree of the inner Galaxy. In this paper, we report the study of a small ISOGAL field in the inner galactic bulge ($l = 0^{0},b = -1^{0}$, area = 0.033deg$^{2}$). Using the multicolor near-infrared data (IJK$_{s}$) of DENIS (DEep Near Infrared Southern Sky Survey) and mid-infrared ISOGAL data, we discuss the nature of the ISOGAL sources. The various color-color and color-magnitude diagrams are discussed in the paper. While most of the detected sources are red giants (RGB tip stars), a few of them show an excess in J-K$_{s}$ and K$_{s}$-[15] colors with respect to the red giant sequence. Most of them are probably AGB stars with large mass-loss rates.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Stars: AGB and post-AGB;stars: circumstellar matter;stars: mass- loss - dust - infrared: stars;Galaxy: bulge.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D. Κ." last="Ojha">D. Κ. Ojha</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Omont">A. Omont</name>
						<affiliation>Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, CNRS, 98 bis, Bd Arago, F-75014, Paris, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Ganesh">S. Ganesh</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Navrangpura, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Simon">G. Simon</name>
						<affiliation>DASGAL, CNRS UMR 8633, Observatoire de Paris, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ." last="Schultheis">Μ. Schultheis</name>
						<affiliation>Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, CNRS, 98 bis, Bd Arago, F-75014, Paris, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-03-27</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-05-11</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Porous and Fluffy Grains in the Regions of Anomalous Extinction</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0091-0099</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>It has long been established that the ratio of total to selective extinction is anomalously large (³ 5) in certain regions of the interstellar medium. In these regions of anomalous extinction the dust grains are likely to be irregular in shape and fluffy in structure. Using discrete dipole approximation (DDA) we calculate the extinction for porous and fluffy grains. We apply DDA first to solid spheroidal particles assumed to be made of a certain (large) number of dipoles. Then we systematically reduce the number of dipoles to model the porous grains. The aggregates of these particles are suggested to form the fluffy grains. We study the extinction for these particles as a function of grain size, porosity and wavelength. We apply these calculations to interpret the observed extinction data in the regions of star formation (e.g. the Orion complex).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Interstellar dust;extinction;porous grains;anomalous extinction.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D. B." last="Vaidya">D. B. Vaidya</name>
						<affiliation>Gujarat College, Ahmedabad 380 006, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. G." last="Anandarao">B. G. Anandarao</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. N." last="Desai">J. N. Desai</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Gupta">R. Gupta</name>
						<affiliation>Inter-University Centre for Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, Pune 411007, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1997-12-24</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-01-29</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03-04" month="09-12" year="2000">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Kodaikanal Observatory – A Historical Account</title>
				<feature>Special issue on 'Cyclical Evolution of Solar Magnetic Fields: Advances in Theory and Observations'</feature>
				<page>0103-0106</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Foreword</title>
				<feature>Special issue on 'Cyclical Evolution of Solar Magnetic Fields: Advances in Theory and Observations'</feature>
				<page>0111-0111</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>New Initiatives for Synoptic Observations</title>
				<feature>Session II – Synoptic Observations</feature>
				<page>0127-0134</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Several new synoptic facilities for long-term studies of the Sun will become operational within the next few years. This paper summarizes information on some of these projects, in particular GONG+, ISOON, GOES/SXI, and SOLIS. SOLIS, the Synoptic Optical Long-Term Investigations of the Sun, is currently being built by the National Solar Observatory and will become operational in 2001. It consists of a 50-cm vector spectromagnetograph, a 14-cm full-disk patrol, and an 8-mm sunas-a-star spectrometer.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>GONG;ISOON;SXI;SOLIS.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="C. U." last="Keller">C. U. Keller</name>
						<affiliation>National Solar Observatory, 950 N. Cherry Ave., Tucson, AZ 85719, USA.</affiliation>
						<email>keller@noao.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Introduction to the Solar Space Telescope</title>
				<feature>Session II – Synoptic Observations</feature>
				<page>0141-0147</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The design of the space solar telescope (SST) (phase B) has been completed. The manufacturing is under development. At the end of 2000, it will be assembled. The basic aspect will be introduced in this paper.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Space telescopes</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Ai">G. Ai</name>
						<affiliation>Beijing Astronomical Observatory / National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100012, China.</affiliation>
						<email>aigx@sun10. .bao.ac.co,in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Jin">S. Jin</name>
						<affiliation>Beijing Astronomical Observatory / National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100012, China.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Wang">S. Wang</name>
						<affiliation>Beijing Astronomical Observatory / National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100012, China.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B." last="Ye">B. Ye</name>
						<affiliation>Beijing Astronomical Observatory / National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100012, China.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Yang"></name>
						<affiliation>Beijing Astronomical Observatory / National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100012, China.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Results from Kodaikanal Synoptic Observations</title>
				<feature>Session II – Synoptic Observations</feature>
				<page>0149-0153</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The synoptic observations of Kodaikanal form one of the longest unbroken solar data from the beginning of the 20th century to the present day, and consists of the white light and monochromatic images of the sun. In this review, I shall discuss the results of the investigations in two areas using these data:</p> 
					<ol type="roman">
						<li>Tilt angles of the magnetic axes of bipolar spot groups, and</li> 
						<li>structure and dynamics of large scale unipolar magnetic regions on the solar surface.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>The observed properties and patterns of behaviour of the tilt angles can be used as effective diagnostics to infer the physical conditions in the subsurface layers of the sun, and thus get an insight into the physical effects that act on the rising magnetic flux tubes during their journey through the convection zone to the surface.</p>
					<p>The second topic of discussion here, namely, the studies of the dynamics of unipolar regions over several solar cycles, show that the global solar activity has a high latitude component which manifests in the form of polar faculae, in addition to the well known sunspot activity at the middle and low latitudes. This raises the question about the origin of this high latitude component.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Synoptic observations;tilt angles of sunspot groups;global solar cycle.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Κ. R." last="Sivaraman">Κ. R. Sivaraman</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034</affiliation>
						<email>siva@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Sunspot Groups as Tracers of Sub-Surface Processes</title>
				<feature>Session III – Sunspots &amp; Solar Cycle</feature>
				<page>0155-0160</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Data on sunspot groups have been quite useful for obtaining clues to several processes on global and local scales within the sun which lead to emergence of toroidal magnetic flux above the sun's surface. I present here a report on such studies carried out at Indian Institute of Astrophysics during the last decade or so.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sunspot group;solar cycle;solar rotation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ. Η." last="Gokhale">Μ. Η. Gokhale</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034, India</affiliation>
						<email>gokhale@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Large-Scale Magnetic Field and Sunspot Cycles</title>
				<feature>Session III – Sunspots &amp; Solar Cycle</feature>
				<page>0161-0162</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Sun: magnetic field;sunspots;solar cycle.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="V. I." last="Makarov">V. I. Makarov</name>
						<affiliation>Kislovodsk Solar Station of the Pulkovo Observatory, Kislovodsk 357700, P.O. Box 145, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email>makarov@gao.spb.ru</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. G." last="Tlatov">A. G. Tlatov</name>
						<affiliation>Kislovodsk Solar Station of the Pulkovo Observatory, Kislovodsk 357700, P.O. Box 145, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Cyclic Evolution of Sunspots: Gleaning New Results from Old Data</title>
				<feature>Session III – Sunspots &amp; Solar Cycle</feature>
				<page>0163-0165</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The records of sunspot number, sunspot areas and sunspot locations gathered over the centuries by various observatories are reanalysed with the aim of finding as yet undiscovered connections between the different parameters of the sunspot cycle and the butterfly diagram. Preliminary results of such interrelationships are presented.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sunspots;solar dynamo.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. Κ." last="Solanki">S. Κ. Solanki</name>
						<affiliation>Max-Planck-Institut fur Aeronomie, D-37191 Katlenburg-Lindau, Germany.</affiliation>
						<email>solanki@linmpi.mpg.de</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ." last="Fligge">Μ. Fligge</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Astronomy, ΕΤΗ Zentrum, 8092 Zurich, Switzerland.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Pulkkinen">P. Pulkkinen</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Astronomy, University of Helsinki, Finland.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Hoyng">P. Hoyng</name>
						<affiliation>SRON, Utrecht, The Netherlands</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>22-Year Periodicity in the Solar Differential Rotation</title>
				<feature>Session III – Sunspots &amp; Solar Cycle</feature>
				<page>0167-0170</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Using the data on sunspot groups compiled during 1879-1975, we determined variations in the differential rotation coefficients $A$ and $Β$ during the solar cycle. The variation in the equatorial rotation rate $A$ is found to be significant only in the odd numbered cycles, with an amplitude $\sim 0.01$ $\mu$rads$^{-1}$. There exists a good anticorrelation between the variations of the differential rotation rate $Β$ derived from the odd and even numbered cycles, suggesting existence of a '22-year' periodicity in $B$. The amplitude of the variation of $Β$ is $\sim 0.05$ $\mu$ rad s$^{-1}$.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sunspot group;solar cycle;solar rotation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J." last="Javaraiah">J. Javaraiah</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034,. India</affiliation>
						<email>jj@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Is a Sunspot in Static or Dynamic Equilibrium?</title>
				<feature>Session III – Sunspots &amp; Solar Cycle</feature>
				<page>0171-0172</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Sun;sunspot;structure.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Venkatakrishnan">P. Venkatakrishnan</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, Post Box No. 198, Badi Road, Udaipur 313 001, India</affiliation>
						<email>pvk@plume.uso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Periodic Variation of the North-South Asymmetry of Solar Activity Phenomena</title>
				<feature>Session III – Sunspots &amp; Solar Cycle</feature>
				<page>0173-0176</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report here a study of various solar activity phenomena occurring in both north and south hemispheres of the Sun during solar cycles 8-23. In the study we have used sunspot data for the period 1832—1976, flare index data for the period 1936-1993, H$\alpha$ flare data 1993-1998 and solar active prominences data for the period 1957-1998. Earlier Verma reported long-term cyclic period in N-S asymmetry and also that the N-S asymmetry of solar activity phenomena during solar cycles 21, 22, 23 and 24 will be south dominated and the N-S asymmetry will shift to north hemisphere in solar cycle 25. The present study shows that the N-S asymmetry during solar cycles 22 and 23 are southern dominated as suggested by Verma.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sunspots;solar activity;solar cycles.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="V. Κ." last="Verma">V. Κ. Verma</name>
						<affiliation>U. P. State Observatory, Manora Peak, Naini Tal, India 263129.</affiliation>
						<email>verma@upso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Solar Filaments as Tracers of Subsurface Processes</title>
				<feature>Session IV – Filaments &amp; Coronal Structures</feature>
				<page>0177-0183</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Solar filaments are discussed in terms of two contrasting paradigms. The standard paradigm is that filaments are formed by condensation of coronal plasma into magnetic fields that are twisted or dimpled as a consequence of motions of the fields' sources in the photo-sphere. According to a new paradigm, filaments form in rising, twisted flux ropes and are a necessary intermediate stage in the transfer to interplanetary space of dynamo-generated magnetic flux. It is argued that the accumulation of magnetic helicity in filaments and their coronal surroundings leads to filament eruptions and coronal mass ejections. These ejections relieve the Sun of the flux generated by the dynamo and make way for the flux of the next cycle.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solar filaments;solar dynamo;magnetic fields.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D. M." last="Rust">D. M. Rust</name>
						<affiliation>Applied Physics Laboratoiy, Johns Hopkins University, 11100 Johns Hopkins Road, Laurel, MD 20723, USA.</affiliation>
						<email>david.rust@jhuapl.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Coronal Structures as Tracers of Sub-Surface Processes</title>
				<feature>Session IV – Filaments &amp; Coronal Structures</feature>
				<page>0185-0192</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The solar corona - one of the most spectacular celestial shows and yet one of the most challenging puzzles - exhibits a spectrum of structures related to both the quiet Sun and active regions. In spite of dramatic differences in appearance and physical processes, all these structures share a common origin: they are all related to the solar magnetic field. The origin of the field is beneath the turbulent convection zone, where the magnetic field is not a master but a slave, and one can wonder how much the coronal magnetic field "remembers" its dynamo origin. Surprisingly, it does. We will describe several observational phenomena that indicate a close relationship between coronal and sub-photospheric processes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun—solar corona;magnetic field;helicity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Alexei A." last="PevtSOV">Alexei A. PevtSOV</name>
						<affiliation>Montana State University, Bozeman, MT 59717, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email>pevtsov@physics.montana.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Richard C." last="Canfield">Richard C. Canfield</name>
						<affiliation>Montana State University, Bozeman, MT 59717, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Polar Magnetic Field Reversals of the Sun in Maunder Minimum</title>
				<feature>Session IV – Filaments &amp; Coronal Structures</feature>
				<page>0193-0196</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A possible scenario of polar magnetic field reversal of the Sun during the Maunder Minimum (1645-1715) is discussed using data of magnetic field reversals of the Sun for 1880-1991 and the $^{14}$C content variations in the bi-annual rings of the pine-trees in 1600-1730 yrs.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: cycle;magnetic field;maunder minimum.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="V. I." last="Makarov">V. I. Makarov</name>
						<affiliation>Kislovodsk Solar Station of the Pulkovo Observatory, •Kislovodsk 357700, P.O. Box 145, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email>makarov@gao.spb.ru</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. G." last="Tlatov">A. G. Tlatov</name>
						<affiliation>Kislovodsk Solar Station of the Pulkovo Observatory, •Kislovodsk 357700, P.O. Box 145, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Periodic Variations in the Coronal Green Line Intensity and their Connection with the White-light Coronal Structures</title>
				<feature>Session IV – Filaments &amp; Coronal Structures</feature>
				<page>0197-0200</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present an analysis of short time-scale intensity variations in the coronal green line as obtained with high time resolution observations. The observed data can be divided into two groups. The first one shows periodic intensity variations with a period of 5 min. the second one does not show any significant intensity variations. We studied the relation between regions of coronal intensity oscillations and the shape of whitelight coronal structures. We found that the coronal green-line oscillations occur mainly in regions where open white-light coronal structures are located.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun;solar corona;5 min variations;solar activity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Milan" last="Minarovjech">Milan Minarovjech</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Institute of the Slovak Academy of Sciences, 05960 Tatranska Lomnica, Slovak Republic.</affiliation>
						<email>milanmin@ta3.sk</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Milan" last="Rybansky">Milan Rybansky</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Institute of the Slovak Academy of Sciences, 05960 Tatranska Lomnica, Slovak Republic.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Vojtech" last="Rusin">Vojtech Rusin</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Institute of the Slovak Academy of Sciences, 05960 Tatranska Lomnica, Slovak Republic.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Long-term Cyclic Variations of Prominences, Green and Red Coronae over Solar Cycles</title>
				<feature>Session IV – Filaments &amp; Coronal Structures</feature>
				<page>0201-0204</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Long-term cyclic variations in the distribution of prominences and intensities of green (530.3 nm) and red (637.4 nm) coronal emission lines over solar cycles 18-23 are presented. Polar prominence branches will reach the poles at different epochs in cycle 23: the north branch at the beginning in 2002 and the south branch a year later (2003), respectively. The local maxima of intensities in the green line show both poleward- and equatorward-migrating branches. The poleward branches will reach the poles around' cycle maxima like prominences, while the equatorward branches show a duration of 18 years and will end in cycle minima (2007). The red corona shows mostly equatorward branches. The possibility that these branches begin to develop at high latitudes in the preceding cycles cannot be excluded.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Prominences;emission corona;cycle activity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Vojtech" last="Rusin">Vojtech Rusin</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical institute, Slovak Academy of Sciences, 059 60 Tatranska Lomnica, Slovak Republic</affiliation>
						<email>vrusin@ta3.sk</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Milan" last="Minarovjech">Milan Minarovjech</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical institute, Slovak Academy of Sciences, 059 60 Tatranska Lomnica, Slovak Republic</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Milan" last="Rybansky">Milan Rybansky</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical institute, Slovak Academy of Sciences, 059 60 Tatranska Lomnica, Slovak Republic</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Large-scale Motion of Solar Filaments</title>
				<feature>Session IV – Filaments &amp; Coronal Structures</feature>
				<page>0205-0208</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Precise measurements of heliographic position of solar filaments were used for determination of the proper motion of solar filaments on the time-scale of days. The filaments have a tendency to make a shaking or waving of the external structure and to make a general movement of whole filament body, coinciding with the transport of the magnetic flux in the photosphere. The velocity scatter of individual measured points is about one order higher than the accuracy of measurements.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun;filaments;horizontal motions.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Pavel" last="Ambrož">Pavel Ambrož</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Institute of the Acad. Sci. of the Czech Republic, CZ-25165 Ondřejov, The Czech Republic.</affiliation>
						<email>pambroz@asu.cas.cz</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Alfred" last="Schroll">Alfred Schroll</name>
						<affiliation>Kanzelhöehe Solar Observatory of the University of Graz, A-9521 Treffen, Austria.</affiliation>
						<email>schroll@solobskh.ac.at</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Magnetic Sun from Different Views: A Comparison of the Mean and Background Magnetic Field Observations made in Different Observatories and in Different Spectral Lines</title>
				<feature>Session IV – Filaments &amp; Coronal Structures</feature>
				<page>0209-0212</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A comparison is made of observational data on the mean magnetic field of the Sun from several observatories (a selection of published information and new measurements). Results of correlation and regression analyses of observations of background magnetic fields at the STOP telescope of the Sayan solar observatory in different spectral lines are also presented. Results obtained furnish an opportunity to obtain more unbiased information about large-scale magnetic fields of the Sun and, in particular, about manifestations of strong (kilogauss) magnetic fields in them.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: magnetic fields;magnetographs.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="M. L." last="Demidov">M. L. Demidov</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Solar-Terrestrial Physics, Irkutsk, P.O.Box 4026, 664033, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email>demid@iszf.irk.ru</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Vector Magnetic Fields, Sub-surface Stresses and Evolution of Magnetic Helicity</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0213-0220</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Observations of the strength and spatial distribution of vector magnetic fields in active regions have revealed several fundamental properties of the twist of their magnetic fields. First, the handedness of this twist obeys a hemispheric rule: left-handed in the northern hemisphere, right-handed in the southern. Second, the rule is weak; active regions often disobey it. It is statistically valid only in a large ensemble. Third, the rule itself, and the amplitude of the scatter about the rule, are quantitatively consistent with twisting of fields by turbulence as flux tubes buoy up through the convection zone. Fourth, there is considerable spatial variation of twist within active regions. However, relaxation to a linear force-free state, which has been documented amply in laboratory plasmas, is not observed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Magnetic fields;currents;magnetic helicity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Richard" last="Canfield">Richard Canfield</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Montana State University, Bozeman, Montana 59717-3840.</affiliation>
						<email>canfield@physics.montana.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Alexei" last="Pevtsov">Alexei Pevtsov</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Montana State University, Bozeman, Montana 59717-3840.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Cyclical Variability of Prominences, CMEs and Flares</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0221-0227</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Solar flares, prominences and CMEs are well known manifestations of solar activity. For many years, qualitative studies were made about the cyclical behaviour of such phenomena. Nowadays, more quantitative studies have been undertaken with the aim to understand the solar cycle dependence of such phenomena as well as peculiar behaviour, such as asymmetries and periodicities, occurring within the solar cycle. Here, we plan to review the more recent research concerning all these topics.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: Activity;prominences;flares;CMEs.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. L." last="Ballester">J. L. Ballester</name>
						<affiliation>Departament de Fisica, Universitat de les Illes Balears. E-07071 Palma de Mallorca, Espana.</affiliation>
						<email>dfsjlb0@ps,uib.es</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Analysis of the 9th November 1990 flare</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0229-0232</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this paper we present complete two-dimensional measurements of the observed brightness of the 9th November 1990 $H\alpha$ flare, using a PDS microdensitometer scanner and image processing software MIDAS. The resulting isophotal contour maps, were used to describe morphological-cum-temporal behaviour of the flare and also the kernels of the flare. Correlation of the $H\alpha$ flare with SXR and MW radiations were also studied.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>$H\alpha$ flare;isophotal contour maps;flare kernels.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Anita" last="Joshi">Anita Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>U. P. State Observatory, Manora Peak, Naini Tal 263129, India.</affiliation>
						<email>anita@upso.emet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Wahab" last="Uddin">Wahab Uddin</name>
						<affiliation>U. P. State Observatory, Manora Peak, Naini Tal 263129, India.</affiliation>
						<email>wahab@upso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A Rapidly Evolving Active Region NOAA 8032 observed on April 15th, 1997</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0233-0236</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The active region NOAA 8032 of April 15, 1997 was observed to evolve rapidly. The GOES X-ray data showed a number of sub-flares and two C-class flares during the 8-9 hours of its evolution. The magnetic evolution of this region is studied to ascertain its role in flare production. Large changes were observed in magnetic field configuration due to the emergence of new magnetic flux regions (EFR). Most of the new emergence occured very close to the existing magnetic regions, which resulted in strong magnetic field gradients in this region. EFR driven reconnection of the field lines and subsequent flux cancellation might be the reason for the continuous occurrence of sub-flares and other related activities.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Shibu K." last="Mathew">Shibu K. Mathew</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, P. O. Box: 198, Udaipur 313 004, India</affiliation>
						<email>shibu@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ashok" last="Ambastha">Ashok Ambastha</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, P. O. Box: 198, Udaipur 313 004, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Low Frequency Radio Emission from the 'Quiet' Sun</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0237-0240</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present observations of the 'quiet' Sun close to the recent solar minimum (Cycle 22), with the Gauribidanur radioheliograph. Our main conclusion is that coronal streamers also influence the observed radio brightness temperature.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun;corona;radio observations;streamers;scattering.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Ramesh">R. Ramesh</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email>ramesh@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Stokes Polarimetry at the Kodaikanal Tower Tunnel Telescope</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0241-0244</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A Stokes Polarimeter has been developed using a masked CCD arrangement for the measurement of the vector magnetic field of sunspots. Charge shifting within the CCD is used to record near simultaneous orthogonal polarisation. The testing of the Stokes Polarimeter and the behavior of the integrated system combined with the Kodaikanal tower tunnel telescope will be discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solar polarimetry;charge shifting;vector magnetic field.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Κ." last="Sankarasubramanian">Κ. Sankarasubramanian</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email>sankar@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Srinivasulu">G. Srinivasulu</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. V." last="Ananth">A. V. Ananth</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Venkatakrishnan">P. Venkatakrishnan</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Udaipur 313004, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Twist of Magnetic Fields in Solar Active Regions</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0245-0247</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Solar active regions;solar magnetic fields.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Hongqi" last="Zhang">Hongqi Zhang</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Observatory, National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100 012, Chin.</affiliation>
						<email>zhq@sunlO.bao.ac.cn</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Lirong" last="Tian">Lirong Tian</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Observatory, National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100 012, Chin.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shudong" last="Bao">Shudong Bao</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Observatory, National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100 012, Chin.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Mei" last="Zhang">Mei Zhang</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Observatory, National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100 012, Chin.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Photospheric Flow near the Flare Locations of Active Regions</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0249-0250</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Active regions;magnetic field;velocity field;flare locations;shear.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Debi Prasad" last="Choudhary">Debi Prasad Choudhary</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, Post Box No. 198, Badi Road, Udaipur 313001, India</affiliation>
						<email>debi@plume.uso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Solar Energetic Particle Events at the Rise Phase of the 23rd Solar Activity Cycle Registered aboard the Spacecraft "INTERBALL-2"</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0251-0254</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The experiment with 10K-80 aboard the INTER-BALL-2 (which detects protons with energies $\gt$7 , 27-41, 41-58, 58-88, 88-180 and 180-300 MeV) registered six events of the solar energetic particle (SEP) increase. These events are during the initial rise phase of the 23rd solar activity cycle. Solar flares with the SEP generation are accompanied by coronal mass ejection (CME). Here we analyze the dynamics of the differential energy spectrum at different phases of the SEP increase.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solar energetic particles;coronal mass ejection;interplanetary shock;differential energy spectrum.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Vladislav" last="Timofeev">Vladislav Timofeev</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Cosmophysical Research and Aeronomy, 31 Lenin Ave., 677891 Yakutsk, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email>v.e.timofeev@sci.yakutia.ru</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>An Operator Perturbation Method of Polarized Line Transfer V. <i>Diagnosis of Solar Weak Magnetic Fields</i></title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0255-0258</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present an application of the PALI (Polarized Approximate Lambda Iteration) method to the resonance scattering in spectral lines formed in the presence of weak magnetic fields. The method is based on an operator perturbation approach, and can efficiently give solutions for oriented vector magnetic fields in the solar atmosphere.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Polarization;magnetic fields, radiative transfer;stars: atmospheres;methods: numerical.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. N." last="Nagendra">K. N. Nagendra</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Observatoire de la Cote d'Azur, (CNRS/UMR 6529), BP. 4229, F-06304, Nice Cedex 4, France.</affiliation>
						<email>knn@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="H." last="Frisch">H. Frisch</name>
						<affiliation>Observatoire de la Cote d'Azur, (CNRS/UMR 6529), BP. 4229, F-06304, Nice Cedex 4, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ." last="Faurobert-Scholl">M. Faurobert-Scholl</name>
						<affiliation>Observatoire de la Cote d'Azur, (CNRS/UMR 6529), BP. 4229, F-06304, Nice Cedex 4, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="F." last="Paletou">F. Paletou</name>
						<affiliation>Observatoire de la Cote d'Azur, (CNRS/UMR 6529), BP. 4229, F-06304, Nice Cedex 4, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>On the Possibility of Radio Emission from Quasi-parallel and Quasi-perpendicular Propagation of Shocks</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0259-0262</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A set of 21 solar type II radio bursts observed using Hiraiso radio spectrograph have been analysed to study the direction of propagation of coronal shocks. Α simple analysis is carried out to find the approximate angle between the shock normal and magnetic field by solving the Rankine-Hugoniot MHD relation with assumption of Alfven speed and plasma beta. From this analysis, it is suggested that both quasi-parallel shocks (favourable) and quasi-perpendicular shocks can generate type II bursts depending upon the circumstances of the corona.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Radio emission;shocks;type II bursts.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Shanmugaraju">A. Shanmugaraju</name>
						<affiliation>School of Physics, Madurai Kamaraj University, Madurai - 625021, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Radio Astronomy Centre, TIFR, Ooty 623001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Umapathy">S. Umapathy</name>
						<affiliation>School of Physics, Madurai Kamaraj University, Madurai - 625021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Emergence of Twisted Magnetic Flux Related Sigmoidal Brightening</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0263-0264</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Sun: Sigmoid;filament;sunspots.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Sundara Raman">K. Sundara Raman</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Kodaikanal 624103, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. B." last="Ramesh">K. B. Ramesh</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, .Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Selvendran">R. Selvendran</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Kodaikanal 624103, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P. S. M." last="Aleem">P. S. M. Aleem</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Kodaikanal 624103, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. M." last="Hiremath">K. M. Hiremath</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, .Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Tessellation of SoHO Magnetograms</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0265-0268</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A gradient based algorithm which divides arbitrary images into non-overlapping surface filling tiles of opposite polarity is used to study the flux and size distributions of large scale magnetic flux concentrations in solar and heliospheric observatory (SoHO) magnetograms. The mean absolute flux and size of the concentrations at the considered scale is found to be about $1.7 \times 10^{18}$Mx and 5.2Mm for both polarities. The form of the flux distribution is characterized by a skewness of $\alpha_{3} = 4.9$ and a kurtosis of $\alpha_{4}$, = 42.8. The fall in the distribution in the range $6.5 \times 10^{17}$Mx to $5 \times 10^{18}$Mx is described by an exponential fit, in agreement with a model for the sustenance of quiet region flux.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: granulation;magnetogram.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Srikant">R. Srikant</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysi cs, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email>srik@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jagdev" last="Singh">Jagdev Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysi cs, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Relationship of Non-potentiality and Flaring: Intercomparison for an M-class Flare</title>
				<feature>Session V – Vector Magnetic Fields, Prominences, CMEs &amp; Flares</feature>
				<page>0271-0274</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have made an attempt to obtain relationship of magnetic shear and vertical currents in NOAA AR7321. Intercomparison of changes observed at several flaring and non-flaring sites associated with an M4/2B flare observed on October 26, 1992 is reported.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Magnetic shear- electrical current-flare.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Ashok" last="Ambastha">Ashok Ambastha</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, Udaipur-313 001, India</affiliation>
						<email>ashok@uso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shibu K." last="Mathew">Shibu K. Mathew</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, Udaipur-313 001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Properties of Flux Tubes and the Relation with Solar Irradiance Variability</title>
				<feature>Session VI – Flux Tubes &amp; Irradiance Variability</feature>
				<page>0275-0282</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>At the solar surface the magnetic field is bundled into discrete elements of concentrated flux, often referred to as magnetic flux tubes, which cover only a small fraction of the solar surface. Flux tubes span a whole spectrum of sizes, ranging from sunspots to features well below the best currently obtainable spatial resolution.</p>
					<p>Whereas sunspots have been well studied, our knowledge of the true brightness of small-scale magnetic features is hampered by the insufficient spatial resolution of the observations. A better understanding of the thermal and magnetic properties of these small-scale features, however, is crucial for an understanding of (climate-relevant) long-term solar irradiance variations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Irradiance;flux tube;sunspot;plage.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ." last="Fligge">Μ. Fligge</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Astronomy, ΕΤΗ Zentrum, 8092 Zurich, Switzerland.</affiliation>
						<email>fligge@astro,phys.ethz.ch</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. K." last="Solanki">S. K. Solanki</name>
						<affiliation>Max-Planck-Institut fürAeronomie, D-37191 Katlenburg-Lindau, Germany</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Dynamical Processes in Flux Tubes and their Role in Chromospheric Heating</title>
				<feature>Session VI – Flux Tubes &amp; Irradiance Variability</feature>
				<page>0283-0287</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We model the dynamical interaction between magnetic flux tubes and granules in the solar photosphere which leads to the excitation of transverse (kink) and longitudinal (sausage) tube waves. The investigation is motivated by the interpretation of network oscillations in terms of flux tube waves. The calculations show that for magnetic field strengths typical of the network, the energy flux in transverse waves is higher than in longitudinal waves by an order of magnitude. But for weaker fields, such as those that might be found in internetwork regions, the energy fluxes in the two modes are comparable. Using observations of footpoint motions, the energy flux in transverse waves is calculated and the implications for chromospheric heating are pointed out.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>MHD;Sun: magnetic fields, oscillations.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. S." last="Hasan">S. S. Hasan</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email>hasan@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Infrared Photometry of Solar Active Regions</title>
				<feature>Session VI – Flux Tubes &amp; Irradiance Variability</feature>
				<page>0289-0292</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Simultaneous time series of broad-band images of two active regions close to the disk center were acquired at the maximum (0.80 $\mu$m) and minimum (1.55 $\mu$m) continuum opacities. Dark faculae are detected in images obtained as weighted intensity differences between both wave-length bands. The elements of quiet regions can be clearly distinguished from those of faculae and pores in scatter plots of brightness temperatures. There is a smooth transition between faculae and pores in the scatter plots. These facts are interpreted in terms of the balance between the inhibition of convective energy transport and the lateral radiative heating.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solar photosphere;faculae;pores.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ." last="Sobotka">Μ. Sobotka</name>
						<affiliation>Institute de Astrof'isica de Canarias, E-38200 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Institute, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, CZ-25165 Ondrejov, The Czech Republic.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ." last="V'azquez">Μ. V'azquez</name>
						<affiliation>Institute de Astrof'isica de Canarias, E-38200 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ. S'anchez" last="Cuberes">Μ. S'anchez Cuberes</name>
						<affiliation>Institute de Astrof'isica de Canarias, E-38200 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. A." last="Bonet">J. A. Bonet</name>
						<affiliation>Institute de Astrof'isica de Canarias, E-38200 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Hanslmeier">A. Hanslmeier</name>
						<affiliation>Institut für Geophysik, Astrophysik und Meteorologie, Universitätsplatz 5, A-8010 Graz, Austria.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>CaII Κ Imaging to Understand UV Irradiance Variability</title>
				<feature>Session VI – Flux Tubes &amp; Irradiance Variability</feature>
				<page>0293-0297</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>To identify and understand the underlying physical mechanisms of total solar and UV irradiance variability and to estimate the contribution of various chromospheric features to UV irradiance, detailed analysis of spatially resolved data is required. The various chromospheric features have been segregated and different parameters have been derived from CaII Κ Spectroheliograms of NSO/Sac Peak and Kodaikanal Observatory and compared with UV irradiance flux measured in MgII h and k lines by NOAA 9 satellite. The important results of this detailed analysis of CaII Κ Images of 1992 together with UV irradiance data will be discussed in this paper.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Chromosphere: CaII Κ Emission;UV Irradiance.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Kariyappa">R. Kariyappa</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email>rkari@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Models of Flux Tubes from Constrained Relaxation</title>
				<feature>Session VI – Flux Tubes &amp; Irradiance Variability</feature>
				<page>0299-0302</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We study the relaxation of a compressible plasma to an equilibrium with flow. The constraints of conservation of mass, energy, angular momentum, cross-helicity and relative magnetic helicity are imposed. Equilibria corresponding to the energy extrema while conserving these invariants for parallel flows yield three classes of solutions and one of them with an increasing radial density profile, relevant to solar flux tubes is presented.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Hydromagnetics;Sun: atmosphere, magnetic fields.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Α." last="Mangalam">Α. Mangalam</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Koramangala, Bangalore 560 034, India.</affiliation>
						<email>mangalam@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V." last="Krishan">V. Krishan</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Koramangala, Bangalore 560 034, India.</affiliation>
						<email>vinod@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Hemispheric Sign Rule of Current Helicity during the Rising Phase of Cycle 23</title>
				<feature>Session VI – Flux Tubes &amp; Irradiance Variability</feature>
				<page>0303-0306</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We compute the signs of two different current helicity parameters (i.e., $\alpha_{\text{best}}$ and $H_{c}$) for 87 active regions during the rise of cycle 23. The results indicate that 59\%\ of the active regions in the northern hemisphere have negative $\alpha_{\text{best}}$ and 65\%\ in the southern hemisphere have positive. This is consistent with that of the cycle 22. However, the helicity parameter $H_{c}$ shows a weaker opposite hemispheric preference in the new solar cycle. Possible reasons are discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: activity;magnetic fields;photosphere.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. D." last="Bao">S. D. Bao</name>
						<affiliation>Beijing Astronomical Observatory/National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100 012, China.</affiliation>
						<email>bshd@sunl0.bao.ac.cn</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G. X." last="Ai">G. X. Ai</name>
						<affiliation>Beijing Astronomical Observatory/National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100 012, China.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="H. Q." last="Zhang">H. Q. Zhang</name>
						<affiliation>Beijing Astronomical Observatory/National Astronomical Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100 012, China.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Magnetoconvection and the Solar Dynamo</title>
				<feature>Session VII – Magnetoconvection &amp; Stellar Activity</feature>
				<page>0307-0313</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We review current understanding of the interaction of magnetic fields with convective motions in stellar convection zones. Among the most exciting recent results is the discovery that magnetic fields need not primarily be confined to the stable layer below the convection zone; numerical simulations have shown that surprisingly, strong magnetic fields can be maintained in the interior of the convection zone.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Magnetic fields;convection;dynamo;Sun.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Å." last="Nordlund">Å. Nordlund</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Observatory &amp; Theoretical Astrophysics Center, Juliane Maries Vej 30, 2100 Copenhagen ɸ, Denmark</affiliation>
						<email>aake@astro.ku.dk</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. B. F." last="Dorch">S. B. F. Dorch</name>
						<affiliation>The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences, Stockholm Observatory, SE-13336 Saltsjöbaden, Sweden</affiliation>
						<email>dorch@astro.su.se</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. F." last="Stein">R. F. Stein</name>
						<affiliation>Dept. of Physics and Astronomy, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824, USA</affiliation>
						<email>rstein@pa.msu.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Large-scale Flow and Transport of Magnetic Flux in the Solar Convection Zone</title>
				<feature>Session VII – Magnetoconvection &amp; Stellar Activity</feature>
				<page>0315-0318</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Horizontal large-scale velocity field describes horizontal displacement of the photospheric magnetic flux in zonal and meridian directions. The flow systems of solar plasma, constructed according to the velocity field, create the large-scale cellular-like patterns with up-flow in the center and the down-flow on the boundaries. Distribution of the large-scale horizontal eddies (with characteristic scale length from 350 to 490 Mm) was found in the broad equatorial zone, limited by $60^{\circ}$ latitude circles on both hemispheres. The zonal averages of the zonal and meridian velocities, and the total horizontal velocity for each Carrington rotation during the activity cycles no. 21 and 22 varies during the 11-yr activity cycle. Plot of RMS values of total horizontal velocity is shifted about 1·6 years before the similarly shaped variation of the magnetic flux.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun;large-scale flow;cyclic variations.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="P. Ambroz">P. Ambroz</name>
						<affiliation>Astronomical Institute of the Acad. Sci. of the Czech Republic, CZ-25165 Ondrejov, The Czech Republic.</affiliation>
						<email>pambroz@asu.cas.cz</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Space Stellar Photometry Mission COROT: Asteroseismology and Search for Extrasolar Planets</title>
				<feature>Session VII – Magnetoconvection &amp; Stellar Activity</feature>
				<page>0319-0322</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The main scientific objectives, asteroseismology and search for extrasolar planets for the COROT photometric mission are presented, and its interest in terms of stellar variability. A description of the payload, details of the scientific program, the ground based preparatory observations and bibliography can be found at http://www.astrsp-mrs.fr/corot/pagecorot.html.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Space;photometry;asteroseismology;extrasolar planets.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Annie" last="Baglin">Annie Baglin</name>
						<affiliation>DESPA, UMR CNRS 8632 Observatoire de Paris, 92195 Meudon, France</affiliation>
						<email>annie.baglin@obspm.fr</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Gerard" last="Vauclair">Gerard Vauclair</name>
						<affiliation>LAT, UMR CNRS 5572, Observatoire de Midi-Pyrenees, 31 400 Toulouse, France</affiliation>
						<email>annie.baglin@obspm.fr</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Corot" last="team">Corot team</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Helioseismology and the Solar Interior Dynamics</title>
				<feature>Session VIII – Helioseismology</feature>
				<page>0323-0329</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The inversion of helioseismic modes leads to the sound velocity inside the Sun with a precision of about 0.1 per cent. Comparisons of solar models with the "seismic sun" represent powerful tools to test the physics: depth of the convection zone, equation of state, opacities, element diffusion processes and mixing inside the radiative zone. We now have evidence that microscopic diffusion (element segregation) does occur below the convection zone, leading to a mild helium depletion in the solar outer layers. Meanwhile this process must be slowed down by some macroscopic effect, presumably rotation-induced mixing. The same mixing is also responsible for the observed lithium depletion. On the other hand, the observations of beryllium and helium 3 impose specific constraints on the depth of this mildly mixed zone. Helioseismology also gives information on the internal solar rotation: while differential rotation exists in the convection zone, solid rotation prevails in the radiative zone, and the transition layer (the so-called "tachocline") is very small. These effects are discussed, together with the astrophysical constraints on the solar neutrino fluxes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Helioseismology;diffusion;light elements;abundances.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Vauclair">S. Vauclair</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratoire d'Astrophysique de Toulouse, 14, Avenue Edouard-Belin, 31400-Toulouse, France.</affiliation>
						<email>sylvie.vauclair@obs-mip.fr</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Perspectives on the Interior of the Sun</title>
				<feature>Session VIII – Helioseismology</feature>
				<page>0331-0337</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The interior of the Sun is not directly accessible to observations. Nonetheless, it is possible to infer the physical conditions inside the Sun with the help of structure equations governing its equilibrium and with the powerful observational tools provided by the neutrino fluxes and oscillation frequencies. The helioseismic data show that the internal constitution of the Sun can be adequately represented by a standard solar model. It turns out that a cooler solar core is not a viable solution for the measured deficit of neutrino fluxes, and the resolution of the solar neutrino puzzle should be sought in the realm of particle physics.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: Oscillations, rotation, interior.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. Μ." last="Chitre">S. Μ. Chitre</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai 400005, India.</affiliation>
						<email>chitre@astro,tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Seismic Tomography of the Near Solar Surface</title>
				<feature>Session VIII – Helioseismology</feature>
				<page>0339-0342</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Surface gravity waves have been used to probe flows in the two megameters beneath the photosphere using the techniques of time-distance helioseismology. The results suggest that supergranule velocities are smaller than at the surface. The outward flow outside a sunspot penumbra (the moat) is observed, as is an inward flow in the region beyond the moat.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Helioseismology;supergranulation;sunspots.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="L." last="Gizon">L. Gizon</name>
						<affiliation>HEPL, Stanford University, Stanford CA 94305, USA.</affiliation>
						<email>lgizon@solar.Stanford.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="T. L." last="Duvall Jr">T. L. Duvall Jr</name>
						<affiliation>NASA/Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt MD 20771, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. M." last="Larsen">R. M. Larsen</name>
						<affiliation>HEPL, Stanford University, Stanford CA 94305, USA.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>SCCM, Stanford University, Stanford CA 94305, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Helioseismic Solar Cycle Changes and Splitting Coefficients</title>
				<feature>Session VIII – Helioseismology</feature>
				<page>0349-0352</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Using the GONG data for a period over four years, we have studied the variation of frequencies and splitting coefficients with solar cycle. Frequencies and even-order coefficients are found to change significantly with rising phase of the solar cycle. We also find temporal variations in the rotation rate near the solar surface.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solar cycle;rotation;activity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. C." last="Tripathy">S. C. Tripathy</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, PO Box No. 198, Udaipur 313 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Kiran" last="Jain">Kiran Jain</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, PO Box No. 198, Udaipur 313 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Bhatnagar">A. Bhatnagar</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, PO Box No. 198, Udaipur 313 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Temporal Variation of Large Scale Flows in the Solar Interior</title>
				<feature>Session VIII – Helioseismology</feature>
				<page>0353-0356</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We attempt to detect short-term temporal variations in the rotation rate and other large scale velocity fields in the outer part of the solar convection zone using the ring diagram technique applied to Michelson Doppler Imager (MDI) data. The measured velocity field shows variations by about 10 m/s on the scale of few days.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: Oscillations, Rotation, Interior.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Sarbani" last="Basu">Sarbani Basu</name>
						<affiliation>Institute for Advanced Study, Olden Lane, Princeton Ν. J. 08540, U.S.A. and Astronomy Department, Yale University, New Haven, CT 06520-8101, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email>basu@astro.yale.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="H. M." last="Antia">H. M. Antia</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Observation of Hysteresis between Solar Activity Indicators and $p$-mode Frequency Shifts for Solar Cycle 22</title>
				<feature>Session VIII – Helioseismology</feature>
				<page>0357-0360</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Using intermediate degree p-mode frequency data sets for solar cycle 22, we find that the frequency shifts and magnetic activity indicators show a "hysteresis" phenomenon. It is observed that the magnetic indices follow different paths for the ascending and descending phases of the solar cycle while for radiative indices, the separation between the paths are well within the error limits.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: oscillations, activity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. C." last="Tripathy">S. C. Tripathy</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, P. B. No. 198, Dewali, Off Bari Road, Udaipur 313 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email>sushant@uso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Brajesh" last="Kumar">Brajesh Kumar</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, P. B. No. 198, Dewali, Off Bari Road, Udaipur 313 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Kiran" last="Jain">Kiran Jain</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, P. B. No. 198, Dewali, Off Bari Road, Udaipur 313 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Bhatnagar">A. Bhatnagar</name>
						<affiliation>Udaipur Solar Observatory, Physical Research Laboratory, P. B. No. 198, Dewali, Off Bari Road, Udaipur 313 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Non-Radial Oscillations in an Axisymmetric MHD Incompressible Fluid</title>
				<feature>Session VIII – Helioseismology</feature>
				<page>0361-0364</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>It is well known from Helioseismology that the Sun exhibits oscillations on a global scale, most of which are non-radial in nature. These oscillations help us to get a clear picture of the internal structure of the Sun as has been demonstrated by the theoretical and observational (such as GONG) studies. In this study we formulate the linearised equations of motion for non-radial oscillations by perturbing the MHD equilibrium solution for an axisymmetric incompressible fluid. The fluid motion and the magnetic field are expressed as scalars $U$, $V$, $Ρ$ and $T$, respectively. In deriving the exact solution for the equilibrium state, we neglect the contribution due to meridional circulation. The perturbed quantities $U_{\ast}$, $V_{\ast}$, $Ρ_{\ast}$, $T_{\ast}$ are written in terms of orthogonal polynomials. A special case of the above formulation and its stability is discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Non-radial oscillations;MHD;axisymmetry.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A. Satya" last="Narayanan">A. Satya Narayanan</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034, India.</affiliation>
						<email>satya@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Mechanism of Cyclically Polarity Reversing Solar Magnetic Cycle as a Cosmic Dynamo</title>
				<feature>Session IX – Dynamo Mechanisms </feature>
				<page>0365-0371</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We briefly describe historical development of the concept of solar dynamo mechanism that generates electric current and magnetic field by plasma flows inside the solar convection zone. The dynamo is the driver of the cyclically polarity reversing solar magnetic cycle. The reversal process can easily and visually be understood in terms of magnetic field line stretching and twisting and folding in three-dimensional space by plasma flows of differential rotation and global convection under influence of Coriolis force. This process gives rise to formation of a series of huge magnetic flux tubes that propagate along iso-rotation surfaces inside the convection zone. Each of these flux tubes produces one solar cycle. We discuss general characteristics of any plasma flows that can generate magnetic field and reverse the polarity of the magnetic field in a rotating body in the Universe. We also mention a list of problems which are currently being disputed concerning the solar dynamo mechanism together with observational evidences that are to be constraints as well as verifications of any solar cycle dynamo theories of short and long term behaviors of the Sun, particularly time variations of its magnetic field, plasma flows, and luminosity.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Dynamo;solar cycle;polarity reversal;differential rotation;turbulence;global convection.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Hirokazu" last="Yoshimura">Hirokazu Yoshimura</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Astronomy, University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan 113-0033.</affiliation>
						<email>yoshimura@astron.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Current Status of Kinematic Solar Dynamo Models</title>
				<feature>Session IX – Dynamo Mechanisms </feature>
				<page>0373-0377</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This review provides a historical overview of how research in kinematic solar dynamo modeling evolved during the last few decades and assesses the present state of research. The early pioneering papers assumed the dynamo to operate in the convection zone. It was suggested in the 1980s that the dynamo operates in a thin layer at the bottom of the convection zone. Some researchers in recent years are arguing that the poloidal field is produced near the surface—an idea that goes back to Babcock (1961) and Leighton (1969).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun;MHD;dynamo theory.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Arnab Rai" last="Choudhuri">Arnab Rai Choudhuri</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560012, India</affiliation>
						<email>arnab@physics.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Solar Internal Rotation and Dynamo Waves: A Two-Dimensional Asymptotic Solution in the Convection Zone</title>
				<feature>Session IX – Dynamo Mechanisms </feature>
				<page>0379-0380</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Sun: magnetic fields, rotation, activity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Gaetano" last="Belvedere">Gaetano Belvedere</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Catania, Astronomy Unit, Via Santa Sofia 78, 95125 Catania, Italy.</affiliation>
						<email>gbelvedere@alpha4.ct.astro,it</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Kirill" last="Kuzanyan">Kirill Kuzanyan</name>
						<affiliation>IZMIRAN, Troitsk, Moscow Region, 142092 Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Dmitry" last="Sokoloff">Dmitry Sokoloff</name>
						<affiliation>Moscow State University, Department of Physics, 119899 Moscow, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Role of Magnetic Buoyancy in a Babcock-Leighton Type Solar Dynamo</title>
				<feature>Session IX – Dynamo Mechanisms </feature>
				<page>0381-0385</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We study the effects of incorporating magnetic buoyancy in a model of the solar dynamo—which draws inspiration from the Babcock-Leighton idea of surface processes generating the poloidal field. We present our main results here.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>MHD;Sun: interior, magnetic fields.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Dibyendu" last="Nandy">Dibyendu Nandy</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560012.</affiliation>
						<email>dandy@physics.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Arnab Rai" last="Choudhuri">Arnab Rai Choudhuri</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560012.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Alpha-Effect, Current and Kinetic Helicities for Magnetically Driven Turbulence, and Solar Dynamo</title>
				<feature>Session IX – Dynamo Mechanisms </feature>
				<page>0387-0388</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Gaetano" last="Belvedere">Gaetano Belvedere</name>
						<affiliation>1Institute of Astronomy, University of Catania, Viale A. Doria 6, 95125 Catania, Italy.</affiliation>
						<email>gbelvedere@alpha4.ct.astro.it</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V. V." last="Pipin">V. V. Pipin</name>
						<affiliation>Institute for Solar-Terrestrial Physics, P.O. Box 4026, 664033 Irkutsk, Russia.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Astrophysikalisches Institut Potsdam, An der Sternwarte 16, D-14482 Potsdam, Germany.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Rüdiger">G. Rüdiger</name>
						<affiliation>Institute ofAstronomy, University of Catania, Viale A. Doria 6, 95125 Catania, Italy.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Astrophysikalisches Institut Potsdam, An der Sternwarte 16, D-14482 Potsdam, Germany.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Cyclical Variation of the Quiet Corona and Coronal Holes</title>
				<feature>Session X – Cycle Variation in the Quiet Corona &amp; Coronal Holes</feature>
				<page>0389-0395</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Recent advances in the understanding of the quiet corona and coronal holes are reviewed. The review is based on long-term accumulation of data from eclipse observations, coronagraph observations, helium 10830 Å spectroheliograms, and X-ray observations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Coronagraphs;solar activity cycle;solar corona;total eclipses;X-ray observations.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Takashi" last="Sakurai">Takashi Sakurai</name>
						<affiliation>National Astronomical Observatory, Japan</affiliation>
						<email>sakurai@solar.mtk.nao.ac.jp</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The EUV Spectrum of Sunspot Plumes Observed by SUMER on SOHO</title>
				<feature>Session X – Cycle Variation in the Quiet Corona &amp; Coronal Holes</feature>
				<page>0397-0401</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present results from sunspot observations obtained by SUMER on SOHO. In sunspot plumes the EUV spectrum differs from the quiet Sun; continua are observed with different slopes and intensities; emission lines from molecular hydrogen and many unidentified species indicate unique plasma conditions above sunspots. Sunspot plumes are sites of systematic downflow. We also discuss the properties of sunspot oscillations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: EUV spectroscopy;sunspot;oscillation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="W." last="Curdt">W. Curdt</name>
						<affiliation>Max-Planck-Institut für Aeronomie, D-37191, Katlenburg-Lindau, Germany.</affiliation>
						<email>curdt@linmpi.mpg.de</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. N." last="Dwivedi">B. N. Dwivedi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Applied Physics, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi-221005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="U." last="Feldman">U. Feldman</name>
						<affiliation>E.O. Hulburt Center for Space Research, NRL, Washington DC 20375, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Exploring Coronal Structures with SOHO</title>
				<feature>Session X – Cycle Variation in the Quiet Corona &amp; Coronal Holes</feature>
				<page>0403-0406</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We applied advanced image enhancement techniques to explore in detail the characteristics of the small-scale structures and/or the low contrast structures in several Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs) observed by SOHO. We highlight here the results from our studies of the morphology and dynamical evolution of CME structures in the solar corona using two instruments on board SOHO: LASCO and EIT.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Corona;CME.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ." last="Karovska">Μ. Karovska</name>
						<affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, Cambridge, MA 02138 USA.</affiliation>
						<email>karovska@cfa.harvard.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Β." last="Wood">Β. Wood</name>
						<affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, Cambridge, MA 02138 USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J." last="Chen">J. Chen</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Research Laboratory, Washington DC, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J." last="Cook">J. Cook</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Research Laboratory, Washington DC, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Howard">R. Howard</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Research Laboratory, Washington DC, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Electron Density and Temperature Measurements, and Abundance Anomalies in the Solar Atmosphere</title>
				<feature>Session X – Cycle Variation in the Quiet Corona &amp; Coronal Holes</feature>
				<page>0407-0411</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Using spectra obtained from the SUMER (Solar Ultraviolet Measurements of Emitted Radiation) spectrograph on the spacecraft SOHO (Solar and Heliospheric Observatory), we investigate the height dependence of electron density, temperature and abundance anomalies in the solar atmosphere. In particular, we present the behaviour of the solar FIP effect (the abundance enhancement of elements with first ionization potential $\lt$ 10 eV in the corona with respect to photospheric values) with height above an active region observed at the solar limb, with emphasis on the so-called transition region lines.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solar atmosphere;abundance anomalies;EUV diagnostics;emission lines.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Anita" last="Mohan">Anita Mohan</name>
						<affiliation>department of Applied Physics, Institute of Technology, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi 221005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Bhola N." last="Dwivedi">Bhola N. Dwivedi</name>
						<affiliation>department of Applied Physics, Institute of Technology, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi 221005, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Max-Planck-Institut für Aeronomie, 37191 Katlenburg-Lindau, Germany.</affiliation>
						<email>dwivedi@banaras.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Enrico" last="Landi">Enrico Landi</name>
						<affiliation>Max-Planck-Institut für Aeronomie, 37191 Katlenburg-Lindau, Germany.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Microwave Enhancement in Coronal Holes: Statistical Properties</title>
				<feature>Session X – Cycle Variation in the Quiet Corona &amp; Coronal Holes</feature>
				<page>0413-0417</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report on the statistical properties of the microwave enhancement (brightness temperature, area, fine structure, life time and magnetic field strength) in coronal holes observed over a period of several solar rotations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: radio radiation;coronal holes;EUV emission.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Ν." last="Gopalswamy">Ν. Gopalswamy</name>
						<affiliation>Bldg 26, Room G-l, Code 682.3, NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt MD, USA.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Center for Solar Physics and Space Weather, The Catholic University of America, Washington DC 20064.</affiliation>
						<email>gopals@fugee.gsfc.nasa.gov</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Κ." last="Shibasaki">Κ. Shibasaki</name>
						<affiliation>Nobeyama Radio Observatory, Minamisaku, Nagano, 384-1305, Japan.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Μ." last="Salem">Μ. Salem</name>
						<affiliation>Dept. of Physics, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH 44106, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Enhanced Coronal Green Line Intensity and the Magnetic Field Gradients</title>
				<feature>Session X – Cycle Variation in the Quiet Corona &amp; Coronal Holes</feature>
				<page>0419-0420</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Sun: Corona;emergence of magnetic flux.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. B." last="Ramesh">K. B. Ramesh</name>
						<affiliation>Indian institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034.</affiliation>
						<email>kbramesh@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. S." last="Nagabhushana">B. S. Nagabhushana</name>
						<affiliation>Indian institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. A." last="Varghese">B. A. Varghese</name>
						<affiliation>Indian institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Multibaseline Observations of the Occultation of Crab Nebula by the Solar Corona at Decameter Wavelengths</title>
				<feature>Session X – Cycle Variation in the Quiet Corona &amp; Coronal Holes</feature>
				<page>0421-0422</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Occultation;solar corona;density fluctuations.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. R." last="Subramanian">K. R. Subramanian</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, India</affiliation>
						<email>subra@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Solar Wind Variation with the Cycle</title>
				<feature>Session XI – Solar Wind &amp; Interplanetary Magnetic Fields</feature>
				<page>0423-0429</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The cyclic evolution of the heliospheric plasma parameters is related to the time-dependent boundary conditions in the solar corona. "Minimal" coronal configurations correspond to the regular appearance of the tenuous, but hot and fast plasma streams from the large polar coronal holes. The denser, but cooler and slower solar wind is adjacent to coronal streamers. Irregular dynamic manifestations are present in the corona and the solar wind everywhere and always. They follow the solar activity cycle rather well. Because of this, the direct and indirect solar wind measurements demonstrate clear variations in space and time according to the minimal, intermediate and maximal conditions of the cycles. The average solar wind density, velocity and temperature measured at the Earth's orbit show specific decadal variations and trends, which are of the order of the first tens per cent during the last three solar cycles. Statistical, spectral and correlation characteristics of the solar wind are reviewed with the emphasis on the cycles.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solar wind;solar activity cycle.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="I. S." last="Veselovsky">I. S. Veselovsky</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Nuclear Physics, Moscow State University, 119899 Moscow, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email>veselov@decl.npi.msu.su</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. V." last="Dmitriev">A. V. Dmitriev</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Nuclear Physics, Moscow State University, 119899 Moscow, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. V." last="Suvorova">A. V. Suvorova</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Nuclear Physics, Moscow State University, 119899 Moscow, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. V." last="Tarsina">M. V. Tarsina</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Nuclear Physics, Moscow State University, 119899 Moscow, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Heliospheric Magnetic Fields, Energetic Particles, and the Solar Cycle</title>
				<feature>Session XI – Solar Wind &amp; Interplanetary Magnetic Fields</feature>
				<page>0431-0437</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The heliosphere is the region filled with magnetized plasma of mainly solar origin. It extends from the solar corona to well beyond the planets, and is separated from the interstellar medium by the heliopause. The latter is embedded in a complex and still unexplored boundary region. The characteristics of heliospheric plasma, fields, and energetic particles depend on highly variable internal boundary conditions, and also on quasi-stationary external ones. Both galactic cosmic rays and energetic particles of solar and heliospheric origin are subject to intensity variations over individual solar cycles and also from cycle to cycle. Particle propagation is controlled by spatially and temporally varying interplanetary magnetic fields, frozen into the solar wind. An overview is presented of the main heliospheric components and processes, and also of the relevant missions and data sets. Particular attention is given to flux variations over the last few solar cycles, and to extrapolated effects on the terrestrial environment.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Heliosphere;heliopause;termination shock;solar cycle;energetic particles;interplanetary neutrals;anomalous component;cosmic rays;interplanetary magnetic fields.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Peter" last="Kiraly">Peter Kiraly</name>
						<affiliation>KFKI Research Institute for Particle and Nuclear Physics, H-1525 Budapest 114, POB 49, Hungary.</affiliation>
						<email>pkiraly@sunserv.kfki.hu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Remote Sensing of the Heliospheric Solar Wind using Radio Astronomy Methods and Numerical Simulations</title>
				<feature>Session XI – Solar Wind &amp; Interplanetary Magnetic Fields</feature>
				<page>0439-0444</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The ground-based radio astronomy method of interplanetary scintillations (IPS) and spacecraft observations have shown, in the past 25 years, that while coronal holes give rise to stable, recurring high speed solar wind streams during the minimum of the solar activity cycle, the slow speed wind seen more during the solar maximum activity is better associated with the closed field regions, which also give rise to solar flares and coronal mass ejections (CME's). The latter events increase significantly, as the cycle maximum takes place. We have recently shown that in the case of energetic flares one may be able to track the associated disturbances almost on a one to one basis from a distance of 0.2 to 1 AU using IPS methods. Time dependent 3D MHD models which are constrained by IPS observations are being developed. These models are able to simulate general features of the solar-generated disturbances. Advances in this direction may lead to prediction of heliospheric propagation of these disturbances throughout the solar system.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun;heliosphere, solar wind.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Ananthakrishnan">S. Ananthakrishnan</name>
						<affiliation>National Center for Radio Astrophysics, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Pune, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Tomography of the Solar Wind using Interplanetary Scintillation</title>
				<feature>Session XI – Solar Wind &amp; Interplanetary Magnetic Fields</feature>
				<page>0445-0446</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Tomography;solar wind;interplanetary scintillation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Divya" last="Oberoi">Divya Oberoi</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Radio Astrophysics, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Pune 411007.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560012.</affiliation>
						<email>div@ncra.tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. Pramesh" last="Rao">A. Pramesh Rao</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Radio Astrophysics, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Pune 411007.</affiliation>
						<email>pramesh@ncra.tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Ulysses Observations of Nonlinear Wave-wave Interactions in the Source Regions of Type III Solar Radio Bursts</title>
				<feature>Session XI – Solar Wind &amp; Interplanetary Magnetic Fields</feature>
				<page>0447-0450</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Ulysses Unified Radio and Plasma Wave Experiment (URAP) has observed Langmuir, ion-acoustic and associated solar type III radio emissions in the interplanetary medium. Bursts of 50-300 Hz (in the spacecraft frame) electric field signals, corresponding to long-wavelength ion-acoustic waves are often observed coincident in time with the most intense Langmuir wave spikes, providing evidence for the electrostatic decay instability. Langmuir waves often occur as envelope solitons, suggesting that strong turbulence processes, such as modulational instability and soliton formation, often coexist with weak turbulence processes, such as electrostatic decay, in a few type III burst source regions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Type III bursts;electrostatic decay;modulational instability.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Thejappa">G. Thejappa</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Astronomy, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742.</affiliation>
						<email>golla@urap.gsfc.nasa.gov</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. J." last="MacDowall">R. J. MacDowall</name>
						<affiliation>NASA, Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD 20771.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Summary Lecture</title>
				<feature>Session XII – Conclusion</feature>
				<page>0451-0457</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This summary lecture makes no attempt to summarize what was actually said at the meeting, since this is well covered by the other contributors. Instead I have structured my presentation in three parts: First I try to demonstrate why the Sun is unique by comparing it with laboratory plasmas. This is followed by some personal reminiscences that go back a significant fraction of the century. I conclude in the form of a poem about this memorable conference in honor of the centennial anniversary of the Kodaikanal Observatory.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun;plasma physics—history of science.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. O." last="Stenflo">J. O. Stenflo</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Astronomy, ΕΤΗ Zentrum, CH-8092 Zurich, Switzerland</affiliation>
						<email>stenflo@astro.phys.ethz.ch</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>List of Participants</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0459-0461</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Author Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0463-0467</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Subject Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0469-0475</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="022">
		<issue inum="02-03" month="06-09" year="2001">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Hard X-ray Spectrum of Mkn 421 during the Active Phase</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0145-0154</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Spectral measurement of Mkn 421 were made in the hard X-ray energy band of 20–200 keV using a high sensitivity, large area scintillation counter telescope on November 21, 2000 and these coincided with the onset of an active X-ray phase as seen in the ASM counting rates on board RXTE. The observed spectrum can not be fitted to a single power law similar to the PDS data of BeppoSAX. The data can be fitted both by a two component power-law function or a combination of an exponential function with a power law component at the high energies above 80 keV. We identify these components with those arising from the synchrotron self compton and the high energy power-law tail arising from the upgrading of the thermal photons due to multiple Compton scattering a la Cyg X-1. A comparison with the earlier data clearly suggests a spectral variability in the hard X-ray spectrum of the source. We propose a continuously flaring geometry for the source as the underlying mechanism for energy release.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>X-rays;AGNs;BL Lac sources, massive black hole candidates, jet emission;individual;Mkn 421.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Manchanda">R. K. Manchanda</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
						<email>ravi@tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-07-27</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2001-09-27</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>H$\alpha$ Emission Line Morphologies in Markarian Starburst Galaxies</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0155-0172</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present broad band $R$ and narrow band H$\alpha$ emission line images of a sample of optically selected starburst galaxies from the Markarian lists. The emission line morphology is studied and global properties like luminosities, equivalent widths and star formation rates are derived. The radial distribution of H$\alpha$ flux and the EW are determined using concentric aperture photometry on the emission line and the continuum images. H$\alpha$ flux is generally found to peak in the nuclear region and fall off outwards. The EW is found to peak off-center in most of the cases implying that though the intensity of emission is maximum at the nucleus, the star formation activity relative to the underlying continuum often peaks away from the center in Markarian starburst galaxies.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: starburst, photometry</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Chitre">A. Chitre</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="U. C." last="Joshi">U. C. Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Navrangpura, Ahmedabad 380 009, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-12-04</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2001-05-10</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Far Infrared Mapping of Three Galactic Star Forming Regions: W3(OH), S209 &amp; S187</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0173-0185</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Three Galactic star forming regions associated with W3(OH), S209 and S187 have been simultaneously mapped in two trans-IRAS far infrared (FIR) bands centered at $\sim 140$ and 200$\mu$m using the TIFR 100 cm balloon borne FIR telescope. These maps showextended FIR emission with structures. The HIRES processed IRAS maps of these regions at 12, 25, 60 &amp; 100 $\mu$m have also been presented for comparison. Point-like sources have been extracted from the longest waveband TIFR maps and searched for associations in the other five bands. The diffuse emission from these regions have been quantified, which turns out to be a significant fraction of the total emission. The spatial distribution of cold dust (T $\lt$ 30 K) for two of these sources (W3(OH) &amp; S209), has been determined reliably from the maps in TIFR bands. The dust temperature and optical depth maps show complex morphology. In general the dust around S209 has been found to be warmer than that in W3(OH) region.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Interstellar dust;W3(OH);S209;S187.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. K." last="Ghosh">S. K. Ghosh</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Bombay 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Institute of Space and Astronautical Science, Kanagawa 229, Japan.</affiliation>
						<email>swarna@tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B." last="Mookerjea">B. Mookerjea</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Bombay 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Joint Astronomy Programme, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="T. N." last="Rengarajan">T. N. Rengarajan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Nagoya University, Nagoya 464-8602, Japan.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. N." last="Tandon">S. N. Tandon</name>
						<affiliation>Inter-University Centre for Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. P." last="Verma">R. P. Verma</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Bombay 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-04-07</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2001-05-20</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Spectroscopic Binaries near the North Galactic Pole Paper 24: HD 106104, 109281, 109463 and 110743</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0187-0211</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The four stars treated in this paper have been under observation with photoelectric radial-velocity spectrometers for many years. They have proved to be binaries with periods of 30, 1828, 1514 and 822 days respectively; the orbits are of modest eccentricity apart from that of HD 110743 which is indistinguishable from a circle. The mass functions are small, and no companion has been observed for any of the stars. HD 110743, a K dwarf, is much the nearest of the four, and its orbit is of short enough period for the photocentric motion to have been recognized by <i>Hipparcos</i>. An eleventh-magnitude star rather more than $1'$ away from HD 106104 is shown to be a genuine physical companion, with practically identical radial velocity, proper motion and distance modulus, although the projected separation is about 13,000 AU.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Radial velocities;spectroscopic binaries;orbits;stars, individual;HD 106104;HD 109281;HD 109463;HD 110743.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R. F." last="Griffin">R. F. Griffin</name>
						<affiliation>The Observatories, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0HA, England</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-10-16</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2001-02-15</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Detection, Excision and Statistics of Interference at the Mauritius Radio Telescope</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0213-0227</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A technique to detect man-made interference in the visibility data of the Mauritius Radio Telescope (MRT) has been developed. This technique is based on the understanding that the interference is generally ‘spiky’ in nature and has Fourier components beyond the maximum frequency which can arise from the radio sky and can therefore be identified. We take the sum of magnitudes of visibilities on all the baselines measured at a given time to improve detectability. This is then high-pass filtered to get a time series from which the contribution of the sky is removed. Interference is detected in the high-pass data using an iterative scheme. In each iteration, interference with amplitudes beyond a certain threshold is detected. These points are then removed from the original time series and the resulting data are high-pass filtered and the process repeated. We have also studied the statistics of the strength, numbers, time of occurrence and duration of the interference at the MRT. The statistics indicate that most often the interference excision can be carried out while post-integrating the visibilities by giving a zero weight to the interference points.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Metre-wave radio telescope;Fourier synthesis;interference excision.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Sachdev">S. Sachdev</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, University of Mauritius, Reduit, Mauritius.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. Udaya" last="Shankar">N. Udaya Shankar</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, University of Mauritius, Reduit, Mauritius.</affiliation>
						<email>uday@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-08-21</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2001-09-28</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="04" month="12" year="2001">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Variability of Extragalactic Objects in Relation to Redshift, Color, Radio Spectral Index and Absorption Lines</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0263-0282</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Optical variability of extragalactic objects, viz., QSOs, BL Lacs and Seyfert galaxies has been monitored systematically over an appreciable period of time and a large amount of data have accumulated. The present work reports results of investigations involving statistical analysis of updated data on relationships between variability and various observed properties of the objects, viz., redshift, color indices, radio spectral index and absorption lines. It is found that at high frequencies (rest frame) radio spectral index does not change significantly with the degree of variability. However, the degree of variability depends on redshifts. On the other hand, presence or absence of absorption lines is significantly associated with variability for QSOs with larger redshifts ($z \gt 1.0$), while no such relationship exists for QSOs at smaller redshifts ($z \lt 1.0$ or other objects. Correlation between color indices and redshifts depends on the degree of variability and the sample chosen for the color index.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies active: galaxies;quasars: general.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D." last="Basu">D. Basu</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Carleton University, Ottawa, ON K1S 5B6, Canada</affiliation>
						<email>basu@physics.carleton.ca</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-11-13</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2001-12-11</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Soft X-ray Variability of the Bright Quasar 3C273</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0283-0292</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present the results from ROSAT observations of 3C273 in the soft X-ray band. The light variation of 3C273 was investigated for three different energy bands of soft, medium, and hard. The maximum variability with a factor of 2 for 551 dayswas confirmed at all three different bands. This appears to be a periodic variation within the period of roughly 6 months. However, the short-term or micro variation was not so distinct and the light variation of each band did not show any correlation between them. The hardness ratio for hard and soft bands shows irregular variation but there was no correlation between them. There is no distinct variation of the photon index in the case of simple power law model fitting. For power law + free absorption model fitting, the average photon index $(\Gamma)$ is 2.08.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: individual (3C273), quasar;X-rays: galaxies.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Chulhee" last="Kim">Chulhee Kim</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Earth Science Education, Chonbuk National University, Korea.</affiliation>
						<email>chkim@astro.chonbuk.ac.kr</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-07-20</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2001-11-02</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>HI Fluctuations at Large Redshifts: I–Visibility correlation</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0293-0307</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We investigate the possibility of probing the large scale structure in the universe at large redshifts by studying fluctuations in the redshifted 1420 MHz emission from the neutral hydrogen (HI) at early epochs. The neutral hydrogen content of the universe is knownfrom absorption studies for $z \lesssim 4.5$. The HI distribution is expected to be inhomogeneous in the gravitational instability picture and this inhomogeneity leads to anisotropy in the redshifted HI emission. The best hope of detecting this anisotropy is by using a large low-frequency interferometric instrument like the Giant Meter-Wave Radio Telescope (GMRT). We calculate the visibility correlation function $\langle V_{v}(\mathbf{U})V_{v'}(\mathbf{U})\rangle$ at two frequencies $v$ and $v'$ of the redshifted HI emission for an interferometric observation. In particular we give numerical results for the two GMRT channels centered around $v=325$ MHz and $v=610$ MHz from density inhomogeneity and peculiar velocity of the HI distribution. The visibility correlation is $\simeq 10^{-10}-10^{-9}$ Jy$^{2}$. We calculate the signal-to-noise for detecting the correlation signal in the presence of system noise and show that the GMRT might detect the signal for integration times $\simeq 100$ hrs. We argue that the measurement of visibility correlation allows optimal use of the uncorrelated nature of the system noise across baselines and frequency channels.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmology: theory, observations, large scale structures;diffuse radiation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Somnath" last="Bharadwaj">Somnath Bharadwaj</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Meteorology &amp; Center for Theoretical Studies, I.I.T. Kharagpur, 721 302, India</affiliation>
						<email>somnath@phy.iitkgp.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shiv K." last="Sethi">Shiv K. Sethi</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, C. V. Raman Avenue, Sadashivnagar, Bangalore 560 080, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>On leave from Harish-Chandra Research Institute, Chhatnag Road, Jhusi, Allahabad 211 019, India.</affiliation>
						<email>sethi@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-03-15</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2002-05-31</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A Map for a Group of Resonant Cases in a Quartic Galactic Hamiltonian</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0309-0319</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present a map for the study of resonant motion in a potential made up of two harmonic oscillators with quartic perturbing terms. This potential can be considered to describe motion in the central parts of non-rotating elliptical galaxies. The map is based on the averaged Hamiltonian. Adding on a semi-empirical basis suitable terms in the unperturbed averaged Hamiltonian, corresponding to the $1:1$ resonant case, we are able to construct a map describing motion in several resonant cases. The map is used in order to find the $x- p_{x}$ Poincare phase plane for each resonance. Comparing the results of the map, with those obtained by numerical integration of the equation of motion, we observe, that the map describes satisfactorily the broad features of orbits in all studied cases for regular motion. There are cases where the map describes satisfactorily the properties of the chaotic orbits as well.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: elliptical-orbits-regular and chaotic motion;maps: averaged Hamiltonian;stability.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. D." last="Caranicolas">N. D. Caranicolas</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Section of Astrophysics, Astronomy and Mechanics, University of Thessaloniki, 540 06 Thessaloniki, Greece</affiliation>
						<email>caranic@helios.astro.auth.</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-10-11</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2001-11-29</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Real-Time Signal Processor for Pulsar Studies</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0321-0342</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This paper describes the design, tests and preliminary results of a real-time parallel signal processor built to aid a wide variety of pulsar observations. The signal processor reduces the distortions caused by the effects of dispersion, Faraday rotation, doppler acceleration and parallactic angle variations, at a sustained data rate of 32 Msamples/sec. It also folds the pulses coherently over the period and integrates adjacent samples in time and frequency to enhance the signal-to-noise ratio. The resulting data are recorded for further off-line analysis of the characteristics of pulsars and the intervening medium. The signal processing for analysis of pulsar signals is quite complex, imposing the need for a high computational throughput, typically of the order of a Giga operations per second (GOPS). Conventionally, the high computational demand restricts the flexibility to handle only a few types of pulsar observations. This instrument is designed to handle a wide variety of Pulsar observations with the Giant Metre Wave Radio Telescope (GMRT), and is flexible enough to be used in many other high-speed, signal processing applications. The technology used includes field-programmable-gate-array(FPGA) based data/code routing interfaces, PC-AT based control, diagnostics and data acquisition, digital signal processor (DSP) chip based parallel processing nodes and C language based control software and DSP-assembly programs for signal processing. The architecture and the software implementation of the parallel processor are fine-tuned to realize about 60 MOPS per DSP node and a multiple-instruction-multiple-data (MIMD) capability.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Stars: neutron;pulsars; interstellar medium: dispersion;Faraday rotation; telescope: GMRT; instrumentation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P. S." last="Ramkumar">P. S. Ramkumar</name>
						<affiliation>Present address: Intel Technology India Pvt Ltd, No. 65, 13th cross, III phase, JP Nagar, Bangalore 560 078.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. A." last="Deshpande">A. A. Deshpande</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, C. V. Raman Avenue, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-04-01</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2002-05-08</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Author Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0343-0344</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Subject Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0345-0349</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="023">
		<issue inum="01-02" month="03-06" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Preface</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0002</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Manchanda">R. K. Manchanda</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B." last="Paul">B. Paul</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Seismic View of the Solar Interior</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0003-0008</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The interior of the Sun is not directly observable to us. Nevertheless, it is possible to infer the physical conditions prevailing in the solar interior with the help of theoretical models coupled with observational input provided by measured frequencies of solar oscillations. The frequencies of these solar oscillations depend on the internal structure and dynamics of the Sun and from the knowledge of these frequencies it is possible to infer the internal structure as well as the large scale flows inside the Sun, in the same way as the observations of seismic waves on the surface of Earth help us in the study of its interior. With the accumulation of seismic data over the last six years it has also become possible to study temporal variations in the solar interior. Some of these seismic inferences would be described.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sun: oscillations, interior, rotation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="H. M." last="Antia">H. M. Antia</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Photometric Variability of Four Coronally Active Stars</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0009-0014</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present photometric observations of four stars that are optical counterparts of soft X-ray/EUV sources, namely 1ES 0829+15.9, 1ES0920-13.6, 2RE J110159+223509 and 1ES 1737+61.2. We have discovered periodic variability in two of the stars, viz., MCC 527 (1ES 0829+15.9; Period = 0$^{d}$.828 $\pm$ 0.0047) and HD 81032 (1ES 0920-13.6; Period = $\sim 57.02 \pm 0.560$ days). HD 95559 (2RE J110159+223509) is found to show a period of 3$^{d}$. HD 160934 (1ES1737+61.2) also shows photometric variability but needs to be monitored further for finding its period. These stars most likely belong to the class of chromospherically active stars.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Stars;variable, optical photometry, X-rays;source.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. C." last="Pandey">J. C. Pandey</name>
						<affiliation>State Observatory, Naini Tal 263 129, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. P." last="Singh">K. P. Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Sagar">R. Sagar</name>
						<affiliation>State Observatory, Naini Tal 263 129, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. A." last="Drake">S. A. Drake</name>
						<affiliation>Code 668, LHEA, NASA/Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD 20771, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Investigation of Nova-like Variable MV Lyr during the 1999–2001 Years</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0015-0018</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A peculiar nova-like MV Lyr was investigated. The CCD-observations ofMVLyr were continued in Crimea during the outbursts and quiescent states. Last year its behavior became non-typical for “anti-dwarf novae”. The length of its first deep minimum was 10 years. A modern state is characterized by very strong outbursts and very often changes of the stages. The periods 0.$^{d}$d128 and 0.$^{d}$d136 were obtained for 1998 and 1999 years accordingly. Possibly, a relation between the photometric period and the brightness exists.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cataclysmic variables;“anti-dwarf novae”.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. A." last="Katysheva">N. A. Katysheva</name>
						<affiliation>Sternberg Astronomical Institute, Moscow, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. Yu." last="Shugarov">S. Yu. Shugarov</name>
						<affiliation>Sternberg Astronomical Institute, Moscow, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="E. P." last="Pavlenko">E. P. Pavlenko</name>
						<affiliation>Crimean Astrophysical Observatory, p. Nauchny, Crimea.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P. V." last="Abolmasov">P. V. Abolmasov</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Department, Moscow State University, Moscow, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>High Energy Phenomena in Eta Carinae</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0019-0022</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have investigated with BeppoSAX the long term behaviour of the harder X-ray component of the supposed supermassive binary system $\eta$ Car along its 5.52 year cycle. We have found that in March 1998 during egress from the last December 1997 eclipse, this component was the same as outside eclipse, but for a large $(\times 3.5)$ increase of NH$_{h}$, that can be attributed to the presence or formation of opaque matter in front of the source near periastron. Unexpectedly, at that time the iron 6.7 keV emission line was 40\%\ stronger. BeppoSAX has for the first time found a <i>hard X-ray tail</i> extending to at least 50 keV, that cannot be adequately fitted with an additional hotter thermal component. The 2–100 keV spectrum of $\eta$ Car is instead well fitted with an absorbed powerlaw spectrum with photon index 2.53, suggesting non-thermal emission as an alternative model for the core source.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Colliding winds model;non-thermal emission;stars: $\eta$ Car;X-ray emission.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Roberto F." last="Viotti">Roberto F. Viotti</name>
						<affiliation>Istituto di Astrofisica Spaziale, CNR, 00133 Roma, Italy.</affiliation>
						<email>uvspace@ias.rm.cnr.it</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Lucio Angelo" last="Antonelli">Lucio Angelo Antonelli</name>
						<affiliation>Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, 00040 Monte Porzio, Italy.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sonja" last="Rebecchi">Sonja Rebecchi</name>
						<affiliation>ASI Science Data Centre, ESA-ESRIN, 00044 Frascati, Italy.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Corinne" last="Rossi">Corinne Rossi</name>
						<affiliation>Dipartimento di Fisica, Università La Sapienza, 00185 Roma, Italy.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Upper Limits on O VI Emission from Voyager Observations</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0023-0026</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have examined 426 <i>Voyager</i> fields distributed across the sky for O VI ($\gamma\gamma$ 1032/1038 Å) emission from the Galactic diffuse interstellar medium. No such emission was detected in any of our observed fields. Our most constraining limit was a 90\%\ confidence upper limit of 2600 photons cm$^{-2}$ sr$^{-1}$ s$^{-1}$ on the doublet emission in the direction (l, b) = (117.3, 50.6). Combining this with an absorption line measurement in nearly the same direction allows us to place an upper limit of 0.01 cm$^{-3}$ on the electron density of the hot gas in this direction. We have placed 90\%\ confidence upper limits of less than or equal to 10,000 photons cm$^{-2}$ sr$^{-1}$ s$^{-1}$ on the O VI emission in 16 of our 426 observations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxy: halo ISM: general.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Jayant" last="Murthy">Jayant Murthy</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Koramangala, Bangalore 560 034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Spectral Properties of the X-ray Binary Pulsar LMC X-4 during Different Intensity States</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0027-0031</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present spectral variations of the binary X-ray pulsar LMC X-4 observed with the RXTE/PCA during different phases of its 30.5 day long third period. Only out-of-eclipse data were used for this study. The 3–25 keV spectrum, modeled with high energy cut-off power-law and iron line emission is found to show strong dependence on the intensity state. Correlations between the Fe line emission flux and different parameters of the continuum are presented here.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Stars: individual: LMC X-4;stars: neutron;X-rays: stars.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Naik">S. Naik</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B." last="Paul">B. Paul</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Superorbital Period Variations in the X-ray Pulsar LMC X-4</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0033-0038</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report the discovery of a decay in the superorbital period of the binary X-ray pulsar LMC X-4. Combining archival data and published long term X-ray light curves, we have found a decay in the third period in this system ($P \sim 30.3$ day, $\dot{P}\sim -2\times 10^{-5}$ s s$^{-1}$). Along with this result, a comparison of the superorbital intensity variations in LMC X-4, Her X-1 and SMC X-1 is also presented.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Accretion, accretion disks;stars: individual (LMC X-4);stars: neutron;X-rays: stars, binaries.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="B." last="Paul">B. Paul</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Colaba, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Kitamoto">S. Kitamoto</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Rikkyo University, Nishii-Ikebukuro, 3-34-1, Toshima-ku, Tokyo, 171-8501, Japan.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>X-ray Spectroscopy of Cygnus X-3</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0039-0043</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have analysed the X-ray spectra of the highly variable X-ray source Cygnus X-3 over a wide energy range from 5 keV to 150 keV using data selected from the RXTE archives. Separate analysis of the low and hard states show the presence of a hard powerlaw tail in both the states. Here we present the result of the wide band spectral study of the source.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Binaries: close;stars: individual: Cygnus X-3;X-rays: binaries.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Choudhury">M. Choudhury</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. R." last="Rao">A. R. Rao</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Very High Energy $\gamma$- rays from Galactic Sources</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0045-0051</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The field of Very High Energy (VHE) gamma ray astronomy using the Atmospheric Cerenkov Technique has entered an interesting phase with detection of various galactic and extragalactic sources. Among galactic sources, only the Crab nebula has been established as a standard candle. Most observations on pulsars are in agreement as to the necessity for the GeV spectra to steepen at $\lt$ 200 GeV. While the Imaging method for increase of sensitivity has been successful with many results, an alternate technique – <i>Wavefront Sampling Technique</i> – is also being used by an increasing number of experiments. The recently commissioned experiment at Pachmarhi (PACT) in India is presented as an example of this technique. Preliminary results from this experiment show detection of VHE $\gamma$-ray emission from</p>
					<ol type="alpha">
						<li>the Crab nebula at a high significance and</li> 
						<li>Crab and Geminga pulsars at $\gt$ 1.5 TeV which could be the second component of the Outer Gap pulsar models.</li>
					</ol>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galactic sources;$\gamma$-ray astronomy;PACT.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P. R." last="Vishwanath">P. R. Vishwanath</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Arecibo Observations of Parkes Multibeam Pulsars</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0053-0057</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The on-going Parkes multibeam survey has been astoundingly successful (Manchester <i>et al.</i> 2001), and its discovery of over 600 pulsars has opened up new avenues for probing the Galaxy’s electron content and magnetic field. Here we report on recent observations made with the Arecibo 305-m telescope, where 80 distant, high dispersion measure pulsars (of which 35 are from the multibeam survey) were studied at multiple frequency bands in the range 0.4–2.4 GHz, in order to determine their scattering properties, rotation measures and spectral indices. The results will be used to meet a variety of science goals; viz., creating an improved model of the electron density, mapping out the Galactic magnetic field, and modeling the pulsar population.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Pulsars;interstellar matter;scattering;polarization.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. D. R." last="Bhat">N. D. R. Bhat</name>
						<affiliation>National Astronomy and Ionosphere Center, Arecibo Observatory, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="F." last="Camilo">F. Camilo</name>
						<affiliation>Columbia Astrophysics Laboratory, Columbia University, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. M." last="Cordes">J. M. Cordes</name>
						<affiliation>National Astronomy and Ionosphere Center and Cornell University, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D. J." last="Nice">D. J. Nice</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Princeton University, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D. R." last="Lorimer">D. R. Lorimer</name>
						<affiliation>Jodrell Bank Observatory, University of Manchester, U.K.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Chatterjee">S. Chatterjee</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Astronomy, Cornell University, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Spectroscopic Studies of X-Ray Binary Pulsars</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0059-0065</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Several new features of X-ray binary pulsars are revealed from recent observations with ASCA, RXTE, BeppoSAX and other X-ray observatories. Among these, I will review in this paper some recent progress in spectroscopic studies of accreting X-ray pulsars in binary systems (XBPs). First, I will discuss soft excess features observed in the energy spectra of XBPs and propose that it is a common feature for various subclasses of XBPs. Next I will present some recent results of high resolution spectroscopy with ASCA and Chandra.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>X-ray binaries, pulsars, spectra.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="F." last="Nagase">F. Nagase</name>
						<affiliation>The Institute of Space and Astronautical Science, Japan.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Evolution of Neutron Star Magnetic Fields</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0067-0072</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This paper reviews the current status of the theoretical models of the evolution of the magnetic fields of neutron stars other than magnetars. It appears that the magnetic fields of neutron stars decay significantly only if they are in binary systems. Three major physical models for this, namely spindown-induced flux expulsion, ohmic evolution of crustal field and diamagnetic screening of the field by accreted plasma, are reviewed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Neutron stars;Magnetic field.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Dipankar" last="Bhattacharya">Dipankar Bhattacharya</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>SROSS C-2 Detections of Gamma Ray Bursts and the SGR 1627-41</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0073-0079</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The GRB monitor (GRBM) on board the Indian SROSS C-2 satellite has detected 53 classical gamma ray bursts since its launch in May, 1994 till its re-entry in July, 2001. For a subset of 26 events, locations were obtained from simultaneous observations by other gamma-ray detectors in space. The sky distribution of these 26 SROSS C-2 bursts is consistent with isotropy. The distribution of event durations shows evidence for bimodality. There is an evidence for a moderate hardness ratio-intensity (HIC) correlation in the data. The SROSS C-2 GRBM has also detected three episodes of emission from the SGR 1627-41.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Gamma Ray Bursts;SGRs.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Sinha">S. Sinha</name>
						<affiliation>ISRO Satellite Center, Bangalore 560 017, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Sreekumar">P. Sreekumar</name>
						<affiliation>ISRO Satellite Center, Bangalore 560 017, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Kasturirangan">K. Kasturirangan</name>
						<affiliation>ISRO Satellite Center, Bangalore 560 017, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Chandra Observations of Tycho’s Supernova Remnant</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0081-0087</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present a new <i>Chandra</i> observation of Tycho’s supernova remnant with the Advanced CCD Imaging Spectrometer. Multicolor X-ray imaging reveals new details of the outer shock and ejecta. At energies between 4 and 6 keV, the outline of the outer shock is clearly revealed in X-rays for the first time. The distribution of the emission from lines of Si and Fe are confirmed to have a different morphology from each other, and the Si ejecta are shown to extend to the blast shock at several locations. Characteristic spectra of the outer shock and ejecta are also presented.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>X-rays;supernova remnants;interstellar medium;shocks;Tycho’s SNR;SN 1572.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="U." last="Hwang">U. Hwang</name>
						<affiliation>NASA GSFC (University of Maryland), USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Petre">R. Petre</name>
						<affiliation>University of Maryland, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. E." last="Szymkowiak">A. E. Szymkowiak</name>
						<affiliation>Yale University, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. S." last="Holt">S. S. Holt</name>
						<affiliation>Olin College of Engineering, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Multiwavelength Study of Two Unique Radio Galaxies</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0089-0093</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present the usage of multi-frequency and multi-band radio, VLA, observations as well as X-ray observations in order to study the environment around two powerful radio galaxies, namely Hercules A and 3 C310. We study their environment both in pc- and kpc-scales. We have chosen these two radio galaxies as they present similar and unique characteristics, compared to the ones from our general knowledge about double radio galaxies associated with active galactic nuclei.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: clusters: individual (Hercules A, 3 C310).</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Nectaria A. B." last="Gizani">Nectaria A. B. Gizani</name>
						<affiliation>Centro de Astronomia e Astrofísica da Univ. de Lisboa, O.A.L., Portugal.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. A." last="Garrett">M. A. Garrett</name>
						<affiliation>Joint Institute for VLBI in Europe, Postbus 2, The Netherlands.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. P." last="Leahy">J. P. Leahy</name>
						<affiliation>Jodrell Bank Observatory, Univ. of Manchester, UK.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Effect of Particle Acceleration Process on the Flare Characteristics of Blazars</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0095-0099</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Following the kinetic equation approach, we study the flare processes in blazars in the optical-to-X-ray region, considering energy dependent acceleration time-scale of electrons and synchrotron and adiabatic cooling as their dominant energy loss processes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Bhattacharyya">S. Bhattacharyya</name>
						<affiliation>Nuclear Research Laboratory, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Sahayanathan">S. Sahayanathan</name>
						<affiliation>Nuclear Research Laboratory, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="C. L." last="Kaul">C. L. Kaul</name>
						<affiliation>Nuclear Research Laboratory, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Heating of the Intracluster Medium by Quasar Outflows</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0101-0105</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We study the possibility of quasar outflows in clusters and groups of galaxies heating the intracluster gas in order to explain the recent observation of excess entropy in this gas. We show that radio galaxies alone cannot provide the energy required to explain the observations but the inclusion of Broad Absorption Line (BAL) outflows can do so, and that in this scenario most of the heating takes place at $z\sim$ 1–4, the “preheating” epoch being at a lower redshift for lower mass clusters.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmology: theory;Galaxies: intergalactic medium;X-rays: galaxies: clusters.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Suparna" last="Roychowdhury">Suparna Roychowdhury</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Biman B." last="Nath">Biman B. Nath</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Probes of Cosmic Star Formation History</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0107-0113</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>I summarize X-ray diagnostic studies of cosmic star formation history in terms of evolutionary schemes for X-ray binary evolution in normal galaxies with evolving star formation. Deep X-ray imaging studies by <i>Chandra</i> and <i>XMM-Newton</i> are now beginning to constrain both the X-ray luminosity evolution of galaxies and the $\log N$–$\log S$ diagnostics of the X-ray background. I discuss these in the above context, summarizing current understanding and future prospects.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: evolution;stars: formation;X-rays: galaxies, background;binaries: close.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Pranab" last="Ghosh">Pranab Ghosh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Bombay 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>CLASS B 1359 + 154: Modelling Lensing by a Group of Galaxies</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0115-0118</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The recently discovered gravitationally lensed system CLASS B1359+154 appears to have six detectable images of a single background source at a redshift of 3.235. A group of galaxies acts as the lens, at a redshift of $\sim 1$. The present work identifies two distinct, physically plausible image configurations, a 7-image one and a 9-image one. Mass models are constructed corresponding to realizations of these two configurations. Both models call for, in addition to non-singular galaxy-type lenses, a larger scale mass component that resembles the extended dark matter distributions seen in relatively low-redshift galaxy groups. It is presently observationally impossible to study the extended X-ray emission from a group at such a high redshift, hence lensing studies are of some interest. A lensed system with a high image multiplicity does not necessarily admit of a unique lensing interpretation; discrimination is possible with additional observable details (e.g., the image parities, which are uncommon among even the simpler systems).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Gravitational lensing: multiple-imaging;individual systems: CLASS B1359 + 154;galaxy groups;dark matter.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Sunita" last="Nair">Sunita Nair</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Preliminary Results on VLT K-band Imaging Observations of GRB Host Galaxies</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0119-0122</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have obtained $K$-band imaging observations of Gamma-Ray Burst (GRB) host galaxies with the near-infrared spectro-imager ISAAC installed on the Very Large Telescope at Paranal (Chile). The derived $K$ magnitudes, combined with other photometric data taken from the literature, are used to investigate the $R$–$K$ colors of GRB hosts. We do not find any extremely reddened starbursts in our sample, despite the capability of GRBs to trace star formation even in dusty regions. The observed $R$–$K$ colors are on the contrary typical of irregular and spiral blue galaxies at high redshift.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: evolution, high-redshift, dust;Gamma-ray Bursts.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="E. Le" last="Floc’h">E. Le Floc’h</name>
						<affiliation>Service d’Astrophysique, CEA-Saclay, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="I. F." last="Mirabel">I. F. Mirabel</name>
						<affiliation>Service d’Astrophysique, CEA-Saclay, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P.-A." last="Duc">P.-A. Duc</name>
						<affiliation>Service d’Astrophysique, CEA-Saclay, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Multi-band Observations of Gamma Ray Bursts</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0123-0127</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This talk focuses on the various aspects we learnt from multiband observations of GRBs both, before and during the afterglow era. A statistical analysis to estimate the probable redshifts of host galaxies using the luminosity function of GRBs compatible with both the afterglow redshift data as well as the overall population of GRBs is discussed. We then address the question whether the observed fields of GRBs with precise localizations from third Inter-Planetary Network (IPN$^{3}$) contain suitable candidates for their host galaxies.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Gamma rays: bursts;CCD: observations;Methods: statistical.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. G." last="Bhargavi">S. G. Bhargavi</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034, India</affiliation>
						<email>bhargavi@iiap.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>An Exact Solution of the Gamma Ray Burst Arrival Time Analysis Problem</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0129-0135</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>An analytical solution of the GRB arrival time analysis is presented. The errors in the position of the GRB resulting from timing and position errors of different satellites are calculated. A simple method of cross-correlating gamma ray burst time-histories is discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Gamma Ray Bursts;triangulation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Sinha">S. Sinha</name>
						<affiliation>ISRO Satellite Center, Bangalore 560 017, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A Circular Statistical Method for Extracting Rotation Measures</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0137-0141</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We propose a new method for the extraction of Rotation Measures from spectral polarization data. The method is based on maximum likelihood analysis and takes into account the circular nature of the polarization data. The method is unbiased and statistically more efficient than the standard $\chi^{2}$ procedure.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Polarization;methods: data analysis;galaxies: magnetic fields.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Sarala">S. Sarala</name>
						<affiliation>Physics Department, IIT, Kanpur 208 016, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Pankaj" last="Jain">Pankaj Jain</name>
						<affiliation>Physics Department, IIT, Kanpur 208 016, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Standing Shocks around Black Holes and Estimation of Outflow Rates</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0143-0147</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We self-consistently obtain shock locations in an accretion flow by using an analytical method. One can obtain the spectral properties, quasi-periodic oscillation frequencies and the outflowrates when the inflow parameters are known. Since temperature of the CENBOL decides the spectral states of the black hole, and also the outflow rate, the outflow rate is directly related to the spectral states.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Accretion;accretion disk;black hole physics;shock waves;outflows.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Santabrata" last="Das">Santabrata Das</name>
						<affiliation>S N Bose National Center for Basic Sciences, Block - JD; Sector - III, Salt Lake, Kolkata - 98, West Bengal, India.</affiliation>
						<email>sbdas@bose.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sandip K." last="Chakrabarti">Sandip K. Chakrabarti</name>
						<affiliation>S N Bose National Center for Basic Sciences, Block - JD; Sector - III, Salt Lake, Kolkata - 98, West Bengal, India.</affiliation>
						<email>chakraba@bose.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Radiatively Driven Winds from Effective Boundary Layer around Black Holes</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0149-0153</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Matter accreting onto black holes suffers a standing or oscillating shock wave in much of the parameter space. The post-shock region is hot, puffed up and reprocesses soft photons from a Keplerian disc to produce the characteristic hard tail of the spectrum of accretion discs. The post-shock torus is also the base of the bipolar jets. We study the interaction of these jets with the hard photons emitted from the disc. We show that radiative force can accelerate outflows but the drag can limit the terminal speed. We introduce an equilibrium speed $v_{eq}$ as a function of distance, above which the flow will experience radiative deceleration.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Accretion;accretion disc;black hole physics;winds;outflows.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Indranil" last="Chattopadhyay">Indranil Chattopadhyay</name>
						<affiliation>S. N. Bose National Centre for Basic Sciences, Block-JD, Sector-III, Kolkata 98.</affiliation>
						<email>indra@bose.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sandip K." last="Chakrabarti">Sandip K. Chakrabarti</name>
						<affiliation>S. N. Bose National Centre for Basic Sciences, Block-JD, Sector-III, Kolkata 98.</affiliation>
						<email>chakraba@bose.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Interaction of Accretion Shocks with Winds</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0155-0164</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Accretion shocks are known to oscillate in presence of cooling processes in the disk. This oscillation may also cause quasi-periodic oscillations of black holes. In the presence of strong winds, these shocks have oscillations in vertical direction as well.We show examples of shock oscillations under the influence of both the effects. When the shocks are absent and the flow is cooler, the wind becomes weaker and the vertical oscillation becomes negligible.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Black hole physics;accretion;winds;shock waves;hydrodynamics.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Kinsuk" last="Acharya">Kinsuk Acharya</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Space Physics, P-61 Southend Gardens, Kolkata 700 084, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sandip K." last="Chakrabarti">Sandip K. Chakrabarti</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Space Physics, P-61 Southend Gardens, Kolkata 700 084, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>S. N. Bose National Center for Basic Sciences, JD Block, Salt Lake, Kolkata 700 098, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D." last="Molteni">D. Molteni</name>
						<affiliation>University of Palermo, Via Archirafi 36, I-90123, Italy.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Tracking the Shadows through GMRT</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0165-0171</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The structures of faint high redshift galaxies cannot be observed directly. But if a luminous quasar is located farther along their line of sight, high resolution absorption lines offer a valuable and reliable probe to their structure. GMRT is suited to monitor the absorption spectra, if the redshifted neutral hydrogen or OH doublet fall in one of the windows of the telescope. We present the OH doublet absorption spectra for the system B0218+357, taken at GMRT this year at resolution of approx. 9.5 km/sec with an rms noise of the order of 1 mJy. Based on our study of the OH doublet and 21cm neutral hydrogen line we infer that, in the lensing spiral galaxy of B0218+57, neutral hydrogen and OH coexist in tenous clouds and there is possibly a hole in the central part of the galaxy. In contrast, the gas is seen in high density clouds in the lens in an otherwise similar system PKS1830-211.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Gravitational lens, molecular absorption lines, quasar;B0218 + 357.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D." last="Narasimha">D. Narasimha</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai 400 005.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N." last="Kanekar">N. Kanekar</name>
						<affiliation>NCRA, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Pune 411 007.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. N." last="Chengalur">J. N. Chengalur</name>
						<affiliation>NCRA, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Pune 411 007.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03-04" month="09-12" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Connecting Global to Local Parameters in Barred Galaxy Models</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0173-0183</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present connections between global and local parameters in a realistic dynamical model, describing motion in a barred galaxy. Expanding the global model in the vicinity of a stable Lagrange point, we find the potential of a two-dimensional perturbed harmonic oscillator, which describes local motion near the centre of the global model. The frequencies of oscillations and the coefficients of the perturbing terms are not arbitrary but are connected to the mass, the angular rotation velocity, the scale length and the strength of the galactic bar. The local energy is also connected to the global energy. A comparison of the properties of orbits in the global and local potential is also made.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: barred;orbits;global and local parameters.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. D." last="Caranicolas">N. D. Caranicolas</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Section of Astrophysics, Astronomy and Mechanics, University of Thessaloniki, 540 06 Thessaloniki, Greece.</affiliation>
						<email>caranic@helios.astro.auth.gr</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-03-26</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2002-11-14</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>TreePM: A Code for Cosmological N-Body Simulations</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0185-0196</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We describe the TreePM method for carrying out large N-Body simulations to study formation and evolution of the large scale structure in the Universe. This method is a combination of Barnes and Hut tree code and Particle-Mesh code. It combines the automatic inclusion of periodic boundary conditions of PM simulations with the high resolution of tree codes. This is done by splitting the gravitational force into a short range and a long range component. We describe the splitting of force between these two parts.We outline the key differences between TreePM and some other N-Body methods.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Gravitation;methods: numerical;cosmology: large scale structure of the universe.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. S." last="Bagla">J. S. Bagla</name>
						<affiliation>Harish-Chandra Research Institute, Chhatnag Road, Jhunsi, Allahabad 211 019, India.</affiliation>
						<email>jasjeet@mri.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-06-13</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2002-11-14</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Spectral Measurements of Cyg X-3: A Thermal Source Embedded in Hot Plasma within a Cold Shell</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0197-0212</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The attempts at unified model fitting to explain the spectral variations in Cyg X-3 suggest equally probable fits with a combination of an absorbed blackbody and a separately absorbed power law with an exponential cut-off or a composite of absorbed free-free emission with a power law hard X-ray component apart from the iron emission line. These seemingly ordinary but ad hoc mixtures of simple X-ray emission mechanisms have a profound implication about the geometry of the X-ray source. While the first set suggests a black-hole nature of the compact object, the second combination is consistent with a neutron star binary picture. The spectral variability at hard X-ray energies above 30 keV can provide crucial input for the unified picture. In this paper, we present spectral observations of Cyg X-3, made in our on-going survey of galactic and extragalactic X-ray sources in the 20–200 keV energy region, using Large Area Scintillation counter Experiment. The data show a clear power-law photon spectrum of the form $\frac{{\rm d}N}{{\rm d}E}\sim E^{-2.8}$ in the 20 to 130 keVenergy range. Acomparison with earlier data suggests that the total number of X-ray photons in the entire 2–500 keV energy band is conserved at all time for a given luminosity level irrespective of the state. We propose that this behaviour can be explained by a simple geometry in which a thermal X-ray source is embedded in a hot plasma formed by winds from the accretion disk within a cold shell. The high/soft and low/hard X-ray states of the source are simply the manifestation of the extent of the surrounding scattering medium in which the seed photons are Comptonized and hot plasma can be maintained by either the X-ray driven winds or the magneto-centrifugal winds.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Low mass X-ray binaries;X-ray sources;Cyg X-3.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Manchanda">R. K. Manchanda</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email>ravi@tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-08-23</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2002-10-21</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Fast Transition between High-soft and Low-soft States in GRS 1915 + 105: Evidence for a Critically Viscous Accretion Flow</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0213-0233</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present the results of a detailed analysis of RXTE observations of class $\omega$ (Klein-Wolt <i>et al.</i> 2002) which show an unusual state transition between high-soft and low-soft states in the Galactic microquasar GRS 1915+105. Out of about 600 pointed RXTE observations, the source was found to exhibit such state transition only on 16 occasions. An examination of the RXTE/ASM data in conjunction with the pointed observations reveals that these events appeared as a series of quasi-regular dips in two stretches of long duration (about 20 days during each occasion) when hard X-ray and radio flux were very low. The X-ray light curve and colour-colour diagram of the source during these observations are found to be different from any reported so far. The duration of these dips is found to be of the order of a few tens of seconds with a repetition time of a few hundred seconds. The transition between these dips and non-dips which differ in intensity by a factor of $\sim 3.5$, is observed to be very fast ($\sim$ a few seconds). It is observed that the low-frequency narrow QPOs are absent in the power density spectrum (PDS) of the dip and non-dip regions of class $\omega$ and the PDS is a power law in the 0.1 – 10 Hz frequency range. There is a remarkable similarity in the spectral and timing properties of the source during the dip and non-dip regions in this set of observations. These properties of the source are distinctly different from those seen in the observations of other classes. This indicates that the basic accretion disk structure during both dip and non-dip regions of class $\omega$ is similar, but differ only in intensity. To explain these observations, we invoke a model in which the viscosity is very close to critical viscosity and the shock wave is weak or absent.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Accretion, accretion discs;binaries: close;black hole physics;stars: individual: GRS 1915 + 105;X-rays: stars</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Naik">S. Naik</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. R." last="Rao">A. R. Rao</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai, 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sandip K." last="Chakrabarti">Sandip K. Chakrabarti</name>
						<affiliation>S. N. Bose National Center for Basic Sciences, Salt Lake, Calcutta, 700 091, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>On the Relativistic Beaming and Orientation Effects in Core-Dominated Quasars</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0235-0242</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this paper, we investigate the relativistic beaming effects in a well-defined sample of core-dominated quasars using the correlation between the relative prominence of the core with respect to the extended emission (defined as the ratio of core- to lobe- flux density measured in the rest frame of the source) and the projected linear size as an indicator of relativistic beaming and source orientation. Based on the orientation-dependent relativistic beaming and unification paradigm for high luminosity sources in which the Fanaroff-Riley class-II radio galaxies form the unbeamed parent population of both the lobe- and core-dominated quasars which are expected to lie at successively smaller angles to the line of sight, we find that the flows in the cores of these core-dominated quasars are highly relativistic, with optimum bulk Lorentz factor, $\gamma_{opt}\sim 6$&#8212;16, and also highly anisotropic, with an average viewing angle, $\sim 9^{\circ}-16^{\circ}$. Furthermore, the largest boosting occurs within a critical cone angle of $\approx 4^{\circ}-10^{\circ}$.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: active, jets, quasars: general.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A. A." last="Ubachukwu">A. A. Ubachukwu</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Nigeria Nsukka, Nigeria</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Regular Associate of the Abdus Salam ICTP, Trieste Italy</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. E." last="Chukwude">A. E. Chukwude</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Nigeria Nsukka, Nigeria</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-07-31</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2002-12-11</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Spectral Variability in Hard X-rays and the Evidence for a 13.5 Years Period in the Bright Quasar 3C273</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0243-0258</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report the observation of nearest quasar 3C273 made with LASE instrument on November 20th, 1998 as a part of our continuing programme of balloon borne hard X-ray observations in the 20–200 keV band using high sensitivity Large Area Scintillation counter Experiment. Our data clearly show a steep spectrum in the 20–200 keV with power law spectral index $\alpha = 226\pm 0.07$. This is in complete contrast to the reported data from OSSE and BeppoSAX which suggest the value of 1.3 to 1.6 for the power law index in the X-ray energy band, but is quite consistent with the value derived for the high energy gamma ray data. A single power law fit in the X-ray and gamma ray energy bands points to a common origin of these photons and the absence of spectral break around 1 MeV as suggested in literature. We have reanalyzed the available data to study the temporal variability of the spectrum in the hard X-ray band. Our analysis reveals that 50 keV flux from the source, shows a strong modulation with a period of about 13.5 years. The analysis of the optical light curve of the source also supports the 5000 day period.We discuss the emission mechanism and the possible sites for X-ray photons along with the implications of the long term periodicity with respect to source geometry.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: active galactic nuclei, jets, binary black hole system;quasars: individual 3C273;X-rays: galaxies.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Manchanda">R. K. Manchanda</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
						<email>ravi@tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-10-21</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2002-12-12</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Author Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0259-0260</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Subject Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0261-0264</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="024">
		<issue inum="01-02" month="03-06" year="2003">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Editorial</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0001</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Rajaram" last="Nityananda">Rajaram Nityananda</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Is the Age Problem Resolved?</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0003-0010</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The cosmological, astrophysical, and nucleocosmochronological methods for estimating the age of the universe and the corresponding uncertainties are comparatively studied in the present paper.We are led to the conclusion that the newmeasurements of cosmological parameters, and the recent estimates of the age of globular clusters have led to the gradual disappearance of the age problem from the arena of modern cosmology.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmology: age of the universe, cosmological parameters.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Ali Akbar" last="Navabi">Ali Akbar Navabi</name>
						<affiliation>Institute for Advanced Studies in Basic Sciences, Zanjan, Iran.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Nematollah" last="Riazi">Nematollah Riazi</name>
						<affiliation>Physics Department and Biruni Observatory, Shiraz University, Shiraz 71454, Iran, and IPM, Farmanieh, Tehran, Iran.</affiliation>
						<email>riazi@physics.susc.ac.ir</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-10-08</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2003-01-16</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Hubble Relation for a Comprehensive Sample of QSOs</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0011-0021</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A correlation between redshifts $(z)$ and apparent magnitudes $(V)$ (Hubble relation) of Quasi Stellar Objects (QSOs) has long been sought. Such a correlation exists for galaxies whose redshifts are of cosmological origin. However, a plot of the two quantities representing the Hubble diagram for QSOs exhibits, in general, a wild scatter. This raises the question whether redshifts of QSOs are cosmological. On the other hand, most luminous QSOs in groups, and subsamples with particular properties, have been reported to show the Hubble relation. In the present paper, we analyse all optically non-variable QSOs in a comprehensive sample. In our analysis we grouped the objects into certain intervals of apparent magnitudes. Correlations obtained between redshifts and magnitudes are all statistically robust. Also, the Hubble relation in the usual form $V=5\log z+C$ is obeyed very convincingly for QSOs with $V\lt 19.5$.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmology;Hubble relation;quasi stellar objects or QSOs;redshifts.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D." last="Basu">D. Basu</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Carleton University, Ottawa, ON K1S 5B6, Canada.</affiliation>
						<email>basu@physics.carleton.ca</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-12-11</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2003-05-31</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>HI Fluctuations at Large Redshifts: II – the Signal Expected for the GMRT</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0023-0035</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>For the GMRT, we calculate the expected signal from redshifted HI emission at two frequency bands centered at 610 and 325MHz. The study focuses on the visibility-visibility cross-correlations, proposed earlier as the optimal statistical estimator for detecting and analyzing this signal. These correlations directly probe the power spectrum of density fluctuations at the redshift where the radiation originated, and thereby provide a method for studying the large scale structures at large redshifts. We present detailed estimates of the correlations expected between the visibilities measured at different baselines and frequencies. Analytic fitting formulas representing the salient features of the expected signal are also provided. These will be useful in planning observations and deciding an optimal strategy for detecting this signal.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmology: theory, observations, large scale structures;diffuse radiation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Somnath" last="Bharadwaj">Somnath Bharadwaj</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Meteorology &amp; Center for Theoretical Studies, I.I.T. Kharagpur 721 302, India.</affiliation>
						<email>somnath@phy.iitkgp.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sanjay K." last="Pandey"></name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, L.B.S. College, Gonda 271 001, India.</affiliation>
						<email>spandey@iucaa.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-05-17</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2003-06-04</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>GMRT Detection of HI 21cm Associated Absorption towards the $z = 1.2$ Red Quasar 3C 190</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0037-0043</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report the GMRT detection of associated HI 21 cm-line absorption in the $z = 1.1946$ red quasar 3C 190. Most of the absorption is blue-shifted with respect to the systemic redshift. The absorption, at $\sim 647.7$MHz, is broad and complex, spanning a velocity width of $\sim 600$ kms$^{-1}$. Since the core is self-absorbed at this frequency, the absorption is most likely towards the hotspots. Comparison of the radio and deep optical images reveal linear filaments in the optical which overlap with the brighter radio jet towards the south-west.We therefore suggest that most of the HI 21 cm-line absorption could be occurring in the atomic gas shocked by the south-west jet.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: active;quasars: absorption lines;radio lines: galaxies;quasars: individual (3C190).</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="C. H." last="Ishwara-Chandra">C. H. Ishwara-Chandra</name>
						<affiliation>National Center for Radio Astrophysics, TIFR, Post Bag 3, Ganeshkhind, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email>ishwar@ncra.tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Dwarakanath">K. S. Dwarakanath</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>dwaraka@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. R." last="Anantharamaiah">K. R. Anantharamaiah</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>dwaraka@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-03-27</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2003-06-05</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Guidelines for Authors</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0045-0050</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03-04" month="09-12" year="2003">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Large Scale Magnetic Fields: Density Power Spectrum in Redshift Space</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0051-0067</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We compute the density redshift-space power spectrum in the presence of tangled magnetic fields and compare it with existing observations. Our analysis shows that if these magnetic fields originated in the early universe then it is possible to construct models for which the shape of the power spectrum agrees with the large scale slope of the observed power spectrum. However requiring compatibility with observed CMBR anisotropies, the normalization of the power spectrum is too low for magnetic fields to have significant impact on the large scale structure at present. Magnetic fields of a more recent origin generically give density power spectrum $\propto k^{4}$ which doesn’t agree with the shape of the observed power spectrum at any scale. Magnetic fields generate curl modes of the velocity field which increase both the quadrupole and hexadecapole of the redshift space power spectrum. For curl modes, the hexadecapole dominates over quadrupole. So the presence of curl modes could be indicated by an anomalously large hexadecapole, which has not yet been computed from observation.</p>
					<p>It appears difficult to construct models in which tangled magnetic fields could have played a major role in shaping the large scale structure in the present epoch. However if they did, one of the best ways to infer their presence would be from the redshift space effects in the density power spectrum.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmology: theory;large-scale structure of the universe;magnetic fields;MHD.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Rajesh" last="Gopal">Rajesh Gopal</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>rajesh@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shiv K." last="Sethi"></name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>sethi@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-09-05</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-01-06</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Studies of Clump Structure of Photodissociation Regions at Millimeter and Sub-millimeterWavelengths</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0069-0083</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>To interpret the millimeter and sub-millimeter line emissions of atomic and molecular species from galactic and extragalactic photodissociation regions, warm gas components and molecular clouds, generally, escape probability formalism of Tielens &amp; Hollenbach (herein referred as TH) are employed which is based on the assumption of plane parallel geometry of infinite slab allowing photons to escape only from the front. Contrary to the assumption observationally it is found that these lines are optically thin except OI(63$\mu$m) and low rotational transitions of CO and some other molecules. This observational evidence led us to assume that emitting regions are finite parallel plane slab in which photons are allowed to escape from both the surfaces (back and front). Therefore, in the present study escape of radiations from both sides of the homogeneous and also clumpy PDR/molecular clouds are taken into consideration for calculating the line intensities at millimeter and sub-millimeter wavelengths (hereinafter referred as QA). Results are compared with that of the TH model. It is found that thermal and chemical structures of the regions are almost similar in both the formalisms. But line intensities are modified by differing factors. Particularly at lowdensity and lowkinetic temperature and also for optically thin lines line intensities calculated from TH and QA model differ substantially. But at density higher than the critical density and also for optically thick lines TH and QA models converge to almost same values. An attempt has been made to study the physical conditions of the M17 region employing the present formalism.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Photodissociation region;clump structure;cooling lines;fine structure transitions and rotational transitions.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Abdul" last="Qaiyum">Abdul Qaiyum</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh 202 002, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Syed Salman" last="Ali">Syed Salman Ali</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh 202 002, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-12-21</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2003-07-05</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Comparing Maps to Symplectic Integrators in a Galactic Type Hamiltonian</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0085-0097</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We obtain the $x - p_{x}$ Poincare phase plane for a two dimensional, resonant, galactic type Hamiltonian using conventional numerical integration, a second order symplectic integrator and a map based on the averaged Hamiltonian. It is found that all three methods give good results, for small values of the perturbation parameter, while the symplectic integrator does a better job than the mapping, for large perturbations. The dynamical spectra are used to distinguish between regular and chaotic motion.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: orbits;regular and chaotic motion maps: averaged Hamiltonian;stability.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. D." last="Caranicolas">N. D. Caranicolas</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Section of Astrophysics, Astronomy and Mechanics, University of Thessaloniki, 540 06 Thessaloniki, Greece.</affiliation>
						<email>caranic@astro.auth.gr</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. J." last="Papadopoulos">N. J. Papadopoulos</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Section of Astrophysics, Astronomy and Mechanics, University of Thessaloniki, 540 06 Thessaloniki, Greece.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-03-31</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2003-06-27</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Mass/Eccentricity Limit in Double Star Astronomy</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0099-0109</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A research that we conducted in 1963 on the evolution of the binaries based on the available orbital data to obtain a philosophical degree, led to the establishment of an interesting and new diagram between the logarithm of the total mass and a particular parameter $X$, bound to the areal constant. This appeared to have a real physical significance but the basic observational material was insufficiently extended to assure its undeniable existence. In 1981, a new research based on a more extended orbital material, has confirmed this diagram. Presently, another important increase in the orbital material and the availability of highly accurate trigonometric parallaxes produced by the Hipparcos satellite, gave us the opportunity to confirm once more the stability of this diagram. This last research is here described.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Stellar evolution;statistics;binaries.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J." last="Dommanget">J. Dommanget</name>
						<affiliation>Observatoire Royal de Belgique, 3, avenue Circulaire, B-1180 Bruxelles, Belgique.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-07-30</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2003-10-03</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Author Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0111-0111</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Subject Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0113-0113</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="025">
		<issue inum="01-02" month="03-06" year="2004">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Optical Variability Properties of High Luminosity AGN Classes</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0055</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We present the results of a comparative study of the intra-night optical variability (INOV) characteristics of radio-loud and radio-quiet quasars, which involves a systematic intra-night optical monitoring of seven sets of high luminosity AGNs covering the redshift range $z\simeq 0.2$ to $z\simeq 2.2$. The sample, matched in the optical luminosity – redshift $(M_{B}-z)$ plane, consists of seven radio-quiet quasars (RQQs), eight radio lobe-dominated quasars (LDQs), five radio core-dominated quasars (CDQs) and six BL Lac objects (BLs). Systematic CCD observations, aided by a careful data analysis procedure, have allowed us to detect INOV with amplitudes as low as about 1\%\. Present observations cover a total of 113 nights (720 hours) with only a single qusar monitored as continuously as possible on a given night. Considering the cases of only unambiguous detections of INOV we have estimated duty cycles (DCs) of 17\%, 12\%, 20\%\ and 61\%\ for RQQs, LDQs, CDQs, and BLs, respectively. The much lower amplitude and DC of INOV shown by RQQs compared to BLs may be understood in terms of their having optical synchrotron jets which are modestly misdirected from us. From our fairly extensive dataset, no general trend of a correlation between the INOVamplitude and the apparent optical brightness of the quasar is noticed. This suggests that the physical mechanisms of INOV and long term optical variability (LTOV) do not have a one-to-one relationship and different factors are involved. Also, the absence of a clear negative correlation between the INOV and LTOV characteristics of blazars of our sample points toward an inconspicuous contribution of accretion disk fluctuations to the observed INOV. The INOV duty cycle of the AGNs observed in this program suggests that INOV is associated predominantly with the highly polarized optical emission components. We also report new VLA imaging of two RQQs (1029 + 329 &amp; 1252 + 020) in our sample which has yielded a 5 GHz detection in one of them (1252 + 020; $S_{5\text{\,GHz}}\simeq 1$ mJy)</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: active;galaxies: jets;galaxies: photometry;quasars: general.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="C. S." last="Stalin">C. S. Stalin</name>
						<affiliation>Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Manora Peak Nainital 263 129, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Radio Astrophysics, TIFR, Pune University Campus, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Laboratoire de Physique Corpusculaire et Cosmolgie, College de France, 11 pl. Marcelin Berthelot, F-75231, Paris Cedex 5, France.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="" last="Gopal-Krishna">Gopal-Krishna</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Radio Astrophysics, TIFR, Pune University Campus, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ram" last="Sagar">Ram Sagar</name>
						<affiliation>Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Manora Peak Nainital 263 129, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Paul J." last="Wiita">Paul J. Wiita</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics &amp; Astronomy, MSC 8R0314, Georgia State University, Atlanta, Georgia 30303-3088, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-06-24</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-06-22</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Associated HI Absorption in the $z = 3.4$ Radio Galaxy B2 0902 + 343 Observed with the GMRT</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0057-0065</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have made observations of the associated HI absorption of a high redshift radio galaxy 0902+34 at $z = 3.395$ with the Giant Meterwave Radio Telescope in the 323+1 MHz band. We find a narrow absorption line with a flux density of 11.5 mJy at a redshift of 3.397 consistent with that observed by Uson <i>>et al.</i> (1991), Briggs <i>et al.</i> (1993) and de Bruyn (1996). A weak broad absorption feature reported by de Bruyn (1996) has not been detected in our observations. We also place an upper limit of 4 mJy $(2\sigma)$ on emission line strength at the position where Uson <i>et al.</i> (1991) claimed to have found a narrow emission line.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: active; absorption lines;radio lines; galaxies;radio galaxies; individual (0902 + 343).</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Poonam" last="Chandra">Poonam Chandra</name>
						<affiliation>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai 400 005, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Joint Astronomy Programme, IISc, Bangalore 560 012, India.</affiliation>
						<email>poonam@tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Govind" last="Swarup">Govind Swarup</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Radio Astrophysics, TIFR, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email>swarup@ncra.tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Vasant K." last="Kulkarni">Vasant K. Kulkarni</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Radio Astrophysics, TIFR, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email>vasant@ncra.tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Nimisha G." last="Kantharia">Nimisha G. Kantharia</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Radio Astrophysics, TIFR, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email>ngk@ncra.tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-01-28</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-06-14</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>HI Fluctuations at Large Redshifts: III – Simulating the Signal Expected at GMRT</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0067-0080</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We simulate the distribution of neutral hydrogen (HI) at the redshifts $z = 1.3$ and 3.4 using a cosmological N-body simulation along with a prescription for assigning HI masses to the particles. The HI is distributed in clouds whose properties are consistent with those of the damped Lyman-$\alpha$ absorption systems (DLAs) seen in quasar spectra. The clustering properties of these clouds are identical to those of the dark matter. We use this to simulate the redshifted HI emission expected at 610 MHz and 325 MHz, two of the observing bands at the GMRT. These are used to predict the correlations expected between the complex visibilities measured at different baselines and frequencies in radio-interferometric observations with the GMRT. The visibility correlations directly probe the power spectrum of HI fluctuations at the epoch when the HI emission originated, and this holds the possibility of using HI observations to study large-scale structures at high $z$.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmology: theory, observations, large scale structures;radiation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Somnath" last="Bharadwaj">Somnath Bharadwaj</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Meteorology and Center for Theoretical Studies, I.I.T. Kharagpur, 721 302, India.</affiliation>
						<email>somnath@phy.iitkgp.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Pennathur Sridharan" last="Srikant">Pennathur Sridharan Srikant</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Meteorology, I.I.T. Kharagpur, 721 302, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Present address: Department of Physics, University of Utah, USA.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-08-25</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-05-07</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Angular Momentum Transport in Quasi-Keplerian Accretion Disks</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0081-0091</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We reexamine arguments advanced by Hayashi &amp; Matsuda (2001), who claim that several simple, physically motivated derivations based on mean free path theory for calculating the viscous torque in a quasi-Keplerian accretion disk yield results that are inconsistent with the generally accepted model. If correct, the ideas proposed by Hayashi &amp; Matsuda would radically alter our understanding of the nature of the angular momentum transport in the disk, which is a central feature of accretion disk theory. However, in this paper we point out several fallacies in their arguments and show that there indeed exists a simple derivation based on mean free path theory that yields an expression for the viscous torque that is proportional to the radial derivative of the angular velocity in the accretion disk, as expected. The derivation is based on the analysis of the epicyclic motion of gas parcels in adjacent eddies in the disk.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Accretion;viscosity, disks, angular momentum.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Prasad" last="Subramanian">Prasad Subramanian</name>
						<affiliation>Inter-University Center for Astronomy and Astrophysics, P.O Bag 4, Ganeshkhind, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email>psubrama@iucaa.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. S." last="Pujari">B. S. Pujari</name>
						<affiliation>Dept. of Physics, University of Pune, Pune 411 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email>bspujari@rediffmail.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Peter A." last="Becker">Peter A. Becker</name>
						<affiliation>School of Computational Sciences, George Mason University, Fairfax, VA 22030, USA.</affiliation>
						<email>pbecker@gmu.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-05-09</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-03-16</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Radial Matrix Elements of Hydrogen Atom and the Correspondence Principle</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0093-0101</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Radial dipole matrix elements having astrophysical importance have been computed for highly excited states of hydrogen atom. Computation is based on Heisenberg’s form of correspondence principle for Coulomb potential. Particular attention has been paid to the choice of classical analogue $(n_{c})$ of principal quantum number $(n)$. The computed radial matrix elements are in good agreement with quantum mechanical results. Further, radial matrix elements for few transitions involving high $n$ neighboring states of hydrogen atom are presented.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Hydrogen excited states;radial matrix element;correspondence principle.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="T. N." last="Chakrabarty">T. N. Chakrabarty</name>
						<affiliation>Applied Physics Department, Fr. Conceicao Rodrigues College of Engineering, Fr. Agnel Ashram, Bandstand, Bandra (W), Mumbai 400 050, India.</affiliation>
						<email>tn_chakrabarty@yahoo.co.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-10-01</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-02-10</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03-04" month="09-12" year="2004">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>TreePM Method for Two-Dimensional Cosmological Simulations</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0103-0113</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We describe the two-dimensional TreePM method in this paper. The 2d TreePM code is an accurate and efficient technique to carry out large two-dimensional N-body simulations in cosmology. This hybrid code combines the 2d Barnes and Hut Tree method and the 2d Particle–Mesh method. We describe the splitting of force between the PM and the Tree parts. We also estimate error in force for a realistic configuration. Finally, we discuss some tests of the code.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Gravitation;methods: numerical;cosmology: large scale structure of the universe.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Suryadeep" last="Ray">Suryadeep Ray</name>
						<affiliation>Harish-Chandra Research Institute, Chhatnag Road, Jhunsi, Allahabad 211019, India.</affiliation>
						<email>surya@mri.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-06-23</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-12-20</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Physics of $\mathbf{E}\times\mathbf{B}$-Drifting Jets</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0115-0127</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>$\mathbf{E}\times \mathbf{B}$-drifting jets have been generally ignored for the past 25 years even though they may well describe all the astrophysical jet sources, both on galactic and stellar scales. Here we present closed-form solutions for their joint field-and-particle distribution, argue that the observed jets are near equipartition, with extremely relativistic, monoenergetic $e^{\pm}$-pairs of bulk Lorentz factor $\gamma  \lesssim 10^{4}$, and are first-order stable. We describe plausible mechanisms for the jets’ (i) formation, (ii) propagation, and (iii) termination. Wherever a beam meets with resistance, its frozen-in Poynting flux transforms the delta-shaped energy distribution of the pairs into an almost white power law, $E^{2}N_{E}\sim E^{-\epsilon}$ with $\epsilon\gtrsim 0$, via single-step falls through the huge convected potential.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Jet sources;monoenergetic beams;$\mathbf{E}\times \mathbf{B}$-drift;unified scheme.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Wolfgang" last="Kundt">Wolfgang Kundt</name>
						<affiliation>IfA of Bonn University, Auf dem Huegel 71, D-53121 Bonn.</affiliation>
						<email>wkundt@astro.uni-bonn.de</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Gopal" last="Krishna">Gopal Krishna</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Radio Astrophysics / TIFR, Pune University Campus, Pune- 411 007.</affiliation>
						<email>krishna@ncra.tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-03-29</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2005-01-10</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>On the Origin of the Wide HI Absorption Line towards Sgr A$^{\ast}$</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0129-0141</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have imaged a region of $\sim 5'$ extent surrounding Sgr A$^{\ast}$ in the HI 21 cm-line absorption using the Very Large Array. A Gaussian decomposition of the optical depth spectra at positions within $\sim 2'$ ($\sim 5$ pc at 8.5 kpc) of Sgr A$^{\ast}$ detects a wide line underlying the many narrow absorption lines. The wide line has a mean peak optical depth of 0.32 $\pm$ 0.12 centered at a mean velocity of $V_{\text{lsr}} = -4\pm 15$ km s$^{-1}$. The mean full width at half maximum is 119$\pm$42 km s$^{-1}$. Such a wide line is absent in the spectra at positions beyond $\sim 2'$ from Sgr A$^{\ast}$. The position-velocity diagrams in optical depth reveal that the wide line originates in various components of the circumnuclear disk (radius $\sim 1.3'$) surrounding Sgr A$^{\ast}$. These components contribute to the optical depth of the wide line in different velocity ranges. The position-velocity diagrams do not reveal any diffuse feature which could be attributed to a large number of HI clouds along the line of sight to Sgr A$^{\ast}$. Consequently, the wide line has no implications either to a global population of shocked HI clouds in the Galaxy or to the energetics of the interstellar medium as was earlier thought.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxy: nucleus;radio lines: ISM.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Dwarakanath">K. S. Dwarakanath</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>dwaraka@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="W. M." last="Goss">W. M. Goss</name>
						<affiliation>National Radio Astronomy Observatory, PO BOX O, Socorro, NM 87801.</affiliation>
						<email>mgoss@aoc.nrao.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. H." last="Zhao">J. H. Zhao</name>
						<affiliation>Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, Cambridge, MA 02138.</affiliation>
						<email>jzhao@cfa.harvard.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="C. C." last="Lang">C. C. Lang</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA 52242.</affiliation>
						<email>cornelia-lang@uiowa.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-05-07</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-10-19</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A High Galactic Latitude HI 21 cm-line Absorption Survey using the GMRT: I. Observations and Spectra</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0143-0183</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have used the Giant Meterwave Radio Telescope (GMRT) to measure the Galactic HI 21-cm line absorption towards 102 extragalactic radio continuum sources, located at high $(|b| \gt 15^{\circ})$ Galactic latitudes. The Declination coverage of the present survey is $\delta \grtsim -45^{\circ}$. With a mean rms optical depth of $\sim 0.003$, this is the most sensitive Galactic HI 21-cm line absorption survey to date. To supplement the absorption data, we have extracted the HI 21-cm line emission profiles towards these 102 lines of sight from the Leiden Dwingeloo Survey of Galactic neutral hydrogen. We have carried out a Gaussian fitting analysis to identify the discrete absorption and emission components in these profiles. In this paper, we present the spectra and the components. A subsequent paper will discuss the interpretation of these results.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>ISM: clouds, kinematics and dynamics;radio lines: ISM.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Rekhesh" last="Mohan">Rekhesh Mohan</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Currently at the Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034, India.</affiliation>
						<email>reks@iiap.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Dwarakanath">K. S. Dwarakanath</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>dwaraka@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Srinivasan">G. Srinivasan</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>srini@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-06-04</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-11-03</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A High Galactic Latitude HI 21 cm-line Absorption Survey using the GMRT: II. Results and Interpretation</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0185-0201</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have carried out a sensitive high-latitude $(|b| \gt 15^{\circ})$ HI 21 cm-line absorption survey towards 102 sources using the GMRT. With a $3\sigma$ detection limit in optical depth of $\sim 0.01$, this is the most sensitive HI absorption survey. We detected 126 absorption features most of which also have corresponding HI emission features in the Leiden Dwingeloo Survey of Galactic neutral Hydrogen. The histogram of random velocities of the absorption features is well-fit by two Gaussians centered at $V_{\text{lsr}} \sim 0$ km s$^{−1}$ with velocity dispersions of $7.6 \pm 0.3$ km s$^{-1}$ and $21\pm 4$ km s$^{-1}$ respectively. About 20\%\ of the HI absorption features form the larger velocity dispersion component. The HI absorption features forming the narrow Gaussian have a mean optical depth of $0.20\pm 0.19$, a mean HI column density of $(1.46 \pm 1.03) \times 10^{20}$ cm$^{-2}$, and a mean spin temperature of $121\pm 69$ K. These HI concentrations can be identified with the standard HI clouds in the cold neutral medium of the Galaxy. The HI absorption features forming the wider Gaussian have a mean optical depth of $0.04\pm 0.02$, a mean HI column density of $(4.3\pm 3.4)\times 10^{19}$ cm$^{-2}$, and a mean spin temperature of $125\pm 82$ K. The HI column densities of these fast clouds decrease with their increasing random velocities. These fast clouds can be identified with a population of clouds detected so far only in optical absorption and in HI emission lines with a similar velocity dispersion. This population of fast clouds is likely to be in the lower Galactic Halo.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>ISM: clouds, kinematics and dynamics;radio lines: ISM.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Rekhesh" last="Mohan">Rekhesh Mohan</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Currently at the Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560 034, India.</affiliation>
						<email>reks@iiap.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Dwarakanath">K. S. Dwarakanath</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>dwaraka@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Srinivasan">G. Srinivasan</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>srini@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-06-04</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-11-03</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>An Apparent Descriptive Method for Judging the Synchronization of Rotation of Binary Stars</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0203-0211</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The problem of the synchronous rotation of binary stars is judged by using a synchronous parameter $Q$ introduced in an apparent descriptive method. The synchronous parameter $Q$ is defined as the ratio of the rotational period to the orbital period. The author suggests several apparent phenomenal descriptive methods for judging the synchronization of rotation of binary stars. The first method is applicable when the orbital inclination is well-known. The synchronous parameter is defined by using the orbital inclination $i$ and the observable rotational velocity $(V_{1,2} \sin i)_{M}$. The method is mainly suitable for eclipsing binary stars. Several others are suggested for the cases when the orbital inclination $i$ is unknown. The synchronous parameters are defined by using $a_{1,2} \sin i$, $m_{1,2} \sin^{3} i$, the mass function $f(m)$ and semi-amplitudes of the velocity curve, $K_{1,2}$ given in catalogue of parameters of spectroscopic binary systems and $(V_{1,2}\sin i)_{M}$. These methods are suitable for spectroscopic binary stars including those that show eclipses and visual binary stars concurrently. The synchronous parameters for fifty-five components in thirty binary systems are calculated by using several methods. The numerical results are listed in Tables 1 and 2. The statistical results are listed in Table 3. In addition, several apparent descriptive methods are discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Binary stars;synchronization of rotation;judgement of apparent phenomenal descriptive methods.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Li" last="Lin-sen">Li Lin-sen</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, Northeast Normal University, Changchun 130 024, China.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-08-22</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-11-06</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Relation between a Function of the Right Ascension and the Angular Distance to the Vertex for Hyades Stars</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0213-0220</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this paper, relation was developed for Hyades stars between a function of the right ascensions and the angular distances from the vertex. The precision criteria of this relation are very satisfactory and a correlation coefficient value of $\simeq 1$ was found which proves that the attributes are completely related linearly. The importance of this relation was illustrated through its usages as:</p>
					<ul>
						<li>a criterion for membership of the cluster,</li>
						<li>a generating function for evaluating some parameters of the cluster,</li>
						<li>a generating function for the initial values of the vertex equatorial coordinates which could then be improved iteratively using the procedure of differential corrections.</li>
					</ul>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Moving clusters;Hyades cluster;open clusters;Hyades astrometric and kinematic.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="M. A." last="Sharaf">M. A. Sharaf</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Astronomy, Faculty of Science, King Abdul Aziz University, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. I." last="Nouh">M. I. Nouh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Astronomy, National Research Institute of Astronomy and Geophysics, Helwan, Egypt.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. S." last="Saad">A. S. Saad</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Astronomy, National Research Institute of Astronomy and Geophysics, Helwan, Egypt.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-07-14</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2004-12-17</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Author Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0221-0222</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Subject Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0223-0223</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="026">
		<issue inum="01" month="03" year="2005">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>GMRT HI Observations of the Eridanus Group of Galaxies</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0070</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The GMRT HI 21cm-line observations of galaxies in the Eridanus group are presented. The Eridanus group, at a distance of $\sim 23$ Mpc, is a loose group of $\sim 200$ galaxies. The group extends to more than 10 Mpc in projection. The velocity dispersion of the galaxies in the group is $\sim 240$ km s$^{-1}$. The galaxies are clustered into different sub-groups. The overall population mix of the group is 30\%\ (E + S0) and 70\%\ (Sp + Irr). The observations of 57 Eridanus galaxies were carried out with the GMRT for $\sim 200$ h. HI emission was detected from 31 galaxies. The channel rms of $\sim 1$ mJy beam$^{-1}$ was achieved for most of the image-cubes made with 4 h of data. The corresponding HI column density sensitivity $(3\sigma)$ is $\sim 1\times 10^{20}$ cm$^{-2}$ for a velocity-width of $\sim 13.4$ km s$^{-1}$. The $3\sigma$ detection limit of HI mass is $\sim 1.2\times 10^{7}$ M$_{\odot}$ for a line-width of 50 km s$^{-1}$. Total HI images, HI velocity fields, global HI line profiles, HI mass surface densities, HI disk parameters and HI rotation curves are presented. The velocity fields are analysed separately for the approaching and the receding sides of the galaxies. These data will be used to study the HI and the radio continuum properties, the Tully–Fisher relations, the dark matter halos, and the kinematical and HI lopsidedness in galaxies.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxies: groups, clusters;individual: Eridanus;radio lines: HI 21cm-line.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Omar">A. Omar</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Present address: ARIES, Manora peak, Nainital 263 129, Uttaranchal, India.</affiliation>
						<email>aomar@upso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Dwarakanath">K. S. Dwarakanath</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>dwaraka@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-08-23</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2005-03-22</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The HI Content of the Eridanus Group of Galaxies</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0071-0087</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The HI content of galaxies in the Eridanus group is studied using the GMRT observations and the HIPASS data. A significant HI deficiency up to a factor of 2–3 is observed in galaxies in the high galaxy density regions. The HI deficiency in galaxies is observed to be directly correlated to the local projected galaxy density, and inversely correlated to the line-of-sight radial velocity. Furthermore, galaxies with larger optical diameters are predominantly in the lower galaxy density regions. It is suggested that the HI deficiency in Eridanus is due to tidal interactions. In some galaxies, evidences of tidal interactions are seen. An important implication is that significant evolution of galaxies can take place in the group environment. In the hierarchical way of formation of clusters via mergers of groups, a fraction of the observed HI deficiency in clusters could have originated in groups. The co-existence of S0s and severely HI deficient galaxies in the Eridanus group suggests that tidal interaction is likely to be an effective mechanism for transforming spirals to S0s.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxy: evolution;galaxies: groups, clusters;individual: Eridanus;radio lines: HI 21cm-line.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Omar">A. Omar</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Present address: ARIES, Manora peak, Nainital 263 129, Uttaranchal, India.</affiliation>
						<email>aomar@upso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Dwarakanath">K. S. Dwarakanath</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>dwaraka@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-08-23</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2005-03-22</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Radio Continuum and Far-infrared Emission from the Galaxies in the Eridanus Group</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0089-0102</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Eridanus galaxies follow the well-known radio–FIR correlation. The majority (70\%) of these galaxies have their star formation rates below that of the Milky Way. The galaxies that have a significant excess of radio emission are identified as low luminosity AGNs based on their radio morphologies obtained from the GMRT observations. There are no powerful AGNs ($L_{20 \text{\,cm}}\gt 10^{23}$W Hz$^{-1}$) in the group. The two most far-infrared and radio luminous galaxies in the group have optical and HI morphologies suggestive of recent tidal interactions. The Eridanus group also has two far-infrared luminous but radio-deficient galaxies. It is believed that these galaxies are observed within a few Myr of the onset of an intense star formation episode after being quiescent for at least a 100 Myr. The upper end of the radio luminosity distribution of the Eridanus galaxies ($L_{20 \text{\,cm}}\sim 10^{22}$W Hz$^{-1}$) is consistent with that of the field galaxies, other groups, and late-type galaxies in nearby clusters.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Galaxy: radio continuum, radio;FIR correlation;galaxies: groups;individual: Eridanus.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Omar">A. Omar</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Present address: ARIES, Manora peak, Nainital 263 129, Uttaranchal, India.</affiliation>
						<email>aomar@upso.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Dwarakanath">K. S. Dwarakanath</name>
						<affiliation>Raman Research Institute, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email>dwaraka@rri.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-08-23</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2005-03-22</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Parametric Identification of Solar Series based on an Adaptive Parallel Methodology</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0103-0115</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this work we present an adaptive parallel methodology to optimize the identification of time series through parametric models, applying it to the case of sunspot series. We employ high precision computation of system identification algorithms, and use recursive least squares processing and ARMAX (Autoregressive Moving Average Extensive) parametric modelling. This methodology could be very useful when the high precision mathematical modelling of dynamic complex systems is required. After explaining the proposed heuristics and the tuning of its parameters, we showthe results we have found for several solar series using different implementations. Thus, we demonstrate how the result precision improves.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sunspot;time series;system identification;parametric modelling;optimization, parallelism;adaptation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Juan A. Gómez" last="Pulido">Juan A. Gómez Pulido</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Computer Science, University of Extremadura, Campus Universitario s/n. 10071 Caceres, Spain.</affiliation>
						<email>jangomez@unex.es</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Miguel A. Vega" last="Rodríguez">Miguel A. Vega Rodríguez</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Computer Science, University of Extremadura, Campus Universitario s/n. 10071 Caceres, Spain.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Juan M. Sánchez" last="Pérez">Juan M. Sánchez Pérez</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Computer Science, University of Extremadura, Campus Universitario s/n. 10071 Caceres, Spain.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-09-04</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2005-03-21</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02-03" month="06-09" year="2005">%raghu, vol 26, issue 2,3
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0000-0000</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-04-18</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-05-11</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="04" month="12" year="2005">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0000-0000</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-04-18</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-05-11</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="027">
		<issue inum="01-02" month="03-06" year="2004">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0000-0000</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-04-18</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A">2000-05-11</date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
</journal>
