<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE bsi SYSTEM "bhavans.dtd">

<jcs>
	<volume vnum="112">
		<issue inum="01" month="02" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Cobalt(III), nickel(II) and ruthenium(II) complexes of 1,10-phenanthroline family of ligands: DNA binding and photocleavage studies</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0001-0017</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>DNA binding and photocleavage characteristics of a series of mixedligand complexes of the type [M(phen)2LL]$^{n+}$ (where M = Co(III), Ni(II) or Ru(II), LL = 1,10-phenanthroline (phen), phenanthroline-dione (phen-dione) or dipyridophenazine (dppz) and  $n = 3$ or 2) have been investigated in detail. Various physico-chemical and biochemical techniques including UV/Visible, fluorescence and viscometric titration, thermal denaturation, and differential pulse voltammetry have been employed to probe the details of DNA binding by these complexes; intrinsic binding constants (Kb) have been estimated under a similar set of experimental conditions. Analysis of the results suggests that intercalative ability of the coordinated ligands varies as dppz $&gt;$ phen $&lt;$ phen-dione in this series of complexes. While the Co(II) and Ru(II) complexes investigated in this study effect photocleavage of the supercoiled pBR 322 DNA, the corresponding Ni(II) complexes are found to be inactive under similar experimental conditions. Results of detailed investigations carried out inquiring into the mechanistic aspects of DNA photocleavage by [Co(phen)2 (dppz)]$^{3+}$ have also been reported. </p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Phenanthroline family of ligands; metal complexes; DNA binding and photocleavage.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Arounaguiri" fname="S." isfellow="0">Arounaguiri, S.</author>
					<author lname="Easwaramoorthy" fname="D." isfellow="0">Easwaramoorthy, D.</author>
					<author lname="Ashokkumar" fname="A." isfellow="0">Ashokkumar, A.</author>
					<author lname="Dattagupta" fname="Aparna" isfellow="0">Dattagupta, Aparna</author>
					<author lname="Maiya" fname="Bhaskar G." isfellow="0">Maiya, Bhaskar G.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Improved technology for manufacture of carbon electrodes</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0019-0026</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Current industrial carbon electrodes are typically manufactured by blending petroleum coke particles (the filler) with molten coal tar pitch (the binder) and extruding the resultant mix to form the `green electrode’. This is then baked under controlled conditions. In case of usage as anodes in steel electric furnaces (or as other carbon and graphite products), the electrodes could undergo further processing like pitch impregnation or graphitization. During heat treatment, some of the organics are destructively distilled, vaporized or decomposed, resulting in carbon deposition in the electrode. As the vaporized materials exit the body of the electrode they cause porosity in the walls, which results in reduction in density, current carrying capacity and flexural strength.</p>
					<p>The paper presents investigations to improve some physico-chemical characteristics of these electrodes (such as coefficient of thermal expansion, mechanical strengths, density, pore volume, porosity etc.), obtained in different manufacture steps, by addition of varieties of coal tar pitch. These include attempts to improve the chemical compatibility of the coke-pitch system in the mixture and establish the method and the point of introduction of additive, the concentration required and appropriate analytical control during the entire manufacture. Methods of analysis used include thermogravimetry and porosimetry. The microstructure of the electrodes is investigated through a wide range and the data obtained include pore size and pore volume distribution, surface area, porosity, particle size distribution and type of pores. The overall results clearly indicate better characteristics and performance for electrodes with additives as against electrodes without them, such as lower porosity, lower thermal expansion coefficients and greater mechanical strength. These data are analyzed with respect to the process step and electrode type.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Electrode characteristics; petroleum coke; porosity; coal tar pitch.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Platon" fname="A." isfellow="0">Platon, A.</author>
					<author lname="Dumbrava" fname="A." isfellow="0">Dumbrava, A.</author>
					<author lname="Iutes-Petrescu" fname="N." isfellow="0">Iutes-Petrescu, N.</author>
					<author lname="Simionescu" fname="Luzia " isfellow="0">Simionescu, Luzia</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Characteristic polynomials of linear polyacenes and their subspectrality</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0027-0033</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Coefficients of characteristic polynomials (CP) of linear polyacenes (LP) have been shown to be obtainable from Pascal’s triangle by using a graph factorisation and squaring technique. Strong subspectrality existing among the members of the linear polyacene series has been shown from the derivation of the CP’s. Thus it has been shown that the entire eigenspectrum of an $n$-ring LP is included in that of $(2n + 1)$-ring LP. Correspondence between the eigenspectra of linear chains and LP’s is brought out by a recently developed vertex-alternation and squaring algorithm.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Characteristic polynomials; linear polyacenes; Pascal’s triangle; subspectrality</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mukherjee" fname="Gautam" isfellow="0">Mukherjee, Gautam</author>
					<author lname="Datta" fname="Kakali" isfellow="0">Datta, Kakali</author>
					<author lname="Mukherjee" fname="Ashok K." isfellow="0">Mukherjee, Ashok K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Density functional studies of molecular structures of N-methyl formamide, N,N-dimethyl formamide, and N,N-dimethyl acetamide</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0035-0042</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Density functional theory was applied to the calculation of molecular structures of N-methyl formamide (NMF), N,N-dimethyl formamide (DMF), and N,Ndimethyl acetamide (DMA). DFT calculations on NMF, DMF, and DMA were performed  using a combination of the local functional of Vosko, Wilk, and Nusair (VWN) with the  nonlocal exchange functional of Becke and the nonlocal correlational functional of Lee, Yang, and Parr (BLYP). The adiabatic connection method (ACM) of Becke has also been used, for the first time, for the calculation of molecular structures of NMF, DMF, and DMA. The calculated molecular structures are in excellent agreement with the experimental geometries of NMF and DMA derived from gas-phase electron-diffraction studies. Sparse experimental data on the gas-phase geometry of DMF reported in the literature compares well with the DFT results on DMF. DFT emerges as a powerful method to calculate molecular structures.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Density functional theory; alkyl amides; molecular structure of alkyl amides; transition state search; peptide models.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Renugopalakrishnan" fname="V." isfellow="0">Renugopalakrishnan, V.</author>
					<author lname="Madrid" fname="G." isfellow="0">Madrid, G.</author>
					<author lname="Cuevas" fname="G." isfellow="0">Cuevas, G.</author>
					<author lname="Hagler" fname="A. T." isfellow="0">Hagler, A. T.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Topological estimation of proton–ligand formation constants of potential antitumour agents: Salicylhydroxamic acids</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0043-0049</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Proton–ligand formation constants of salicylhydroxamic acids (SHA) and their nuclear substituted derivatives have been estimated topologically using the normalized Wiener index, referred to as mean square Wiener index (Wms). Regression analysis of the data indicates that Wms can be used successfully for estimating and monitoring proton-ligand formation constants.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Salicylhydroxamic acids; antitumour agents; topological indices; normalized Wiener index; mean square Wiener index.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Karmarkar" fname="Sneha" isfellow="0">Karmarkar, Sneha</author>
					<author lname="Khadikar" fname="P. V." isfellow="0">Khadikar, P. V.</author>
					<author lname="Agarwal" fname="Vijay K." isfellow="0">Agarwal, Vijay K.</author>
					<author lname="Mathur" fname="Keshav C." isfellow="0">Mathur, Keshav C.</author>
					<author lname="Mandloi" fname="Manorama" isfellow="0">Mandloi, Manorama</author>
					<author lname="Joshi" fname="Shobha" isfellow="0">Joshi, Shobha</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Hydrophobic interactions of phenoxazine modulators with bovine serum albumin</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0051-0061</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The interaction of 10-(3’-N-morpholinopropyl)phenoxazine [MPP], 10-(4’-N-morpholinobutyl)phenoxazine [MBP], 10-(3’-N-morpholinopropyl)-2-chlorophenoxazine [MPCP], 10-(3’-N-piperidinopropyl)-2-chlorophenoxazine [PPCP] or 10-(3’-N-morpholinopropyl)-2-trifluoromethylphenoxazine [MPTP] with bovine serum albumin (BSA) has been studied by gel filtration and equilibrium dialysis methods. The binding of these modulators, based on dialysis experiments, has been characterized using the following parameters: percentage of bound drug ($\beta$), the association constant ($K_1$), the apparent binding constant ($k$) and the free energy change ($\Delta F^\circ$). The binding of phenoxazine derivatives to serum transporter protein, BSA, is correlated with their octanol-water partition coefficient, $\log_{10}~ P$. In addition, effect of the displacing activities of hydroxyzine and acetylsalicylic acid on the binding of phenoxazine derivatives to albumin has been studied. Results of the displacement experiments show that phenoxazine benzene rings and tertiary amines attached to the side chain of the phenoxazine moiety are bound to a hydrophobic area on the albumin molecule.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Phenoxazine; hydrophobic interaction; displacement experiments; bovine serum albumin.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kalpana" fname="H. N." isfellow="0">Kalpana, H. N.</author>
					<author lname="Channu" fname="B. C." isfellow="0">Channu, B. C.</author>
					<author lname="Dass" fname="Chhabil" isfellow="0">Dass, Chhabil</author>
					<author lname="Houghton" fname="P. J." isfellow="0">Houghton, P. J.</author>
					<author lname="Thimmaiah" fname="K. N." isfellow="0">Thimmaiah, K. N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Pulsed laser excitation of phosphate stabilised silver nanoparticles</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0063-0072</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Laser flash photolysis studies were carried out on two types of silver nanoparticles prepared by  $\gamma$-radiolysis of $Ag^+$ solutions in the presence of polyphosphate as the stabiliser. Type I silver nanoparticles displayed a surface plasmon band at 390 nm. Type II silver nanoparticles showed a 390 nm surface plasmon band with a shoulder at 550 nm. On photoexcitation in the surface plasmon band region, using 35 picosecond laser pulses at 355 nm and 532 nm, the type II solutions showed transient bleaching and absorption signals in the 450–900 nm region, which did not decay appreciably up to 5 nanoseconds. These transient changes were found to get annealed in the interval  $t$ where $5 \text{ ns } &lt; t &lt; 100$ ns. Extended photolysis of the nanoparticle solutions with repetitive laser pulses resulted in a decrease in the values of the average particle size which were measured by employing the dynamic light scattering technique.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords> Pulsed laser excitation; silver nanoparticles; surface plasmon band; sodium polyphosphate stabilizer.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mohanty" fname="Jyotirmayee" isfellow="0">Mohanty, Jyotirmayee</author>
					<author lname="Palit" fname="Dipak K." isfellow="0">Palit, Dipak K.</author>
					<author lname="Shastri" fname="Laxminarayan V." isfellow="0">Shastri, Laxminarayan V.</author>
					<author lname="Sapre" fname="Avinash V." isfellow="0">Sapre, Avinash V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="04" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics and mechanism of the oxidation of formic and oxalic acids by quinolinium fluorochromate </title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0073-0081</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Kinetics and mechanism of oxidation of formic and oxalic acids by quinolinium fluorochromate (QFC) have been studied in dimethylsulphoxide. The main product of oxidation is carbon dioxide. The reaction is first-order with respect to QFC. Michaelis–Menten type of kinetics were observed with respect to the reductants. The reaction is acid-catalysed and the acid dependence has the form: $k_{\text obs} = a + b[H^+]$. The oxidation of $\alpha$-deuterioformic acid exhibits a substantial primary kinetic isotope effect ($k_H/k_D = 6⋅01$ at 303 K). The reaction has been studied in nineteen different organic solvents and the solvent effect has been analysed using Taft’s and Swain’s multiparametric equations. The temperature dependence of the kinetic isotope effect indicates the presence of a symmetrical cyclic transition state in the rate-determining step. Suitable mechanisms have been proposed</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oxidation of acids; organic acids; quinolinium fluorochromate; halochromate (VI).</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Khurana" fname="Madhu" isfellow="0">Khurana, Madhu</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="Pradeep K." isfellow="0">Sharma, Pradeep K.</author>
					<author lname="Banerji" fname="Kalyan K." isfellow="0">Banerji, Kalyan K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>An indigenous cluster beam apparatus with a reflectron time-of-flight mass spectrometer</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0083-0095</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The design and fabrication of a Smalley-type cluster source in combination with a reflectron based time-of-flight (TOF) mass spectrometer are reported. The generation of clusters is based on supersonic jet expansion of the sampling plume. Sample cells for both liquid and solid targets developed for this purpose are described. Two pulsed Nd-YAG lasers are used in tandem, one (532 nm) for target vapourization and the other (355 nm) for cluster ionization. Methanol clusters of nuclearity up to 14 (mass 500 amu) were produced from liquid methanol as the test sample. The clusters were detected with a mass resolution of ~ 2500 in the R-TOF geometry. Carbon clusters up to a nuclearity of 28 were obtained using a polyimide target. The utility of the instrument is demonstrated by carrying out experiments to generate mixed clusters from alcohol mixtures.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mass spectrometer; cluster source; instrumentation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Raina" fname="G." isfellow="0">Raina, G.</author>
					<author lname="Kulkarni" fname="G. U." isfellow="0">Kulkarni, G. U.</author>
					<author lname="Yadav" fname="R. T." isfellow="0">Yadav, R. T.</author>
					<author lname="Ramamurthy" fname="V. S." isfellow="0">Ramamurthy. V. S.</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="C. N. R." isfellow="0">Rao, C. N. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Generation, structure and reactivity of arynes: A theoretical study</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0097-0108</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The semiempirical AM1 SCF-MO method is used to study the benzyne mechanism for aromatic nucleophilic substitution of various  $m$-substituted chlorobenzenes and 3-chloropyridine. The calculations predict that most of the fixed substituents studied here would induce the formation of 2,3-arynes through their electron-withdrawing resonance or inductive effects. The geometry and electronic structure of the 2,3- and 3,4-arynes investigated here, confirm the generally accepted $o$-benzyne structure postulated for arynes. The sites of nucleophilic addition to arynes as predicted here are in fair agreement with expectation and experimental findings.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Benzyne mechanism; aryne bond; nucleophilic addition to arynes; AM1 SCF-MO method.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Dkhar" fname="Peter G. S." isfellow="0">Dkhar, Peter G. S.</author>
					<author lname="Lyngdoh" fname="R. H. Duncan" isfellow="0">Lyngdoh, R. H. Duncan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis of cadmium sulphide in pure and mixed Langmuir–Blodgett films of $n$-octadecylsuccinic acid</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0109-0118</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Cadmium sulphide (CdS) nanoparticles were grown by the reaction of sodium sulphide (Na$_2$S) with Langmuir–Blodgett (LB) films of cadmium salts of $n$-octadecylsuccinic acid (ODSU) and with LB films of ODSU in mixtures of octadecylamine and octadecyl alcohol. The results indicate that heterogeneous nucleation and aggregation in the pure ODSU LB films due to processes like Ostwald ripening are destabilized by the presence of the long-chain amine and alcohol in mixed systems. CdS nanoparticles in the LB films were monitored by UV-visible absorption spectra, which allow an estimation of the size of the particles. The morphology, size and nature of the nanocrystallites formed depend on whether the sulphidation was done on the pure film or in the mixed films. It is seen that particles of size around 1⋅6 nm were formed in ODSU/octadecylalcohol and ODSU/octadecylamine mixed LB films while in pure ODSU films the size was about 2⋅7 nm. These films showed typical needle-shaped structures, as observed by the optical microscopic technique. Mean size and morphology were confirmed by transmission and scanning electron microscopy, while selective area electron diffraction patterns showed six-fold symmetry and indicated that the CdS crystals grow epitaxially with respect to the monolayer. Further, the crystallisation enhanced in the mixed LB films showed a characteristic zinc oxide (Wurtzite) structure compared with the pure ODSU matrix. </p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>CdS; LB films; octadecylsuccinic acid; epitaxy.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Hemakanthi" fname="G." isfellow="0">Hemakanthi, G.</author>
					<author lname="Nair" fname="Balachandran Unni" isfellow="0">Nair, Balachandran Unni</author>
					<author lname="Dhathathreyan" fname="Aruna" isfellow="0">Dhathathreyan, Aruna</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Molecular complexes of phenols with DDQ</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0119-0126</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="T. Vinod" isfellow="0">Kumar, T. Vinod</author>
					<author lname="Veeraiah" fname="T." isfellow="0">Veeraiah, T.</author>
					<author lname="Venkateshwarlu" fname="G." isfellow="0">Venkateshwarlu, G.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of piperidones on hydrogen permeation and corrosion inhibition of mild steel in acidic solutions </title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0127-0136</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The influence of 3-methyl-2,6-diphenyl piperidin-4-one (MDPO) and 2-phenyl decahydroquinoline-4-one (PDQO) synthesised in the laboratory on hydrogen permeation and corrosion inhibition of mild steel in 1N H$_2$SO$_4$ has been studied using weight loss and various electrochemical AC and DC corrosion-monitoring techniques. Both the compounds inhibit the corrosion of mild steel in H$_2$SO$_4$ Potentiodynamic polarisation studies clearly reveal that they behave predominantly as cathodic inhibitors. The extent of decrease in hydrogen permeation current through steel surfaces has been studied by the hydrogen electropermeation technique. Double layer capacitance ($C_{dl}$) and charge transfer resistance ($R_t$) values are derived from Nyquist plots obtained from AC impedance studies. The adsorption of these compounds on mild steel surfaces from H$_2$SO$_4$ obeys Temkin’s adsorption isotherm.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Corrosion inhibition; piperidones; hydrogen permeation; metal embrittlement; impedance measurements.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Muralidharan" fname="S." isfellow="0">Muralidharan, S.</author>
					<author lname="Chandrasekar" fname="R." isfellow="0">Chandrasekar. R.</author>
					<author lname="Iyer" fname="S. V. K." isfellow="0">Iyer, S. V. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Novel application of Wiener vis-à-vis Szeged indices: Antitubercular activities of quinolones </title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0137-0146</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The paper gives a brief account of the recently introduced Szeged index (Sz). Using this index antitubercular activities of N-2,4-difluorophenyl quinolones are subjected to quantitative structure–activity relationship analysis. The potential of Sz related to the Wiener index (W) is critically discussed. In addition, Huckel molecular orbital energies: $E_{\text HOMO}$, $E_{\text LUMO}$ and $E_{\text total}$ were also used for comparing and modelling antitubercular activities of the quinolones. The results, based on univariate as well as multivariate regressions, have shown that W, Sz and $E_{\text total}$ give better results and that the correlations improve in multivariate regression analyses.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Quantitative structure–activity relationship; Wiener and Szeged indices; antitubercular activity; fluorophenyl quinolones; modelling of drug activity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Agarwal" fname="Vijay K." isfellow="0">Agarwal, Vijay K.</author>
					<author lname="Bano" fname="Shahnaz" isfellow="0">Bano, Shahnaz</author>
					<author lname="Mathur" fname="Keshav C." isfellow="0">Mathur, Keshav C.</author>
					<author lname="Khadikar" fname="Padmakar V." isfellow="0">Khadikar, Padmakar V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Replacing the hydrogen in the intermolecular hydrogen bond of the cyanuric acid–bipyridyl adduct by Ag(I)</title>
				<feature>Rapid Communication</feature>
				<page>0147-0151</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A complex between cyanuric acid (CA), 4,4′-bipyridyl (BP) and Ag(I), with the composition, [Ag$_2$(C$_3$H$_2$N$_3$O$_3$-$\kappa$N)$_2$ (C$_{10}$H$_8$N$_2$-$\kappa$N)] has been prepared. Crystal structure analysis shows that it has a chain structure in which the CA molecules are linked to the BP units through silver atoms by the formation of N–Ag–N bonds, wherein one of the hydrogens of CA is replaced by Ag(I), showing thereby the chains connected to one another by N–H$_{\ldots}$O hydrogen bonds formed between the CA molecules. This intermolecular chain structure resembles the chain structure of the CA.BP adduct where CA-BP-CA chains formed by N–H$_{\ldots}$N hydrogen bonds are linked to one another by N–H$_{\ldots}$O hydrogen bonds between the CA molecules.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cyanuric acid–Ag–4,4′-bipyridyl adduct; N–Ag–N chains; crystal structure analysis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sivashankar" fname="K." isfellow="0">Sivashankar, K.</author>
					<author lname="Ranganathan" fname="Anupama" isfellow="0">Ranganathan, Anupama</author>
					<author lname="Pedireddi" fname="V. R." isfellow="0">Pedireddi, V. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="06" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Foreword &#8212; Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0153-0153</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Krishnamurthy" fname="S. S." isfellow="0">Krishnamurthy, S. S.</author>
					<author lname="Samuelson" fname="A. G." isfellow="0">Samuelson, A. G.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Polyimido sulphur anions S(NR)$^m−$$_n$: Free radicals and coordination behaviour</title>
				<feature>Special Issue on Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0155-0170</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In a reaction sequence of amide addition followed by halogen oxidation the triazasulphite S(NR)$^{2 −}_3$ and the tetrazasulphate S(NR)$^{2 −}_4$ are readily accessible from sulphur diimide S(NR)$_2$ via sulphur triimide S(NR)$_3$. Addition of lithium organics to sulphur triimide provides a general route to triazasulphonates RS(NR)$^{2−}_3$. All these anions resemble potential tripodal coordination behaviour because of their nitrogen donor centres. Furthermore, the sulphur polyimido ligands are capable of responding to the various requirements of different metals (even in mixed metal species) by charge (de)localization. This paper deals with the synthetic routes of the sulphur nitrogen anions and their coordination behaviour. Their reactivity, mainly towards main group metal synthons, is also discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sulphur nitrogen anions; sulphur triimide metal synthons; tripodal coordination behaviour; halogen oxidation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Stalke" fname="Dietmar" isfellow="0">Stalke, Dietmar</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Si–O and P–O motifs in inorganic rings and clusters</title>
				<feature>Special Issue on Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0171-0178</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This article presents a brief overview of different kinds of silanols and the important reactions of N-bonded silanetriols. The synthesis and characterization of silanediols containing Si–N and Si–C bonds, (2,4,6-Me$_{3}$C$_{6}$H$_{2}$)N(SiMe$_{3}$)Si(Me)(OH)$_2$ ({\bf 1e}) is described. {\bf 1e} shows a polymeric crinkled tape type of structure due to extensive intermolecular hydrogen bonding. We also describe the formation of a neutral copper(II) complex derived from the reaction of CuCl$_2$ with (O)P(3,5-Me_{2}Pz)$_3$ where the ligand undergoes a facile P–N bond cleavage and functions as an N$_2$O type of tridentate ligand.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Silanols; metallasiloxanes; hydrogen bonding; phosphonates; metal clusters.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chandrasekhar" fname="V." isfellow="0">Chandrasekhar, V.</author>
					<author lname="Nagendran" fname="S." isfellow="0">Nagendran, S.</author>
					<author lname="Kingsley" fname="S." isfellow="0">Kingsley, S.</author>
					<author lname="Krishnan" fname="V." isfellow="0">Krishnan, V.</author>
					<author lname="Boomishankar" fname="R." isfellow="0">Boomishankar, R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Modelling tyrosinase monooxygenase activity. Activation of dioxygen by dicopper(I) complexes and characterisation of dicopper(II) complexes</title>
				<feature>Special Issue on Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0179-0186</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Activation of dioxygen on dicopper(I) centres was systematically investigated using a group of open-chain and a macrocyclic $m$-xylyl-based dinucleating ligand from a bioinorganic viewpoint. Even though intermediate peroxodicopper(II) species was not detected (even at –$80^\circ$C for the open-chain system), the putative intermediate reacted with C–H groups in ligands giving oxygenated products (C–OH groups). Absorption, spectroscopic and magnetic properties of the final dicopper(II) complexes have been investigated.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Dioxygen; dicopper complexes; $m$-xylyl-based dinucleating ligands; stoichiometric oxidation reactions.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Gupta" fname="Rajeev" isfellow="0">Gupta, Rajeev</author>
					<author lname="Ghosh" fname="Debalina" isfellow="0">Ghosh, Debalina</author>
					<author lname="Mukherjee" fname="Rabindranath" isfellow="0">Mukherjee, Rabindranath</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Palladium and platinum organochalcogenolates and their transformation into metal chalcogenides</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0187-0196</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Platinum group metal chalcogenides find extensive applications in catalysis and in the electronic industry. To develop an efficient low temperature clean preparation of these materials, molecular routes have been explored. Thus the chemistry of mononuclear organochalcogenolates of the type [M(ER $1/4$)$_2$(PR$_3$)$_2$], binuclear benzylselenolates, [M$_2$Cl$_2$($\sim$-SeBz)$_2$(PR$_3$)$_2$], allylpalladium complexes [Pd$_2$($\sim$-ER)$_2$($y^3-C$_4$H$_7$)$_2$] and palladium/platinum sulphido/selenido-bridged  complexes, [M$_2$($\sim$-E)$_2$L$_4$] (M = Pd or Pt; E = S, Se or Te; L = tertiary phosphine ligand) has been investigated. All the complexes have been characterized by elemental analysis, NMR ({}^1 H, {}^{31}P, {}^{77}Se, {}^{195}Pt) spectroscopy and in some cases by X-ray diffraction. The thermal behaviour of these complexes has been studied by TGA. The pyrolysis of allylpalladium complexes in refluxing xylene yields Pd$_4$E as established by analysis and XRD patterns.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Palladium; platinum; organochalcogenolates; chalcogenides; NMR</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Dey" fname="S." isfellow="0">Dey, S.</author>
					<author lname="Singhal" fname="A." isfellow="0">Singhal, A.</author>
					<author lname="Jain" fname="V. K." isfellow="0">Jain, V. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>An overview on the applications of `Doyle catalysts’ in asymmetric cyclopropanation, cyclopropenation and C–H insertion reactions</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0197-0207</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The chiral dirhodium(II) carboxamidates are a unique class of chiral catalysts useful for asymmetric inter- and intramolecular cyclopropanation, cyclopropenation and C–H insertion reactions with excellent enantioselectivities. The broad applications of these catalysts in organic syntheses are briefly reviewed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Doyle catalysts; asymmetric cyclopropanation; cyclopropenation; chiral catalysis; C–H insertions; chiral methyl phenidate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Colacot" fname="Thomas J." isfellow="0">Colacot, Thomas J.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Modern aspects on tri- and tetranuclear cluster complexes supported by phosphido bridges</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0209-0213</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This report on small cluster complexes with metal–metal bonds in the field of coordination chemistry documents results in the following scientific areas. (1) Systematic synthetic routes via ditransition metal carbonyl derivative of manganese and rhenium (group 7) to functionalized triangulo- and tetrahedro-clusters including structural characterization, (2) Dynamic properties of mono- and diauration isomers like M$_2$($\sim$-AuPR$_3$)($\sim$-PCyH)(CO)$_8$/M$_2$($\sim$-H)($\sim_3$-PCy(AuPR$_3$))(CO)$_8$ (isomerization) and M$_2$($\sim$-AuPR$_3$)$_2$($\sim_4$-PCy)(CO)$_8$/M$_2$($\sim$-AuPR$_3$)($\sim_3$-PCy(AuPR$_3$))(CO)$_8$ (M = Mn, Re;  R = organic residue) (rearrangement and valence isomerization) and MM $1/4$($\sim$-H)($\sim$ -PCy$_2$)($\sim_4$ -PCy(AuPR$_3$))(CO)$_6$ (M = M $1/4$, M$\'0$ M $1/4$) (topomerization) going from one to the other homologue and the kinetic study of isomerization in the framework Re$_2$(AuPCy$_3$)$_2$($\sim$-PMeN$_2$($\sim$-C(Bu)O)(CO)$_6$, (3) Correlations of chirality transfer in diastereomeric  \textit{tetrahedro}-clusters Re$_2$(M$^1$PR$_3$)$_2$($\sim$-PCy$_2$)(CO)$_7$(y$^1$-L*) ($M^1$= coin metals, L* = chiral ligand as ($+$) or ($–$) prolinate, for example) from CD data. These selected contributions will be discussed to answer the question  “Do small cluster complexes remain as a future challenge in cluster chemistry?”</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Heterometallic cluster complexes; hydroformylation catalysts; topomerization process; diastereomers; isomerization process.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Haupt" fname="H. J." isfellow="0">Haupt, H. J.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Structural and functional properties of designed globins</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0215-0221</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>\textit{De novo} design of artificial proteins is an essential approach to elucidate the principles of protein architecture and to understand specific functions of natural proteins and also to yield novel molecules for medical and industrial aims. We have designed artificial sequences of 153 amino acids to fit the main-chain framework of the sperm whale myoglobin structure based on the knowledge-based energy functions  to evaluate the compatibility between protein tertiary structures and amino acid sequences. The synthesized artificial globins bind a single heme per protein molecule  as designed, which show well-defined electrochemical and spectroscopic features characteristic of proteins with a low-spin heme. Redox and ligand binding reactions of the artificial heme proteins were investigated and these heme-related functions were found to vary with their structural uniqueness. Relationships between the structural and functional properties are discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Heme; myoglobin; protein design; structure and function.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Isogai" fname="Yasuhiro" isfellow="0">Isogai, Yasuhiro</author>
					<author lname="Ishii" fname="Ishii" isfellow="0">Ishii, Anna</author>
					<author lname="Ishida" fname="Manabu" isfellow="0">Ishida, Manabu</author>
					<author lname="Masahiro" fname="Mukai" isfellow="0">Mukai, Masahiro</author>
					<author lname="Ota" fname="Motonori" isfellow="0">Ota, Motonori</author>
					<author lname="Nishikawa" fname="Ken" isfellow="0">Nishikawa, Ken</author>
					<author lname="Iizuka" fname="Tetsutaro" isfellow="0">Iizuka, Tetsutaro</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Models for the active site in galactose oxidase: Structure, spectra and redox of copper(II) complexes of certain phenolate ligands</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0223-0238</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Galactose oxidase (GOase) is a fungal enzyme which is unusual among metalloenzymes in appearing to catalyse the two electron oxidation of primary alcohols to aldehydes and H$_2$O$_2$. The crystal structure of the enzyme reveals that the coordination geometry of mononuclear copper(II) ion is square pyramidal, with two histidine imidazoles, a tyrosinate, and either H$_2$O ($p$H 7 0) or acetate (from buffer, $p$H 4 5) in the equatorial sites and a tyrosinate ligand weakly bound in the axial position. This paper summarizes the results of our studies on the structure, spectral and redox properties of certain novel models for the active site of the inactive form of GOase. The monophenolato Cu(II) complexes of the type [Cu(L1)X][H(L1) = 2-(\textit{bis}(pyrid-2-ylmethyl)aminomethyl)-4-nitrophenol and X$^-$= Cl$^-${\bf 1}, NCS$^-${\bf 2}, CH$_3$COO$^-${\bf 3}, ClO$_4^-${\bf 4}] reveal a distorted square pyramidal geometry around Cu(II) with an unusual axial coordination of phenolate moiety. The coordination geometry of {\bf 3} is reminiscent of the active site of GOase with an axial phenolate and equatorial CH$_3$COO$^-$ ligands. All the present complexes exhibit several electronic and EPR spectral features which are also similar to the enzyme. Further, to establish the structural and spectroscopic consequences of the coordination of two tyrosinates in GOase enzyme, we studied the monomeric copper(II) complexes containing two phenolates and imidazole/pyridine donors as closer structural models for GOase. N,Ndimethylethylenediamine and N,N -dimethylethylenediamine have been used as starting materials to obtain a variety of 2,4-disubstituted phenolate ligands. The X-ray crystal structures of the complexes [Cu(L5)(py)], ({\bf 8}) [H$_2$ (L5) = N,N-dimethyl-N ,N -\textit{bis}(2-hydroxy-4-nitrobenzyl) ethylenediamine, py = pyridine] and [Cu(L8)(H$_2$O)] ({\bf 11}), [H$_2$(L8) = N,N -dimethyl-N,N -\textit{bis}(2-hydroxy-4-nitrobenzyl)ethylenediamine] reveal distorted square pyramidal geometries around Cu(II) with the axial tertiary amine nitrogen and water coordination respectively. Interestingly, for the latter complex there are two different molecules present in the same unit cell containing the methyl groups of the ethylenediamine fragment cis to each other in one molecule and trans to each other in the other. The ligand field and EPR spectra of the model complexes reveal square-based geometries even in solution. The electrochemical and chemical means of generating novel radical species of the model complexes, analogous to the active form of the enzyme is presently under investigation.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cu(II) phenolate complexes; X-ray structures; electronic spectra; electron paramagnetic resonance spectra; redox behaviour; galactose oxidase.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Vaidyanathan" fname="Mathrubootham" isfellow="0">Vaidyanathan, Mathrubootham</author>
					<author lname="Palaniandavar" fname="Mallayan" isfellow="0">Palaniandavar, Mallayan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Aspects of organochalcogen (S, Se, Te) compounds stabilized by intramolecular coordination</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0239-0248</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The application of intramolecular coordination in the isolation of novel diaryl diselenides and their derivatives, monomeric chalcogenolato complexes of group 12 metals, glutathione peroxidase mimics, hybrid bi-, tri- and multidentate ligands and selenium-containing azamacrocycles is described.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Intramolecular coordination; metal chalcogenolates; glutathione peroxidase mimics; hybrid chalcogen ligands; selenium macrocycles.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mugesh" fname="G." isfellow="0">Mugesh, G.</author>
					<author lname="Panda" fname="Arunashree" isfellow="0">Panda, Arunashree</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="Harkesh B." isfellow="0">Singh, Harkesh B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Inorganic–organic hybrid framework solids</title>
				<feature>Special Issue on Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Recent developments in the area of hybrid structures are overviewed with special emphasis on iron phosphate–oxalate materials. The structure of the iron phosphate–oxalates consists of iron phosphate chains or layers that are connected by oxalate moieties completing the architecture. The compounds exhibit interesting magnetic properties originating from the super-exchange interactions that are predominantly anti-ferromagnetic, involving the iron phosphates and the oxalate moieties. One of the materials, {\bf IV}, also exhibits interesting adsorptive properties reminiscent of aluminosilicate zeolites. The aluminum phosphate–oxalate,  {\bf VII},  indicates that hybrid structures can be formed with zeolite architecture.</p> 
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Framework; iron phosphate–oxalate structures; hybrid structures; crosslinked oxalates; self-organization; structure-directing amine.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Natarajan" fname="Srinivasan" isfellow="0">Natarajan, Srinivasan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Extended metal–organic solids based on benzenepolycarboxylic and aminobenzoic acids</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0273-0290</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This article describes the recent results obtained in our laboratory on the interaction of polyfunctional ligands with divalent alkaline earth metal ions and a few  divalent transition metal ions. Treatment of MCl$_2$ $n$H$_2$O (M = Mg, Ca, Sr or Ba)with 2-amino benzoic acid leads to the formation of complexes [Mg(2-aba)$_2$] ({\bf 1}), [Ca(2-aba)$_2$(OH$_2$)$_3$] ({\bf 2}), [{Sr(2-aba)$_2$(OH$_2$)$_2$}$_2$ H$_2$O)] ({\bf 3}), [Ba(2-aba)$_2$(OH$_2$)] ({\bf 4}), respectively. While the calcium ions in {\bf 2} are hepta-coordinated, the strontium and barium ions in {\bf 3} and {\bf 4} reveal a coordination number of nine apart from additional metal–metal interactions. Apart from the carboxylate functionality, the amino group also binds to the metal centres in the case of strontium and barium complexes {\bf 3} and {\bf 4}. Complexes [{Mg(H$_2$O)_$6$}(4-aba)$_2$ 2H$_2$O] ({\bf 5}), [Ca(4-aba)$_2$(H_$2$O)$_2$] ({\bf 6}) prepared from 4-aminobenzoic acid reveal more open or layered structures. Interaction of 2-mercaptobenzoic acid with $MCl$_2$\cdot6H$_2$O (M = Mg, Ca), however, leads to the.oxidation of the thiol group resulting in the disulphide 2,2 -dithio\textit{bis}(benzoic acid). New metal–organic framework based hydrogen-bonded porous solids [{M(btec)(OH$_2$)4}$_n$ $n$(C$_4$H$_{12}$N$_2) 4$n$H_$2$O] (btec = 1,2,4,5-benzene tetracarboxylate) (M = Co {\bf 9}; Ni {\bf 10}; Zn {\bf 11}) have been synthesized from 1,2,4,5-benzene tetracarboxylic acid in the presence of piperazine. These compounds are made up of extensively hydrogenbonded alternating layers of anionic M-btec co-ordination polymer and piperazinium cations. Compounds {\bf 2–11} described herein form polymeric networks in the solid–state with the aid of different coordinating capabilities of the carboxylate anions hydrogen bonding interactions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Coordination polymer; aminobenzoic acid; benzene tetracarboxylic acid; alkaline earth metals; supramolecular chemistry.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Murugavel" fname="R." isfellow="0">Murugavel, R.</author>
					<author lname="Anantharaman" fname="G." isfellow="0">Anantharaman, G.</author>
					<author lname="Krishnamurthy" fname="D." isfellow="0">Krishnamurthy, D.</author>
					<author lname="Sathiyendiran" fname="M." isfellow="0">Sathiyendiran, M.</author>
					<author lname="Walawalkar" fname="M. G." isfellow="0">Walawalkar, M. G.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Macrocyclic effects upon isomeric Cu$^{II}M$^{II}$ and M$^{II}$Cu$^{II}$ cores. Formation with unsymmetric phenol-based macrocyclic ligands</title>
				<feature>Special Issue on Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0291-0310</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This paper discusses coordination-position isomeric M$^{II}$Cu$^{II}$ and Cu$^{II}$M$^{II}$ complexes, using unsymmetric dinucleating macrocycles (L$^{m;n}$)$^{2-}$ ((L^{2;2})$^{2-$}$, (L$^{2;3})$^{2–}$ and (L^{2;4})$^{2–}$) that comprise two 2-(N-methyl)-aminomethyl-6-iminomethyl-4-bromophenonate entities, combined through the ethylene chain ($m = 2$) between the two amine nitrogens and through the ethylene, trimethylene or tetramethylene chain ($n = 2$, 3 or 4) between the two imine nitrogens. The macrocycles have dissimilar N(amine)$_2$O$_2$  and N(imine)$_2$O$_2$ metal-binding sites sharing the phenolic oxygens. The reaction of the mononuclear Cu$^{II}$ precursors, [Cu(L$^{2;2}$)], [Cu(L$^{2;2}$)] and [Cu(L$^{2;2}$)], with a M$^{II}$ perchlorate and a M$^{II}$ acetate salt formed (acetato)M$^{II}$ Cu$^{II}$ complexes:[CoCu(L^{2;2})(AcO)]ClO$_4$ 0 5H$_2$O] ({\bf 1}), [NiCu(L$^{2;2}$) (AcO)]ClO$_4$ ({\bf 2}), [ZnCu(L$^{2;2}$((AcO)]ClO$_4$ ({\bf 3}), [CoCu(L$^{2;3}$)(AcO)]ClO$_4$ 0 5H$_2$O ({\bf 4}), [NiCu(L$^{2;3}$)(AcO)]ClO$_4$ ({\bf 5}), [ZnCu(L$^{2;3}$)(AcO)]ClO$_4$ 0 5H$_2$O ({\bf 6}), [CoCu(L$^{2;4}$)(AcO)(DMF)]ClO$_4$ ({\bf 7}), [NiCu(L$^{2;4}$)(AcO)]ClO$_4$ 2DMF ({\bf 8}) and [ZnCu(L$^{2;4}$)(AcO)]ClO$_4$ ({\bf 9}) (the formulation [M$_a$M$_b$ (L$^{m;n}$)]$^{2+}$ means that M$_a$ resides in the aminic site and M$_b$ in the iminic site). The site selectivity of the metal ions is demonstrated by X-ray crystallographic studies for {\bf 2} MeOH, {\bf 3}, {\bf 5}, {\bf 7}, and {\bf 9}. An (acetato)Cu$^{II}$Zn$^{II}$ complex, [CuZn(L$^{2;3}$)(AcO)]ClO$^4$ ({\bf 10}), was obtained by the reaction of [PbCu(L$^{2;3}$)]-(ClO$_4$)$_2$ with ZnSO$_4$ 4H$_2$O, in the presence of sodium acetate. Other complexes of the Cu$^{II}$M$^{II}$ type were thermodynamically unstable to cause a scrambling of metal ions. The Cu migration from the iminic site to the aminic site in the synthesis of {\bf 10} is explained by the `kinetic macrocyclic effect’. The coordination-position isomers, {\bf 6} and {\bf 10}, are differentiated by physicochemical properties.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Heterodinuclear complex; coordination-position isomers; macrocyclic effect; crystal structure.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Yonemura" fname="Masami" isfellow="0">Yonemura, Masami</author>
					<author lname="Nakamura" fname="Yuuki" isfellow="0">Nakamura, Yuuki</author>
					<author lname="Usuki" fname="Naoki" isfellow="0">Usuki, Naoki</author>
					<author lname="Okawa" fname="Hisashi" isfellow="0">Okawa, Hisashi</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Fluorescence metrology of silica sol–gels – The effect of D$_2$O and inorganic salts</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0311-0322</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have developed a new method for measuring in-situ the growth of the nanometre-size silica particles which lead to the formation of sol–gel glasses. This technique is based on the decay of fluorescence polarisation anisotropy due to Brownian rotation of dye molecules bound to the particles. Results to date give near ångstrom resolution and demonstrate the feasibility of the approach both for providing industrial quality control and helping fundamental research. Our approach has several key advantages over traditional techniques for nanometre metrology, such as small angle X-ray and neutron scattering and electron microscopy. In this paper we present silica particle growth dynamics in a hydrogel as detected by two near-infrared dyes, the effect of adding D$_2$O on the hydrodynamic radius and the effect of salt addition.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Fluorescence anisotropy; sol–gel; particle size; syneresis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Birch" fname="D. J. S." isfellow="0">Birch, D. J. S.</author>
					<author lname="Geddes" fname="C. D." isfellow="0">Geddes, C. D.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Stereochemical trends of metal derivatives of some heterocyclic-2-thiones and thiosemicarbazones</title>
				<feature>Modern Trends in Inorganic Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0323-0329</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The interaction of heterocyclic thiones/thiosemicarbazones with metals has been the subject of several investigations as these ligands contain chemically active groups, –N(H)–C(=S)– –N=C(–SH)– ,and are useful model compounds for sulphur-containing analogues of purine and pyrimidine bases. Heterocylic-2-thiones  bind to metals in several ways and lead to the formation of monomeric or polymeric complexes. For example, the simplest prototype of heterocylic-2-thiones, namely, pyridine-2-thione has several ways of binding, notably, terminal S-bonding and S-bridging (in neutral form), while in anionic form the modes are terminal S-bonding, S-bridging, N,S-chelation, N,S-bridging, N,S-chelation-cum-S-bridging and N,S-bridging-cum-S-bridging. Similarly, thiosemicarbazones bind to metals as S-bonded unidentates or N,S-chelates. In this paper, the chemistry of pyridine-2-thione, its N-oxide, 2-(benzylthio)pyridine-1-oxide thione with metals like iron(II), ruthenium(II), nickel(II), palladium(II), platinum(II), copper(I), copper(II), silver(I) and mercury(II) is briefly described. As regards thiosemicarbazones, focus is only on two compounds, namely organomercury(II) and organothallium(III). A variety of new molecules, well characterised by NMR and X-ray crystallography, is introduced.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Heterocyclic thiones; thiosemicarbazones; tertiary phosphines; coordination properties; pyridine-2-thione; 1-hydroxy-pyridine-2-thione.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lobana" fname="Tarlok S." isfellow="0">Lobana, Tarlok S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="04" month="08" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Isomorphous substitution of Mn(II), Ni(II) and Zn(II) in AlPO-31 molecular sieves and study of their catalytic performance</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0439-0448</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Isomorphously substituted molecular sieves, MAPO-31, NAPO-31 and ZAPO-31, were prepared under mild hydrothermal conditions from gels containing sources of aluminium, phosphorus, appropriate metal and dipropylamine (DPA), presumably acting as a structure-directing template. They were characterized by XRD, FTIR, TGA, inductively coupled plasma (ICP), ESR, Brunauer, Emmett, Teller (BET) and diffusion reflectance spectroscopy (DRS) techniques. In the XRD, the peak at 2 = 16 7° of the metal substituted AlPO-31 is more intense than that of pure AlPO-31 suggesting preferential occupation of the plane corresponding to it as compared to other planes. The O-H stretch in the IR spectra of the metal-substituted molecular sieves is blue-shifted with respect to the parent AlPO-31 molecular sieves possibly due to metal substitution. The g values obtained from the ESR spectra of MAPO-31 and NAPO-31 also substantiate framework substitution. Ethylation of toluene was carried out between 300 and 450°C over the above catalysts as a model test reaction. The high toluene conversion over metal-substituted  molecular sieves proves the isomorphic substitution of metal ions in the AlPO-31 framework.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Molecular sieves; MAPO-31; NAPO-31; ZAPO-31; ethylation of toluene.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Umamaheswari" fname="V." isfellow="0">Umamaheswari, V.</author>
					<author lname="Arabindoo" fname="C. Banumathi" isfellow="0">Arabindoo, C. Banumathi</author>
					<author lname="Palanichamy" fname="M." isfellow="0">Palanichamy, M.</author>
					<author lname="Murugesan" fname="V." isfellow="0">Murugesan, V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis, spectroscopic, electrochemical and luminescence studies of ruthenium (II) polypyridyls containing multifunctionalized 1,2,4-triazole as co-ligand</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0449-0458</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Ruthenium (II) 2,2 -bipyridyl and 1,10-phenanthroline complexes with 4-amino-3-hydrazino-5-mercapto-1,2,4-triazole (LH$_2$) as co-ligand were synthesised and characterized by elemental analysis, IR, UV/Vis, ${}^1$H NMR spectra and FAB-mass data. The electrochemical and luminescent properties of the complexes were also studied.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Ruthenium (II) polypyridyls; 4-amino-3-hydrazino-5-mercapto-1,2,4-triazole; N$_2$-complex.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mishra" fname="L." isfellow="0">Mishra, L.</author>
					<author lname="Yadaw" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Yadaw, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Fluorescent zinc–terpyridine complex containing coordinated peroxo counter ion in aqueous medium</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0459-0463</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We describe a mixed ligand–zinc ($d^{10}$) complex containing coordinated peroxo ion and 2,2'2"-terpyridine and exhibiting fluorescence in the visible region (473 nm) on excitation at 390 nm in aqueous medium at room temperature. We also discuss the unusual phenomenon of enhancement of this fluorescence intensity on addition of some transition metal ions (3$d^5$, 3$d^{10}$, 4$d^0$ and 3$d^9$ electronic configurations).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Zinc peroxo complex; terpyridine complexes; fluorescence enhancement.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kapoor" fname="S." isfellow="0">Kapoor, S.</author>
					<author lname="Sastry" fname="M. S." isfellow="0">Sastry, M. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>EGDMA–cross-linked polystyrene resin: An efficient support for gel phase peptide synthesis</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This article illustrates the application of a 2$&#37;$ ethyleneglycol dimethacrylate–cross-linked polystyrene support (EGDMA–PS) in manual solid phase peptide synthesis. This copolymer has been characterised and optimised for peptide synthesis by performing the synthesis of a few model peptides and two biologically important peptides. EGDMA–cross-linked polystyrene support was prepared by the suspension polymerisation of the monomers EGDMA and styrene. EGDMA–PS resin undergoes facile swelling in a variety of solvents, both polar and nonpolar, used in peptide synthesis. The polymer was functionalised by Friedel–Crafts chloromethylation reaction. Peptides were assembled on a 2$&#37;$ cross-linked chloromethyl polymer support of capacity 1 63 mmol Cl/g. The biological peptides synthesised are an 11-residue peptide ATP binding site of the CDC2 kinase and a difficult sequence-a nineresidue peptide  34-42 corresponding to a portion of the hydrophobic terminus of the-amyloid protein  1-42. After synthesis, the peptides were cleaved from the support by treating with neat TFA. Purity of the peptides obtained in good yield was checked by TLC and HPLC methods and found to be fairly high.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solid-phase peptide synthesis; EGDMA–PS supports.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ajikumar" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Ajikumar, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Devaky" fname="K. S." isfellow="0">Devaky, K. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Charge-transfer spectra of ferrocene in halocarbon solvents under photoexcitation</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0475-0485</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The changes in the electronic absorption spectra of ferrocene in the halocarbon solvents chloroform and carbontetrachloride have been investigated under photoexcitation in nitrogen atmosphere. Photoexcitations have been made with monochromatic light (using an Xe-source and a monochromator), at intervals of a few nanometers in the spectral range 220–750 nm. Analysing the spectra  by a modified method the position of the charge-transfer-to-solvent (CTTS) band has been located for both the solvents. The position of the CTTS band in the case of carbontetrachloride solution located (320 nm) by the present study is different from the previously reported value (307 nm), while from the previous studies the position of the CTTS band in the case of the spectra of ferrocene in chloroform was not clear. From the present investigation, the changes in spectra after photoexcitation studied as a function, the concentration of ferrocene in the solution and the time (duration) of photoexcitations, have been observed to be systematic. Using the position of the new band (320 nm) for the CTTS transition in the case of carbontetrachloride, ionization potential of ferrocene has been estimated and the estimated value has shown excellent agreement with the experimental value indicating the exactness of the newly located CTTS band position.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Ferrocene; charge-transfer; halocarbon solvents; photoexcitation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Thander" fname="Alfazuddin" isfellow="0">Thander, Alfazuddin</author>
					<author lname="Mallik" fname="Biswanath" isfellow="0">Mallik, Biswanath</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Quenching of nucleotide-derived radicals by bisbenzimidazole derivative Hoechst-33258 in aqueous solution</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0487-0496</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The pulse radiolysis technique has been employed to investigate the reaction of DNA-minor-groove ligand  \textit{bis}benzimidazole Hoechst 33258 with pyrimidine and purine nucleotide-derived radicals. Formation of an N-centred Hoechst-33258 radical is observed. Bimolecular rate constants and the yields of Hoechst-33258 radical have been evaluated. While the rate constant for the reaction of pyrimidine-derived radicals with Hoechst-33258 remained the same (1–2) $\times$ $10^9$ dm$^3$ mol$^{-1}$s$^{-1}$, the yields of the Hoechst-33258 radical varied from 25$&#37;$ (5 -cytidine monophosphate) to 75$&#37;$ (5 -guanosine monophosphate) under anoxic conditions. The rate constant values for the reaction of purine-derived radicals with Hoechst-33258, under oxic and anoxic conditions, remained the same whereas with pyrimidine-derived radicals, the rate constant value under oxic conditions was about two orders of magnitude lower than under anoxic conditions. The difference in the yields of Hoechst-33258 radical with various nucleotide-derived radicals suggest the formation of different types of radicals and that the reaction mainly occurs by electron transfer from Hoechst-33258 to the nucleotide radicals.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Nucleotide-derived radicals; Hoechst-33258; pulse radiolysis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mohan" fname="H." isfellow="0">Mohan, H.</author>
					<author lname="Adhikary" fname="A." isfellow="0">Adhikary, A.</author>
					<author lname="Jain" fname="V." isfellow="0">Jain, V.</author>
					<author lname="Mittal" fname="J. P." isfellow="0">Mittal, J. P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>The kinetics and mechanism of induced thermal decomposition of peroxomonosulphate by phase transfer catalysts</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0497-0505</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The kinetics of induced decomposition of potassium peroxomonosulphate (PMS) by the phase transfer catalysts (PTC), viz. tetrabutylammonium chloride [TBAC] and tetrabutylphosphonium chloride [TBPC] have been investigated. The effect of [PMS], [PTC], ionic strength of the medium and temperature on the rate of decomposition of PMS was studied. The rate of decomposition of PMS was monitored under pseudo-first-order condition at a constant temperature (50 $\pm$ 0 1$^\circ$C). The rate of decomposition was first order with respect to PMS for TBAC and half order for TBPC. The order with respect of PTC was found to be unity for TBAC and half order for TBPC. A suitable kinetic scheme has been proposed to account for the experimental data and its significance is discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Thermal decomposition; potassium peroxomonosulphate; phase transfer catalysts.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Balakrishnan" fname="T." isfellow="0">Balakrishnan, T.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="S. Damodar" isfellow="0">Kumar, S. Damodar</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="05" month="10" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics of oxidation of nickel(II) aza macrocycles by peroxydisulphate in aqueous media</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0507-0514</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The kinetics of the oxidation of nickel (II) hexaaza and nickel (II) pentaaza macrocycles by the peroxydisulphate anion, S$_2$O$_8^{2-}$, were studied in aqueous media. Effect of $p$H on reaction rate was also studied. The rate increases with increase of S$_2$O$_8^{2-}$ concentration. Rates are almost independent of acid between  $p$H 4 and 2, giving overall a relatively simple second-order rate law followed by oxidation within the ion pair solvent shell. Using rate = +1/2 d[Ni(L)$^{3+}$]/dt = k[Ni(L)$^{2+}$][S_2O$_8^{2-}$], oxidation rate constants were determined.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Kinetics; oxidation; peroxydisulphate; Ni(II) hexaazamacrocycle; Ni(II) pentaaza macrocycle.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lalitham" fname="J." isfellow="0">Lalitham, J.</author>
					<author lname="Vijayaraghavan" fname="V. R." isfellow="0">Vijayaraghavan, V. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Copper(II) complex of 3-cinnamalideneacetylacetone: Synthesis and characterisation</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0512-0521</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A bidentate ligand derived from cinnamaldehyde and acetylacetone and its copper(II) complex have been synthesized and characterized by elemental analysis, UV-Vis, IR, ESR and magnetic susceptibility measurements. Magnetic susceptibility measurements, ESR and electronic spectral data indicate the presence of six coordinated Cu(II) ion. The ligand and complex are tested for antibacterial activity against \textit{Pseudomonas aeroginosa}. They are found to show the antibacterial activity</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>\textbf{\textit{b}}-Diketones; Knoevenagel condensate; electron spin resonance; \textit{Pseudomonas aerogenosa; Caesalpinia bonducella}.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Veeraraj" fname="A." isfellow="0">Veeraraj, A.</author>
					<author lname="Sami" fname="P." isfellow="0">Sami, P.</author>
					<author lname="Raman" fname="N." isfellow="0">Raman, N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Chemistry of azopyrimidines. Part IV. Aromatic hydroxylation in palladium(II)-arylazopyrimidines</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0523-0534</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>2-(Arylazo)pyrimidines (aapm) are N,N -chelating ligands and synthesise orange-red complexes of composition [Pd(aapm)Cl$_2$],  {\bf 1}, with Pd(MeCN)$_2$Cl$_2$ in MeCN. The complex has  \textit{cis}-PdCl$_2$ configuration [(Pd−Cl): 340, 360 cm$^{-1}$]. The treatment of Tollen’s reagent (`AgOH’) leads to chelatative hydroxylation in the pendant aryl ring, affording a green phenolato complex, Pd(aapmO)Cl, {\bf 5} (aapmO is deprotonated 2-((8-hydroxo)arylazo)pyrimidine). The reaction is also carried out by controlled addition of dilute sodium hydroxide in air or by the addition of PhIO/$m$-chloroperbenzoic acid to a MeCN suspension of the complex. A single Pd–Cl stretch at 360 cm$^{-1}$ supports the composition of phenolato complex. Unlike Pd(aapm)Cl$_2$ the hydroxylated product, Pd(aapmO)Cl, has a structured intense absorption in the visible region near 670 nm. The Pd–Cl bond in Pd(aapmO)Cl is highly sensitive to nucleophilic substitution and slowly hydrolyses in aqueous medium.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Arylazopyrimidines; palladium(II); aromatic hydroxylation; oxygen insertion; spectral characterization; electrochemistry.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Santra" fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Santra, P. K.</author>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="R." isfellow="0">Roy, R.</author>
					<author lname="Sinha" fname="C." isfellow="0">Sinha, C.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A method for increasing the surface area of perovskite-type oxides</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0535-0542</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A method based on hydrothermal treatments is described for increasing the surface area of sintered ABO$_3$-type perovskite oxides. Influence of hydrothermal treatments, such as water treatment at 125–300$^\circ$C under autogeneous pressure and steam treatment at 350–800$^\circ$C, to low surface area (or sintered) LaCoO$_3$ and LaMnO$_3$ perovskite oxides on their surface properties (viz. surface area, crystal size and morphology and surface La/(Co or Mn) ratio) and also catalytic activity in complete combustion of methane at different temperatures (450–600$\circ$C) has been thoroughly investigated. The hydrothermal treatments result in the activation of the perovskite oxides by increasing their surface area very markedly.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>ABO$_3$-type perovskite oxides; LaCoO$_3$; LaMnO$_3$; hydrothermal treatment; catalytic combustion of methane.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Banerjee" fname="S." isfellow="0">Banerjee, S.</author>
					<author lname="Choudhary" fname="V. R." isfellow="0">Choudhary, V. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Electrochemical behaviour of alkaline copper complexes </title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0543-0550</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A search for non-cyanide plating baths for copper resulted in the development of alkaline copper complex baths containing trisodium citrate [TSC] and triethanolamine [TEA]. Voltammetric studies were carried out on platinum to understand the electrochemical behaviour of these complexes. In TSC solutions, the deposition of copper involves the slow formation of a monovalent species. Adsorption of this species obeys Langmuir isotherm. In TEA solutions the deposition involves the formation of monovalent ions obeying the non-activated Temkin isotherm. Conversion of divalent to monovalent copper is also slow. In TEA and TSC alkaline copper solutions, the predominant species that undergo stepwise reduction contain only TEA ligands</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Alkaline copper complexes; non-cyanide plating.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Aravinda" fname="C. L." isfellow="0">Aravinda, C. L.</author>
					<author lname="Mayanna" fname="S. M." isfellow="0">Mayanna, S. M.</author>
					<author lname="Muralidharan" fname="V. R." isfellow="0">Muralidharan, V. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Oxidation of caffeine by phosphate radical anion in aqueous solution under anoxic conditions</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0551-0557</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The photooxidation of caffeine in presence of peroxydiphosphate (PDP) in aqueous solution at natural $p$H ($\sim$7 5) has been carried out in a quantum yield reactor using a high-pressure mercury lamp. The reactions  were followed spectrophotometrically by measuring the absorbance of caffeine at {}_${\max}$ (272 nm). The rates of reaction were calculated under different experimental conditions. The quantum yields were calculated from the rates of oxidation of caffeine and the intensity of light at 254 nm which was measured by using peroxydisulphate solution as a standard chemical actinometer. The reaction rates of oxidation of caffeine by PDP increase with increase in [PDP] as well as with increase in light intensity, while they are independent of [caffeine]. The quantum yields of oxidation of caffeine by PDP are independent of [PDP] as well as light intensity. However, quantum yields of oxidation of caffeine by PDP increase with increase in caffeine concentration. On the basis of these experimental results and product analysis, a probable mechanism has been suggested in which PDP is activated to phosphate radical anions (PO$_4^{.2-}$) by direct photolysis of PDP and also by the sensitizing effect of caffeine. The phosphate radical anions thus produced react with caffeine by electron transfer reaction, resulting in the formation of caffeine radical cation, which deprotonates in a fast step to produce C8OH adduct radicals. These radicals might react with PDP to give final product 1,3,7-trimethyluric acid and PO$_4^{.2-}$ radicals, the latter propagates the chain reaction.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oxidation of caffeine; phosphate radical anion; peroxydiphosphate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="Maram Ravi" isfellow="0">Kumar, Maram Ravi</author>
					<author lname="Adinarayana" fname="Mundra" isfellow="0">Adinarayana, Mundra</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="06" month="12" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Exogenous bridging and nonbridging in Cu(II) complexes of Mannich base ligands: Synthesis and physical properties</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0559-0572</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Preparation of pentadentate ligands L$^1$, L$^2$, L$^3$ and L$^4$, where L$^1$=4-chloro-3-methyl-2[(prolin-1-yl)methyl]-6-[N-phenyl piperazin-1-yl)methyl]phenol, L$^2$= 4-ethyl-2-[(prolin-1-yl)methyl]-6-[(N-phenyl piperazin-1-yl)methyl]phenol, L$^3$ =4-chloro-3-methyl-2-[(prolin-1-yl)methyl]-6-[N-methyl piperazin-1-yl]methyl phenol, L$^4$ = 4-methoxy-2-[(prolin-1-yl)methyl]-6-[(N-phenyl piperazin-1-yl)methyl]phenol is described together with that of the corresponding Cu(II) complexes with various bridging motifs like OH, OAc and NO$_2$. The complexes are characterized by elemental analysis, electrochemical and electron paramagnetic spectral studies. Redox properties of the complexes in acetonitrile are highly quasireversible due to the chemical or/and stereochemical changes subsequent to electron transfer. The complexes show resolved copper hyperfine EPR at room temperature, indicating the presence of weak antiferromagnetic coupling between the copper atoms. Strengths of the antiferromagnetic interactions are in the order NO$_2$ $&gt;$ OAc $&gt;$ OH.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Unsymmetrical ligands; dinuclear complex; synthetic models; cyclic voltammetry and electron paramagnetic resonance.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sujatha" fname="S." isfellow="0">Sujatha, S.</author>
					<author lname="Rajendiran" fname="R. M." isfellow="0">Rajendiran, T. M.</author>
					<author lname="Kannappan" fname="R." isfellow="0">Kannappan, R.</author>
					<author lname="Venkatesan" fname="R." isfellow="0">Venkatesan, R.</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="P. Sambasiva" isfellow="0">Rao, P. Sambasiva</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Investigation of properties of rare earth complexes with dibromo-$p$-methyl-methylsulfonazo by spectral correction technique</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0573-0578</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The reactions were sensitive between seven rare earth (RE) metals Nd(III), La(III), Ce(III), Pr(III), Sm(III), Eu(III) and Gd(III) and dibromo-$p$-methylmethylsulfonazo (DBMMSA) in acidic solution. The spectral correction method has been applied in the determination of properties of RE complexes instead of ordinary spectrophotometry. Composition ratios, real molar absorptivities ( ) and stepwise stability constants ($K$) of each of the RE complexes were determined easily because the method eliminated the absorption influence of excess of ligand on complex. Results showed that the cumulative  $K$ values of the complexes were between 3 91 $\times$ 10$^{14}$ and 2 34 $\times$ 10$^{28}$ and the real (not apparent) absorptivity between 8 85 $\times$ 10$^4$ and 2 12 $\times$ 10$^5$ l mol$^{-1}$cm$^{-1}$ at 640 nm.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Spectral correction technique; rare earth; dibromo-$p$-methylmethylsulfonazo (DBMMSA).</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Hong" fname="Fa-Shui" isfellow="0">Hong, Fa-Shui</author>
					<author lname="Ye" fname="Qing-Song" isfellow="0">Ye, Qing-Song</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Coenzyme B$_{12}$ model studies: An HSAB approach to the equilibria and kinetics of axial ligation of alkyl(aquo)-cobaloximes by imidazole and cyanide</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0579-0591</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Kinetics and equilibria of the axial ligation of alkyl(aquo)cobaloximes by imidazole and cyanide have been measured spectrophotometrically in aqueous solutions of ionic strength 1⋅0 M at 25$\circ$C as a function of $p$H. Comparison of $K_{\text{IMD}}$ and $K_{\text{CN}}$– of CH$_3$, C$_2$H$_5$ and BrCH$_2$ cobaloximes indicates that their stability is in the order BrCH$_2$ $&gt;$ CH$_3$ $&gt;$ C$_2$H$_5$. As the electron-withdrawing capacity of the alkyl group \textit{trans} to water increases, the electron density of the cobalt(III) decreases and thus it becomes a stronger Lewis acid and binds more strongly to imidazole and cyanide. The association and dissociation rate constants are better correlated to the relative softness of the ligand showing that cyanide binds 30 times faster than imidazole. These complexes are isolated and are characterized by IR and ${}^1$H NMR spectra.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Alkyl cobaloximes; association constants; hand and soft acids and bases; rhodoximes; dissociation constants.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sridhar" fname="Vaddeboina" isfellow="0">Sridhar, Vaddeboina</author>
					<author lname="Satyanarayana" fname="S." isfellow="0">Satyanarayana, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and characterization of mixed ligand complexes of bio-metals with pyrimidine nucleoside (uridine) and amino acids</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0593-0600</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The mixed ligand complexes of Cu(II), Ni(II) and Co(II) with uridine and amino acids,  L-alanine,  L-phenylalanine and  L-tryptophan were synthesized and characterized by elemental analysis, conductivity data, infrared spectra, electronic spectra and magnetic susceptibility data. In these complexes, the nucleoside (uridine) acts as a monodentate ligand coordinating through O(4) under the conditions of investigation, whereas the amino acids coordinate through the carboxylate oxygen and the amino nitrogen. Distorted octahedral geometry for Cu(II) and octahedral geometries for both Ni(II) and Co(II) are proposed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mixed ligand complexes; divalent complexes of Cu, Ni and Co; uridine; L-aminoacids.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Reddy" fname="P. Rabindra" isfellow="0">Reddy, P. Rabindra</author>
					<author lname="Reddy" fname="A. Mohan" isfellow="0">Reddy, A. Mohan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Hydrogen bonded complexes of cyanuric acid with pyridine and guanidinium carbonate</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0607-0614</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Hydrogen bonded complexes of cyanuric acid (CA) with pyridine, [C$_3$N$_3$H$_3$O$_3$:C$_5$H$_5$N], {\bf 1}, and guanidinium carbonate [C$_3$H$_2$N$_3$][C(NH$_2$)$_3$], {\bf 2}, have been prepared at room temperature and characterized by single-crystal  X-ray diffraction. Structure of {\bf 1} shows pyridine molecules substituting the inter-tape hydrogen bond in CA by N–H$\ldots$N and C–H$\ldots$O hydrogen bonds. The structure reveals CA-pyridine hydrogen-bonded single helices held together by dimeric N–H$\ldots$O hydrogen bonding between CA molecules. In {\bf 2}, the CA tapes, resembling a sine wave interact with the guanidinium cations through N–H$\ldots$O and N–H$\ldots$N hydrogen bonds forming guanidinium cyanurate sheets.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cyanuric acid-pyridine adduct; guanidinium cyanurate; single helices; crystal structure analysis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sivashankar" fname="K." isfellow="0">Sivashankar, K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetic investigation of the oxidation of N-alkyl anilines by peroxomonophosphoric acid in anionic surfactant sodium lauryl sulphate</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0615-0622</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Kinetics of oxidation of N-methyl and N-ethyl aniline by peroxomono-phosphoric acid (PMPA) in aqueous and 5$&#37;$ (v/v)  acetonitrile medium respectively have been studied in presence of anionic micelles of sodium lauryl sulphate (SLS) at different  $p$H. Oxidation rate of both the substrates increases up to a certain [SLS] much below the critical micellar concentration (cmc) after which the rate is retarded. Kinetic data have been used to compute the binding constants of both substrate and oxidant with the micelle. A scheme explaining the kinetic data has been proposed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Anionic surfactants; peroxomonophosphoric acid; oxidation of N-alkyl anilines.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Panigrahi" fname="G. P." isfellow="0">Panigrahi, G. P.</author>
					<author lname="Panda" fname="Jagannath" isfellow="0">Panda, Jagannath</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Theoretical studies on the conformations of selenamides</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0623-0629</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>\textit{Ab initio} $\text{HF}/6-31+G^{\ast}$, $\text{MP}2/6-31+G^{\ast}$, $\text{B3LYP}/6-31+G^{\ast}$ level calculations have been performed on HSe–NH$_2$ to estimate the Se–N rotational barriers and N-inversion barriers. Two conformers have been found with syn and anti arrangement of the NH$_2$ hydrogens with respect to Se–H bond. The N inversion barriers in selenamide are 1 65, 2 47, 1 93 kcal/mol and the Se–N rotational barriers are 6 58, 6 56 and 6 12 kcal/mol respectively at $\text{HF}/6-31+G^{\ast}$, $\text{MP}2/6-31+G^{\ast}$ and $\text{B3LYP}/6-31+G^{\ast}$ levels respectively. The $n_{\text N} {}^{\ast}_{\text{Se–H}}$ negative hyperconjugation is found to be responsible for the higher rotational barriers.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Selenamides; Se–N interactions; conformations; \textit{ab initio} calculations.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Moudgil" fname="Rajnish" isfellow="0">Moudgil, Rajnish</author>
					<author lname="Kaur" fname="Damanjit" isfellow="0">Kaur, Damanjit</author>
					<author lname="Vashisht" fname="Rachita" isfellow="0">Vashisht, Rachita</author>
					<author lname="Bharatam" fname="Prasad V." isfellow="0">Bharatam, Prasad V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="113">
		<issue inum="01" month="02" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Editors’ note</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Peroxidase-like catalytic activities of ionic metalloporphyrins supported on functionalised polystyrene surface</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0001-0009</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Metalloderivatives of anionic tetrasulphonated tetraphenylporphyrin (MTPPS, M = Mn(III), Fe(III) and Co(III)) were synthesized and immobilized on cationically functionalised divinylbenzene(DVB)–crosslinked polystyrene(PS). These supported catalysts (PS-MTPPS) were found to exhibit peroxidase-like activity. The co-oxidation of 4-aminoantipyrine and phenol by H$_2$O$_2$ was attempted with these catalysts to mimic this enzyme function. The catalytic efficiency of all these immobilized MTPPS was found to be superior to the corresponding unsupported MTPPS in solution. The effect of the central metal ion of the porphyrin, $p$H of the reaction medium and also the temperature effect are investigated. The ideal  $p$H was seen to be in the 8 0–8 5 range, with maximum effect at 8 2. The efficiency order for the various PS-MTPPS was seen to be Co$&gt;$Mn$&gt;$Fe, with CoTPPS showing efficiency comparable to that of horseradish peroxidase. The catalytic efficiency was found to be increasing with temperature for all the catalysts. The re-usability of these PS-MTPPS systems for peroxidase-like activity was also studied and it was found that they exhibited a very high degree of recyclability without much poisoning.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Polystyrene support; metalloporphyrins; peroxidase model; enzyme catalysis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Vinodu" fname="Mikki V." isfellow="0">Vinodu, Mikki V.</author>
					<author lname="Padmanabhan" fname="M." isfellow="0">Padmanabhan, M.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical </feature>
				<page>0011-0020</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Reaction between 3-formylsalicylic acid and  \textit{bis}-(2-aminophenyl)-disulphide yields a septadentate Schiff base with N$_2$SO$_4$ donor frame of which the inner compartment is N$_2$SO$_2$ and the outer is O$_2$O$_2$ type. It forms several complexes with inner copper centre and outer nontransition/transition metal ions. The complexes have been characterised by elemental analyses, spectral  (IR, absorption, diffused reflectance), thermal and magnetic data. Dinuclear copper complexes exhibit subnormal magnetic moments ( 0 80 BM), showing magnetic exchange, and six-line solid-state ESR spectra at 77 K.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Septadentate Schiff base; copper complexes; compartmental ligand; subnormal magnetic moment; spectral characterization; ESR spectra.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Nag" fname="J. K." isfellow="0">Nag, J. K.</author>
					<author lname="Das" fname="D." isfellow="0">Das, D.</author>
					<author lname="Pal" fname="S." isfellow="0">Pal, S.</author>
					<author lname="Sinha" fname="C." isfellow="0">Sinha, C.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthetic, spectral and solution studies on imidazolate-bridged copper(II)–copper(II) and copper(II)–zinc(II) complexes</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical </feature>
				<page>0021-0027</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Synthesis, spectral and solution studies on 2-ethyl imidazolate-bridged (2-EtIm) homo-binuclear copper(II)–copper(II) and hetero-binuclear copper(II)–zinc(II) homologue are described. Magnetic moment values of homo-binuclear complexes indicate that the imidazolate group can mediate antiferromagnetic interactions. Optical spectra of hetero-binuclear complex at varying $p$H values suggest that the imidazolate-bridged complex is stable over the $p$H-range 7 15–10 0.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>2-Ethylimidazolate-bridged; homo/hetero-binuclear complexes; antiferromagnetic interactions.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="Subodh" isfellow="0">Kumar, Subodh</author>
					<author lname="Patel" fname="R. N." isfellow="0">Patel, R. N.</author>
					<author lname="Khadikar" fname="P. V." isfellow="0">Khadikar, P. V.</author>
					<author lname="Pandeya" fname="K. B." isfellow="0">Pandeya, K. B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis of cyano-bridged bimetallic complexes of ${}^5$-indenyl ruthenium(II): Characterization and spectroscopic studies</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical </feature>
				<page>0029-0033</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Reactions of the cyanide complexes of the type [(Ind)Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$CN] ({\bf 1}), [(Ind)Ru(dppe)CN] ({\bf 2}), [(Cp)Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$CN] ({\bf 3}), with the corresponding chloro complexes [(Ind)Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$Cl] ({\bf 4}), [(Ind)Ru(dppe)Cl] ({\bf 5}), [(Cp)Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$Cl] ({\bf 6}), in the presence of NH$_4$PF$_6$ salt give homometallic cyano-bridged compounds of the type [(Ind)(PPh$_3$)$_2$Ru–CN–Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$(Cp)]PF$_6$ ({\bf 7}), [(Ind)(PPh$_3$)$_2$Ru–CN–Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$(Ind)] PF$_6$ where Ind = indenyl, ${}^5-$C$_9$H$_7$, ({\bf 8}), [(Cp)(PPh$_3$)$_2$Ru–CN–Ru(dppe)(Ind)]PF$_6$, dppe = (Ph$_2$PCH$_2$CH$_2$PPh$_2$) ({\bf 9}), [(Ind(dppe)Ru–CN–Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$(Ind)PF$_6$ ({\bf 10}) and [(Ind)(dppe)Ru–CN–Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$(Cp)]PF$_6$ ({\bf 11}) respectively. Reaction of complex  {\bf 3} with [(p-cymene)RuCl$_2$]$_2$ dimer gave a mixed dimeric complex [(Cp)Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$–CN–RuCl$_2$($p$-cymene)] ({\bf 12}). All these complexes have been characterized by IR, ${}^1$H, ${}^{13}$C and ${}^{31}$ P NMR spectroscopy and C, H, N analyses.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cyano-bridged; ${}^5$-indenyl; bimetallic complexes; ruthenium.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="K. Mohan" isfellow="0">Rao, K. Mohan</author>
					<author lname="Rymmai" fname="E. K." isfellow="0">Rymmai, E. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Can Co(II) or Cd(II) substitute for Zn(II) in zinc fingers?</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0035-0042</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Zinc finger domains consist of sequences of amino acids containing cysteine and histidine residues tetrahedrally coordinated to a zinc ion. The role of zinc in a DNA binding finger was considered purely structural due to the absence of redox chemistry in zinc. However, whether other metals e.g. Co(II) or Cd(II) can substitute Zn(II) is not settled. For an answer the detailed interaction of Co(II) and Cd(II) with cysteine methylester and histidine methylester has been investigated as a model for the zinc  core in zinc fingers. The study was extended to different temperatures to evaluate the thermodynamic parameters associated with these interactions. The results suggest that zinc has a unique role.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Zinc finger; cobalt; cadmium; cysteine methylester; histidine methylester; stability constants; thermodynamic parameters.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Reddy" fname="P. Rabindra" isfellow="0">Reddy, P. Rabindra</author>
					<author lname="Radhika" fname="M." isfellow="0">Radhika, M.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics and mechanism of the oxidation of some diols by benzyltrimethylammonium tribromide</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0043-0054</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The kinetics of oxidation of five vicinal and four non-vicinal diols, and two of their monoethers by benzyltrimethylammonium tribromide (BTMAB) have been studied in 3:7 ($v/v$) acetic acid–water mixture. The vicinal diols yield the carbonyl compounds arising out of the glycol bond fission while the other diols give the hydroxycarbonyl compounds. The reaction is first-order with respect to BTMAB. Michaelis–Menten type kinetics is observed with respect to diol. Addition of benzyltrimethylammonium chloride does not affect the rate. Tribromide ion is postulated to be the reactive oxidizing species. Oxidation of [1,1,2,2-$^2$H$_4$] ethanediol shows the absence of a kinetic isotope effect. The reaction exhibits substantial solvent isotope effect. A mechanism involving a glycol-bond fission has been proposed for the oxidation of the vicinal diols. The other diols are oxidized by a hydride ion transfer to the oxidant, as are the monohydric alcohols.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Diols; benzyltrimethylammonium tribromide; oxidation; kinetics; mechanism; kinetic isotope effect.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Goswami" fname="Garima" isfellow="0">Goswami, Garima</author>
					<author lname="Kothari" fname="Seema" isfellow="0">Kothari, Seema</author>
					<author lname="Banerji" fname="Kalyan K." isfellow="0">Banerji, Kalyan K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Small-angle neutron scattering study of sodium cholate and sodium deoxycholate interacting micelles in aqueous medium</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0055-0062</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Small angle neutron scattering (SANS) measurements of D$_2$O solutions (0 1 M) of sodium cholate (NaC) and sodium deoxycholate (NaDC) were carried out at $T$ = 298 K. Under compositions very much above the critical micelle concentration (CMC), the bile salt micelle size growths were monitored by adopting Hayter–Penfold type analysis of the scattering data. NaC and NaDC solutions show presence of correlation peaks at $Q$ = 0 12 and 0 1 Å$^{-1}$ respectively. Monodisperse ellipsoids of the micelles produce best fits. For NaC and NaDC systems, aggregation number (9 0, 16 0), fraction of the free counterions per micelle (0 79, 0 62), semi-minor (8 0 Å) and semi-major axes (18 4, 31 7 Å) values for the micelles were deduced. Extent of micellar growth was studied using ESR correlation time measurements on a suitable probe incorporating NaC and NaDC micelles. The growth parameter (axial ratio) values were found to be 2 3 and 4 0 for NaC and NaDC systems respectively. The values agree with those of SANS.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Biosurfactants; sodium deoxycholate micelles; bile salt micelles; SANS study; ESR correlation times.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Santhanalakshmi" fname="J." isfellow="0">Santhanalakshmi, J.</author>
					<author lname="Lakshmi" fname="G. Shantha" isfellow="0">Lakshmi, G. Shantha</author>
					<author lname="Aswal" fname="V. K." isfellow="0">Aswal, V. K.</author>
					<author lname="Goyal" fname="P. S." isfellow="0">Goyal, P. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>An insight into the passivation of cupronickel alloys in chloride environment</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0063-0076</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Cupronickels offer enhanced corrosion protection in marine environments by the formation of passive films on the surface. Cyclic voltammetric studies were carried on cupronickels in chloride solutions at  $p$H 6 3 to understand the role of chloride ions in passive film formation. Increase in nickel content of the alloy and of chloride ions in solution decreases film resistance. Chloride ions take part in reduction of the passive film to copper. A solid-state model for passive film formation involving chloride ions has been attempted.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cupronickels; passivation; solid-state model; cyclic voltammetry; marine environment.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mathiyarasu" fname="J." isfellow="0">Mathiyarasu, J.</author>
					<author lname="Palaniswamy" fname="N." isfellow="0">Palaniswamy, N.</author>
					<author lname="Muralidharan" fname="V. S." isfellow="0">Muralidharan, V. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="04" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Functional model of oxomolybdoenzymes: Synthesis and characterization of a molybdenum complex with sulphur and pterin ligands exhibiting saturation kinetics with pyridine N-oxide</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0077-0087</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Redox reaction between 6-acetonylisoxanthopterin (H$_2$pte) and [Mo${}^{VI}$O$_2$(ssp)] [ssp = anion of 2-(salicylideneamino) benzenethiol] in CH$_3$OH–C$_2$H$_5$OH medium produces a new mixed ligand compound [Mo$^{IV}$ (ssp) (Hpte) (OCH$_3$)] ({\bf 1}). It has been characterized by elemental analysis, ESMS data, UV-Vis, IR, ${}^1$ H NMR (1D and 2D) spectroscopy and cyclic voltammetry. Kinetics of formation of this compound as well as that of its reaction with pyridine N-oxide have been followed spectrophotometrically. Both the reactions follow substrate saturation kinetics and involve metal-centred oxygen atom transfer process. Large negative values of entropy of activation indicate the operation of associative mechanism.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mixed ligand molybdenum (IV) compound with a 6-substituted pterin; model system of oxomolybdoenzymes; oxygen atom transfer reaction.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ali" fname="M. D. Afsar" isfellow="0">Ali, M. D. Afsar</author>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="Parag S." isfellow="0">Roy, Parag S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Metal–selenium interactions. Crystal structure of binuclear [($^1$ -iodo)-($^2$ - -iodo) (triphenyl selenophosphorane–Se)mercury(II)]$_2$ complex</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0089-0094</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Reaction of mercury(II) diiodide with triphenyl selenophosphorane–Se (1:1 mole ratio) in acetone followed by recrystallisation of the product from chloroform formed crystals of stoichiometry &#123;HgI$_2$(Ph$_3$PSe)&#125;({\bf 1}). Compound {\bf 1} existsas a centrosymmetric homobimetallic dimer, &#123;Hg( -I)I(Ph$_3$PSe)&#125;$_2$, as monoclinic crystals of space group  $P2_1/n$. The dimer comprises two ${}_2$-iodo atoms that form unequal Hg–I bonds &#123;2 8230(10), 3 1135(9) Å&#125; and two equal terminal Hg–I bonds &#123;2 6524(10) Å&#125;. The Se atom of Ph$_3$PSe forms terminal Hg–Se bond &#123;2 5914(11)Å&#125; and thus the geometry about each Hg centre is distorted tetrahedral and the range of tetrahedral bond angles is 92 97(2) to 130 85(3)$^{\circ}$, the largest being that of Se(1)–Hg(1)–I(1) and the shortest, I(2)–Hg(1)–I(2)$^{\ast}$. Hg–Hg and I–I separations of &#123;4 0930(11)Å&#125; and &#123;4 3097(15)Å&#125; are more than the sums of their respective van der Waal radii &#123;3 00 Å and 4 24 Å&#125;.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Binuclear complex; mercury(II) iodide; triphenyl seleno-phosphoraneSe; centrosymmetric; phosphine chalcogenides.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lobana" fname="Tarlok S." isfellow="0">Lobana, Tarlok S.</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="Amarjeet" isfellow="0">Singh, Amarjeet</author>
					<author lname="Kaur" fname="Mandeep" isfellow="0">Kaur, Mandeep</author>
					<author lname="Castineiras" fname="Alfonso" isfellow="0">Castineiras, Alfonso</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>New mesogenic homologous series of  -methylcinnamates</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0095-0102</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Compounds of a new smectogenic homologous series of  -methylcinnamates were prepared by condensing different 4-$n$-alkoxybenzoyl chloride with methoxyethyl  \textit{trans}-4-hydroxy- -methylcinnamate. In this series, the first six members are non-mesogenic.  $n$-Heptyloxy derivative exhibits monotropic smectic A phase whereas rest of the members exhibit enantiotropic smectic A mesophase. The compounds are characterized by combination of elemental analysis and spectroscopic techniques. Enthalpies of few homologues are measured by DSC techniques. Fluorescent properties are also observed. The thermal stabilities of the present series are compared with those of other structurally related mesogenic homologous series.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Smectic A; ambient temperature;  -methylcinnamates.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Vora" fname="R. A." isfellow="0">Vora, R. A.</author>
					<author lname="Prajapati" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Prajapati, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics and mechanism of the oxidation of formic and oxalic acids by benzyltrimethylammonium dichloroiodate</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0103-0108</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The oxidation of formic and oxalic acids by benzyltrimethylammonium dichloroiodate (BTMACI), in the presence of zinc chloride, leads to the formation of carbon dioxide. The reaction is first order with respect to BTMACI, zinc chloride and organic acid. Oxidation of deuteriated formic acid indicates the presence of a kinetic isotope effect. Addition of benzyltrimethylammonium chloride enhances the rate. It is proposed that the reactive oxidizing species is [(PhCH$_2$Me$_3$N)$^+$ (IZn$_2$Cl$_6$)$^−$]. Suitablemechanisms have been proposed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Polyhalogens; benzytrimethylammonium dichloroiodate; organic acids.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Gupta" fname="Poonam" isfellow="0">Gupta, Poonam</author>
					<author lname="Kothari" fname="Seema" isfellow="0">Kothari, Seema</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Powder XRD investigations on dotriacontane in mixtures: Phase strength and super lattices</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0109-0117</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Powder XRD investigations on dotriacontane-decane and dotriacontane-decanol mixtures are made. Phase strength, phase separation and formation of superlattices are discussed. The role of tunnel-like defects is considered.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Hydrocarbons; mixtures; phase strength; tunnel-like defects; super lattices.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shashikanth" fname="P. B." isfellow="0">Shashikanth, P. B.</author>
					<author lname="Prasad" fname="P. B. V." isfellow="0">Prasad, P. B. V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Anomalous spreading behaviour of polyethyleneglycoldistearate monolayers at air/water interface</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0119-0127</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Spreading behaviour of the dimeric surfactant polyethyleneglycoldistearate (PEGDS) monolayer at air/water interface has been studied using surface pressure–area ( –$A$) isotherms as a function of temperature. The isotherms show a plateau suggesting a transition between a liquid expanded (LE) and a condensed state. The condensed state possibly arises due to nucleation and growth of multilayers from the monolayer. Isobaric measurements of both  $A–T$ and  $–T$ at constant area show transitions at $T = 295$ K. These plots suggest a melting followed by formation of condensed microcrystallites. Structure optimization carried out using various angles of orientation of the alkyl tails with respect to the backbone in PEGDS reveals tilt transitions of the tails in different states which can be related to the packing behaviour seen in the isotherms. Optical microscopy has been used to confirm the structures in these states.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Anomalous behaviour; polythyleneglycoldistearate; air/water interface; surface pressure–area isotherms; condensed microcrystallites.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Collins" fname="S. John" isfellow="0">Collins, S. John</author>
					<author lname="Dhathathreyan" fname="Aruna" isfellow="0">Dhathathreyan, Aruna</author>
					<author lname="Ramasami" fname="T." isfellow="0">Ramasami, T.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Multiphoton dissociation/ionisation of dimethyl sulphide (CH$_3$SCH$_3$) at 355 and 532 nm</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0129-0138</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Multiphoton dissociation/ionization has been studied for CH$_3$SCH$_3$ at 355 and 532 nm using a time-of-flight mass spectrometer. The major ion signals observed at 355 nm are C$^+$, CH$_3^+$, HCS$^+$, CH$_2$S$^+$, CH$_3$S$^+^ and CH$_3$SCH$_3^+$. Power dependence studies at 355 nm show a  $(2 + 1)$ REMPI process for the formation of parent ion. Peaks at  $m/e = 46$, 47 and 61 show two-photon laser power dependence whereas $m/e = 15$ and 45 peaks show four-photon dependence. However, in 532 nm photoionisation, no parent ion signal is observed. A peak at $m/e = 35$ corresponding to SH$_3^+$ has been observed. SH$_3^+$ has been suggested to originate from CH$_3$SCH$_2^+$ via a cyclic transition state. Photoionisation results of CH$_3$SCH$_3$ have been compared with those of CH$_3$SSCH$_3$, at these two wavelengths.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Dimethyl sulphide, multiphoton ionization; time-of-flight mass spectroscopy.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Vatsa, Rajesh K." fname="Vatsa, Rajesh K." isfellow="0">Vatsa, Rajesh K.</author>
					<author lname="Majumder, Chiranjib" fname="Majumder, Chiranjib" isfellow="0">Majumder, Chiranjib</author>
					<author lname="Jayakumar, Onnattu D." fname="Jayakumar, Onnattu D." isfellow="0">Jayakumar, Onnattu D.</author>
					<author lname="Kulshreshtha, Shailendra K." fname="Kulshreshtha, Shailendra K." isfellow="0">Kulshreshtha, Shailendra K.</author>
					<author lname="Mittal, Jai P." fname="Mittal, Jai P." isfellow="0">Mittal, Jai P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics and mechanism of oxidation of aliphatic alcohols by tetrabutylammonium tribromide</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0139-0146</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Oxidation of nine primary aliphatic alcohols by tetrabutylammonium tribromide (TBATB) in aqueous acetic acid leads to the formation of the corresponding aldehydes. The reaction is first order with respect to TBATB. Michaelis–Menten type kinetics is observed with respect to alcohols. The reaction failed to induce the polymerization of acrylonitrile. Tetrabutylammonium chloride has no effect on the reaction rate. The proposed reactive oxidizing species is the tribromide ion. The oxidation of [1,1-$^2$H$_2$]ethanol exhibits a substantial kinetic isotope effect. The effect of solvent composition indicates that the rate increases with increase in the polarity of the solvent. The reaction is susceptible to both polar and steric effects of substituents. A mechanism involving transfer of a hydride ion in the ratedetermining step has been proposed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Aliphatic alcohols; hydride ion transfer; tetrabutylammonium tribromide.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Baghmar" fname="Manju" isfellow="0">Baghmar, Manju</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="Pradeep K." isfellow="0">Sharma, Pradeep K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Preparation of copper sulphide clusters in organic–inorganic composites of Langmuir–Blodgett films of amphiphilic Schiff bases</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0147-0155</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Copper sulphide clusters were prepared in Langmuir–Blodgett films of copper complexes of amphiphilic Schiff bases-3,4-dimethoxy-N-benzylidene hexadeylamine ({\bf I}) and 3,4-dimethoxy-N-benzylidene-4 -(hexadecylamino) benzylamine ({\bf II}) The clusters obtained were analysed using UV-Vis spectroscopy and optical microscopy. Brewster angle microscopic studies on monolayers of  {\bf I} and  {\bf II} at air/water interface showed formation of needle-like domains which seem to cluster faster in  {\bf I} than in {\bf II}. Atomic force microscopy  (AFM) studies also showed fairly uniform sized clusters in {\bf II} whereas in the case of {\bf I} they seem to show varying sizes. From the results it is concluded that  -elongation in the polar head groups leads to controlled cluster sizes in compound {\bf II} as compared to those in compound {\bf I}.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Copper sulphide clusters; Langmuir–Blodgett films; organic–inorganic composites; amphiphilic Schiff bases.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Hemakanthi" fname="G." isfellow="0">Hemakanthi, G.</author>
					<author lname="Dhathathreyan" fname="Aruna" isfellow="0">Dhathathreyan, Aruna</author>
					<author lname="Ramasami" fname="T." isfellow="0">Ramasami, T.</author>
					<author lname="Möbius" fname="D." isfellow="0">Möbius, D.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>TRANES analysis of the fluorescence of nile red in organized molecular assemblies confirms emission from two species</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0157-0163</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Time-resolved area normalized emission spectroscopy (TRANES) is a new method for the analysis of fluorescence of dyes in complex chemical and biological systems (A S R Koti, M M G Krishna and N Periasamy, 2001,  \textit{J. Phys. Chem.} {\bf 105}, 1767). The model-free method extends the power of time-resolved emission spectroscopy (TRES) analysis and removes the ambiguity in the interpretation when the emission spectrum is time-dependent. Observation of an isoemissive point in TRANES analysis of fluorescence is an unambiguous indication for the presence of two emissive species in the sample. The isoemissive point occurs at a wavelength where the ratio of the radiative rates of the two species is equal to the ratio of their total radiative rates. The polarity-sensitive nile red dye shows timedependent emission spectra in the organized bilayer assemblies of TX micelle and bilayer egg-phosphotidylcholine (egg-PC) membrane. Time-dependent spectra in complex systems support many important models (solvation model and heterogeneity in the ground and/or excited state). TRANES analysis shows that the fluorescence emission of nile red in TX micelle and egg-PC membrane is due to two emissive species solubilized in different sites.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>TRANES; TRES; fluorescence; nile red; solvent relaxation; organized molecular assemblies; solvation dynamics.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Koti" fname="A. S. R." isfellow="0">Koti, A. S. R.</author>
					<author lname="Periasamy" fname="N." isfellow="0">Periasamy, N.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="06" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Dioxobridged complexes of molybdenum (IV) and tungsten (IV) with N-alkylphenothiazines and their interactions with L-cysteine and L-histidine</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0165-0172</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Six new dioxobridged complexes of molybdenum (IV) and tungsten (IV) with N-alkylphenothiazines having the general formula M$_2$O$_4$(L)$_2$(H$_2$O)$_2$ [where M = molybdenum or tungsten and L = N-alkylphenothiazines] have been synthesised. The complexes have been characterised on the basis of analytical, molar conductance, magnetic susceptibility, spectral data, TGA and DTA. The low magnetic moments for the complexes are due to spin–spin interaction or metal–metal bonding. The interactions of these complexes with some biologically important amino acids have been studied.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Dioxobridged complexes of Mo(IV) &amp; W(IV); N-alkylphenothiazines; complexes of amino acids.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Keshavan" fname="B." isfellow="0">Keshavan, B.</author>
					<author lname="Gowda" fname="Kempe" isfellow="0">Gowda, Kempe</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Studies on the reactivity of $\textit{cis}-RuCl$_2$ fragment in Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$(TaiMe)Cl$_2$ with N,N-chelators (TaiMe = 1-methyl-2-($p$-tolylazo)imidazole). Spectral and electrochemical characterisation of the products</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0173-0182</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Dechlorination of Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$(TaiMe)Cl$_2$ (TaiMe = $p$-Me-C$_6$H$_4$ -N=NC$_3$H$_2$NN(1)-Me ({\bf 1}), 1-methyl-2-($p$-tolylazo)imidazole) has been carried out in acetone solution by Ag$^+$ and reacted with N,N -chelators to synthesise [Ru(PPh$_3$)$_2$(TaiMe)(N,N )]$^{2+}$. The complexes have been isolated as their perchlorate salts. The N,N chelators are 1-alkyl-2-(phenylazo)imidazoles (PaiX, X = Me, Et, CH$_2$Ph); 2-(arylazo)pyridines, (Raap,  $p$-R-C$_6$H$_4$–N=N–C$_5$H$_4$N; R = H, Me, Cl); 2-(arylazo)pyrimidines (Raapm,  $p$-R–C$_6$H$_4$–N=N–C$_3$N$_2$H$_2$; R = H, Me, Cl); 2,2 -bipyridine (bpy) and 1,10-phenanthroline ($o$-phen). Unsymmetrical N,N chelators may give two isomers and this is indeed observed. The ${}^1$H NMR spectral data refer to the presence of two isomers in the mixture in different proportions. With consideration of coordination pairs in the order of PPh$_3$, PPh$_3$; N,N (N refers to N(immidazole)) and N ,N (N refers to N(azo)), the complexes have been characterised as  \textit{trans-cis-cis}  and \textit{trans-trans-trans} configuration; the former predominates in the mixture. Electrochemical studies exhibit high potential Ru(III)/Ru(II) couple and quasireversible N=N reduction. Electronic spectra show high intensity ( 10$^4$) MLCT transition in the visible region (520 $\pm$ 10) nm alongwith a shoulder ( 10$^3$) in the longer wavelength region.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Ruthenium(II) mixed chelates; arylazoheterocycles; phosphine; MLCT</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Pal" fname="Sanjib" isfellow="0">Pal, Sanjib</author>
					<author lname="Sinha" fname="Chittaranjan" isfellow="0">Sinha, Chittaranjan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and characterisation of Cu(II), Ni(II), Mn(II), Zn(II) and VO(II) Schiff base complexes derived from o-phenylenediamine and acetoacetanilide</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0183-0189</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Neutral tetradentate N$_2$O$_2$ type complexes of Cu(II), Ni(II), Mn(II), Zn(II) and VO(II) have been synthesised using a Schiff base formed by the condensation of $o$-phenylenediamine with acetoacetanilide in alcohol medium. All the  complexes were characterised on the basis of their microanalytical data, molar conductance, magnetic susceptibility, IR, UV–Vis ${}^1$H NMR and ESR spectra. IR and UV–Vis spectral data suggest that all the complexes are square-planar except the Mn(II) and VO(II) chelates, which are of octahedral and square pyramidal geometry respectively. The monomeric and neutral nature of the complexes was confirmed by their magnetic susceptibility data and low conductance values. The ESR spectra of copper and vanadyl complexes in DMSO solution at 300 K and 77 K were recorded and their salient features are reported.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>$o$-Phenylenediamine; acetoacetanilide; Schiff base complexes; electron spin resonance.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Raman" fname="N." isfellow="0">Raman, N.</author>
					<author lname="Raja" fname="Y. Pitchaikani" isfellow="0">Raja, Y. Pitchaikani</author>
					<author lname="Kulandaisamy" fname="A." isfellow="0">Kulandaisamy, A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A convenient procedure for the synthesis of allyl and benzyl ethers from alcohols and phenols</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0191-0196</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Allyl and benzyl ethers of alcohols can be prepared conveniently and in high yield with allyl and benzyl bromide in the presence of solid potassium hydroxide  without use of any solvent. Phenols can be converted to allyl ethers but are inert to benzylation under above conditions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Allyl and benzyl ethers; potassium hydroxide; solvent-free conditions.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="H. Surya Prakash" isfellow="0">Rao, H. Surya Prakash</author>
					<author lname="Senthilkuma" fname="S. P." isfellow="0">Senthilkuma, S. P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Enantioselective solvent-free Robinson annulation reactions</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0197-0213</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The enantioselective cyclization of the prochiral cyclic substrates {\bf 1} to {\bf 7} and {\bf 26}, can be carried out in the neat using $S$-proline as catalyst. The substrates {\bf 18} to {\bf 22} and {\bf 27} could not be cyclized with S-proline but could be cyclized with a mixture of $S$-phenylalanine and  $d$-camphorsulphonic acid. The enantioselective cyclization of prochiral acyclic triones {\bf 45} and {\bf 47} and also the racemic tricarbonyl compounds {\bf 54} to {\bf 57} could also be carried out in the  \text{neat} using  $S$-proline as catalyst. The optically active enediones obtained in the above cyclizations could also be obtained directly from 1,3-diones or 2-hydroxymethylene cycloalkanones in a one-pot reaction with methyl vinyl ketone (MVK) and  S-proline in the absence of solvents. ${}^{13}$C NMR studies of the one-pot synthesis of {\bf S-11} and {\bf S-14} reveal that the annulations involve initial formation of an acid-base complex followed by a Michael reaction and then an enantioselective cyclization. Such enantioselective cyclizations probably occur on the surface of $S$-proline crystals.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Enantioselective annulation; cyclization;  $S$-proline;  $S$-phenylalanine; $d$-camphorsulphonic acid.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rajagopal" fname="D." isfellow="0">Rajagopal, D.</author>
					<author lname="Narayanan" fname="R." isfellow="0">Narayanan, R.</author>
					<author lname="Swaminathan" fname="S." isfellow="0">Swaminathan, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Excess molar volumes and viscosities of binary mixtures of 1,2-diethoxyethane with chloroalkanes at 298 15 K</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0215-0225</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Excess molar volumes ($V^E_m$) and viscosities ( ) of the binary mixtures of 1,2-diethoxyethane with di-, tri- and tetrachloromethane have been measured at 298 15 K and atmospheric pressure over the entire mole fraction range. The deviations in viscosities ( ln ) and excess energies of activation ( $G^{*E}$) for viscous flow have been calculated from the experimental data. The Prigogine–Flory–Patterson (PFP) model has been used to calculate $V^E_m$, and the results have been compared with experimental data. The Bloomfield and Dewan model has been used to calculate viscosity coefficients and these have also been compared with experimental data for the three mixtures. The results have been discussed in terms of dipole–dipole interactions between 1,2-diethoxyethane and chloroalkanes and their magnitudes decreasing with the dipole character of the molecules. A short comparative study with results for mixtures with polyethers and chloroalkanes is also described.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Excess volumes; viscosity deviations; binary mixtures; 1,2-diethoxyethane; chloroalkanes.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Pal" fname="Amalendu" isfellow="0">Pal, Amalendu</author>
					<author lname="Bhardwaj" fname="Rakesh Kumar" isfellow="0">Bhardwaj, Rakesh Kumar</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and characterization of submicron-sized mesoporous aluminosilicate spheres</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0227-0234</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Me soporous a luminosilicate spheres of 0 3–0 4 $\mu$m diameter, with different Si/Al ratios, have been prepared by surfactant templating. Surface area of these materials is in the 510–970 m$^2$g$^{-1}$  range and pore diameter in the 15–20 Å range.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mesoporous solids;  mesoporous aluminosilicate spheres; surfacetant templating.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Gundiah" fname="Gautam" isfellow="0">Gundiah, Gautam</author>
					<author lname="Eswaramoorthy" fname="M." isfellow="0">Eswaramoorthy, M.</author>
					<author lname="Neeraj" fname="S." isfellow="0">Neeraj, S.</author>
					<author lname="Natarajan" fname="Srinivasan" isfellow="0">Natarajan, Srinivasan</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="C. N. R." isfellow="0">Rao, C. N. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Benzyl alcohol–ammonia (1:1) cluster structure investigated by combined IR–UV double resonance spectroscopy in jet and $ab$ \textit{initio} calculation</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0235-0244</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Laser-induced fluorescence excitation and IR–UV double resonance spectroscopy have been used to determine the hydrogen-bonded structure of benzyl alcohol–ammonia (1:1) cluster in a jet-cooled molecular beam. In addition, $ab$ \textit{initio} quantum chemical calculations have been performed at HF/6-31G and HF/6-31G(d, p) levels for different ground state equilibrium structures of the cluster to correlate the calculated OH and NH frequencies and their intensities with experimental results. The broad red-shifted OH-stretching mode in the IR–UV double resonance spectrum suggests strong hydrogen bonding between the hydroxyl hydrogen and the lone pair of the ammonia nitrogen. The position and intensity distribution of the calculated NH and OH modes for the minimum-energy gauche form at HF/6-31$G$ level have better correlation with the experimental results compared to other calculated ground state equilibrium conformers. These results lead to the conclusion that the minimum energy gauche form of the cluster is populated in the jet-cooled condition.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Benzyl alcohol–ammonia cluster; IR–UV double resonance; $ab$-\textit{initio} calculations; jet-cooled molecular beams.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Guchhait" fname="Nikhil" isfellow="0">Guchhait, Nikhil</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="04" month="08" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and physiochemical studies on binuclear Cu(II) complexes derived from 2,6-[(N-phenylpiperazin-1-yl)methyl]-4-substituted phenols</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0245-0256</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Preparation of the ligands HL$^1$= 2,6-[(N-phenylpiperazin-1-yl)methyl]-$p$-ethylphenol; HL$^2$ = 2,6-[(N-phenylpiperazin-1-yl)methyl]-$p$-methoxyphenol and HL$^3$ = 2,6-[(N-phenylpiperazin-1-yl)methyl]-$p$-nitrophenol are described together with their Cu(II) complexes with different bridging units. The exogenous bridges incorporated into the complexes are: hydroxo [Cu$_2$L(OH)(H$_2$O)$_2$](ClO$_4$)$_2$.H$_2$O(L$^1$ = {\bf 1a}, L$^2$ = {\bf 1b}, $L^3$ = {\bf 1c}), acetato [Cu$_2$L(OAc)$_2$]ClO$_4$.H$_2$O (L$^1$ = {\bf 2a}, L$^2$ = {\bf 2b}, L$^3$ = {\bf 2c}) and nitrito [Cu$_2$L$^1$(NO$_2$)$_2$(H$_2$O)$_2$]ClO$_4$.H$_2$O (L$^1$ = {\bf 3a}, L$^2$ = {\bf 3b}, L$^3$ = {\bf 3c}). Complexes {\bf 1a}, {\bf 1b}, {\bf 1c} and {\bf 2a}, {\bf 2b}, {\bf 2c} contain bridging exogenous groups, while {\bf 3a}, {\bf 3b}, {\bf 3c} possess only open  -phenolate structures. Both the ligands and complexes were characterized by spectral studies. Cyclic voltammetric investigation of these complexes revealed that the reaction process involves two successive quasireversible one-electron steps at different potentials. The first reduction potential is sensitive to electronic effects of the substituents at the aromatic ring of the ligand system, shifting to positive potentials when the substituents are replaced by more electrophilic groups. EPR studies indicate very weak interaction between the two copper atoms. Various covalency parameters have been calculated.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Unsymmetrical ligands; dinuclear complexes; synthetic models; cyclic voltammetry.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Karthikeyan" fname="S." isfellow="0">Karthikeyan, S.</author>
					<author lname="Rajendiran" fname="T. M." isfellow="0">Rajendiran, T. M.</author>
					<author lname="Kannappan" fname="R." isfellow="0">Kannappan, R.</author>
					<author lname="Mahalakshmy" fname="R." isfellow="0">Mahalakshmy, R.</author>
					<author lname="Venkatesan" fname="R." isfellow="0">Venkatesan, R.</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="P. Sambasiva" isfellow="0">Rao, P. Sambasiva</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Spectral, magnetic and biological studies of 1,4-dibenzoyl-3-thiosemicarbazide complexes with some first row transition metal ions</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0257-0273</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The ligand 1,4-dibenzoyl-3-thiosemicarbazide (DBtsc) forms complexes [M(DBtsc-H)(SCN)] [M = Mn(II), Co(II) or Zn(II)], [M(DBtscH)(SCN)(H$_2$O)] [M = Ni(II) or Cu(II)], [M(DBtsc-H)Cl] [M = Co(II), Ni(II), Cu(II) or Zn(II)] and [Mn(DBtsc)Cl$_2$], which have been characterized by elemental analyses, magnetic susceptibility measurements, UV/Vis, IR, ${}^1$H and ${}^{13}$C NMR and FAB mass spectral data. Room temperature ESR spectra of the Mn(II) and Cu(II) complexes yield $&lt;g&gt;$ values, characteristic of tetrahedral and square planar complexes respectively. DBtsc and its soluble complexes have been screened against several bacteria, fungi and tumour cell lines.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>3$d$-Metal complexes; thiosemicarbazide; antitumour activity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="N. K." isfellow="0">Singh, N. K.</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="S. B." isfellow="0">Singh, S. B.</author>
					<author lname="Shrivastav" fname="A." isfellow="0">Shrivastav, A.</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="S. M." isfellow="0">Singh, S. M.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Thermal decomposition of potassium \textit{bis}-oxalatodiaquaindate(III) monohydrate</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0275-0284</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Indium (III) is precipitated with oxalic acid in the presence of potassium nitrate maintaining an overall concentration of 0 125 M in HNO$_3$. Chemical analysis of the complex salt obtained indicates the formula, K[In(C$_2$O$_4$)$_2$] 3H$_2$O. Thermal decomposition studies show that the compound decomposes first to the anhydrous potassium indium oxalate and then to the final mixture of the oxides through formation of potassium carbonate and indium (III) oxide as intermediates. Isothermal study, X-ray diffraction pattern and IR spectral data support the proposed thermal decomposition mechanism.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>\textit{bis}-oxalates; indium (III); potassium indium oxalate; thermal decomposition.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kebede" fname="T." isfellow="0">Kebede, T.</author>
					<author lname="Ramana" fname="K. V." isfellow="0">Ramana, K. V.</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="M. S. Prasada" isfellow="0">Rao, M. S. Prasada</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Design, synthesis and physico-chemical investigation of a dinuclear zinc(II) complex with a novel ‘end-off’ compartmental ligand</title>
				<feature>Inorganic</feature>
				<page>0285-0290</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A novel dinucleating pentadentate Schiff base, resulting from the condensation of 2,6-diformyl-$p$-cresol and N-methyl-indolyl-3-thiohydrazide, and its Zn complex have been prepared and characterized on the basis of elemental analysis, IR, UV-Visible, ${}^1$H NMR and ${}^{13}$C NMR studies. The ligand is acyclic and consists of a phenolate head unit, with two inbuilt azomethine shoulders and two indole thiohydrazide arms forming SNONS coordinating sites. NMR and IR spectral studies show that the ligand exists in thioketo form. Each Zn ion in the dinuclear core is in tetrahedral environment with endogenous phenolate bridging and exogenous acetate bridging. The zinc complex in DMF exhibits fluorescence.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>N-methyl-indolyl-3-thiohydrazone; compartmental ligand; Zn(II) complex of thiohydrazone; 2,6-diformyl-$p$-cresol.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Naik" fname="Anil D." isfellow="0">Naik, Anil D.</author>
					<author lname="Revankar" fname="Vidyanand K." isfellow="0">Revankar, Vidyanand K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Histidine as a catalyst in organic synthesis: A facile \textit{in situ} synthesis of  ,N-diarylnitrones</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0291-0296</page>
				<abstract>
					<p> , N-diarylnitrones were synthesized by the reduction of a mixture of nitro- and benzaldehyde derivatives with zinc dust using histidine as a catalyst.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords> , N-diarylnitrones; zinc dust; organic synthesis; histidine as catalyst.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mallesha" fname="H." isfellow="0">Mallesha, H.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="K. R. Ravi" isfellow="0">Kumar, K. R. Ravi</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="B. K. Vishu" isfellow="0">Kumar, B. K. Vishu</author>
					<author lname="Mantelingu" fname="K." isfellow="0">Mantelingu, K.</author>
					<author lname="Rangappa" fname="K. S." isfellow="0">Rangappa, K. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Theoretical study of the mechanism of proton transfer in tautomeric systems: Alloxan</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0297-0306</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Semiempirical SCF-MO studies of tautomerism in alloxan preclude the possibility of direct proton transfer in the gas phase due to the strain in the four-centred transition state, in which the proton being transferred is forced to come close to the positively charged carbon atom at the opposite corner of the four-membered ring. However, in aqueous solution, the activation barrier reduces appreciably, not only due to reduction in strain, but also due to charge separation in the transition state, which is stabilized due to ionic resonance. The N–H bond is almost broken, while the O–H bond is only partially formed in the transition state. The other stabilizing effect in aqueous solution is due to bulk solvent dielectric effects, which stabilize the transition state to a greater extent due to its higher dipole moment. Although the transition states for proton transfer to the neighbouring oxygen atoms on either side have comparable energies, as the mechanisms of proton transfer leading to the formation of the 2-hydroxy and 4-hydroxy tautomers are similar, bulk solvent effects are larger in the latter due to the higher dipole moment of the transition state. The reason is the almost complete separation of the two entities, i.e. the alloxan anion and the hydronium ion in the latter case, indicating that in this case a dissociative mechanism of the kind encountered in acid–base equilibria is operating.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Proton transfers; tautomerism; dissociative process; direct proton transfer.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kakkar" fname="R." isfellow="0">Kakkar, R.</author>
					<author lname="Sarma" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Sarma, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Katoch" fname="V." isfellow="0">Katoch, V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>An investigation of the photo-reactive and unreactive polymorphs of $o$-ethoxy cinnamic acid and of its photodimer</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0307-0324</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Detailed X-ray crystallographic investigation of the reactive - and the unreactive -polymorphs of  $o$-ethoxy cinnamic acid has been carried out along with that of the photodimer,  -truxillic acid. The molecule is quite planar in the -form, but in the  -form, the side groups deviate significantly from the plane of the benzene ring.  The carboxylic groups form normal cyclic hydrogen bonds in the  -form and near-symmetric hydrogen bonds in the  -form. The infrared spectrum of the  -form shows the characteristic features of the cyclic dimer, but that of the  -form is entirely different, marked by the absence of the O–H stretching band in the 3000 cm$^{-1}$ region. Charge density analysis throws some light on the structure and reactivity of the molecule in the two forms. The near-symmetric hydrogen bond in the  -form is ionic and appears to restrict conjugation by way of distorting the molecule. This unusual feature keeps the cinnamoyl double bonds away from each other, rendering it photochemically unreactive. In the  -form, however, the double bonds have a closer approach. The cyclobutyl ring of the photodimer consists of weak single bonds, with the new pair being slightly longer</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Photoreactivity; polymorphism; ethoxy cinnamic acid; electronic charge density; X-ray structure.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Gopalan" fname="R. Srinivasa" isfellow="0">Gopalan, R. Srinivasa</author>
					<author lname="Kulkarni" fname="G. U." isfellow="0">Kulkarni. G. U.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics of oxidation of acidic amino acids by sodium N-bromobenzenesulphonamide in acid medium: A mechanistic approach</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0325-0332</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Kinetics of oxidation of acidic amino acids (glutamic acid (Glu) and aspartic acid (Asp)) by sodium N-bromobenzenesulphonamide (bromamine-B or BAB) has been carried out in aqueous HClO$_4$ medium at 30$^\circ$C. The rate shows firstorder dependence each on [BAB]$_o$ and [amino acid]$_o$ and inverse first-order on [H$^+$]. At [H$^+$] $&gt;$ 0 60 mol dm$^{-3}$, the rate levelled off indicating zero-order dependence on [H$^+$] and, under these conditions, the rate has fractional order dependence on [amino acid]. Succinic and malonic acids have been identified as the products. Variation of ionic strength and addition of the reaction product benzenesulphonamide or halide ions had no significant effect on the reaction rate. There is positive effect of dielectric constant of the solvent. Proton inventory studies in H$_2$O–D$_2$O mixtures showed the involvement of a single exchangeable proton of the OH$^-$ ion in the transition state. Kinetic investigations have revealed that the order of reactivity is Asp $&gt;$ Glu. The rate laws proposed and derived in agreement with experimental results are discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Acidic amino acids; bromamine-B; oxidation kinetics, acid medium.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="Puttaswamy" isfellow="0">Puttaswamy</author>
					<author lname="Vaz" fname="Nirmala" isfellow="0">Vaz, Nirmala</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>TEA CO$_2$ laser-induced reaction of CH$_3$NO$_2$ with CF$_2$HCl: A mechanistic study</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0333-0342</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Dissociation of nitromethane has been observed when a mixture of CF$_2$HCl and CH$_3$NO$_2$ is irradiated using pulsed TEA CO$_2$ laser at 9R (24) line (1081 cm$^{-1}$), which is strongly absorbed by CF$_2$HCl but not by CH$_3$NO$_2$. Under low laser fluence conditions, only nitromethane dissociates, whereas at high fluence CF$_2$HCl also undergoes dissociation, showing that dissociation occurs via the vibrational energy transfer processes from the TEA CO$_2$ laser-excited CF$_2$HCl to CH$_3$NO$_2$. Time-resolved infrared fluorescence from vibrationally excited CF$_2$HCl and CH$_3$NO$_2$ molecules as well as UV absorption of CF$_2$ radicals are carried out to elucidate the dynamics of excitation/dissociation and the chemical reactions of the dissociation products.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Nitromethane; excitation dissociation; energy transfer; infrared fluorescence; CF$_2$ radicals.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Vatsa" fname="Rajesh K." isfellow="0">Vatsa, Rajesh K.</author>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="Sisir K." isfellow="0">Sarkar, Sisir K.</author>
					<author lname="Mittal" fname="Jai P." isfellow="0">Mittal, Jai P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Reduction of CO$_2$ by nickel (II) macrocycle catalyst at HMDE</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0343-0350</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>With the aim of finding a suitable electrocatalyst for the efficient reduction of carbon dioxide, the electrochemistry of nickel (II) complex of 1,3,6,9,11,14-hexaazatricyclo [12 2 1 1] octadecane was studied using cyclic voltammetry (CV) and controlled-potential electrolysis (CPE) techniques in the presence and absence of CO$_2$ in 100$&#37;$ H$_2$O, CH$_3$CN–H$_2$O mixtures (20–100$&#37;$) and DMF–H$_2$O (70–100$&#37;$) mixtures. The efficiency of this process is determined using the coulometry technique. CO is the major product in the  gaseous phase and HCOOH the sole product formed in the solution phase.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Nickel (II) azamacrocycle; electrocatalytic reduction of CO$_2$; electrochemical reduction.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Scibioh" fname="M. Aulice" isfellow="0">Scibioh, M. Aulice</author>
					<author lname="Ragini" fname="P. V." isfellow="0">Ragini, P. V.</author>
					<author lname="Rani" fname="S." isfellow="0">Rani, S.</author>
					<author lname="Vijayaraghavan" fname="V. R." isfellow="0">Vijayaraghavan, V. R.</author>
					<author lname="Viswanathan" fname="B." isfellow="0">Viswanathan, B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Mechanism of oxidation of L-methionine by iron(III)-1,10-phenanthroline complex – A kinetic study</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0351-0359</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Kinetics and mechanism of oxidation of  L-methionine by iron(III)–1, 10-phenanthroline complex have been studied in perchloric acid medium. The reaction is first order each in iron(III) and methionine. Increase in [phenanthroline] increases the rate while increase in [HClO$_4$] decreases it. While the reactive species of the substrate is the zwitterionic form, that of the oxidant is [Fe(phen)$_2$(H$_2$O)$_2$]$^{3+}$. The proposed mechanism leads to the rate law $$\dfrac{d[Fe(phen)^{2+}_3]}{dt} = \dfrac{k_2 K_4 K_3 K^2_2 [Fe^{III}] [\text{phen}^2] [\text{Met}]}{(1+K_1 [H^+]) ([H^+]^2 + K_4 K_3 K^2_2[\text{phen}]^2)}.$$</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oxidation of methionine; iron(III)–phenanthroline complex.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Vani" fname="P." isfellow="0">Vani, P.</author>
					<author lname="Kishore" fname="K. Krishna" isfellow="0">Kishore, K. Krishna</author>
					<author lname="Rambabu" fname="R." isfellow="0">Rambabu, R.</author>
					<author lname="Dikshitulu" fname="L. S. A." isfellow="0">Dikshitulu, L. S. A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="05-06" month="10-12" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Foreword &#8212; Solid State and Materials Chemistry</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0361-0361</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Gopalakrishnan" fname="J." isfellow="0">Gopalakrishnan, J.</author>
					<author lname="Seshadri" fname="Ram" isfellow="0">Seshadri, Ram</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Basic building units, self-assembly and crystallization in the formation of complex inorganic open architectures</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0363-0374</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Careful investigations of open-framework metal phosphates reveal that the formation of these complex architectures is likely to involve a process wherein one-dimensional ladders or chains, and possibly zero-dimens ional  monomers, transform to higher dimensional structures. The one-dimensional ladder appears to be the primary building unit of these structures. At one stage of the building-up process, spontaneous self-assembly of a low-dimensional structure such as the ladder seems to occur, followed by crys tallization of a two- or  three-dimensional structure.  Accordingly, many of the higher dimensional structures retain the structural features of the 1D structure, indicating the occurrence of self-assembly. These findings mark the beginnings of our understan ding of complex supramolecular inorganic materials.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Complex inorganic open architectures; open-framework metal phosphates; one-dimensional ladder; supramolecular inorganic materials</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="C. N. R." isfellow="0">Rao, C. N. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Nanotubes and nanowires</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0375-0392</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Synthesis and characterization of nanotubes and nanowires constitute an important part of nanoscience  since these materials are essential bui lding units for several devices. We have prepared aligned  carbon nanotube bundles and Y-junction nanotubes by the pyrolysis of appropriate organic precursors. The aligned bundles are useful for field  emission display while the Y-junction nanotubes are likely to be useful as nanochips since they exhibit diode properties at the junction. By making use of carbon nanotubes, nanowires of metals, metal oxides and GaN have be en obt a ined. Both the oxide and GaN nanowires are single crystalline. Gold nanowires exhibit plasmon bands varying markedly with the aspect ratio. GaN nanowires show excellent photoluminescence characteristics. It has been possible to synthesise nanotubes and nanowires of metal chalcogenides by employing different strategies.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Nanotubes; nanowires; Y-junction; GaN; metal chal cogenides; metal oxides.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="C. N. R." isfellow="0">Rao, C. N. R.</author>
					<author lname="Govindaraj" fname="A." isfellow="0">Govindaraj, A.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Relaxation in binary mixtures: Non-ideality, heterogeneity and re-entrance</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0393-0413</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Binary mixtures show many kinds of fascinating dynamical behaviour which has eluded microscopic description till very recently. In this work we show that much of the anomalous behaviour can be explained by building suitable models and  carrying out theoretical and simulation studies. Specifically, three well-known problems have been addressed here. (a) Non-ideality in composition dependence of viscosity, (b) re-entrant behaviour of orientational relaxation, and (c) heterogeneity in supercooled binary mixtures. The physical origin of the dynamical behaviour of binary mixtures can be understood in terms of composition fluctuation, a study of which has also been presented in this paper.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Binary mixtures; non-ideality; orientational relaxation; composition fluctuation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mukherjee" fname="A." isfellow="0">Mukherjee, A.</author>
					<author lname="Srinivas" fname="G." isfellow="0">Srinivas, G.</author>
					<author lname="Bhattacharyya" fname="S." isfellow="0">Bhattacharyya, S.</author>
					<author lname="Bagchi" fname="B." isfellow="0">Bagchi, B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Electron–electron interactions in the chemical bond: ``1/3” Effect in the bond length of hydrogen molecule</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0415-0425</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The  prominent  ``1/3”  effect  observed in the Hall effect plateaus of twodimensional electron gas (2DEG) systems has been postulated to indicating 1/3 fractional charge quasiparticle excitations arising from electron–electron interactions. Tunneling shot-noise experiments on 2DEF exhibiting fractional quantum Hall effect (FQHE) shows evidence for tunnelling of particles with $e$ and  $e/3$ charges for a constant band mass. A "1/3” effect in the hydrogen molecule is seen in as much as its internuclear distance, $d_{H-H} = D^- + D^+,$ with $|D^+/D^-| = 1/3$. This is examined in terms of electron–electron interactions involving electron- and hole quasiparticles, ($e^-$) and ($h^+$), equivalent to those observed in FQHE shot-noise experiments. The ($e/m$) ratio of the ($e^-$) and ($h^+$) quasiparticles is kept at 1: –3. Instead of a 2DEG, these particles are treated as being in flat Bohr orbits. A treatment in the language of charge-flux tube composites for the hydrogen atom as well as the hydrogen molecule is attempted. Such  treatment  gives important insights into changes in chemical potential and bond energy on crossing a phase boundary during the atom-bond transition as well as on models for FQHE itself.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Electron–electron interactions; quantum Hall effect; hydrogen-molecule bond length.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ganguly" fname="P." isfellow="0">Ganguly, P.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>New lithium-ion conducting perovskite oxides related to (Li, La)TiO$_3$</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>04270-0433</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We describe the synthesis and lithium-ion conductivity of new perovskite-related oxides of the formulas, LiCa$_{1 65}$ $\Box_{0 \; 35}$ Ti$_{1 \;3}$ B$_{1\; 7}$ O$_9$ (B =Nb, Ta) ({\bf I, II}), LiSr$_2$Ti$_{2\; 5}$ W$_{0\;5}$ O$_9$ ({\bf III}) and LiSr$_{1 \;65} $\Box_{0\; 35}$Ti$_{2\; 15}$W$_{0\; 85}$O$_9$ ({\bf IV}). Oxides {\bf I}  and {\bf II} crystallize in or thorhombic (GdFeO$_3$-type) structure, while oxides {\bf III} and {\bf IV} possess cubic symmetry. All of them exhibit significant lithium-ion conduction at high temperatures, the highest conductivity of $\sim$ $10^{-2}$S/cm at 800$^\circ$C among the oxides is exhibited by the composition {\bf IV}. The results are discussed in the light of previous work on lithium-ion conducting perovskite oxides containing  $d^0$ cations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Lithium ion conductors; lithium–lanthanum perovskites; lithium–lanthanum titanates.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sebastian" fname="Litty" isfellow="0">Sebastian, Litty</author>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Shukla, A. K.</author>
					<author lname="Gopalakrishnan" fname="J." isfellow="0">Gopalakrishnan, J.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>\textit{Ab initio} structure determination via powder X-ray diffraction</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0435-0444</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Structure determination by powder X-ray diffraction data has gone through a recent surge since it has become important to get to the structural information of materials which do not yield good quality single crystals. Although the method of structure completion when once the starting model is provided is facile through the Rietveld refinement technique, the structure solution $ab$ \textit{initio} os still not push-button technology. In this article a survey of the recent development in this area is provided with an illustration of the structure determination of $-NaBi$_3$V$_2$O$_{10}$.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Structure determination; powder X-day diffraction; pattern decomposition; structure refinements.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Porob" fname="Digamber G." isfellow="0">Porob, Digamber G.</author>
					<author lname="Row" fname="T. N. Guru" isfellow="0">Row, T. N. Guru</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Epitaxial oxide thin films by pulsed laser deposition: Retrospect and prospect</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0445-0458</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Pulsed laser deposition (PLD) is a unique method to obtain epitaxial multi-component oxide films. Highly stoichiometric, nearly single crystal-like materials in the form of films can be made by PLD. Oxides which are synthesized at  high oxygen pressure  can be made into films at low oxygen partial pressure. Epitaxial thin films of high  $T_c$ cuprates, metallic, ferroelectric, ferromagnetic, dielectric oxides, super conduc tor–metal–superconductor Josephson junctions and oxide superlattices have been made by PLD. In this article, an overview of preparation, characterization and properties of epitaxial oxide films and their applications are presented. Future prospects of the method for fabricating epitaxial films of transition metal nitrides, chalcogenides, carbides and borides are discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Pulsed laser deposition; epitaxial films; superconducting oxide films; metallic oxides; ferromagnetic oxide films; superlattices.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Hegde" fname="M. S." isfellow="0">Hegde, M. S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Quantum phenomena in magnetic nano clusters</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0459-0486</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>One of the fascinating fields of study in magnetism in recent years has been the study of quantum phenomena in nanosystems. While semiconductor structures have provided paradigms of nanosystems from the stand point of electronic phenomena,  the synthesis of high nuclearity transition metal complexes have provided examples of nano magnets. The range and diversity of the properties exhibited by these systems rivals its electronic counterparts. Qualitative understanding of these phenomena requires only a knowledge of basic physics, but quantitative study throws up many challenges that are similar to those encountered in the study of correlated electronic systems. In this article, a brief overview of the current trends in this area are highlighted and some of the efforts of our group in developing a quantitative understanding of this field are outlined.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Quantum phenomena in magnetic systems; magnetic nano clusters; molecular magnets; nanoscale materials and structures.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Raghu" fname="C." isfellow="0">Raghu, C.</author>
					<author lname="Rudra" fname="Indranil" isfellow="0">Rudra, Indranil</author>
					<author lname="Sen" fname="Diptiman" isfellow="0">Sen, Diptiman</author>
					<author lname="Ramasesha" fname="S." isfellow="0">Ramasesha S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Visualizing lone pairs in compounds containing heavier congeners of the carbon and nitrogen group elements</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0487-0496</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this mini-review, I discuss some recent work on the stereochemistry and bonding of lone pairs of electrons in divalent compounds of the heavier carbon group elements  (Sn$^{II}$, Pb$^{II}$) and in trivalent compounds of the heavier nitrogen group elements (Bi$^{III}$). Recently developed methods that permit the real-space visualization of bonding patterns on the basis of density functional calculations of electronic  structure, reveal details of the nature of selectron lone pairs in compounds of the heavier main group elements – their stereochemistry and their inertness (or lack thereof). An examination of  tetragonal $P4/nmm$ SnO, $\alpha$-PbO  and BiOF, and cubic  $Fm3m$ PbS provides a segue into perovskite phases of technological significance, including ferroelectric PbTiO$_3$ and antiferroelectric/piezoelectric PbZrO$_3$, in both of which the lone  pairs on Pb atoms play a pivotal rôle.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Main group elements; lone pairs; stereochemistry; ferroelectricity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Seshadri" fname="Ram" isfellow="0">Seshadri, Ram</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0497-0514</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Structures of NASICON glasses of the general formula AB$_2$(PO$_4$)$_3$, where A = Li, Na or K and B = Fe, Ga, Ti, V or Nb, have been investigated using vibrational (IR and Raman) spectroscopies. Phosphate species appear to establish an equilibrium via a disproportionation reaction involving a dynamical bond-switching mechanism where both charge and bonds are conserved. B ions in the system acquire different coordinations to oxygens. Alkali ions cause absorptions due to cage vibrations. All the observed spectroscopic features are consistent with speciation involving disproportionation reactions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>NASICON glasses; dynamical bond-switching mechanism; disproportiona tion reactions.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="K. J." isfellow="0">Rao, K. J.</author>
					<author lname="Sobha" fname="K. C." isfellow="0">Sobha, K. C.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="Sundeep" isfellow="0">Kumar, Sundeep</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Properties of a new magnetic material: Sr$_2$FeMoO$_6$</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0515-0525</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Recently, there have been a large number of investigations of the physical properties of Sr$_2$FeMoO$_6$ and related compounds, in view of their significant negative magnetoresistive property at room  temperature and in low applied magnetic fields. We review these investigations, detailing the microscopic mechanism controlling the electronic and magnetic properties of this system.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Room temperature colossal magnetoresistance; order–disorder effects; electronic and magnetic structures.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sarma" fname="D. D." isfellow="0">Sarma, D. D.</author>
					<author lname="Ray" fname="Sugata" isfellow="0">Ray, Sugata</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>AC impedance behaviour and state-of-charge dependence of Zr$_{0 \; 5}$Ti$_{0 \;5}$V$_{0\; 6}$Cr$_{0 \;2}$Ni$_{1 \;2}$ metal-hydride electrodes</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0527-0537</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Metal-hydride electrodes made of an AB$_2$ alloy of the composition Zr$_{0 \cdot 5}$Ti$_{0\cdot 5}$V$_{0\cdot 6}$Cr$_{0 \cdot 2}$Ni$_{1 \cdot 2}$ are studied for AC impedance behaviour at several of their state-of-charge values. Impedance data at any state-of-charge comprise two RC-time constants and accordingly are analysed by using a nonlinear-least-square-fitting procedure. Resistance of the electrode and frequency maximum ($f^\ast$) of the lowfrequency semicircle are found useful for predicting state-of-charge of the metalhydride electrodes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Hydrogen-storage alloy; metal-hydride electrode; AC impedance; AB$_2$ alloys; state-of-charge.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Munichandraiah" fname="N." isfellow="0">Munichandraiah, N.</author>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Shukla, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Hydrocarbon chain conformation in an intercalated surfactant monolayer and bilayer</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0539-0558</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Cetyl trimethyl ammonium (CTA) ions have been confined within galleries of layered CdPS$_3$ at two different grafting densities. Low grafting densities are obtained on direct intercalation of CTA ions into CdPS$_3$ to give Cd$_{0 \cdot 93}$PS$_3$(CTA)$_{0 \cdot 14}$. Intercalation occurs with a lattice expansion of $4\codt 8$ Å with the interlamellar surfactant ion lying flat forming a monolayer. Intercalation at higher grafting densities was effected by a two-step ion-exchange process to give Cd$_{0 \cdot 83}$PS$_3$(CTA)$_{0 \cdot 34}$, with a lattice expansion of $26 \cdot 5$ Å. At higher grafting densities the interlamellar surfactant ions adopt a tilted bilayer structure. ${}^{13}$C NMR and orientation-dependent IR vibrational spectroscopy on single crystals have been used to probe the conformation and orientation of the methylene ‘tail’ of the intercalated surfactant in the two phases. In the monolayer phase, the confined methylene chain adopts an essentially all-trans conformation with most of the trans chain aligned parallel to the gallery walls. On lowering the temperature, molecular plane aligns parallel, so that the methylene chain lies flat, rigid and aligned to the confining surface. In the bilayer phase, most bonds in the methylene chain are in trans conformation. It is possible to identify specific conformational sequences containing a gauche bond, in the interior and termini of the intercalated methylene. These high energy conformers disappear on cooling leaving all fifteen methylene units of the intercalated cetyl trimethyl ammonium ion in trans conformational registry at 40 K.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Intercalation; layered compound; surfactant assembly; conformation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Venkataraman" fname="N. V." isfellow="0">Venkataraman, N. V.</author>
					<author lname="Vasudevan" fname="S." isfellow="0">Vasudevan, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Diffusion of hydrocarbons in confined media: Translational and rotational motion</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Diffusion of monatomic guest species within confined media has been understood to a good degree due to investigations carried out during the past decade and a half. Most guest species that are of industrial relevance are actually polyatomics such as, for example, hydrocarbons in zeolites. We attempt to investigate the influence of non-spherical nature of guest species on diffusion. Recent molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of motion of methane in NaCaA and NaY, benzene in NaY and one-dimensional channels AlPO$_4$-5, VPI-5 and carbon nanotube indicate interesting insights into the influence of the host on rotational degrees of freedom and rientational properties. It is shown that benzene in one-dimensional channels where the levitation parameter is near unity exhibits translational motion opposite to what is expected on the basis of molecular anisotropy. Rotational motion of benzene also possesses rotational diffusivities around C$_6$ and $C_2$ axes opposite to what is expected on the basis of molecular geometry. Methane shows orientational preference for $2 +2$ or $1 + 3$ depending on the magnitude of the levitation parameter.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Diffusion hydrocarbons; orientational preference; translational–orientational coupling; molecular dynamics.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bhide" fname="S. Y." isfellow="0">Bhide, S. Y.</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="A. V. Anil" isfellow="0">Kumar, A. V. Anil</author>
					<author lname="Yashonath" fname="S." isfellow="0">Yashonath, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Computer simulation study of water using a fluctuating charge model</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0579-0590</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Hydrogen bonding in small water clusters is studied through computer simulation methods using a sophisticated, empirical model of interaction developed by Rick \textit{et al} (S W Rick, S J Stuart and B J Berne 1994 \textit{J. Chem. Phys.} {\bf 101} 6141) and others. The model allows for the charges on the interacting sites to fluctuate as a function of time, depending on their local environment. The charge flow is driven by the difference in the electronegativity of the atoms within the water molecule, thus effectively mimicking the effects of polarization of the charge density. The potential model is thus transferable across all phases of water. Using this model, we have obtained the minimum energy structures of water clusters up to a size of ten. The cluster structures agree well with experimental data. In addition, we are able to distinctly identify the hydrogens that form hydrogen bonds based on their charges alone, a feature that is not possible in simulations using fixed charge models. We have also studied the structure of liquid water at ambient conditions using this fluctuating charge model.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Water; clusters; fluctuating charge; electronegativity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Krishnan" fname="M." isfellow="0">Krishnan, M.</author>
					<author lname="Verma" fname="A." isfellow="0">Verma, A.</author>
					<author lname="Balasubramanian" fname="S." isfellow="0">Balasubramanian, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effects of hydrogen-bond environment on single particle and pair dynamics in liquid water</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0591-0601</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have performed molecular dynamics simulations of liquid water at 298 and 258 K to investigate the effects of hydrogen-bond environment on various single-particle and pair dynamical properties of water molecules at ambient and supercooled conditions. The water molecules are modelled by the extended simple point charge (SPC/E) model. We first calculate the distribution of hydrogen-bond environment in liquid water at both temperatures and then investigate how the selfdiffusion and orientational relaxation of a single water molecule and also the relative diffusion and relaxation of the hydrogen-bond of a water pair depend on the nature of the hydrogen-bond environment of the tagged molecules. We find that the various dynamical quantities depend significantly on the hydrogen-bond environment, especially at the supercooled temperature. The present study provides a molecular-level insight into the dynamics of liquid water under ambient and supercooled conditions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Water; hydrogen-bonds; diffusion; orientational relaxation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chandra" fname="Amalendu" isfellow="0">Chandra, Amalendu</author>
					<author lname="Chowdhuri" fname="Snehasis" isfellow="0">Chowdhuri, Snehasis</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Phase analysis and dielectric properties of oxides obtained in the MgO–(1$–x$)Nb$_2$O$_5–(x)$Ta$_2$O$_5$ system</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0603-0610</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>MgNb$_{2–x}$Ta$_x$O$_6$ ($0 \leq x \leq 2$) phases can be obtained as the major phase (75 to 90$&#37;$) by solid state reactions starting from oxides. These oxides crystallize in the orthorhombic columbite structure till $x = 1 \cdot 75$ and the tetragonal trirutile structure for MgTa$_2$O$_6$ ($x = 2 \cdot 0$). For all the compositions there exist secondary phases like Nb$_2$O$_5$ or Ta$_2$O$_5$ in addition to the major AB$_2$O$_6$ phase. Sintered disks (1200$\circ$C) show dielectric constants varying between 14$\cdot$8 and 16$\cdot$0 for the entire range of composition at a frequency of 500 kHz. The dielectric loss is nearly constant around 0$\cdot$025 to 0$\cdot$03 between $0 \leq x \leq 1$ but increases to 0$\cdot$17 for the MgTa$_2$O$_6$ phase ($x = 2\cdot 0$). Scanning electron micrographs reveal a gradual decrease in grain size with increase in Ta concentration with a size of 3 micron for the $x=0$ composition (sintered at 1200$^\circ$C) while the $x = 2$ phase shows a grain size of approximately 0$\cdot$5 microns. The microwave dielectric constant at $\sim$14 GHz is found to be 20$\cdot$9 for the $x = 0$ composition and $17 \cdot 7$ for the $x = 2$ composition.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Ceramics; electronic materials; oxides.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Thirumalm" fname="M." isfellow="0">Thirumalm, M.</author>
					<author lname="Ganguli" fname="A. K." isfellow="0">Ganguli, A. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Self-assembling bilayers of palladiumthiolates in organic media</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0611-0619</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Alkylthiolates of palladium forming a homologous series (butyl to octadecyl) have been prepared and characterized using X-ray diffraction and STM. The thiolates adopt an unusual bilayered lamellar structure, whose thickness is governed by the length of the alkyl chain. These mesophases melt in the temperature range, 60$^\circ$ to 100$\circ$C, with the melting point increasing linearly with the thiol chain length. There is evidence to suggest that the alkyl chains are orientationally disordered especially prior to melting.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Self-assembling bilayers; palladiumthiolates; lamellar structures.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Thomas" fname="P. John" isfellow="0">Thomas, P. John</author>
					<author lname="Lavanya" fname="A." isfellow="0">, A.</author>
					<author lname="Sabareesh" fname="V." isfellow="0">Sabareesh, V.</author>
					<author lname="Kulkarni" fname="G. U." isfellow="0">Kulkarni, G. U.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Morpholinium intercalated vanadophosphates</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The present paper reports the formation of two morpholinium (Morp) incorporated solids precipitated from aqueous vanadate solution acidifed with phosphoric acid: a zero-dimensional, mixed-valent phosphovanadate cluster containing solid, [Morp]$_6$[P$^V$O$_4$  $\subset$ V$^{IV}_3$V$^V_{11}$O$_{32}$(OH)$_6$].2H$_2$O, {\bf 1} and a two-dimensional layered solid, [Morp]$_{0 \cdot 23}$[V$^{IV,V}$OPO$_4$]$1 \cdot 1$H$_2$O, {\bf 2}. While {\bf 2} precipitates out from the reaction mixture in the presence of a reducing agent hydrazine hydrate, {\bf 1} crystallises out in its absence.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Intercalation; single crystal structure; vanadophosphate; morpholinium; vanadyl phosphate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="Sanjeev" isfellow="0">Sharma, Sanjeev</author>
					<author lname="Ramanan" fname="A." isfellow="0">Ramanan, A.</author>
					<author lname="Vittal" fname="J. J." isfellow="0">Vittal, J. J.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and properties of MoSi$_2$ based engineering ceramics</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0633-0649</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Molybdenum disilicide is a high temperature structural ceramic with many attractive properties for engineering applications. Foremost amongst these is its stability in corrosive atmospheres up to about 1600$^\circ$C. However, there are a few undesirable properties that need to be addressed before it can become a viable material in high temperature applications. Since MoSi$_2$ forms thermodynamically stable composites with both metals and ceramics, many reinforcing materials are incorporated into the matrix to improve the fracture toughness and creep properties. The low temperature oxidation can be controlled by making high density ($&gt;$ 95&#37; of theoretical density) compacts. This article summarizes the important attempts that are made in improving the properties of molybdenum disilicide-based ceramics by the reinforcement with other materials.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Molybdenum disilicide; high temperature applications; reactive infiltration.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Tantri" fname="P. Srikari" isfellow="0">Tantri, P. Srikari</author>
					<author lname="Bhattacharya" fname="Anup K." isfellow="0">Bhattacharya, Anup K.</author>
					<author lname="Ramasesha" fname="Sheela K." isfellow="0">Ramasesha, Sheela K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>XRD and UV-Vis diffuse reflectance analysis of CeO$_2$–ZrO$_2$ solid solutions synthesized by combustion method</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0651-0658</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A series of ceria-incorporated zirconia (Ce$_{1-x}$Zr$_x$O$_2$, $x = 0$ to 1) solid solutions were prepared by employing the solution combustion synthesis route. The products were characterized by XRD and UV-Vis-NIR diffuse reflectance spectroscopy. The materials are crystalline in nature and the lattice parameters of the solid solution series follow Vegard’s law. Diffuse reflectance spectra of the solid solutions in the UV region show two intense bands at 250 and 297 nm which are assigned respectively to Ce$^{3+} \leftarrow$ O$^{2-}$ and Ce$^{4+} \leftarrow $ O$^{2-}$ charge transfer transitions. The two vibrational bands in 6960 cm$^{-1}$ and 5168 cm$^{-1}$ in the NIR region indicate the presence of surface hydroxyl groups on these materials.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Ce$_{1-x}Zr$_x$O$_2$ solid solutions; combustion synthesis; diffuse reflectance spectroscopy (DRS).</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="G. Ranga" isfellow="0">Rao, G. Ranga</author>
					<author lname="Sahu" fname="H. Ranjan" isfellow="0">Sahu, H. Ranjan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Applications of self-assembled monolayers in materials chemistry</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0659-0670</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Self-assembly provides a simple route to organise suitable organic molecules on noble metal and selected nanocluster surfaces by using monolayers of long chain organic molecules with various functionalities like –SH, –COOH, –NH$_2$, silanes etc. These surfaces can be effectively used to build-up interesting nano level architectures. Flexibility with respect to the terminal functionalities of the organic molecules allows the control of the hydrophobicity or hydrophilicity of metal surface, while the selection of length scale can be used to tune the distant-dependent electron transfer behaviour. Organo-inorganic materials tailored in this fashion are extremely important in nanotechnology to construct nanoelctronic devices, sensor arrays, supercapacitors, catalysts, rechargeable power sources etc. by virtue of their size and shape-dependent electrical, optical or magnetic properties. The interesting applications of monolayers and monolayer-protected clusters in materials chemistry are discussed using recent examples of size and shape control of the properties of several metallic and semiconducting nanoparticles. The potential benefits of using these nanostructured systems for molecular electronic components are illustrated using Au and Ag nanoclusters with suitable bifunctional SAMs.</p> 
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Self-assembled monolayer; monolayer protected clusters; molecular electronics; bio-mimetic synthesis; superlattice.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chaki" fname="Nirmalya K." isfellow="0">Chaki, Nirmalya K.</author>
					<author lname="Aslam" fname="M." isfellow="0">Aslam, M.</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="Jadab" isfellow="0">Sharma, Jadab</author>
					<author lname="Vijayamohanan" fname="K." isfellow="0">Vijayamohanan, K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>The many ways of making anionic clays</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0671-0680</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Together with hydrotalcite-like layered double hydroxides, bivalent and trivalent metal hydroxides and their hydroxy salts are actually anionic clays consisting of positively charged hydroxide layers with anions intercalated in the interlayer region. The anionic clays exhibit anion sorption, anion diffusion and exchange properties together with surface basicity making them materials of importance for many modern applications. In this article, we discuss many different ways of making anionic clays and compare and contrast the rich diversity of this class of materials with the better-known cationic clays.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Anionic clays; hydrotalcite; layered double hydroxides.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rajamathi" fname="Michael" isfellow="0">Rajamathi, Michael</author>
					<author lname="Thomas" fname="Grace S." isfellow="0">Thomas, Grace S.</author>
					<author lname="Kamath" fname="P. Vishnu" isfellow="0">Kamath, P. Vishnu</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>M$_4$C$_9^+$(M = Ti, V): New gas phase clusters</title>
				<feature>Solid State and Materials Chemistry</feature>
				<page>0681-0688</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>New metal–carbon clusters, M$_4$C$_9^+$ (M = Ti, V), generated using a combined thermal arc discharge evaporation set-up, have been studied with quadrupole mass spectrometry. Reactivities of these clusters have been investigated by means of association reactions with H$_2$O. Metal–carbon clusters of other compositions have also been studied. We speculate on the mechanism of formation of larger metal–carbon clusters.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Metal–carbon clusters; gas phase clusters.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Selvan" fname="R." isfellow="0">Selvan, R.</author>
					<author lname="Gowrishankar" fname="L." isfellow="0">Gowrishankar, L.</author>
					<author lname="Pradeep" fname="T." isfellow="0">Pradeep, T.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
	<volume vnum="114">
		<issue inum="01" month="02" year="2002">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Coenzyme B$_{12}$ model studies: Equilibrium constants for the $p$Hdependent axial ligation of benzyl(aquo)cobaloxime by various N- and S-donor ligands</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical </feature>
				<page>0001-0010</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Equilibria of the axial ligation of benzyl(aquo)cobaloximes by imidazole, 1-methyl imidazole, histidine, histamine, glycine, ethyl glycine ester, thiourea and urea have been spectrophotometrically measured in aqueous solutions of ionic strength $1\cdot 0$ M (KCl) at 25$^\circ$C as a function of $p$H. The equilibrium constants are in the order CN$^- &gt;$ 1-methyl imidazole $&gt;$ imidazole $&gt;$ histidine $&gt;$ histamine $&gt;$glycine $&gt;$ethyl glycine ester $&gt;$ thiourea $&gt;$ urea. The order of stability of benzyl(ligand)cobaloxime is explained based on the basicity of the ligand, Co(III) $\rightarrow L d\pi–p\pi$ back bonding and soft–soft and soft–hard interaction. Imidazole, substituted imidazoles, histidine and histamine form more stable complexes than glycine, ethyl glycine ester in contrast to the basicity of the ligands. Benzyl(ligand)cobaloximes were isolated and characterized by elemental analysis, IR and ${}^1$H NMR spectra.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Benzyl(aquo)cobaloxime; dimethylglyoxime; soft–soft interaction; $d\pi–p\pi$ back bonding; imidazole; primary amine.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Reddy" fname="D. Sudarshan" isfellow="0">Reddy, D. Sudarshan</author>
					<author lname="Reddy" fname="N. Ravi Kumar" isfellow="0">Reddy, N. Ravi Kumar</author>
					<author lname="Sridhar" fname="V." isfellow="0">Sridhar, V.</author>
					<author lname="Satyanarayana" fname="S." isfellow="0">Satyanarayana, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Equilibria and kinetics for $p$H-dependent axial ligation of alkyl(aquo) cobaloximes with aromatic and aliphatic N-donor ligands</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical </feature>
				<page>0011-0023</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Equilibria and kinetics of the reaction of bromomethyl(aquo) cobaloxime with histamine, histidine, glycine and ethyl glycine ester and iodomethyl(aquo) cobaloxime with cyanide, imidazole and substituted imidazoles were studied as a function of $p$H at 25$\circ$C, $1 \cdot 0$ M ionic strength (KCl) by spectrophotometry technique. The rate of substitution of H$_2$O varies with the $pKa$ of the incoming ligand, thus establishing the existence of nucleophilic participation of the ligand in the transition state. Dissociation kinetic reactions were also studied as a function of $p$H. Binding and kinetic data were interpreted based on the basicity, steric crowd of the entering ligand and HSAB principle. To compare the rate constants of the entering ligands $p$H independent second-order rate constants were calculated.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Alkylcobaloximes; histamine; histidine; imidazoles; equilibrium constants.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sridhar" fname="V." isfellow="0">Sridhar, V.</author>
					<author lname="Reddy" fname="D. Sudarshan" isfellow="0">Reddy, D. Sudarshan</author>
					<author lname="Reddy" fname="N. Ravikumar" isfellow="0">Reddy, N. Ravikumar</author>
					<author lname="Satyanarayana" fname="S." isfellow="0">Satyanarayana, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical </feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Saravanan" fname="K." isfellow="0">Saravanan, K.</author>
					<author lname="Govindarajan" fname="S." isfellow="0">Govindarajan, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Dipicolinate complexes of main group metals with hydraziniumcation</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical </feature>
				<page>0025-0036</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Some new coordination complexes of hydrazinium main group metal dipicolinate hydrates of formulae (N$_2$H$_5$)2M(dip)$_2.n$H$_2$O (where, M = Ca, Sr, Ba or Pb and $n = 0, 2, 4$ and 3 respectively and dip = dipicolinate), N$_2$H$_5$Bi(dip)$_2.3$H$_2$O and (N$_2$H$_5$)$_3$Bi(dip)$_3.4$H$_2$O have been prepared and characterized by physico-chemical techniques. The infrared spectra of the complexes reveal the presence of tridentate dipicolinate dianions and non-coordinating hydrazinium cations. Conductance measurements show that the mono, di and trihydrazinium complexes behave as 1 : 1, 2 : 1 and 3 : 1 electrolytes respectively, in aqueous solution. Thermal decomposition studies show that these compounds lose water followed by endothermic decomposition of hydrazine to give respective metal hydrogendipicolinate intermediates, which further decompose exothermically to the final product of either metal carbonates (Ca, Sr, Ba and Pb) or metal oxycarbonates (Bi). The coordination numbers around the metal ions differ from compound to compound. The various coordination numbers exhibited by these metals are six (Ca), seven (Ba), eight (Sr) and nine (Pb and Bi). In all the complexes the above coordination number is attained by tridentate dipicolinate dianions and water molecules. The X-ray diffraction patterns of these compounds differ from one another suggesting that they are not isomorphous.</p> 
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Hydrazinium; dipicolinate; main group metals; thermal analysis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Saravanan" fname="K." isfellow="0">Saravanan, K.</author>
					<author lname="Govindarajan" fname="S." isfellow="0">Govindarajan, S.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Interactions between oxovanadium (IV), glycylvaline and imidazoles: An aqueous potentiometric and spectroscopic study</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical </feature>
				<page>0037-0046</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Speciation has been determined in aqueous oxovanadium, glycylvaline and imidazoles at $25 \pm 1^\circ$C and $\sim = 0.1$M NaClO$_4$ using a combination of potentiometry, and visible and EPR spectroscopy. Results of potentiometric and spectroscopic methods are consistent. Calculations of stability constants have been made using the SCOGS computer program.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oxovanadium (IV); glycylvaline; imidazoles.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Patel" fname="R. N." isfellow="0">Patel, R. N.</author>
					<author lname="Soni" fname="V. K." isfellow="0">Soni, V. K.</author>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">Shukla, K. K.</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="S." isfellow="0">Sharma, S.</author>
					<author lname="Pandeya" fname="K. B." isfellow="0">Pandeya, K. B.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Lifetimes of $\alpha$-halo and $\alpha$-azidobenzyl carbocations in aqueous solution</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0047-0054</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The title cations were produced in aqueous solution by chemical initiation (solvolysis) of benzyl-\textit{gem}-dihalides and benzyl-\textit{gem}-diazides. The solvolysis reactions of benzyl-\textit{gem}-dihalides and benzyl-\textit{gem}-diazides in water proceed by a stepwise mechanism through $\alpha$-halobenzyl carbocation and $\alpha$-azidobenzyl carbocation intermediates, which are captured by water to give the corresponding carbonyl compounds as the sole detectable products. Rate constant ratio $k_x/k_s (M${-1}$) for partitioning of the carbocation between reaction with halide/azide ion and reaction with water is determined by analysis of halide/azide common ion inhibition of the solvolysis reaction. The rate constants k$_s$(s^{-1}$) for the reaction of the cation with solvent water were determined from the experimental values of $k_x/k_s$ and $k_{solv}$, for the solvolysis of the benzyl-\textit{gem}-dihalides and benzyl-\textit{gem}-diazides respectively, using $k_x = 5 \tiems 10^9$ M$^{-1}$ s$^{-1}$ for diffusion-limited reaction of halide/azide ion with $\alpha$-substituted benzyl carbocations. The values of 1$/k_s$ are thus the lifetimes of the $\alpha$-halobenzyl carbocations and $\alpha$-azidobenzyl carbocations respectively.</p> 
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Solvolysis; lifetimes; $\alpha$-halobenzyl carbocations; $\alpha$-azidobenzyl carbocations.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sanjeev" fname="R." isfellow="0">Sanjeev, R.</author>
					<author lname="Jagannadham" fname="V." isfellow="0">Jagannadham, V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>An analysis on the transmission of electron density through sulphur atoms in the quaternization reactions of benzothiazoles</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0055-0060</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mishra" fname="B. K." isfellow="0">Mishra, B. K.</author>
					<author lname="Patel" fname="Sabita" isfellow="0">Patel, Sabita</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Partitioning of methyl internal rotational barrier energy of thioacetaldehyde</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0061-0074</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The nature of methyl internal rotational barrier in thioacetaldehyde has been investigated by relaxation effect, natural bond orbital (NBO) analysis and Pauling exchange interactions. The true experimental barrier can be obtained by considering fully relaxed rotation. Nuclear-electron attraction term is a barrier forming term in the fully relaxed rotation, but it appears as an antibarrier for rigid rotation. It is seen that during methyl rotation, the torsional mode is coupled with the aldehydic hydrogen out-of-plane wagging motion. Natural bond orbital analysis shows that the principal barrier forming term originates from the C–C bond. The lengthening of the C–C bond is explained by considering charge transfer interaction between several bonding and antibonding orbitals in the C–C bond region, which leads to higher bonding overlap for the eclipsed conformer compared to the staggered conformer. S–C($\sigma$)/C$_{\text{me}}$–H$_{\text{ip}}$ and C–H$_{\text{ald}}$/C$_{\text{me}}–H$_{\text{op}}$ interactions appear to be the main barrier-forming Pauling exchange terms but have less contribution to make to the barrier compared to the C–C bond interaction.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Methyl rotation; natural bond orbitals; Pauling exchange interaction; thioacetaldehyde.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Guchhait" fname="Nikhil" isfellow="0">Guchhait, Nikhil</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>EPR investigations of electron transfer in one-electron reduced a-1,4 K5[PV2W10O40].3H2O</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0075-0082</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Heteropoly blues of $\alpha$-1,2 and $\alpha$-1,4 isomers of [PV$_2$W$_{10}$O$_{40}]$^{5-} have been prepared by using the electrochemical technique. EPR spectra, measured as a function of temperature over a wide range (20–300 K), are explicable in terms of electronhopping processes in heteropoly blues. Temperature dependence of A||of the isomers suggest that the activation energy for electron hopping is greater for the $\alpha$-1,4 isomer than the $\alpha$-1,2 isomer. Other parameters like stability of the blues and intra-molecular electron transfer rate constants are also evaluated using EPR as the tool.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>$\alpha$-1,4 isomer; $\alpha$-1,2 isomer; heteropoly blues</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Varghese" fname="C. M." isfellow="0">Varghese, C. M.</author>
					<author lname="Shunmugasundaram" fname="A." isfellow="0">Shunmugasundaram, A.</author>
					<author lname="Murugesan" fname="R." isfellow="0">Murugesan, R.</author>
					<author lname="Jeyabalan" fname="T." isfellow="0">Jeyabalan, T.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Photoisomerization of merocyanine 540 in polymer–surfactant aggregate</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0083-0091</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Photoisomerization of merocyanine 540 (MC540) in a polymer–surfactant aggregate is studied using picosecond time resolved emission spectroscopy. The aggregate consists of the polymer, poly(vinylpyrrolidone) (PVP) and the surfactant, sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS). With increase in the concentration of SDS in an aqueous solution of MC540 containing PVP, the emission quantum yield and lifetime of MC540 increase markedly. This indicates marked retardation in the nonradiative photoisomerization process of MC540, when it binds to the polymersurfactant aggregate. The critical association concentration of SDS for binding to PVP has been found to be 0$\cdot$5 mM. This is about 16 times lower than the CMC of SDS in pure water (8 mM).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Dynamics of photoisomerization; polymer–surfactant aggregate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sen" fname="Sobhan" isfellow="0">Sen, Sobhan</author>
					<author lname="Sukul" fname="Dipankar" isfellow="0">Sukul, Dipankar</author>
					<author lname="Dutta" fname="Partha" isfellow="0">Dutta, Partha</author>
					<author lname="Bhattacharyya" fname="Kankan" isfellow="0">Bhattacharyya, Kankan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="04" year="2002">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A new layered iron fluorophosphate</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0093-0105</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A new iron fluorophosphate of the composition, [C$_6$N$_4$H$_{21}$] [Fe$_2$F$_2$(HPO$_4$)$_3$][H$_2$PO$_4$]$\cdot$2H$_2$O, {\bf I} has been prepared by the hydrothermal route. This compound contains iron fluorophosphate layers and the H$_2$PO$_4^-$ anions are present in the interlayer space along with the protonated amine and water molecules. The compound crystallizes in the monoclinic space group $P2$_1/c$. ($a = 13\cdot 4422(10)$ Å, $b = 9 \cdot 7320(10)$ Å, $c = 18 \cdot 3123(3)$ Å, $\beta = 92\cdot 1480^{\circ}$, $V = 2393 \cdot 92(5)$ Å$_3$, $Z = 4$, $M = 719 \cdot 92$, $d_{\text{calc.}} = 1 \cdot 997$ g cm$^{-3}$, $R_1 = 0 \cdot 03$ and $wR_2 = 0 \cdot 09$).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Open-framework materials; layered iron phosphate, hydrothermal synthesis.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Choudhury" fname="Amitava" isfellow="0">Choudhury, Amitava</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis and characterization of a reduced heteropolytungstovanadate: (NH4)7[ 36 IV 2 VI 4 10VVO W V O ]×ca. 22H2O</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0107-0114</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The compound (NH$_4$)$_7$[V$^V$O_4$W$_{10}^{VI}$V$_2$V$^{VI}_2$$O_{36}]$\cdot$×ca.22H$_2$O ({\bf 1}) has been synthesized from an aqueous ammonium acetate buffer ($p$H 4) containing sodium vanadate, sodium tungstate and sodium dithionite. Compound ({\bf 1}) crystallizes in a cubic space group $Fm3$, with $a = 22 \cdot 2001$(6) Å and $Z = 8$. The anion [V$^{\text{V}}$O$_4$W$^{\text{VI}}_{10}$V$^{\text{IV}}_2$O$_{36}$]$^{7-} is a typical Keggin type structure with V$^{\text{V}}$O$_4$ as the central tetrahedron. ({\bf 1}) has further been characterized by elemental analyses, redox titration, IR, EPR, and electronic spectroscopy and room temperature magnetic moment measurement.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Heteropolytungstovanadate; crystal structure; Keggin type anion; reduction; spectral characterization.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shivaiah" fname="Vaddypally" isfellow="0">Shivaiah, Vaddypally</author>
					<author lname="Das" fname="Samar K." isfellow="0">Das, Samar K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Potentiometric and spectrometric study: Copper(II), nickel(II) and zinc(II) complexes with potentially tridentate and monodentate ligands</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0115-0124</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Equilibrium and solution structural study of mixed-metal–mixed-ligand complexes of Cu(II), Ni(II) and Zn(II) with L-cysteine, L-threonine and imidazole are conducted in aqueous solution by potentiometry and spectrophotometry. Stability constants of the binary, ternary and quaternary complexes are determined at $25 \pm 1^\circ$C and in $I = 0 \cdot 1$ M NaClO$_4$. The results of these two methods are made selfconsistent, then rationalized assuming an equilibrium model including the species H$_3$A, H$_2$A, A, BH, B, M(OH), M(OH)$_2$, M(A), MA(OH), M(B), M(A)(B), M$_2$(A)$_2$(B), M$_2$(A)$_2$(B–H), M$^1$M$^2$(A)$_2$(B) and M$^1$M$^2$(A)$_2$(B–H) (where the charges of the species have been ignored for the sake of simplicity) (A = L-cysteine, L-threonine, salicylglycine, salicylvaline and BH = imidazole). Evidence of the deprotonation of BH ligand is available at alkaline $p$H. N$_1$H deprotonation of the bidentate coordinated imidazole ligand in the binuclear species at $p$H $&gt;$ 7$\cdot$0 is evident from spectral measurements. Stability constants of binary M(A), M(B) and ternary M(A)(B), complexes follow the Irving–Williams order.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Homo/hetero-binuclear complexes; imidazole; metal(II); equilibrium study.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Patel" fname="R. N." isfellow="0">Patel, R. N.</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="Nripendra" isfellow="0">Singh, Nripendra</author>
					<author lname="Shrivastava" fname="R. P." isfellow="0">Shrivastava, R. P.</author>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">Shukla, K. K.</author>
					<author lname="Singh," fname="P. K." isfellow="0">Singh, P. K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Syntheses and absorption–structure relationships of some new photosensitizer cyanine dyes</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0125-0136</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>New biheterocyclic compound was synthesized as starting material to prepare new photosensitizers mono-, tri-, substituted tri-, azadimethine and mixed cyanine dyes. Absorption–structure relationship of the synthesized cyanine dyes were determined by studying their electronic spectral behaviour in ethanol. The structure of the compounds were identified by elemental analysis, IR and ${}^1$H NMR spectral data.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cyanine dyes; absorption–structure relationship; photosensitizer dyes; biheterocyclic compounds.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shindy" fname="H. A." isfellow="0">Shindy, H. A.</author>
					<author lname="Koraiem" fname="A. I. M." isfellow="0">Koraiem, A. I. M.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics and mechanism of the oxidation of organic sulphides by $2,2'$-bipyridinium chlorochromate</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0137-0148</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The oxidation of 34 organic sulphides by $2,2'$-bipyridinium chlorochromate (BPCC) resulted in the formation of the corresponding sulphoxides. The reaction is first order with respect to both BPCC and the sulphide, and is catalysed by hydrogen ions. The hydrogen-ion dependence has the form: $k_{\text{obs}} = a+b$[H$^{+}$]. The oxidation was studied in 19 different organic solvents. An analysis of the solvent effect by Swain’s equation showed that the both cation- and anion-solvating powers of the solvents play important roles. The rates of oxidation meta- and $p$-substituted phenyl methyl sulphides were correlated with Charton’s LDR equation. The rates of the $o$-compounds showed excellent correlation with the LDRS equation. Oxidation of the $p$-compounds is more susceptible to the delocalization effect. Oxidation of the $m$-compounds exhibited a greater dependence on the field effect. In the oxidation of the $o$-compounds, the contribution of delocalized effect is slightly more than that of the field effect. The oxidation of alkyl phenyl sulphides is subject to both polar and steric effects of the alkyl groups. Polar reaction constants are negative, indicating an electron-deficient sulphur centre in the rate-determining step. A mechanism involving formation of a sulphurane intermediate in the slow step has been proposed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Correlation analysis; halochromates; organic sulphides.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Vyas" fname="Shashi" isfellow="0">Vyas, Shashi</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="Pradeep K." isfellow="0">Sharma, Pradeep K.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Kinetics and mechanism of oxidation of dimethyl sulphoxide by sodium bromate–sodium bisulphite reagent in aqueous medium</title>xs
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0149-0154</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Rates of oxidation of dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO) by HOBr produced in situ from sodium bromate-sodium bisulphite reagent have been studied iodometrically in aqueous medium. The order in [DMSO] is one when [DMSO] $&lt;$ 0$\cdot$01 mol dm$^{-3}$, fractional when [DMSO] is between 0$\cdot$01 and 0$\cdot$5 mol dm$^{-3}$ and zero when (DMSO) $&lt;$ 0$\cdot$5 mol dm$^{-3}$. Different rate laws are operative under these three conditions though HOBr is the effective oxidizing species in all the cases. A mechanism involving an intermediate four-membered cyclic transition state between DMSO and HOBr (formation constant $K$), which decomposes in a slow step with a rate constant ($k$) has been proposed. Thermodynamic parameters for the adduct formation step and activation parameters for the first-order decomposition of the adduct step have been evaluated in the temperature range 308–323 K. Activation parameters have also been determined while the orders in [DMSO] are unity and zero. The reaction product has been identified as dimethyl sulphone (DMSO$_2$).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oxidation of DMSO; sodium bromate–sodium bisulphite reagent.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Viroopakshappa" fname="J." isfellow="0">Viroopakshappa, J.</author>
					<author lname="Jagannadham" fname="V." isfellow="0">Jagannadham, V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effects of preparation temperature on the conductivity of polypyrrole conducting polymer</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0155-0162</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>An attempt has been made to investigate the effect of temperature on the conductivity of polypyrrole conducting polymer films prepared by an electrochemical method in an aqueous medium using camphor sulfonate as the dopant. The polymer was grown from aqueous solutions employing a range of temperatures (1–60$^\circ$C). It was found that with increase in temperature the conductivity decreased and the optimum temperature was found to be between 10 and 30$^\circ$C. The results show that the polymer formed at low temperature has higher conductivity and is stronger than that formed at higher temperatures. Characterization by X-ray scattering shows that interlayer distance, $d_{\text{Bragg}}$ (Å), increases with increasing temperature. The morphology of the films formed was studied by using a scanning electron microscope (SEM). The changes in conductivity and physical appearance were interpreted as being due to compactness in the molecular packing and formation of $\alpha \beta$ linkages in the film.</p> 
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Conducting polymer; polypyrrole; camphor sulfonate dopant; electrochemical polymerization.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kassim" fname="Anuar" isfellow="0">Kassim, Anuar</author>
					<author lname="Basar" fname="Zarina Bte" isfellow="0">Basar, Zarina Bte</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="06" year="2002">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Mixed ligand complex formation of Fe$^{\text{III}}$ with boric acid and typical N-donor multidentate ligands</title>
				<feature>Inorganic and Analytical</feature>
				<page>0163-0174</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Equilibrium study of the mixed ligand complex formation of Fe$^{\text{III}}$ with boric acid in the absence and in the presence of $2,2'$-bipyridine, 1,10-phenanthroline, diethylenetriamine and triethylenetetramine (L) in different molar ratios provides evidence of formation of Fe(OH)$^{2+}$, Fe(OH)$^+_2$, Fe(L)$^{3+}$, Fe(H$_2$BO$_4$), Fe(OH)(H$_2$BO$_4$)$^-$, Fe(OH)$_2$(H$_2$BO$_4$)$^{2-}$, Fe(L)(H$_2$BO$_4$) and Fe$_2$(L)$_2$(BO$_4$)$^+$ complexes. Fe(L)$^{3+}_2$, Fe(L)$_2$(H$_2$BO$_4$) and Fe$_2$(L)$_4$(BO$_4$)$^+$ complexes are also indicated with $2,2'$-bipyridine and 1,10-phenanthroline. Complex formation equilibria and stability constants of the complexes at $25 \pm 0 \times 1^\circ$C in aqueous solution at a fixed ionic strength, $I = 0 \cdot 1$ mol $dm^{-3}$ (NaNO$_3$) have been determined by potentiometric method.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mixed ligand-Fe$^{\text{III}}$-borate complexes; complex equilibria; N-donor multidentate ligands.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mukherjee" fname="G. N." isfellow="0">Mukherjee, G. N.</author>
					<author lname="Das" fname="Ansuman" isfellow="0">Das, Ansuman</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Five decades in the study of natural products*</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0175-0195</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This paper describes the five-decade long fascinating journey taken by Prof. T R Govindachari towards the study of the natural products of India. A variety of Indian plants were investigated by him for the study of their constituent alkaloids and terpenoids. The concluding part of the paper summarizes the isolation and identification of the constituents of the \textit{Neem} kernel, which eventually led to the first X-ray structure determination of azadirachtin A.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Natural products; tylophora alkaloids; carpaine; tiliacorine; ishwarone; azadirachtin A.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Govindachari" fname="T. R." isfellow="0">Govindachari, T. R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synthesis of novel cationic lipids with fully or partially non-scissile linkages between the hydrocarbon chains and pseudoglyceryl backbone</title>
				<feature>Organic</feature>
				<page>0197-0201</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Five novel cationic lipids with fully or partially \textit{non-scissile} linkage regions between the pseudoglyceryl backbone and the hydrocarbon chains have been synthesized. The membrane-forming properties of these new lipids are briefly presented.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cationic lipids; non-scissile linkages; glycerol backbone; membranes; gene transfection.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Santanu" fname="Bhattacharya" isfellow="0">Santanu Bhattacharya</author>
					<author lname="Saubhik" fname="Haldar" isfellow="0">Saubhik Haldar</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Vapour phase alkylation of ethylbenzene with $t$-butyl alcohol over mesoporous Al-MCM-41 molecular sieves</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0203-0212</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The alkylation of ethylbenzene with $t$-butyl alcohol was studied over Al-MCM-41 (Si/Al = 50 and 90) and Al, Mg-MCM-41 (Si/(Al $+$ Mg) =50) in the vapour phase from 200 to 400$^\circ$C. The products were $p-t$-butylethylbenzene ($p-t$-BEB), $p-t$-butylvinylbenzene ($p-t$-BVB) and $m-t$-butylethylbenzene ($m-t$-BEB). Ethylbenzene conversion decreased with increase in temperature and increase in the ethylbenzene content of the feed. The reaction between the freely diffusing ethylbenzene in the channel and the $t$-butyl cations remaining as charge compensating ions yielded $p-t$-BEB. $p-t$-BVB, an unexpected product in this investigation, was produced by dehydrogenation of $p-t$-BEB over alumina particles present in the channels of the molecular sieves. Adsorption of ethylbenzene on Brønsted acid sites and its subsequent reaction with very closely adsorbed $t$-butyl cations proved to be necessary to obtain $m-t$-BEB. Though $m-t$-BEB was obtained, the corresponding $m-t$-butylvinylbenzene was not observed in this study. Study of time durations indicated rapid and slow catalyst deactivation at lower and higher streams respectively.</p> 
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mesoporous molecular sieves; Al-MCM-41; ethylbenzene; $t$-butylation; $t$-butyl alcohol.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Umamaheswari" fname="V." isfellow="0">Umamaheswari, V.</author>
					<author lname="Palanichamy" fname="M." isfellow="0">Palanichamy, M.</author>
					<author lname="Arabindoo" fname="Banumathi" isfellow="0">Arabindoo, Banumathi</author>
					<author lname="Murugesan" fname="V." isfellow="0">Murugesan, V.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Liquid crystalline behaviour of mixtures of structurally dissimilar mesogens in binary systems</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0213-0221</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have studied four binary systems comprising four ester components, viz. 4-nitrophenyl-$4'$-$n$-alkoxybenzoates (where $n$-alkoxy is nbutoxy, C$_4$, $n$-hexyloxy, C$_6$, $n$-octyloxy, C$_8$ and $n$-decyloxy, C$_{10}) and one azo component, 4-$n$-decyloxy phenylazo-$4'$-isoamyloxy benzene. A variety of mesomorphic properties are observed in these mixtures. The properties of these systems are discussed on the basis of phase diagrams.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Binary mixture; non-mesomorphic; smectic A; nematic.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Dave" fname="Jayrang S." isfellow="0">Dave, Jayrang S.</author>
					<author lname="Menon" fname="Meera R." isfellow="0">Menon, Meera R.</author>
					<author lname="Patel" fname="Pratik R." isfellow="0">Patel, Pratik R.</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Theoretical studies on electron delocalisation in selenourea</title>
				<feature>Physical and Theoretical</feature>
				<page>0223-0230</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>$Ab$ \textit{initio} and density functional calculations have been performed on the different possible structures of selenourea ($su$), urea ($u$) and thiourea ($tu$) to understand the extent of delocalisation in selenourea in comparison to urea and thiourea. Selenourea ($su-1$) with $C_2$ symmetry has the minima on the potential energy surface at MP2(fu)/$6-31+G^\ast$ level. The C–N rotational barrier in selenourea is 8$\cdot$69 kcal/mol, which is 0$\cdot$29 and 0$\cdot$11 kcal/mol more than that of urea and thiourea respectively at MP2(fu)/$6-31+G^\ast$ level. N-inversion barrier is 0$\cdot$55 kcal/mol at MP2(fu)$6-31+G^\ast$ level. NBO analysis has been carried out to understand the nature of different interactions responsible for the electron delocalisation.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Selenourea; electron delocalisation; C–N rotational barriers; Ninversion barriers; NBO analysis; $ab$ \textit{initio} and density functional.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Moudgil" fname="Rajnish" isfellow="0">Moudgil, Rajnish</author>
					<author lname="Bharatam" fname="Prasad V." isfellow="0">Bharatam, Prasad V.</author>
					<author lname="Kaur" fname="Ravneet" isfellow="0">Kaur, Ravneet</author>
					<author lname="Kaur" fname="Damanjit" isfellow="0">Kaur, Damanjit</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">%%%%%%% prathibha
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
	<volume vnum="">
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
	<volume vnum="">
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
	<volume vnum="">
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
	<volume vnum="">
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
	<volume vnum="">
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
	<volume vnum="">
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
	<volume vnum="">
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="0000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>00-00</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>		
</jcs>

