<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cs SYSTEM "jess.dtd">

<jess>
	<volume vnum="109">
		<issue inum="01" month="03" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Editorial</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0004</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors />
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Important Crustal Growth in the Phanerozoic: Isotopic Evidence of Granitoids from East-Central Asia</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0005-0020</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The growth of the continental crust is generally believed to have been essentially completed in the Precambrian, and the amount of juvenile crust produced in the Phanerozoic is considered insignificant. Such idea of negligible growth in the Phanerozoic is now challenged by the revelation of very large volume of juvenile crust produced in the period of 500 to 100 Ma in several orogenic belts. While appreciable volumes of juvenile terranes in North America (Canadian Cordillera, Sierra Nevada and Peninsular Range, Appalachians) have been documented based on Nd isotopic data, the mass of new crust formed in the East-Central Asian Orogenic Belt (ECAOB), eastern part of the Altaid Tectonic Collage, appears to be much greater than the above terranes combined. New and published Nd-Sr isotope data indicate that the Phanerozoic granitoids from the southern belt of the ECAOB (Xinjiang-West Mongolia-Inner Mongolia-NE China) as well as from Mongolia and Transbaikalia were generated from sources dominated by a depleted mantle component. These granitoids represent a significant growth of juvenile crust in the Phanerozoic.</p>
					<p>Although most plutons in this huge orogenic belt belong to the calc-alkaline series, the ECAOB is also characterized by the emplacement of voluminous A-type granites. The origin of these rocks is probably multiple and is still widely debated. However, the isotopic data (Sr-Nd-O) and trace element abundance patterns of A-type granites from the ECAOB clearly indicate their mantle origin.</p>
					<p>The evolution of the ECAOB and the entire Altaid Collage is most likely related to successive accretion of arc complexes. However, the emplacement of a large volume of post-tectonic A-type granites requires another mechanism, probably through a series of processes including underplating of massive basaltic magma, partial melting of these basic rocks to produce granitic liquids, followed by extensive fractional crystallization. The proportion of juvenile to recycled, as well as that of arc-related to plume-generated, continental crust remains to be evaluated by more systematic dating and isotope tracer studies.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Crustal evolution;granites;Phanerozoic;Sr-Nd isotopes;east-central Asia.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Jahn" fname="Bor-Ming" isfellow="0">Bor-ming Jahn</author>
					<author lname="Wu" fname="Fuyan" isfellow="0">Fuyuan Wu</author>
					<author lname="Hong" fname="Dawei" isfellow="0">Dawei Hong</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Anasagar gneiss: A folded granitoid pluton in the Phanerozoic South Delhi Fold Belt, central Rajasthan</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0022-0038</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Anasagar gneiss was emplaced as a concordant sheet like body along the contact of quartzite and pelitic/semipelitic schist horizons in the northern part of the South Delhi Fold Belt. It is typically a granite gneiss containing megacrysts of K-feldspar set in a recrystallised foliated matrix. The megacrysts are in general converted to granular aggregates, often retaining their crystal outline. Garnet, sillimanite (fibrolite) and rarely staurolite are the metamorphic minerals in the gneiss; these are also present in the enveloping supracrustal rocks. Both the gneiss and the supracrustal rocks are involved in polyphase deformation. F1 isoclinal folds are present only on minor scale in the supracrustal rocks. F2 major and minor folding have affected both the gneiss and the supracrustal rocks. These are asymmetrical folds with alternate flat and steep, locally overturned, limbs and have consistent easterly vergence. F3 folds are upright and coaxial with F2. F4 puckers and large scale warps have E-W to ESE-WNW subvertical axial planes. The gneiss is exposed in the core of an F3 arch on the flat limb of a major F2 antiform whose axial trace is bent by an F4 fold. The intrusion was pre-F2 and late-tectonic with F1. U-Pb zircon dating suggests a crystallization age of 1849 ± 8 Ma. Hence the Anasagar gneiss is older than the late- to post-tectonic ``Erinpura-type'' granite in the South Delhi Fold Belt.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Mukhopadhyay" fname="Dhruba" isfellow="0">Dhruba Mukhopadhyay</author>
					<author lname="Bhattacharyya" fname="Tapas" isfellow="0">Tapas Bhattacharyya</author>
					<author lname="Chattopadhyay" fname="Nandini" isfellow="0">Nandini Chattopadhyay</author>
					<author lname="Lopez" fname="Robert" isfellow="0">Robert Lopez</author>
					<author lname="T. Tobisch" fname="Othmar" isfellow="0">Othmar T. Tobisch</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Emplacement of Amba Dongar Carbonatite-alkaline Complex at Cretaceous/Tertiary Boundary: Evidence from 40Ar-39Ar Chronology</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0039-0047</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>$^{40}{\rm Ar}-^{39}{\rm Ar}$ analyses of three fresh alkaline rock samples and a phlogopite separate from a carbonatite from Amba Dongar carbonatite-alkaline complex of the Deccan Flood Basalt Province, India, yield indistinguishable precise plateau ages of $64.8\pm 0.6, 64.7\pm 0.5, 65.5\pm  0.8$ and $65.3\pm 0.6 {\rm Ma}$, giving a mean plateau age of $65.0\pm  0.3{\rm Ma}$, which is the age of emplacement of this complex. This age implies contemporaneity of Amba Dongar with several other carbonatite-alkaline activities of Chhota Udaipur subprovince and is consistent with their Reunion-Deccan plume origin hypothesis. The emplacement of these complexes at 65 Ma makes them very significant in the ongoing debate on the K/T extinctions owing to their capacity to rapidly inject a substantial amount of ${\rm CO}_2$ and ${\rm SO}_2$ into the atmosphere.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Amba Dongar carbonatites;Deccan Flood Basalts;$^{40} Ar-^{39} Ar$ chronology;K/T boundary.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="S. Ray" fname="Jyotiranjan" isfellow="0">Jyotiranjan S. Ray</author>
					<author lname="Pande" fname="Kanchan" isfellow="0">Kanchan Pande</author>
					<author lname="Venkatesan" fname="T. R." isfellow="0">T. R. Venkatesan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Sr Isotopic Evidence on the Spilitic Degradation of the Deccan Basalt</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0049-0055</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Similar Sr isotopic ratios ($\sim$0.7055) for the tholeiite-spilite flow unit and the associated mineral phases, of Bombay (Deccan Traps) provide a direct evidence for the spilitic degradation of tholeiite. In contrast, a dramatic increase in the rare earth elements (REE) from basalt to spilite is rather puzzling as rare earths are considered to be relatively immobile. The geochemistry thus suggests that the process of spilitization is due to the reaction with a complex fluid having identical Sr-isotopic composition as that of the basaltic magma - thereby masking the details of the mixing process.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Spilites;Deccan basalt;Sr isotopes.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Subbarao" fname="K. V." isfellow="0">K. V. Subbarao</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Sm-Nd Ages of Two Meta-Anorthosite Complexes Around Holenarsipur: Constraints on the Antiquity of Archean Supracrustal Rocks of the Dharwar Craton</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0057-0065</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Whole-rock Sm-Nd isochron ages are reported for two stratiform meta-anorthosite complexes emplaced into the Archean supracrustal-gneiss association in the amphibolite facies terrain around Holenarsipur, in the Dharwar carton, South India.  While these metaperidotite-pyroxenite-gabbro-anorthosite complexes are petrologically and geochemically similar, they differ in the intensity of tectonic fabric developed during the late Archean (c.2.5Ga) deformation.  They also differ in their whole-rock Sm-Nd isochron ages and initial Nd isotopic compositions: $3.285\pm 0.17$ {\rm Ga}, $\varepsilon {\rm Nd} =0.82\pm 0.78$ for the Honnavalli meta-anorthosite complex from a supracrustal enclave in the low-strain zone, and $2.495\pm 0.033 {\rm Ga},\varepsilon {\rm Nd} =-2.2+-0.3$ for the Dodkadnur meta-anorthosites from the high-strain southern arm of the Holenarsipur Supracrustal Belt (HSB).  We interpret these results as indicating that the magmatic protoliths of both meta-anorthosite complexes were derived from a marginally depleted mantle at c.3.29 Ga but only the Dodkadnur rocks were isotopically reequilibrated on a cm-scake about 800 Ma later presumably due to the development of strong penetrative fabrics in them during Late Archean thermotectonic event around 2.5Ga.  Our results set a younger age limit at c.3.29Ga for the supracrustal rocks of the HSB in the Dharwar craton.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Archean;anorthosite;Dharwar craton;Sm-Nd;Geochronology.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bhaskar Rao" fname="Y. J." isfellow="0">Y. J. Bhaskar Rao</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="Anil" isfellow="0">Anil Kumar</author>
					<author lname="Vrevsky" fname="A. B." isfellow="0">A. B. Vrevsky</author>
					<author lname="Srinivasan" fname="R." isfellow="0">R. Srinivasan</author>
					<author lname="Anantha Iyer" fname="G. V." isfellow="0">G. V. Anantha Iyer</author>		
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Compilation of Radiogenic Isotope Data in Mexico and their Petrogenetic Implications</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0067-0078</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Seven hundred and twenty-five Sr, two hundred and forty-three Nd and one hundred and fifty-one Pb isotopic ratios from seven different Mexican magmatic provinces were compiled in an extensive geochemical database. Data were arranged according to the Mexican geological provinces, indicating for each province total number of analyses, range and mean of values and two times standard deviation ($2\sigma$). Data from seven provinces were included in the database: Mexican Volcanic Belt (MVB), Sierra Madre Occidental (SMO), Baja California (BC), Pacific Ocean (PacOc), Altiplano (AP), Sierra Madre del Sur (SMS), and Sierra Madre Oriental (SMOr). Isotopic values from upper mantle and lower crustal xenoliths, basement outcrops and sediments from the Cocos Plate were also compiled. In the MVB the isotopic ratios range as follows: $^{87}{\rm Sr}/^{86}{\rm Sr} 0.703003-0.70841; ^{143} {\rm Nd}/^{144}{\rm Nd} 0.512496-0.513098; ^{206}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 18.567-19.580; ^{207}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 15.466-15.647; ^{208}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 38.065-38.632$. The SMO shows a large variation in $^{87}{\rm Sr}/^{86}{\rm Sr}$ ranging from ~ 0.7033 to 0.71387. $^{143}{\rm Nd}/^{144} {\rm Nd}$ ratios are relatively less variable with values from 0.51191 to 0.51286. Pb isotope ratios in the SMO are as follows: $^{206}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 18.060-18.860; ^{207}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 15.558- 15.636; ^{208}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 37.945-38.625$. PacOc rocks show the most depleted Sr and Nd isotopic ratios (0.70232-0.70567 for Sr and 0.512631-0.513261 for Nd). Pb isotopes for PacOc show the following range: $^{206}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 18.049-19.910; ^{207}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 15.425-15.734; ^{208}{\rm Pb}/^{204}{\rm Pb} 37.449-39.404$. The isotopic ratios of the AP rocks seem to be within the range of those from the PacOc.</p>
					<P>Most samples with reported Sr and Nd isotopic data are spread within and around the ``mantle array''. The SMO seems to have been formed by a mixing process between mantle derived magmas and continental crust. The MVB appears to have a larger mantle component, with AFC as the dominant petrogenetic process for the evolved rocks. There is still a need for Pb isotopic data in all Mexican magmatic provinces andofNdisotopes in BC,AP, SMS, and SMOr.</P>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Radiogenic isotopes;Sr, Nd, Pb;magmatic provinces;Mexico;Pacific Ocean;Cocos Plate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>	
					<author lname="Torres-Alvarado" fname="Ignacio. S." isfellow="0">Ignacio. S. Torres-Alvarado</author>
					<author lname="Verma1" fname="Surendra. P." isfellow="0">Surendra. P. Verma1</author>
					<author lname="Carrasco-Nunez" fname="Gerardo" isfellow="0">Gerardo Carrasco-Nunez</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Error Propagation in Equations for Geochemical Modeling of Radiogenic Isotopes in Two-Component Mixing</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0079-0088</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This paper presents error propagation equations for modeling of radiogenic isotopes during mixing of two components or end-members. These equations can be used to estimate errors on an isotopic ratio in the mixture of two components, as a function of the analytical errors or the total errors of geological field sampling and analytical errors. Two typical cases (``Small errors'' and ``Large errors'') are illustrated for mixing of Sr isotopes. Similar examples can be formulated for the other radiogenic isotopic ratios. Actual isotopic data for sediment and basalt samples from the Cocos plate are also included to further illustrate the use of these equations. The isotopic compositions of the predicted mixtures can be used to constrain the origin of magmas in the central part of the Mexican Volcanic Belt. These examples show the need of high quality experimental data for them to be useful in geochemical modeling of magmatic processes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Isotopic ratios;geochemistry;error propagation;mixing; Mexico;Cocos plate.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Verma" fname="Surendra. P." isfellow="0">Surendra. P. Verma</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Isotopic Composition of Xenon in Petroleum from the Shell Bullwinkle Field</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0089-0094</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have measured the abundance and isotopic composition of xenon in petroleum samples from the Shell Bullwinkle Field off the coast of Louisiana. We used an oxidation and purification procedure designed to insure complete extraction and clean up of xenon from the petroleum.</p>
					<P>The xenon isotopic composition was found to be similar to the atmospheric value for one petroleum sample. While the results of the second sample suggest possible enrichment of the heavier isotopes, the errors associated with these excesses preclude a definitive statement to that effect. No monoisotopic enrichment in $^{129}{\rm Xe}$ was detected in either sample, the presence of which might have allowed us to deduce the petroleum age. Our results represent only the second xenon measurement from petroleum, and the concentrations are within the range of values published in the earlier report.</P>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Xenon;petroleum;isotopic composition;mass spectrometry.</keywords>
				<allauthors>    
					<author lname="Nuzzo*" fname="J." isfellow="0">J. Nuzzo*</author>
					<author lname="Hyman" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Hyman</author>
					<author lname="Rowe**" fname="M. W." isfellow="0">M. W. Rowe**</author>
					<author lname="Mnraoz" fname="" isfellow="0">Mnraoz</author>
					<author lname="Palma" fname="R. L." isfellow="0">R. L. Palma</author>
					<author lname="J." fname="Westrich" isfellow="0">J. Westrich</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Factors Controlling the Groundwater Transport of U, Th, Ra, and Rn</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0095-0108</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A model for the groundwater transport of naturally occurring U, Th, Ra, and Rn nuclides in the $^{238}{\rm U}$ and $^{232}{\rm Th}$ decay series is discussed. The model developed here takes into account transport by advection and the physico-chemical processes of weathering, decay,  $\alpha$-recoil, and sorption at the water-rock interface. It describes the evolution along a flowline of the activities of the $^{238}{\rm U}$ and $^{232}{\rm Th}$ decay series nuclides in groundwater. Simple sets of relationships governing the activities of the various species in solution are derived, and these can be used both to calculate effective retardation factors and to interpret groundwater data. For the activities of each nuclide, a general solution to the transport equation has been obtained, which shows that the activities reach a constant value after a distance $\bar{x}_i$, characteristic of each nuclide. Where   $\bar{x}_i$ is much longer than the aquifer length, (for $^{238}{\rm U}, ^{234}{\rm U}$, and $^{232}{\rm Th}$), the activities grow linearly with distance. Where  $\bar{x}_i$  is short compared to the aquifer length, (for $^{234}{\rm Th}, ^{230}{\rm Th}, ^{228}{\rm Th}, ^{228}{\rm Ra}$, and $^{224}{\rm Ra}$), the activities rapidly reach a constant or quasi-constant activity value. For $^{226}{\rm Ra}$ and $^{222}{\rm Rn}$, the limiting activity is reached after 1 km.</p>
					<p>High $\delta^{234}{\rm U}$ values (proportional to the ratio $\varepsilon^{234}{\rm Th}/^{W238}{\rm U}$) can be obtained through high recoil fraction and/or low weathering rates. The activity ratios $^{230}{\rm Th}/^{232}{\rm Th}, ^{228}{\rm Ra}/^{226}{\rm Ra}$ and $^{224}{\rm Ra}/^{226}{\rm Ra}$ have been considered in the cases where either weathering or recoil is the predominant process of input from the mineral grain. Typical values for weathering rates and recoil fractions for a sandy aquifer indicate that recoil is the dominant process for Th isotopic ratios in the water. Measured data for Ra isotope activity ratios indicate that recoil is the process generally controlling the Ra isotopic composition in water. Higher isotopic ratios can be explained by different desorption kinetics of Ra. However, the model does not provide an explanation for $^{228}{\rm Ra}/^{226}{\rm Ra}$ and $^{224}{\rm Ra}/^{226}{\rm Ra}$ activity ratios less than unity.</p>
					<p>From the model, the highest $^{222}{\rm Rn}$ emanation equals $2\varepsilon$. This is in agreement with the hypothesis that $^{222}{\rm Rn}$ activity can be used as a first approximation for input by recoil (Krishnaswami et al 1982). However, high $^{222}{\rm Rn}$ emanation cannot be explained by production from the surface layer as formulated in the model. Other possibilities involve models including surface precipitation, where the surface layer is not in steady-state.</p> 
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Groundwater;trace elements;isotopes;pollutants.</keywords>
				<allauthors>   
					<author lname="Tricca" fname="A." isfellow="0">A. Tricca</author>
					<author lname="Porcelli" fname="D." isfellow="0">D. Porcelli</author>
					<author lname="Wasserburg" fname="G. J." isfellow="0">G. J. Wasserburg</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Stable isotope systematics of surface water bodies in the Himalayan and trans-Himalayan (Kashmir) region</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0109-0115</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Stable hydrogen ($\delta{\rm D}$) and oxygen ($\delta^{18}{\rm O}$) isotope ratios of the headwaters of the Indus and its tributaries, surface ice in glaciers, saline and fresh water lakes and thermal springs in the Himalayan and Trans- Himalayan (Kashmir) region are reported. The $\delta{\rm D}-\delta^{18}{\rm O}$ relationship for the river samples shows a slope of $9.12 \pm 0.29$ which agrees well with the estimate of $8.99\pm 0.33$ based on a simple Rayleigh fractionation model. The unique signature of a higher deuterium excess (d) of the `Western Disturbance' is preserved in these samples. An altitude effect of -0.9 per mil/km is observed in the $\delta^{18}{\rm O} of Indus waters. At a lower altitude (Beas) the altitude effect is almost double, indicating that the altitude effect decreases with elevation in this region.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Himalaya;springs;stable isotopes;altitude effect.</keywords>
				<allauthors>  
					<author lname="Pandey" fname="Kanchan" isfellow="0">Kanchan Pandey</author>
					<author lname="Padia" fname="J. T." isfellow="0">J. T. Padia</author>
					<author lname="Ramesh" fname="R." isfellow="0">R. Ramesh</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">K. K. Sharma</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Climatic significance of D/H and $^{13}{\rm C}/^{12}{\rm C}$ ratios in Irish oak cellulose</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0117-0127</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>$\delta{\rm D}$ and $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ analyses of cellulose nitrate from two modern Irish oak trees that form part of the 7400 year long chronology were carried out, covering a period of 123 years (1861-1983 A.D.) with a 5 year resolution so as to assess the potential of this long chronology for retrieval of palaeoenvironmental data. One of the trees (Q5293) showed significant correlations of $\delta{\rm D}, \delta^{13}{\rm C}$ and ring width with mean annual temperatures as recorded at the Armagh weather station nearby and the mean fall temperatures of Central England. The other tree (Q5296) did not exhibit any significant climatic correlations either because it grew utilizing a nearby permanent source of ground water or because the intra-ring isotopic variations in Irish oak are significant enough to mask the climatic signal. Whilst our results have given a positive indication of the usefulness of these trees for palaeoenvironmental information, more trees need to be analysed to confirm our findings.</p>
					<P>Even though one of the trees did not exhibit climatic correlations, both trees show a significant positive correlation of $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ and a negative correlation of $\delta{\rm D}$ with ring width variations. Furthermore, two tree samples that grew during the 1620s B.C., when a volcano is thought to have erupted on the Aegean island of Santorini, show increased $\delta{\rm D}$ and decreased $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ for one to two decades following the eruption, though the magnitudes of change seem to vary with site and trees. We have proposed a possible mechanism based on tree phenology to explain both the above effects.</P>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Tree-rings;Irish oak;hydrogen isotopes;carbon isotopes;palaeoclimate.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Baillie" fname="M. G. L." isfellow="0">M. G. L. Baillie</author>
					<author lname="Pilcher" fname="J. R." isfellow="0">J. R. Pilcher</author>
					<author lname="Pollard" fname="A. M." isfellow="0">A. M. Pollard</author>
					<author lname="Ramesh" fname="R." isfellow="0">R. Ramesh</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Late Glacial and Holocene  Paleoliminology of two temperate lakes inferred from sediment organic $\delta^13{\rm C}$ chronology</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0129-0140</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The stable carbon isotope ($\delta^{13}{\rm C}$) and elemental C/N ratios in Total Organic Carbon (TOC) extracted from radiometrically dated cores from two Midwestern USA lakes were determined to investigate the factors that control these values in temperate lakes. The range of $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ values ( -26 to -32%) and C/N ratios (mean value $\sim$ 10.8) are typical of values reported for other temperate lake organic matter in this region. In the core from Lake Winnebago, Wisconsin, a negative correlation was seen between the TOC and $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$, which can be interpreted in terms of a re-mixing and consumption of sedimented organic carbon along with rapid equilibration throughout the water column. No correlation was seen between the TOC and $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ in the record from Ladd Lake, Ohio, implying that in this latter lake productivity alone was not a singular process controlling the isotope ratio. Here, it is suggested that equilibrium conditions are maintained such that the DIC of the water is never depleted of aqueous ${\rm CO}_2$ during high organic production and the resulting $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ of the organic carbon lacks correlation with the TOC. Further, in this lake a fine resolution analysis was carried out which indicated a possible anthropogenic influence on the isotope ratio around times when human settlement ($\sim$ 300 yrs ago) and enhanced agricultural practices ( $\sim$ 80 yrs ago) were significant. The study shows that carbon isotope studies are useful in paleolimnologic investigations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Organic carbon;lake sediments;carbon isotope ratios;lake productivity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lovan" fname="N. A." isfellow="0">N. A. Lovan</author>
					<author lname="Krishnamurthy" fname="R. V." isfellow="0">R. V. Krishnamurthy</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Is there a stable isotope evidence for the CO2 fertiliser effect</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0141-0144</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>It has been suggested that part of the so-called ''missing sink'' of carbon dioxide introduced into the atmosphere by anthropogenic activities, that is the imbalance between estimated anthropogenic carbon dioxide emissions and oceanic uptake, may be stored in the vegetation in midlatitudes. Precise mecha- nisms of abstraction of additional carbon dioxide by vegetation, also known as the ``fertilization effect'', are poorly understood. Stable carbon and hydrogen isotope ratios of cellulose extracted from annual growth rings (covering the time period 1980-1993) in an oak tree from Kalamazoo, SW Michigan provide a basis to investigate at a physiological level how the fertilization effect may operate. The carbon isotope ratios show that the intercellular concentration of carbon dioxide increased due to an increase in stomatal opening. Although increased intercellular concentration of carbon dioxide translated to increased Water Use Efficiency and assimilation rates, it also resulted in increased transpiration rate as shown by higher D/H of the fixed carbon. The two-fold significance of the isotope data are: first, they provide the first field evidence based on isotope studies for excess ${\rm CO}_2$ induced biomass production and second, they suggest that this mechanism is likely to operate only in limited environments. Vegetation in regions where mois- ture availability is not restricted so that there can be a gain in water use efficiency despite increased leaf evaporation are best suited to sequester excess carbon from the atmosphere.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Carbon isotopes;intercellular carbon dioxide;fertilization effect;hydrogen isotopes.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Krishnamurthy" fname="R. V." isfellow="0">R. V. Krishnamurthy</author>
					<author lname="Machavaram" fname=" M." isfellow="0">M. Machavaram</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Effect of intraband variability on stable isotope and density time series obtained from banded corals</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0145-0151</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Density, $\delta^{18}{\rm O}$ and $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ were measured along two tracks, one close to the central growth axis and the other, $\sim 20^\circ$ off the axis, in a coral (Porites lutea) collected from the Stanley Reef, Central Great Barrier Reef, Australia. The $\delta^{18}{\rm O}$ variations in the coral are well correlated with sea surface temperature changes. The common variances between the two tracks were about 60% in the $\delta^{18}{\rm O}, \delta^{13}{\rm C}$ and the skeletal density variations. Part of the noise (40%) could be due to the difficulty of sampling exactly time contemporaneous parts of each band along the two tracks and part of it could be due to genuine intraband variability. In spite of the intraband variability, the time series obtained from the two tracks are similar, indicating that the dominant causative factor for the isotopic variations is external, i.e., the environmental conditions that prevail during the growth of the coral; density band formation does not appear to be directly controlled by the sea surface temperature.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Carbon isotope;oxygen isotope;SST;climate;coral;Great Barrier Reef.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chakraborty" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Chakraborty</author>
					<author lname="Ramesh*" fname="R." isfellow="0">R. Ramesh*</author>
					<author lname="Lough" fname="J. M." isfellow="0">J. M. Lough</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Glacial-interglacial changes in the surface water characteristics of the  Andaman Sea: Evidence from stable ratios of planktonic foraminifera</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0153-0156</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Stable carbon and oxygen isotopic analyses of the planktonic foraminifera (Globigerinoides ruber) from a deep sea sediment core (GC-1) in the Andaman Sea show high glacial-to-Holocene $\delta^{18}{\rm 0}$ amplitude of 2.1% which is consistent with previously published records from this marginal basin and suggest increased salinity and/or decreased temperature in the glacial surface waters of this region.</p>
					<P>A pulse of $^{18}{\rm O}$ enrichment during the last deglaciation can be attributed to a Younger Dryas cooling event and/or to a sudden decrease of fresh water influx from the Irrawady and Salween rivers into the Andaman Sea. High $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ values observed during the isotopic stages 2 and 4 are probably due to the enhanced productivity during glacial times in the Andaman Sea.</P>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Stable isotopes;Younger Dryas;deglaciation;holocene, last glacial maximum (LGM).</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ahmad" fname="S. M." isfellow="0">S. M. Ahmad</author>
					<author lname="Patil" fname="D. J." isfellow="0">D. J. Patil</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="P. S." isfellow="0">P. S. Rao</author>
					<author lname="Nath" fname="B. N." isfellow="0">B. N. Nath</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="B. R." isfellow="0">B. R. Rao</author>
					<author lname="Rajagopalan" fname="G." isfellow="0">G. Rajagopalan</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Palaeomonsoon and  palaeoproductivity records of   $\delta^{18}{\rm O}, \delta^{13}{\rm C}$ and ${\rm CaCO}_3$ variations in the northern Indian Ocean sediments</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0157-0169</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>$\delta^{18}{\rm O}$ and $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ of G. sacculifer have been measured in five cores from the northern Indian Ocean. In addition, high resolution analysis (1 to 2 cm) was performed on one core (SK-20-185) for both $\delta^{18}{\rm O}$ and $\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ in five species of planktonic foraminifera. ${\rm CaCO}_3$ variation was measured in two cores. The results, presented here, show that</p>
					<ul>
						<li>the summer monsoon was weaker during 18 ka and was stronger during 9 ka, relative to modern conditions;</li>
						<li>$\delta^{13}{\rm C}$ variations are consistent with independent evidence that shows that during the last glacial maximum (LGM; 18 ka) the upwelling was reduced while during 9 ka it was vigorous;</li>
						<li>calculation of ${\rm CaCO}_3$ flux shows that the LGM was characterized by low biogenic productivity in the Arabian Sea while during the Holocene productivity increased by $\sim$65%, as a direct consequence of the changes in upwelling. Similar changes (of lesser magnitude) are also seen in the equatorial Indian Ocean. The amount of terrigenous input into the Arabian Sea doubled during LGM possibly due to the higher erosion rate along the west coast;</li>
						<li>$\delta^{18}{\rm O}$ values indicate that the Arabian Sea was saltier by 1 to 2% during LGM. The northern part was dominated by evaporation while in the equatorial part there was an increased precipitation.</li>
					</ul>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oxygen isotopes;carbon isotopes;sediments;foraminifera;productivity;monsoon.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sarkar" fname="A." isfellow="0">A. Sarkar</author>
					<author lname="Ramesh" fname="R." isfellow="0">R. Ramesh</author>
					<author lname="Bhattacharya" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">S. K. Bhattacharya</author>
					<author lname="Price" fname="N. B." isfellow="0">N. B. Price</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Long-term records of erosional change from marine ferromanganese  crusts</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0171-0180</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Ferromanganese crusts from the Atlantic, Indian and Pacific Oceans record the Nd and Pb isotope compositions of the water masses from which they form as hydrogenous precipitates. The $^{10}{\rm Be}/^{9}{\rm Be}$-calibrated time series for crusts are compared to estimates based on Co-contents, from which the equatorial Pacific crusts studied are inferred to have recorded ca. 60 Ma of Pacific deep water history.</p>
					<P>Time series of $\varepsilon Nd$ show that the oceans have maintained a strong provinciality in Nd isotopic composition, determined by terrigenous inputs, over periods of up to 60 Ma. Superimposed on the distinct basin-specific signatures are variations in Nd and Pb isotope time series which have been particularly marked over the last 5 Ma.</P>
					<P>It is shown that changes in erosional inputs, particularly associated with Himalayan uplift and the northern hemisphere glaciation have influenced Indian and Atlantic Ocean deep water isotopic composi- tions respectively. There is no evidence so far for an imprint of the final closure of the Panama Isthmus on the Pb and Nd isotopic composition in either Atlantic or Pacific deep water masses.</P>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Ferromanganese crusts;Atlantic;Pacific;Indian Ocean;Nd and Sr isotopes;erosion.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="O'Nions" fname="R. Keith" isfellow="0">R. Keith O'Nions</author>
					<author lname="Frank" fname="Martin" isfellow="0">Martin Frank</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Cosmogenic $^{10}{\rm Be}$: A critical view on its widespread dominion in geosciences</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0181-0186</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The radionuclide $^{10}{\rm Be}$ (half-life 9 1:5 my), produced naturally in the Earth's atmosphere by nuclear interactions of cosmic rays, was sought in ocean sediments in the late fifties, considering its potential usefulness as a radiotracer for dating sediments. $^{10}{\rm Be}$ was discovered independently by two groups, one in India and the other in the USA, and used only for dating marine sediments and manganese nodules until the seventies. Subsequently, as a result of a technical advance resulting in the improvement in the sensitivity of measurement of $^{10}{\rm Be}$ by about a factor of $10^6$, there was a global rush to measure this nuclide in most materials participating in the physical, chemical and biological processes in the dynamic geosphere. This paper outlines the reasons for this ``isotope rush'', and the lessons learned from these studies. I also present my personal views of the special attractive features of this nuclide on the one hand, and on the other, the pitfalls or the wrong message this nuclide could convey!</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>$^{10}{\rm Be}$;cosmic rays;geochronology</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lal" fname="D." isfellow="0">D. Lal</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Sr isotopes in the Orgueil CI meteorite:  Chronology of early solar system hydrothermal  activity</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0187-0193</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>New Sr isotopic analyses and calculated formation ages of carbonates from the Orgueil CI meteorite are reported. Among the samples analyzed in this work, dolomites give the youngest formation ages and may have been deposited intermittently starting near the time of parent body formation and continuing for at least 30 Ma. The Sr isotope data also suggest that breunnerites (Fe-Mn-Mg carbonates) crystallized after dolomite formation. Leaching experiments on bulk meteorite samples provide evidence for a very mobile, water soluble Sr reservoir in Orgueil that is characterized by extremely radiogenic Sr ($^{87}{\rm Sr}/^{86}{\rm Sr} \approx 0.81- 0.82$). This unsupported Sr reflects recent element redistribution, possibly at the time of parent body breakup recorded by the $\sim 10$ Ma exposure age of Orgueil. The carbonate data in particular corroborate earlier indications that hydrothermal processes were among the earliest events to affect the CI parent body.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Orgueil;carbonate;Sr isotopes;hydrothermal;chronology.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Macdougall" fname="J. D." isfellow="0">J. D. Macdougall</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Conceptual problems with remote element synthesis</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0195-0203</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The notion of remote element synthesis has recently been modified to explain the presence of nucleogenetic isotopic anomalies and decay products of short-lived nuclides by injection of a small amount of exotic nucleogenetic material. Even with this modification, remote element synthesis seems inconsistent with the following observations:</p>
					<ul>
						<li>Evidence of coupled variations in the chemical and isotopic compositions of the source material for meteorites.</li>
						<li>Residual coupling of chemical and isotopic heterogeneities across planetary distances in the solar system today.</li>
						<li>The mass-fractionation relationship seen across isotopes of elements in the planetary system, in the solar wind, and in solar flares.</li>
						<li>Linkage of short-lived radioactivities with isotopic anomalies and with physical properties of their host grains, as expected for early condensate of fresh stellar debris.</li>
						<li>Temporal and spatial distributions of short-lived nuclides and their decay products.</li>
						<li>Mirror-image ( $+$ and $-$ ) isotopic anomalies in meteorite grains that sum to ``normal'' isotopic ratios, as expected of unmixed products of the same nuclear reactions that produced our bulk elements.</li>
						<li>The lack of supporting evidence for ``presolar'' grains or nearby stars that injected exotic material into the early solar nebula.</li>
					</ul>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Element synthesis;isotopes;solar system;meteorites;planets.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Manuel" fname="O." isfellow="0">O. Manuel</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="06" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Preface</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0205-0206</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Bay of Bengal Monsoon Experiment (BOBMEX) -- A component of the Indian Climate Research Programme (ICRP)</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0207-0209</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Indian Climate Research Programme (ICRP) focuses on the study of climate variability and its impact on agriculture. To address the role of the Bay of Bengal in monsoon variability, a process study was organised during July-August 1999, deploying research ships, buoys, INSAT, coastal radar and conventional observational systems to collect information about the coupled ocean-atmosphere system over the warm waters of the Bay of Bengal. The paper gives the background of the ICRP and the organisation and implementation of the Bay of Bengal Monsoon Experiment (BOBMEX) in its field phase.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Monsoon;climate variability;Bay of Bengal;ocean-atmosphere coupling.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sikka" fname="D. R." isfellow="0">D. R. Sikka</author>
					<author lname="Sanjeeva Rao" fname="P." isfellow="0">P. Sanjeeva Rao</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Synoptic Weather Conditions during the Pilot Study of Bay of Bengal Monsoon Experiment (BOBMEX)</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0211-0220</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>BOBMEX-Pilot was organised from 23rd October - 11th November, 1998 when the seasonal trough had already shifted to south Bay of Bengal. The activity during this period was marked by the development of a monsoon depression from 26th-29th October that weakened over the sea; onset of northeast monsoon along the east coast of India on 29th October; a low pressure area that formed on 2nd November over southwest Bay off Sri Lanka -southTamilnadu coast; and another cyclonic circulation that formed towards the end of the BOBMEX-Pilot period. This paper describes the development of these synoptic systems through synoptic charts and satellite data.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>BOBMEX;northeast monsoon;satellite imagery;monsoon depression</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kalsi" fname="S. R." isfellow="0">S. R. Kalsi</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Surface Meteorological Instrumentation for BOBMEX</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0221-0227</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Although India has a long experience in ship-borne experiments and oceanographic instrumentation, the atmospheric component has not received much attention in the past. In this paper, the basis of the atmospheric instrumentation system assembled for use on board ORV Sagar Kanya for the BOBMEX- Pilot experiment is described along with some representative results. Wherever possible, Woods Hole's IMET recommendations for meteorological sensors for applications in the marine environment have been followed to keep our measurements in par with international standards. The sensors were tested during the BOBMEX-Pilot experiment and all sensors worked well. Velocity, humidity and temperature data have been successfully collected using fast sensors. It is shown that the component due to the ship's pitching motion can be removed from the measured vertical velocity by making use of an accelerometer. This makes it possible to calculate the surface fluxes by direct methods.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Meteorological instrument;air-sea flux.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Bhat" fname="G. S." isfellow="0">G. S. Bhat</author>
					<author lname="Ameenulla" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Ameenulla</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Atmospheric Boundary Layer Characteristics during BOBMEX-Pilot Experiment</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0229-0237</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The atmospheric boundary layer characteristics observed during the BOBMEX-Pilot experiment are reported. Surface meteorological data were acquired continuously through an automatic weather monitoring system and manually every three hours. High resolution radiosondes were launched to obtain the vertical thermal structure of the atmosphere. The study area was convectively active, the SSTs were high, surface air was warm and moist, and the surface air moist static energy was among the highest observed over the tropical oceans. The mean sea air temperature difference was about $1.25^\circ C$ and the sea skin temperature was cooler than bucket SST by $0.5^\circ C$. The atmospheric mixed layer was shallow, fluctuated in response to synoptic conditions from 100 m to 900 m with a mean around 500 m.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Marine boundary layer;air-sea coupling.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bhat" fname="G. S." isfellow="0">G. S. Bhat</author>
					<author lname="Ameenulla" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Ameenulla</author>
					<author lname="Venkataramana" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Venkataramana</author>
					<author lname="Sengupta" fname=" K." isfellow="0">K. Sengupta</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Inertial-Dissipation flux measurements over south Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX-- Pilot experiment</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0239-0247</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This paper describes measurement of air-sea parameters and estimation of sensible and latent heat fluxes by the ``Inertial-Dissipation'' technique over south Bay of Bengal. The data were collected on ORV Sagar Kanya during BOBMEX-Pilot cruise during the period 23rd October 1998 to 12th November 1998 over south Bay of Bengal. The fluxes are estimated using the data collected through fast response sensors namely Gill anemometer, Sonic anemometer and IR Hygrometer. In this paper the analyses carried out for two days, one relatively cloud free day on November 3rd and the other cloudy with rain on November 1st, are presented. Sea surface and air temperatures are higher on November 3rd than on November 1st. Sensible heat flux for both the days does not show any significant variation over the period of estimation, whereas latent heat flux is more for November 3rd than November 1st. An attempt is made to explain the variation of latent heat flux with a parameter called thermal stability on the vapor transfer from the water surface, which depends on wind speed and air to sea surface temperature difference.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Planetary boundary layer;air-sea flux;turbulence.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Venkataramana" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Venkataramana</author>
					<author lname="SenGupta" fname="K." isfellow="0">K. SenGupta</author>
					<author lname="Bhat" fname="G. S." isfellow="0">G. S. Bhat</author>
					<author lname="Ameenulla" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Ameenulla</author>
					<author lname="Raju" fname="J. V. S." isfellow="0">J. V. S. Raju</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>BOBMEX-98 Pilot: Measurement and analysis of incoming shortwave radiation data</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0249-0254</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Empirical formulae for estimation of hourly incoming shortwave radiation over the Indian Ocean under different cloud amounts have been developed by using the pyranometer measurements of the incoming solar radiation and the cloud observations during BOBMEX Pilot (October - November 1998) cruise.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Radiation;cloud;empirical formulae.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Gopala Reddy" fname="K." isfellow="0">K. Gopala Reddy</author>
					<author lname="Sree Ram" fname="P." isfellow="0">P. Sree Ram</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Thermohaline structure and circulation in the upper layers of the southern Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX-Pilot (October -- November 1998)</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0255-0265</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Hydrographic data collected on board ORV Sagar Kanya in the southern Bay of Bengal during the BOBMEX-Pilot programme (October - November 1998) have been used to describe the thermohaline structure and circulation in the upper 200 m water column of the study region. The presence of seasonal Inter-Tropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ) over the study area, typically characterized with enhanced cloudiness and flanked by the respective east/northeast winds on its northern part and west/southwest winds on its southern part, has led to net surface heat loss of about 55 W/$m^2$. The sea surface dynamic topography relative to 500 db shows that the upper layer circulation is characterised by a cyclonic gyre encompassing the study area. The eastward flowing Indian Monsoon Current (IMC) between $5^\circ $ N and $7^\circ $ N in the south and its northward branching along ${87}^\circ $ E up to ${13}^\circ $ N appear to feed the cyclonic gyre. The Vessel-Mounted Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler (VM-ADCP) measured currents confirm the presence of the cyclonic gyre in the southern Bay of Bengal during the withdrawing phase of the southwest monsoon from the northern/central parts of the Bay of Bengal.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Bay of Bengal;thermohaline circulation;Indian Monsoon Current;BOBMEX.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Ramesh Babu" fname="V." isfellow="0">V. Ramesh Babu</author>
					<author lname="Murty" fname="V. S. N." isfellow="0">V. S. N. Murty</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="L. V. G." isfellow="0">L. V. G. Rao</author>
					<author lname="Prabhu" fname="C. V." isfellow="0">C. V. Prabhu</author>
					<author lname="Tilvi" fname="V." isfellow="0">V. Tilvi</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Diurnal variability of upper ocean temperature and heat budget in the southern Bay of Bengal during October -- November, 1998 (BOBMEX-Pilot)</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0267-0277</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Time-series data on upper-ocean temperature, Vessel-Mounted Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler (VM-ADCP) measured currents and surface meteorological parameters have been obtained for the first time in the southern Bay of Bengal at $7^\circ N, 10^\circ $ N, and $13^\circ $ N locations along $87^\circ $ E during October - November, 1998 under BOBMEX-Pilot programme. These data have been analysed to examine the diurnal variability of upper oceanic heat budget and to estimate the eddy diffusivity coefficient of heat in the upper layer. Diurnal variation of near-surface temperature is typical at northern location ($13^\circ $ N) with a range of $0.5^\circ $ C while the diurnal range of temperature is enhanced to $0.8^\circ $ C at the central location ($10^\circ $ N) due to intense solar radiation (1050 W/ ${\rm m}^2$), clear skies and low wind speeds. At the southern location ($7^\circ $ N), the diurnal variation of temperature is atypical with the minimum temperature occurring at 2000 hrs instead of at early morning hours. In general, the diurnal curve of temperature penetrated up to 15 to 20 m with decreasing diurnal range with depth. The VM-ADCP measured horizontal currents in the upper ocean were predominantly easterly/northeasterly at southern location, north/northerly at central location and northwesterly at northern location, thus describing a large-scale cyclonic gyre with the northward meridional flow along $87^\circ $ E. The magnitudes of heat loss at the surface due to air-sea heat exchanges and in the upper 50 m layer due to vertical diffusion of heat are highest at the southern location where intense convective activity followed by overcast skies and synoptic disturbance prevailed in the lower atmosphere. This and the estimated higher value ($0.0235 m^2/s$) of eddy diffusivity coefficient of heat in the upper ocean (0-50 m depth) suggest that 1-D processes controlled the upper layer heat budget at the southern location. On the other hand, during the fair weather conditions, at the central and northern locations, the upper layer gained heat energy, while the sea surface lost (gained) heat energy at northern (central) location. This and lower values of eddy diffusivity coefficient of heat (0.0045 and $0.0150m^2 /s$) and the northward intensification of horizontal currents at these locations suggest the greater role of horizontal heat advection over the 1-D processes in the upper ocean heat budget at these two locations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Bay of Bengal;upper ocean heat budget;BOBMEX;eddy diffusivity of heat.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Murty" fname="V. S. N." isfellow="0">V. S. N. Murty</author>
					<author lname="Ramesh Babu" fname="V." isfellow="0">V. Ramesh Babu</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="L. V. G." isfellow="0">L. V. G. Rao</author>
					<author lname="Prabhu" fname="Charuta. V." isfellow="0">Charuta. V. Prabhu</author>
					<author lname="Tilvi" fname="V." isfellow="0">V. Tilvi</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Controls of dimethyl sulphide in the Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX-Pilot cruise 1998</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0279-0283</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The air-sea exchange is one of the main mechanisms maintaining the abundances of trace gases in the atmosphere. Some of these, such as carbon dioxide and dimethyl sulphide (DMS), will have a bearing on the atmospheric heat budget. While the former facilitates the trapping of radiation (greenhouse effect) the latter works in the opposite direction through reflectance of radiation back into space by sulphate aerosols that form from oxidation of DMS in atmosphere. Here we report on the first measurements made on DMS in the Bay of Bengal and the factors regulating its abundance in seawater. Phytoplankton alone does not seem to control the extent of DMS concentrations. We find that changes in salinity could effectively regulate the extent of DMSP production by marine phytoplankton. In addition, we provide the first ever evidence to the occurrence of DMS precursor, DMSP, in marine aerosols collected in the boundary layer. This suggests that the marine aerosol transport of DMSP will supplement DMS gaseous evasion in maintaining the atmospheric non-sea salt sulphur budget.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Dimethyl sulphide;air-sea exchange;BOBMEX;Bay of Bengal;aerosols.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Shenoy" fname="D. M." isfellow="0">D. M. Shenoy</author>
					<author lname="Dileep Kumar" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Dileep Kumar</author>
					<author lname="Sarma" fname="V. V. S. S." isfellow="0">V. V. S. S. Sarma</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Marine boundary layer simulation and verification during BOBMEX-Pilot using NCMRWF model</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0285-0292</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A global spectral model (T80L18) that is operational at NCMRWF is utilized to study the structure of the marine boundary layer over the Bay of Bengal during the BOBMEX-Pilot period. The vertical profiles of various meteorological parameters within the boundary layer are studied and verified against the available observations. The diurnal variation of various surface fields are also studied. The impact of non-local closure scheme for the boundary layer parameterisation is seen in simulation of the flow pattern as well as on the boundary layer structure over the oceanic region.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Marine boundary layer;parameterisation;BOBMEX;non-local closure;global model.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Basu" fname="Swati" isfellow="0">Swati Basu</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Numerical simulation of the marine boundary layer characteristics over the Bay of Bengal as revealed by BOBMEX-98 Pilot experiment</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0293-0303</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>An attempt has been made to study the marine boundary layer characteristics over Bay of Bengal using BOBMEX (Bay of Bengal and Monsoon Experiment) pilot experiment data sets, which was conducted between 23rd October and 12th November 1998 on board ORV Sagar Kanya. A one-dimensional multi- level atmospheric boundary layer with TKE-$\varepsilon $ closure scheme is employed to study the marine boundary layer characteristics. In this study two synoptic situations are chosen: one represents an active convection case and the other a suppressed convection. In the present article the marine boundary layer charac- teristics such as temporal evolution of turbulent kinetic energy, height of the boundary layer and the air- sea exchange processes such as sensible and latent heat fluxes, drag coefficient for momentum are simulated during both active and suppressed convection. Marine boundary layer height is estimated from the vertical profiles of potential temperature using the stability criterion. The model simulations are compared with the available observations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>BOBMEX;Turbulent Kinetic Energy;Marine Boundary Layer;flux.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Satyanarayana" fname="A. N. V." isfellow="0">A. N. V. Satyanarayana</author>
					<author lname="Mohanty" fname="U. C." isfellow="0">U. C. Mohanty</author>
					<author lname="Sam" fname="N. V." isfellow="0">N. V. Sam</author>
					<author lname="Basu" fname="Swati" isfellow="0">Swati Basu</author>
					<author lname="Lykossov" fname="V. N." isfellow="0">V. N. Lykossov</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Conserved variable analysis of the marine boundary layer and air-sea exchange processes using BOBMEX-pilot data sets</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0305-0314</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The present study is based on the observed features of the MBL (Marine Boundary Layer) during the Bay of Bengal and Monsoon Experiment (BOBMEX) - Pilot phase. Conserved Variable Analysis (CVA) of the conserved variables such as potential temperature, virtual potential temperature, equivalent potential temperature, saturation equivalent potential temperature and specific humidity were carried out at every point of upper air observation obtained on board ORV Sagar Kanya. The values are estimated up to a maximum of 4 km to cover the boundary layer. The Marine Boundary Layer Height is estimated from the conserved thermodynamic profiles. During the disturbed period when the convective activity is observed, the deeper boundary layers show double mixing line structures. An attempt is also made to study the oceanic heat budget using empirical models. The estimated short-wave radiation flux compared well with the observations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Marine Boundary Layer Height (MBLH);Convective Boundary Layer (CBL);Conserved Variable Analysis (CVA).</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sam" fname="N. V." isfellow="0">N. V. Sam</author>
					<author lname="Mohanty" fname="U. C." isfellow="0">U. C. Mohanty</author>
					<author lname="Satyanarayana" fname="A. N. V." isfellow="0">A. N. V. Satyanarayana</author>	
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="09" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Ocean circulation in the tropical Indo-Pacific during early Pliocene (5.6 - 4.2 Ma):  Paleobiogeographic and isotopic evidence</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0315-0328</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A Comparison of late Neogene planktic foraminferal biogeography and stable isotopic records of shallow dwelling and deep dwelling planktic foraminifera from DSDP sites 214 (Ninetyeast Ridge, northeast Indian Ocean) and 586B (ontong-Java Plateau, western Equatorial Pacific) provides a clue to the nature of the ocean circulation in the tropical Indo-Pacific during early Pliocene.</p>
					<p>The Present study reveals that the late Neogene planktic foraminiferal data from the eastern and western sides of the Indonesian Seaway are very similar. The only distinct inter-ocean difference however is the absence of Pulleniatina spectablis from the Indian Ocean. This species makes its first evolutionary appearance in the Equatorial Pacific at about 5.6 Ma (Early Gilbert reversed) and ranges up to 4.2 Ma (Top Conhiti subchron). The complete absence of Pulleniatina spectablis from the Indian Ocean is attributed to blocking of westward flow of tropical waters of the Pacific to the Indian Ocean resulting in a major change in the tropical Pacific and Indian oceans during 5.6 to 4.2 ma.</p>
					<p>In order to understand the nature of this blockage, isotopic depth ranking of selected planktic foraminifera and thus may be interpreted that the shallow sills that mark the Seaway in modern times were present as early as 5.6 Ma.</p>
					<p>The distribution of Pulleniatina spectablis throughout the Equatorial Pacific reveals that Modern Equatorial Pacific Under Current (Cromwell Current) flowing towards east at a depth of 200-300 m (which is also the depth habitat of  Pulleniatina spectablis) was present at the beginning of the Pliocene (5.6 Ma).</p>
					<p>As a dequel to the blocking of the Indonesian Seaway and the resultant interruption in the flow of central Equatorial Current System of the Pacific to the west there was an increase in the western Pacific Warm Pool Waters and strengthening of the gyral circulation in the Pacific and Indian Oceans. This eventually triggered the intensification of the Asian Monsoon System.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Planktic foraminifera;paleobiogeography;oxygen and carbon isotopes;Asian monsoon;ocean circulation.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Srinivasan" fname="M. S." isfellow="0">M. S. Srinivasan</author>
					<author lname="Sinha" fname="D. K." isfellow="0">D. K. Sinha</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Response of an ocean general circulation model to wind and thermodynamic forcings</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0329-0337</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The stretched-coordinate ocean general circulation model has been designed to study the observed variability due to wind and thermodynamic forcings. The model domain extends from $60^\circ N$ to $60^\circ S$ and cyclically continuous in the longitudinal direction. The horizontal resolution is $5^\circ \times 5^\circ$ and 9 discrete vertical levels. First a spin-up experiment has been done with ECMWF-AMIP 1979 January mean fields. The wind stress, ambient atmospheric temperature, evaporation and precipitation have been used in order to derive mechanical and thermodynamical surface forcings. Next, the experiment has been extended for another 30 years (3 cycles each of 10 year period) with varying surface boundary conditions (from January 1979 to December 1988 of ECMWF-AMIP monthly fields for each cycle) along with 120 years extended spin-up control run's results as initial conditions. The results presented here are for the last 10 years simulations. The preliminary results of this experiment show that the model is capable of simulating some of the general features and the pattern of interannual variability of the ocean.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>ECMWF;AMIP;WOCE;stretched-coordinate;interannual variability.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chakraborty" fname="A." isfellow="0">A. Chakraborty</author>
					<author lname="Upadhyaya" fname="H. C." isfellow="0">H. C.  Upadhyaya</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="O. P." isfellow="0">O. P. Sharma</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Precipitation reconstruction using ring-width chronology of Himalayan cedar from western Himalaya: Preliminary results</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0339-0345</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Himalayan cedar (Cedrus deodara (D. Don) G. Don) due to its long age and wide ecological amplitude in the Himalayan region has strong dendroclimatic potential. A well replicated ring-width chronology of it, derived from the ensemble of tree-ring samples of two adjacent homogeneous sites, has been used to reconstruct precipitation for the non-monsoon months (previous year October to concurrent May) back to AD 1171. This provides the first record of hydrological conditions for the western Himalayan region, India during the whole of the `Little Ice Age' and latter part of the `Medieval Warm Period'. The reconstruction revealed the wettest and the driest non-monsoon months during the fourteenth and the thirteenth centuries, respectively. The seventeenth century consistently recorded dry non-monsoon months in the western Himalayan region. Surplus precipitation, especially more pronounced since the 1950s, is recorded in the current century.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Tree rings;Himalayan cedar;Cedrus deodara;precipitation reconstruction;western Himalaya;India.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Yadav" fname="Ram. R." isfellow="0">Ram. R. Yadav</author>
					<author lname="Park" fname="Won-Kyu" isfellow="0">Won-Kyu Park</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Diverse signatures of deformation, pressure-temperature and anatexis in the Rayagada sector of the Eastern Ghats granulite terrane</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0347-0369</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The granulites and granitoids around Rayagada in the north central part of the Eastern Ghats belt display structural and petrological differences when compared to similar rocks from Chilka and Jenapore in the northern Eastern Ghats. The impress of $F_1$ deformation is almost erased while that of $F_3$ is muted. The metapelites have a restricted chemical range and are non-migmatitic. There are two varieties of leptynitic granitoids, one of which is interlayered with yet another S-type granite containing cordierite. The maximum recorded temperature from geothermometers is $780^\circ C$, but the magnitude of pressure is comparatively low, the highest value being 6.3 kbar. Another distinctive feature of the pressure- temperature record is the absence of evidence of decompression in the lower realms of pressure and temperature. Metamorphic reactions that could be identified indicate cooling, a noteworthy reaction being the sillimanite to andalusite transformation. Integration of data from pressure-temperature sensors suggest cooling at two pressures, 6 and 5 kbar. The generation of two types of granitoids from metapelites is interpreted to be due to intersection with solidus curves for pelitic and graywacke-like compositions, constrained by recent experiments, at 6 and 5 kbar. The first melting occurred on a prograde path while the second one was due to increase in temperature during exhumation at tectonic rates.</p>
					<p>Thus inspite of a broad similarity in the geodynamic scenario across the northern part of the Eastern Ghat belt, differences in exhumation rates and in style of melting were responsible for producing different signatures in the Rayagada granulite terrane.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Eastern Ghats granulites;cordierite granite;anatexis at two PT;exhumation rates.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sen" fname="S. K." isfellow="0">S. K. Sen</author>
					<author lname="Bhattacharya" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Bhattacharya</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Plain strain problem of poroelasticity using eigenvalue approach</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0371-0380</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A plain strain problem of an isotropic elastic liquid-saturated porous medium in poroelasticity has been studied. The eigenvalue approach using the Laplace and Fourier transforms has been employed and these transforms have been inverted by using a numerical technique. An application of infinite space with concentrated force at the origin has been presented to illustrate the utility of the approach. The displacement and stress components in the physical domain are obtained numerically. The results are shown graphically and can be used for a broad class of problems related to liquid-saturated porous media.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Plain strain;liquid-saturated porous;eigenvalue;Laplace and Fourier transforms.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="Rajneesh" isfellow="0">Rajneesh Kumar</author>
					<author lname="Miglani" fname="Aseem" isfellow="0">Aseem Miglani</author>
					<author lname="Garg" fname="N. R." isfellow="0">N. R. Garg</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Aeromagnetic study of peninsular India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0381-0391</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The degree sheet Aeromagnetic maps up to $17^\circ N$, acquired from the Geological Survey of India, have been manually redigitised at 6 minute intervals to study the long wavelength anomalies over peninsular India. These data have been collected at different survey altitude, epochs, flight line directions, etc. Great care has been taken to correct the total field map and remove the contribution due to the core field and prepare an accurate crustal anomaly map. For the first time, a regional map, depicting the NW-SE structural features north of the orthopyroxene isograd with the essentially E-W features to the south of it and revealing several well known structures, is presented. The analytical signal is calculated to delineate the source fields of these anomalies. It dramatically maps the charnockites and is able to delineate the orthopyroxene isograd. In the Dharwar region the magnetic signatures are associated with the intrusives/ iron ore bodies. Thus, we find that the source rocks of the aeromagnetic anomalies are the host province of charnockites in the SGT and the intrusives/iron ore bodies in the Dharwar belt. Gravity residuals are calculated and a tectonic map of the region is presented from the combined geopotential data.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Aeromagnetic;Southern Granulite Terrain;IGRF;analytical signal;metamorphism.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Harikumar" fname="P." isfellow="0">P. Harikumar</author>
					<author lname="Rajaram" fname="Mita" isfellow="0">Mita Rajaram</author>
					<author lname="Balakrishnan" fname="T. S." isfellow="0">T. S. Balakrishnan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="04" month="12" year="2000">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Editorial</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0393-0394</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Analysis of pathfinder SST algorithm for global and regional conditions</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0395-0405</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>As part of the Pathfinder program developed jointly by National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) and National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) a large database of in situ sea surface temperature (SST) measurements coincident with satellite data is now available to the user community. The Pathfinder Matchup Database (PMDB) is a multi-year, multi-satellite collection of coincident measurements from the Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer (AVHRR) and broadly distributed buoy data (matchups). This database allows the user community to test and validate new SST algorithms to improve the present accuracy of surface temperature measurements from satellites. In this paper we investigate the performance of a global Pathfinder algorithm to specific regional conditions. It is shown that for zenith angles less than $45^\circ $, the best-expected statistical discrepancy between satellite and buoy data is about $\sim 0.5 $ K. In general, the bias of the residuals (satellite - buoy) is negative in most regions, except in the North Atlantic and adjacent seas, where the residuals are always positive. A seasonal signal in SST residuals is observed in all regions and is strongest in the Indian Ocean. The channel-difference term used as a proxy for atmospheric water vapor correction is observed to be unresponsive for columnar water vapor values greater than 45 mm and high zenith angles. This unresponsiveness of the channels leads to underestimation of sea surface temperature from satellites in these conditions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sea surface temperature;AVHRR;satellite;Indian Ocean;matchup.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="Ajoy" isfellow="0">Ajoy Kumar</author>
					<author lname="Minnett" fname="P." isfellow="0">P. Minnett</author>
					<author lname="Podesta" fname="G." isfellow="0">G. Podesta</author>
					<author lname="Evans" fname="R." isfellow="0">R. Evans</author>
					<author lname="Kilpatrick" fname="K." isfellow="0">K. Kilpatrick</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Radiative Transfer Code: Application to the calculation of PAR</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0407-0413</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The production of carbon in the ocean, the so-called primary production, depends on various physico- biological parameters: the biomass and nutrient amounts in oceans, the salinity and temperature of the water and the light available in the water column. We focus on the visible spectrum of the solar radiation defined as the Photosynthetically Active Radiation (PAR). We developed a model (Chami et al. 1997) to simulate the behavior of the solar beam in the atmosphere and the ocean. We first describe the theoretical basis of the code and the method we used to solve the radiative transfer equation (RTE): the successive orders of scattering (SO). The second part deals with a sensitivity study of the PAR just above and below the sea surface for various atmospheric conditions. In a cloudy sky, we computed a ratio between vector fluxes just above the sea surface and spherical fluxes just beneath the sea surface. When the optical thickness of the cloud increases this ratio remains constant and around 1.29. This parameter is convenient to convert vector flux at the sea surface as retrieved from satellite to PAR. Subsequently, we show how solar radiation as vector flux rather than PAR leads to an underestimate of the primary production up to 40% for extreme cases.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>PAR;cloud coverage;primary productivity.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Emmanuel" fname="D." isfellow="0">D. Emmanuel</author>
					<author lname="Phillippe" fname="D." isfellow="0">D. Phillippe</author>
					<author lname="Malik" fname="C." isfellow="0">C. Malik</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Bio-optical properties of gelbstoff in the Arabian Sea at the onset of southwest monsoon</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0415-0425</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>As part of the German JGOFS Indian Ocean Programme, a cruise occurred in the Arabian Sea in May 1997 at the onset of the southwest monsoon. Data on gelbstoff, chlorophyll $a$ and tryptophan-like fluorescence as well as gelbstoff absorption were obtained. They indicate, that these optical parameters support the interpretation of hydrographic and biogeochemical conditions. Tryptophan-like fluorescence seems to be a useful indicator of changes in the constitution of the biomass.</p>
					<p>A comparison of gelbstoff absorption and fluorescence data from the upper 100 m reveals only a weak covariance. Special emphasis is given to the fit procedure used for retrieving the exponential slope $S$ of the spectral absorption coefficient. $S$ values with a mean of 0.016 $nm^{-1}$ are found in the 350 to 480 nm wavelength range. A mean slope $S$ set to the frequently reported value of 0.014 $nm^{-1}$ in the exponential description of gelbstoff absorption might lead to a systematic over/underestimation, and thus to systematic errors, if single-wavelength absorption values are extrapolated to other spectral regions on the basis of this parameter.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Gelbstoff;chlorophyll;absorption;fluorescence;tryptophan-like.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Breves" fname="Wiebke" isfellow="0">Wiebke Breves</author>
					<author lname="Reuter" fname="Rainer" isfellow="0">Rainer Reuter</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Seasonal variability of seasurface chlorophyll-a of waters around Sri Lanka</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0427-0432</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Remotely sensed data on ocean colour of waters surrounding Sri Lanka received from the Coastal Zone Colour Scanner (CZCS) are processed and analyzed. Raw data of 1 km resolution on relatively cloud free days during 1978--1986 are processed to produce sea surface chlorophyll maps within latitudes 4.5N--11N and longitudes 78E--85E, a region in the Indian Ocean surrounding Sri Lanka. The processed data include about 110 single day maps and composite averages for each month and season. The months of July, August and September are omitted in the calculation of averages due to insufficient data. The waters in the Gulf of Mannar and Palk Bay areas show high chlorophyll-a concentrations throughout the year. However, these high  values may represent other suspended particles and dissolved organic matter besides chlorophyll-a as this region is shallow (&lt; 100 m). Regions with high chlorophyll concentrations (&gt;0:5 mg $m^{-3}$) along the coast and western ocean region can be seen in the months of October and November, after the southwest monsoon period. As high surface chlorophyll concentrations may indicate high productivity, these regions need extensive measurements of primary production and also continuous monitoring of fish catches, during and after the southwest monsoon. Studies of particle composition in shallow water areas, in particular waters in Palk Bay and Gulf of Mannar, should be carried out in order to elucidate the effect of non-phytogenic.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Chlorophyll-a;CZCS;Sri Lanka;seasonal variability;fishery industry</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Yapa" fname="Kanthi K. A. S." isfellow="0">Kanthi K. A. S. Yapa</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Physical control of primary productivity on a seasonal scale in the central and eastern Arabian Sea</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0433-0441</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Using \textit{in situ} data collected during 1992--1997, under the Indian programme of Joint Global Ocean Flux Study (JGOFS), we show that the biological productivity of the Arabian Sea is tightly coupled to the physical forcing mediated through nutrient availability. The Arabian Sea becomes productive in summer not only along the coastal regions of Somalia, Arabia and southern parts of the west coast of India due to coastal upwelling but also in the open waters of the central region. The open waters in the north are fertilized by a combination of divergence driven by cyclonic wind stress curl to the north of the Findlater Jet and lateral advection of nutrient-rich upwelled waters from Arabia. Productivity in the southern part of the central Arabian Sea, on the other hand, is driven by advection from the Somalia upwelling. Surface cooling and convection resulting from reduced solar radiation and increased evaporation make the northern region productive in winter. During both spring and fall inter-monsoons, this sea remains warm and stratified with low production as surface waters are oligotrophic. Inter-annual variability in physical forcing during winter resulted in one-and-a-half times higher production in 1997 than in 1995.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Primary production;upwelling;winter cooling;Ekman-pumping, nutrient transport;Arabian Sea</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="kumar" fname="S. Prasanna" isfellow="0">S. Prasanna kumar</author>
					<author lname="Madhupratap" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Madhupratap</author>
					<author lname="kumar" fname="M. Dileep" isfellow="0">M. Dileep kumar</author>
					<author lname="Gauns" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Gauns</author>
					<author lname="Muraleedharan" fname="P. M." isfellow="0">P. M. Muraleedharan</author>
					<author lname="Sarma" fname="V. V. S. S." isfellow="0">V. V. S. S. Sarma</author>
					<author lname="Souza" fname="S. N. De" isfellow="0">S. N. De Souza</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Abundance and relationship of bacteria with transparent exopolymer particles during the 1996 summer monsoon in the Arabian Sea</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0443-0451</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Bacterial abundance and production, numbers, sizes and concentrations of transparent exopolymer particles (TEP) and total organic carbon (TOC) were measured during the 1996 summer monsoon to understand the relationship between TEP, the most labile particulate organic carbon, and bacteria. While high regional variability in the vertical distribution of TOC was discernible, TEP concentrations  were high in surface waters at 18--$20^\circ N$ along $64^\circ E$ with concentrations well over 25 mg alginic acid equivalents $1^{-1}$ due to upwelling induced productivity. Their concentrations decreased with depth and were lower between 200 and 500 m. Bacterial concentrations were up to $1.99 \times 10^8 1^{-1}$ in the surface waters and decreased by an order of magnitude or more at depths below 500 m. A better relationship has been found between bacterial abundance and concentrations of TEP than between bacteria and TOC, indicating that bacterial metabolism is fueled by availability of TEP in the Arabian Sea. Assuming a carbon assimilation of 33%, bacterial carbon demand (BCD) is estimated to be 1.017 to 4.035 g C $m^{-2} d^{-1}$ in the surface waters. The observed TEP concentrations appear to be sufficient in meeting the surface and  subsurface BCD in the northern Arabian Sea.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Bacteria;TEP;primary production;organic carbon;zooplankton;Arabian Sea</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Ramaiah" fname="N." isfellow="0">N. Ramaiah</author>
					<author lname="Sarma" fname="V. V. S. S." isfellow="0">V. V. S. S. Sarma</author>
					<author lname="Gauns" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Gauns</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="M. Dileep" isfellow="0">M. Dileep Kumar</author>
					<author lname="Madhupratap" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Madhupratap</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A vertically resolved model for phytoplankton aggregation</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0453-0469</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This work presents models of the vertical distribution and flux of phytoplankton aggregates, including changes with time in the distribution of aggregate sizes and sinking speeds. The distribution of sizes is described by two parameters, the mass and number of aggregates, which greatly reduces the computational cost of the models. Simple experiments demonstrate the effects of aggregation on the timing and depth distribution of primary production and export. A more detailed ecological model is applied to sites in the Arabian Sea; it demonstrates that aggregation can be important for deep sedimentation even when its effect on surface concentrations is small, and it presents the difference in timing between settlement of aggregates and fecal pellets.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Model;phytoplankton;aggregation;Arabian Sea.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kriest" fname="Iris" isfellow="0">Iris Kriest</author>
					<author lname="Evans" fname="Geoffrey T." isfellow="0">Geoffrey T. Evans</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Seasonal controls on surface $pCO_2$ in the central and eastern Arabian Sea</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0471-0479</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The variability in partial pressure of carbon dioxide ($pCO_2$) and its control by biological and physical processes in the mixed layer (ML) of the central and eastern Arabian Sea during inter-monsoon, northeast monsoon, and southwest monsoon seasons were studied. The ML varied from 80--120 m during NE monsoon, 60--80 m and 20--30 m during SW- and inter-monsoon seasons, respectively, and the variability resulted from different physical processes. Significant seasonal variability was found in $pCO_2$ levels. During SW monsoon, coastal waters contain two contrasting regimes; (a) $pCO_2$ levels of 520--685 $\mu$atm were observed in the SW coast of India, the highest found so far from this region, driven by intense upwelling and (b) low levels of $pCO_2$ ($266 \mu$atm) were found associated with monsoonal fresh water influx. It varied in ranges of 416--527 $\mu$atm and 375--446 $\mu$atm during inter- and NE monsoon, respectively, in coastal waters with higher values occurring in the north. The central Arabian Sea $pCO_2$ levels were 351--433, 379--475 and 385--432 $\mu$atm during NE- inter and SW monsoon seasons, respectively. The mixed layer $pCO_2$ relations with temperature, oxygen, chlorophyll $a$ and primary production revealed that the former is largely regulated by physical processes during SW- and NE monsoon whereas both physical and biological processes are important in inter-monsoon. Application of Louanchi \textit{et al} (1996) model revealed that the mixing effect is the dominant during monsoons, however, the biological effect is equally significant during SW monsoon whereas thermodynamics and fluxes influence during inter-monsoons.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Carbon dioxide;productivity;thermodynamics;mixing;flux;Arabian Sea</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Sarma" fname="V. V. S. S." isfellow="0">V. V. S. S. Sarma</author>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="M. Dileep" isfellow="0">M. Dileep Kumar</author>
					<author lname="Gauns" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Gauns</author>
					<author lname="Madhupratap" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Madhupratap</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>350 ka organic $\delta^{13}C$ record of the monsoon variability on the Oman continental margin, ArabianSea</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0481-0489</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The stable isotope compositions of sedimentary organic carbon and content of organic carbon for sediment cores recovered at two sites (sites 724C and 725C) during Ocean Drilling Program (ODP) Leg. 117 on the Oman continental margin are used to document variability of the monsoon winds for the past 350 ka. Although both sites have a mean $\delta^{13}C$ value of $-20.1%$, three zones depleted in $^{13}C$ are observable at site 724C during isotope stages 3, 8 and 10, while only one zone is recognizable at site 725C. Increased coastal upwelling during isotope stage 3 owing to intense SW monsoon winds resulted in higher concentration of $CO_2$ in the water column causing the formation of organic matter that was depleted in $^{13}C$. The other two zones deposited during oxygen isotope stages 8 and 10, which are also characterized by low values of organic carbon, nitrogen and C/N ratios, could be attributed to the dilution by terrestrial material derived from paleosol by transported by northwesterlies. Because of utilization of $^{13}C$ enriched dissolved $CO_2$ during the last glacial maximum Holocene sedimentary organic materials are depleted in $^{13}C$ relative to the the fomer. The content of residues organic carbon (ROC) is higher at site 724C (with an average of $2.3 \pm 1.2%$) relative to site 725C, which averages to $0.9 \pm 0.4%$ probably because of differences in the degree of preservation. Organic material deposited at site 725C has undergone more degradation relative to site 724C as reflected by a systematic downcore decrease in $^{13}C$ resulting from a loss of $^{13}C$ enriched organic compounds. Owing to lack of good chronology at site 725C, a zone that is characterized by low $\delta^{13}C$ values it could not be correlated with the other three zones observed at Site 724C.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Stable carbon isotopes;organic carbon;monsoon;Pleistocene</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Muzuka" fname="Alfred N. N." isfellow="0">Alfred N. N. Muzuka</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>4D-Var data assimilation system for a coupled physical biological model</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0491-0502</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A 3-compartment model of phytoplankton growth dynamics has been coupled with a primitive-equation circulation model to better understand and quantify physical and biological processes in the Adriatic Sea. This paper presents the development and application of a data assimilation procedure based on optimal control theory. The aim of the procedure is to identify a set of model coefficient values that ensures the best fit between data and model results by minimizing a function that measures model and data discrepancies. In this sense, twin experiments have been successfully implemented in order to have a better estimation of biological model parameters and biological initial conditions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Data assimilation;parameter estimation;bio-physical model.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Lellouche" fname="J. M." isfellow="0">J. M. Lellouche</author>
					<author lname="Ouberdous" fname="M." isfellow="0">M. Ouberdous</author>
					<author lname="Eifler" fname="W." isfellow="0">W. Eifler</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A coupled physical-biological-chemical model for the Indian Ocean</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0503-0537</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A coupled physical-biological-chemical model has been developed at C-MMACS. for studying the time- variation of primary productivity and air-sea carbon-dioxide exchange in the Indian Ocean. The physical model is based on the Modular Ocean Model, Version 2 (MOM2) and the biological model describes the nonlinear dynamics of a 7-component marine ecosystem. The chemical model includes dynamical equation for the evolution of dissolved inorganic carbon and total alkalinity. The interaction between the biological and chemical model is through the Redfield ratio. The partial pressure of carbon dioxide $pCO_2$ of the surface layer is obtained from the chemical equilibrium equations of Peng \textit{et al} 1987. Transfer coefficients for air-sea exchange of $CO_2$ are computed dynamically based on the wind speeds. The coupled model reproduces the high productivity observed in the Arabian Sea off the Somali and Omani coasts during the Southwest (SW) monsoon. The entire Arabian Sea is an outgassing region for $CO_2$   in spite of high productivity with transfer rates as high as 80 m-mol $C/m^2/day$ during SW monsoon near the Somali Coast on account of strong winds.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Coupled ocean model;Indian Ocean;carbon flux;marine preductivity;JGOFS.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Swathi" fname="P. S." isfellow="0">P. S. Swathi</author>
					<author lname="Sharada" fname="M. K." isfellow="0">M. K. Sharada</author>
					<author lname="Yajnik" fname="K. S." isfellow="0">K. S. Yajnik</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0539-0544</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0545-0548</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0549-0551</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="110">
		<issue inum="01" month="03" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Seismically constrained two-dimentional crustal thermal structure of the Cambay basin</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0008</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The temperature field within the crust is closely related to tectonic history as well as many othergeological processes inside the earth. Therefore, knowledge of the crustal thermal structure of a region is of great importance for its tectonophysical studies. This work deals with the two-dimensional thermal modelling to delineate the crustal thermal structure along a 230 km long Deep Seismic Sounding (DSS) profile in the north Cambay basin. In this work P-wave velocities obtained from the DSS studies have been converted into heat generation values for the computation of temperature distribution. The model result reveals the Curie isotherm at a depth of $\approx 22$ km and Moho temperature at around $900^\Circ $C.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cambay basin;P-wave velocity;heat flow;heat generation;2-D modelling;crustal thermal structure;Mohodepth;Curie isotherm.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Thiagarajan" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Thiagarajan</author>
					<author lname="Ramana" fname="D. V." isfellow="0">D. V. Ramana</author>
					<author lname="Rai" fname="S. N." isfellow="0">S. N. Rai</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Earthquake source model using strong motion displacement as response of finite elastic media</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0009-0023</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The strong motion displacement records available during an earthquake can be treated as the response of the earth as the a structural system to unknown forces acting at unknown locations. Thus, if the part of the earth participating in ground motion is modelled as a known finite elastic medium, one can attempt to model the source location and forces generated during an earthquake as an inverse problem in structural dynamics. Based on this analogy, a simple model for the basic earthquake source is proposed. The unknown source is assumed to be a sequence of impulses acting at locations yet to be found. These unknown impulses and their locations are found using the normal mode expansion along with a minimization of mean square error. The medium is assumed to be finite, elastic, homogeneous, layered and horizontal with a specific set of boundary conditions. Detailed results are obtained for Uttarkashi earthquake. The impulse locations exhibit a linear structure closely associated with the causative fault. The results obtained are shown to be in good agreement with reported values. The proposed engineering model is then used to simulate the acceleration time histories at a few recording stations. The earthquake source in terms of a sequence of impulses acting at different locations is applied on a 2D finite elastic medium and acceleration time histories are found using finite element methods. The synthetic accelerations obtained are in close match with the recorded accelerations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Strong motion;array data;normal mode;elastic medium;earthquake source;mean square error</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Iyengar" fname="R. N." isfellow="0">R. N. Iyengar</author>
					<author lname="Agrawal" fname="Shailesh K. R." isfellow="0">Shailesh K. R. Agrawal</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Gravity inferred subsurface structure of Gadwal Schist belt, Andhra Pradesh</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0025-0032</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Detailed gravity data collected across the Gadwal schist belt in the state of Andhra Pradesh show an  8.4 mgal residual gravity anomaly associated with meta-sediments/volcanics of the linear NNW--SSE trending schist belt that shows metamorphism from green schist to amphibolite facies. This schist belt is flanked on either side by the peninsular gneissic complex. The elevation and slab Bouguer corrected residual gravity profile data were interpreted using 2-D prism models. The results indicate a synformal structure having a width of 1.8 km at the surface, tapering at a depth of about 2.6 km with a positive density contrast of 0.15 gm/cc with respect to the surrounding peninsular gneissic complex.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Schist belt;subsurface structure;gravity-inferred basement</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ramadass" fname="G." isfellow="0">G. Ramadass</author>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="I. B. Ramaprasada" isfellow="0">I. B. Ramaprasada Rao</author>
					<author lname="Srinivasulu" fname="N." isfellow="0">N. Srinivasulu</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Finite element concept to derive isostatic residual maps - Application to Gorda Plate and Sierra Nevada regions</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0033-0038</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A new space-domain operator based on the shape function concept of finite element analysis has been developed to derive the residual maps of the Gorda Plate of western United States. The technique does not require explicit assumptions on isostatic models. Besides delineating the Gorda Plate boundary, the residual maps exhibit a close match both in their anomaly patterns and magnitudes with previously computed residual maps based on the theory of isostasy.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Finite element concept;isostatic anomaly;Gorda Plate;Sierra Nevada</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mallick" fname="K." isfellow="0">K. Mallick</author>
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">K. K. Sharma</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Geochemistry of sericite deposits at the base of the Paleoproterozoic Aravalli Supergroup, Rajasthan, India: Evidence for metamorphosed and metasomatised Precambrian Paleosol</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0039-0061</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Fine grained sericite deposits occur at the interface between Archean Mewar Gneiss Complex and the Proterozoic Aravalli Supergroup independent of shearing. They show a gradational contact with the basement granites and gneisses and a sharp contact with the overlying quartz pebble conglomeratic quartzites. Rip-up clasts of these sericite schists are found in the overlying conglomerates. The sericite schists are rich in sericite towards the top and contain chlorite towards the base. The sericite in these schists was formed by metasomatic alteration of kyanite and not from the feldspars of the basement granitoids and gneisses. Uni-directional variations of $SiO_2$ and $Al_2O_3$ , high $Al_2O_3$ content (&gt;30%), positive correlation between $Al_2O_3$ and $TiO_2$ , Ti/Al and Ti/Zr ratios, high pre-metasomatic chemical  indices of alteration (&gt;90), and enrichment of heavy rare earth elements relative to the parent granites and gneisses---all these chemical characteristics combined with field evidence suggest that the sericite schists are formed from a paleosol protolith, which developed on Archean basement between 2.5 and $\sim 2.1$ Ga in the Precambrian of Rajasthan. The superimposed metasomatic alteration restricts the use of $Fe^{2+} /Ti$ and $Fe^{3+} //Ti$ ratios of these paleosols for interpretation of $PO_2$ conditions in the atmosphere.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Paleoproterozoic;Aravalli Supergroup;paleosols;geochemistry;weathering indices;trace and REE compositions</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Sreenivas" fname="B." isfellow="0">B. Sreenivas</author>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="A. B." isfellow="0">A. B. Roy</author>
					<author lname="Srinivasan" fname=" R." isfellow="0">R. Srinivasan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Are Majhgawan-Hinota pipe rocks truly group-I kimberlite?</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0063-0076</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The diamond bearing pipe rocks in Majhgawan–Hinota (more than four pipes) occur as intrusives in sandstones of Kaimur Group. These Proterozoic ($974\pm 30–1170 \pm 20 Ma$) intrusive rocks, occupying the southeastern margin of Aravalli craton, were called as `micaceous kimberlite' in tune with the reported kimberlite occurrences from other parts of the world. Judging from the definition of kimberlite, as approved by the IUGS Subcommission on Systematics of Igneous Rocks, it is not justified to call these rocks as `micaceous kimberlite'. Rather the mineralogical assemblages such as absence of typomorphic mineral monticellite (primary), abundance of phlogopite cognate, frequent presence of barite and primary carbonate mostly as calcite coupled with ultrapotassic and volatile-rich (dominantly $H_2 O$) nature and high concentration of incompatible elements (such as Ba, Zr, Th, U), low Th/U ratios, low REE and no Eu-anomaly clearly indicate a close similarity with that of South African orangeites. Thus orangeites of Proterozoic age occur outside the Kaapvaal craton of South Africa which are much younger (200 Ma to 110 Ma) in age.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Pipe rocks;mineralogy;chemistry;Proterozoic age;kimberlite;orangeite;Majhgawan–Hinota;Madhya Pradesh.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shanker" fname="Ravi" isfellow="0">Ravi Shanker</author>
					<author lname="Nag" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Nag</author>
					<author lname="Ganguly" fname="A." isfellow="0">A. Ganguly</author>
					<author lname="Absar" fname="A." isfellow="0">A. Absar</author>
					<author lname="Rawat" fname="B. P." isfellow="0">B. P. Rawat</author>
					<author lname="Singh" fname="G. S." isfellow="0">G. S. Singh</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Retrieval of vertical wind profiles during monsoon from satellite observed winds over the Indian Ocean using complex EOF analysis</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0077-0086</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The aim of this paper is to study the feasibility of deriving vertical wind profiles from current satellite observations. With this aim, we carried out complex empirical orthogonal function (CEOF) analysis of a large number of radiosonde observations of wind profiles over the Indian Ocean during the monsoon months. It has been found that the first two CEOFs explain 67% of the total variance in wind fields. While the first principal component is well correlated with the winds at 850 mb ($r= 0.80$), the second one is highly correlated with winds at 200 mb ($r= 0.89$). This analysis formed the basis of a retrieval algorithm which ensures the retrieval of vertical profiles of winds using satellite tracked cloud motion vector winds. Under the assumption that accurate measurements of wind are available at the above mentioned levels, the r.m.s. error of retrieval of each component of wind is estimated to range between $2ms^{-1}$ and $6ms^{-1}$ at different levels, which is much less than the natural variance of winds at these levels. For a better visualization of retrieval, we have provided retrieved and true wind profiles side by side for four typical synoptic conditions during the monsoon season.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Complex EOF analysis;cloud motion vector winds;wind profiles;retrieval; monsoon.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kishtawal" fname="C. M." isfellow="0">C. M. Kishtawal</author>
					<author lname="Basu" fname="Sujit" isfellow="0">Sujit Basu</author>
					<author lname="Karthikeyan" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Karthikeyan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Occurrence of heavy rainfall around the confluence line in monsoon disturbances and its importance in causing floods</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0087-0094</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>It is well known that heavy rainfall occurs in the southwestern sector of the monsoon depressions due to strong convergence in that sector. By examining the rainfall distribution associated with the monsoon disturbances (lows and depressions) in one of the central Indian river basins, `Godavari', the author found that when the disturbance-centre is away from the basin, heavy rainfall may also occur in the basin area close to the confluence line and cause severe floods in the river. The confluence line is the zone of convergence between the northeasterlies to the west of the disturbance centre and the monsoon westerlies. This study further reveals the importance of the position and movement of the confluence line with respect to the basin, on which the intensity and the raising period of the resulting flood depend.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Monsoon disturbances;confluence line;heavy rainfall, floods.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Rao" fname="G. Nageswara" isfellow="0">G. Nageswara Rao</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>	
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="06" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Marine  biogeochemistries of Be and Al:  A study based on cosmogenic $^{10}Be$, Be and Al in marine calcite, aragonite, and opal</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0095-0102</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The geochemical behaviors of Be and Al in ocean waters have been successfully studied in recent years using natural, cosmogenic, radioactive $^{10}Be$ and $^{26}Al$ as tracers. The present day dissolved concentrations and distribution of the stable and radioactive isotopes of Be and Al in ocean waters have revealed their short residence times and appreciable effects of exchange uxes at the coastal and ocean-sediment interfaces. It follows that concentrations of these particle-active elements must have varied in the past with temporal changes in climate, biological productivity and aeolian ux of continental detritus to the oceans. We therefore investigated the feasibility of extending the measurements of Be and Al isotope concentrations in marine systems to the $10^3-10^6 y$ BP time scale. We report here the discovery of significant amounts of intrinsic Be and Al in marine foraminiferal calcite and coral aragonite, and of Al in opal (radiolarians) and aragonite (coral), which makes it possible to determine $^{10}Be/Be$ and $^{26}Al/Al$ in oceans in the past. We also report measured $^{10}Be/ ^9Be$ in foraminiferal calcite in Pacific Ocean cores, which reveal that the concentrations and ratios of the stable and cosmogenic isotopes of Be and Al have varied signicantly in the past 30 ky. The implications of these results are discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cosmogenic $^{10}Be$;Be, Al marine geochemistry;aeolian Be, Al.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Dong" fname="Weiquan" isfellow="0">Weiquan Dong</author>
					<author lname="Lal" fname="Devendra" isfellow="0">Devendra Lal</author>
					<author lname="Ransom" fname="Barbara" isfellow="0">Barbara Ransom</author>
					<author lname="Berger" fname="Wolfgang" isfellow="0">Wolfgang Berger</author>
					<author lname="Caffee" fname="Marc W." isfellow="0">Marc W. Caffee</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>High Iridium concentration of alkaline rocks of Deccan and implications to K/T boundary</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0103-0110</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report here an unusually high concentration of iridium in some alkali basalts and alkaline rocks of Deccan region having an age of about 65Ma, similar to the age of the Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary. The alkali basalts of Anjar, in the western periphery of Deccan province, have irid-ium concentration as high as 178pg/g whereas the alkaline rocks and basalts associated with the Amba Dongar carbonatite complex have concentrations ranging between 8 and 80 pg/g. Some of these values are more than an order of magnitude higher than the concentration in the tholeiiticbasalts of Deccan, indicating the significance of alkaline magmatism in the iridium inventory at the Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary. Despite higher concentration, their contribution to the global inventory of iridium in the Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary clays remains small. The concentration of iridium in uorites from Amba Dongar was found to be &lt; 30 pg/g indicating that iridium is not incorporated during their formation in hydrothermal activity.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Carbonatite;Deccan;iridium;alkaline rocks;K/T boundary;Anjar;Amba Dongar</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="P. N." isfellow="0">P. N. Shukla</author>
					<author lname="Bhandari" fname="N." isfellow="0">N. Bhandari</author>
					<author lname="Das" fname="Anirban" isfellow="0">Anirban Das</author>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="A. D." isfellow="0">A. D. Shukla</author>
					<author lname="Ray" fname="J. S." isfellow="0">J. S. Ray</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Geochemistry and magnetostratigraphy of Deccan flows at Anjar, Kutch</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0111-0132</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Chemical analysis of nine Deccan flow basalts at Anjar, Kutch, western India, indicates that all,except the uppermost flow F-9, are alkaline. In their major and trace element composition, the alkali basalts resemble Ocean island basalts (OIB). Similarities of many diagnostic trace element ratios (e.g. Sm/Nd, Ba/Nb,Y/Nb and Zr/Nb) are similar to those found in the R\acute{e}union Island basalts. The uppermost basalt is tholeiitic and chemically resembles the least contaminated Deccan basalt (Ambenali type). The Anjar basalts have iridium concentration ranging between 2 and 178 pg/g. Some of these values are higher by about an order of magnitude compared to the Ir concentration in other basalts of the Deccan. A synthesis of chemical, palaeomagnetic and geochronologic data enables us to construct a chemical and magnetic stratigraphy for these flows.</p>
					<p>The three flows below the iridium enriched intertrappean bed (IT III) show normal magnetic polarity whereas all except one of the upper basalts show reversed magnetic polarity. The sequence seems to have started in polarity zones 31N and probably continued up to 28R or 27R. The results presented here support the view that Deccan volcanism in Kutch occurred on a time span of a few million years.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Anjar flows;K/T boundary;alkali basalts;magnetostratigraphy;geochemistry;ocean island basalts;R\acute{e}union plume.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="A. D." isfellow="0">A. D. Shukla</author>
					<author lname="Bhandari" fname="N." isfellow="0">N. Bhandari</author>
					<author lname="Kusumgar" fname="Sheela" isfellow="0">Sheela Kusumgar</author>
					<author lname="Shukla" fname="P. N." isfellow="0">P. N. Shukla</author>
					<author lname="Ghevariya" fname="Z. G." isfellow="0">Z. G. Ghevariya</author>
					<author lname="Gopalan" fname="K." isfellow="0">K. Gopalan</author>
					<author lname="Balaram" fname="V." isfellow="0">V. Balaram</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>No K/T boundary at Anjar, Gujarat, India: Evidence from magnetic susceptibility and carbon isotopes</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0133-0142</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The paper describes the variation pattern of magnetic susceptibility of Lameta sediments and isotopic variation of organic $^{13}C$ from Chui Hill, Bergi, Kholdoda, Pisdura and Girad. The susceptibility pattern and a negative carbon isotopic anomaly allows xation of the K/T boundary at these localities and they dier in these aspects from the inter-trappean sediments at Anjar.</p>
					<p>Paleomagnetic measurements of the Anjar sediment and the overlying basalt ow demonstrate reversed polarity. The Lameta sediments with dinosaur nests at Kheda and the overlying intertrappean sediments are of normal polarity</p>
					<p>The clay layers at Anjar, associated closely with Ir-enrichments, are strongly leached, rhyolitic bentonites containing low-quartz paramorphs after high-quartz with glass inclusions.</p>
					<p>It is concluded, that the inter-trappean lake deposits at Anjar were deposited in the early part of magnetochron 29R and are unrelated to the K/T boundary.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Iridium;rhyolites;paleomagnetics;Deccan;Lameta</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Hansen" fname="H. J." isfellow="0">H. J. Hansen</author>
					<author lname="Mohabey" fname="D. M." isfellow="0">D. M. Mohabey</author>
					<author lname="Toft" fname="P." isfellow="0">P. Toft</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>REE geochemistry of ore zones in the Archean auriferous schist belts of the eastern Dharwar craton, south India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0143-0159</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The eastern Dharwar Craton of southern India includes at least three $\sim 2700Ma$ supracrustal belts (schist belts) which have mesothermal, quartz-carbonate vein gold mineralization emplaced within the sheared metabasalts. In the Hutti and the Kolar schist belts, the host rocks are amphibolites and the ore veins have been anked by only a thin zone of biotitic alteration; in the Ramagiri belt, however, the host rocks to the veins have been a ected by more extensive but lower temperature alteration by uids. The rare earth element (REE) geochemistry of the host metabasalts, alteration zones, ore veins and the bulk sulfides separated from the ore veins and the alteration zones suggest that</p>
					<ul>
						<li>the REE chemistry of the immediate host rocks has been modified by uids which added LREE,</li>
						<li>the REE abundance of the ore veins vary with the amount of host rock fragments included in the veins,</li>
						<li>the sulfides formed during mineralization have significant REE concentration with patterns nearly identical to the ore veins and alteration zones and</li>
						<li>therefore the ore uids involved in gold mineralization here could be LREE enriched.</li>
					</ul>
					<p>Because alteration and mineralization involved addition of REE, more LREE compared to HREE, the uids could be of higher temperature origin. The initial Nd isotope ratios in the host rocks ($\varepsilon Nd$ calculated at 2700 Ma) showed a large variation ($+$8 to $-$4) and a deep crustal source for the uid REE seems likely. A crustal source for Pb and Os in the ore samples of Kolar belt has previously been suggested (Krogstad \textit {et al} 1995; Walker \textit {et al} 1989). Such a source for ore uids is consistent with a late Archean (2500Ma) accretionary origin for the terrains of the eastern Dharwar Craton.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>REE geochemistry, Archean, lode gold deposit, eastern Dharwar Craton</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Giritharan" fname="T. S." isfellow="0">T. S. Giritharan</author>
					<author lname="Rajamani" fname="V." isfellow="0">V. Rajamani</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Extreme heterogeneity in Sr isotope systematic in the Himalayan leucogranites: A possible mechanism of partial melting based on thermal modeling</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0161-0169</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The small leucogranite plutons occurring in linear belts in the Higher Himalayas have formed due to post-collision partial melting within the Himalayan crust. Several studies have documented that the Sr isotopic ratios in the granite bodies show chaotic variation and meaningful Rb-Sr isochron ages are dicult, if not impossible, to obtain. In tectonically overthickened crust, the depth-temperature prole (geotherm) remains strongly transient for the rst tens of millions of years. It is proposed here that the intersecting relations between the transient geotherms and activity-dependent solidus/melting curves may generate small pods of magma at di erent depths and at di erent times. Each of these pods will have its unique Sr isotopic ratios. Coalescence of   these small pods of magma without any e ective homogenization due to deformation-induced fast segregation, ascent and emplacement may lead to pluton-wide extreme heterogeneity in Sr isotopic ratios.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Himalayan leucogranites;partial melting;thermal model;Sr isotope ratio.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mukhopadhyay" fname="Dilip K." isfellow="0">Dilip K. Mukhopadhyay</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Estimation of source parameters of Chamoli Earthquake, India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0171-0177</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The devastating earthquake (mb $=$ 6.6) at Chamoli, Garhwal Himalaya, which occurred in the morning hours on 29th March 1999, was recorded on Delhi Strong Motion Accelerograph (DSMA) Network operated by the Central Building Research Institute, Roorkee. In this paper the source parameters of this event calculated from the Strong Motion Data are presented. The seismic moment for this event has been found to be of the order of $10^{25}$ dyne.cm and the moment mag- nitude has been calculated in the range of 6.53--6.69 at different stations. The stress drop and source radius for the earthquake are also calculated.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Chamoli earthquake;strong motion accelerograph;seismic moment;source radius;stress drop;moment magnitude.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Pandey" fname="Y." isfellow="0">Y. Pandey</author>
					<author lname="Dharmaraju" fname="R." isfellow="0">R. Dharmaraju</author>
					<author lname="Chauhan" fname="P. K. S." isfellow="0">P. K. S. Chauhan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Computing energy budget within a crop canopy from Penmann's formulae</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0179-0184</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Lhomme's model (1988a), that extended Penmann's formulae to a multi-layer model, is rede-fined as a function of micrometeorological and physiological profiles of crop canopy. The sources and sinks of sensible and latent heat uxes are assumed to lie on a fictitious plane called zero-displacement plane. Algorithms are given to compute sensible and latent heat ux densities. Per-formance of the algorithms is compared with that of earlier algorithms.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Latent heat flux;sensible heat flux;net radiation;aerodynamical resistance;boundary layer resistance;stomatal resistance.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Mohan" fname="Mahendra" isfellow="0">Mahendra Mohan</author>
					<author lname="Srivastava" fname="K. K." isfellow="0">K. K. Srivastava</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="09" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>$^{40}Ar-^{39}Ar$ age of carbonatite-alkaline magmatism in Sung Valley, Maghalaya, India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0185-0190</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>$^{40} Ar-^{39}Ar$ analyses of one alkali pyroxenite whole rock and two phlogopite separates of calcite carbonatites from the Sung Valley carbonatite-alkaline complex, which is believed to be a part of the Rajmahal-Bengal-Sylhet (RBS) ood basalt province, yielded indistinguishable plateau ages of $108.8 \pm 2.0Ma, 106:4 \pm 1.3 Ma$ and $107.5 \pm 1.4 Ma$, respectively. The weighted mean of these ages, $107.2 \pm 0.8 Ma$, is the time of emplacement of this complex. This implies that Sung Valley complex and probably other such complexes in the Assam-Meghalaya Plateau postdate the main ood basalt event (i.e., the eruption of tholeiites) in the RBS province by $\sim 10 Ma$.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>$^{40}Ar-^{39}Ar$ dating;carbonatite;Sung Valley;Rajmahal Traps;Kerguelen plume.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ray" fname="Jyotiranjan S." isfellow="0">Jyotiranjan S. Ray</author>
					<author lname="Pande" fname="Kanchan" isfellow="0">Kanchan Pande</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Development of micro-scale joints in volcanic rocks under thermal stress</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0191-0203</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Petrographic studies of samples of the Rajmahal basalt reveal a variety of microscopic joints within phenocrysts, which seem to have developed under the in uence of thermal stresses during cooling. The theoretical analysis shows that:</p>
					<ul>
						<li>thermal stresses develop in a system only under unsteady state of cooling,</li>
						<li>the stresses responsible for the development of joints are tensile in nature, and</li>
						<li>the magnitude of stresses increases with increasing rates of cooling.</li>
					</ul>
					<p>In order to understand the effects of cooling rate on the mode of jointing, analogue model experiments were performed by quenching melt films of organic, crystalline materials under varying cooling conditions. In experiments, non-branching linear joints developed at relatively lower rates of cooling by a process of sub-critical crack propagation. On the other hand, at higher rates of cooling the mechanism of crack propagation was essentially supercritical leading to the development of branching joints.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Tensile stress;jointing;crack propagation;cooling rate.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Samanta" fname="Susanta Kumar" isfellow="0">Susanta Kumar Samanta</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Scattering of a spherical pulse from a small inhomogeneity: Dilation and rotation</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0205-0213</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Perturbations in elastic constants and density distinguish a volume inhomogeneity from its homogeneous surroundings. The equation of motion for the first order scattering is studied in the perturbed medium. The scattered waves are generated by the interaction between the primary waves and the inhomogeneity. First order scattering theory is modified to include the source term generating the primary waves. The body force equivalent to the scattering source is presented in a convenient form involving the perturbations in wave velocities and gradient of density perturbation.</p>
					<p>A procedure is presented to study the scattering of a spherical pulse from a small inhomogeneity, in time domain. The size of inhomogeneity is assumed small as compared to its distance from source and receiver. No restrictions are placed on the positions of source, receiver and inhomogeneity. The dilatation and rotations are calculated for a pulse scattered from an arbitrary point in a spherical volume. The aggregate of the scattered phases from all the points of the inhomogeneity, reaching at a fixed receiver, gives the amount of scattering from the inhomogeneity. The interaction of both P and S waves with inhomogeneity are considered. Dilatation and rotations for scattering are obtained as integral expressions over the solid angle of inhomogeneity. These expressions are computed numerically, for hypothetical models. The effects of source (unit force) orientations, velocity and density perturbations, and size of inhomogeneity, on the scattered phases, are discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Scattering;inhomogeneity;spherical pulse;perturbations;dilatation;rotation</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Sharma" fname="M. D." isfellow="0">M. D. Sharma</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Dynamical problem of micropolar viscoelasticity</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0215-0223</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The dynamic problem in micropolar viscoelastic medium has been investigated by employing eigen value approach after applying Laplace and Fourier transformations. An example of infinite space with concentrated force at the origin has been presented to illustrate the application of the approach. The integral transforms have been inverted by using a numerical technique to obtain the displacement components, force stresses, couple stress and microrotation in the physical domain. The results for these quantities are given and illustrated graphically.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Micropolar;viscoelasticity;eigen value;Laplace and Fourier transforms.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kumar" fname="Rajneesh" isfellow="0">Rajneesh Kumar</author>
					<author lname="Choudhary" fname="Suman" isfellow="0">Suman Choudhary</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Utility of DMSP-SSM/I for integrated water vapour over the Indian seas</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0225-0229</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Recent algorithms for Special Sensor Microwave/Imager (DMSP-SSM/I) satellite data are used for estimating integrated water vapour over the Indian seas. Integrated water vapour obtained from these algorithms is compared with that derived from radiosonde observations at Minicoy and Port Blair islands. Algorithm-3 of Schlussel and Emery (1990) performed best. On the basis of this algorithm, distribution of integrated water vapour is determined during the monsoon depression (22nd{27th July, 1992) that formed over the Bay of Bengal.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>DMSP-SSM/I;integrated water vapour;IRS-P4.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Mahajan" fname="P. N." isfellow="0">P. N. Mahajan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Estimation of surface latent heat fluxes from IRS-P4/MSMR satellite data</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0231-0238</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The brightness temperatures of the Microwave sensor MSMR (Multichannel Scanning Microwave Radiometer) launched in May 1999 onboard Indian Oceansat-1 IRS-P4 are used to develop a direct retrieval method for latent heat ux by multivariate regression technique. The MSMR measures the microwave radiances at 8 channels at frequencies of 6.6, 10.7, 18 and 21 GHz at both vertical and horizontal polarizations. It is found that the surface LHF (Latent Heat Flux) is sensitive to all the channels. The coeficients were derived using the National Centre for Environmental Prediction (NCEP) reanalysis data of three months: July, September, November of 1999. The NCEP daily analyzed latent heat uxes and brightness temperatures observed by MSMR were used to derive the coeficients. Validity of the derived coeficients was checked with \textit {in situ} observations over the Indian Ocean and with NCEP analyzed LHF for global points. The LHF derived directly from the MSMR brightness temperature (Tb) yielded an accuracy of 35 watt/ $m^2$. LHF was also computed by applying bulk formula using the geophysical parameters extracted from MSMR. In this case the errors were higher apparently due to the errors involved in derivation of the geophysical parameters.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Multi-frequency Scanning Microwave Radiometer (MSMR);Latent heat flux (LHF);National Centre for Environmental Prediction (NCEP).</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Singh" fname="Randhir" isfellow="0">Randhir Singh</author>
					<author lname="Simon" fname="B." isfellow="0">B. Simon</author>
					<author lname="Joshi" fname="P. C." isfellow="0">P. C. Joshi</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Soil thermal properties at Kalpakkam in coastal south India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0239-0245</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Time series of soil surface and subsurface temperatures, soil heat ux, net radiation, air temperature and wind speed were measured at two locations in Kalpakkam, coastal southeast India. The data were analysed to estimate soil thermal di usivity, thermal conductivity, volumetric heat capacity and soil heat ux. This paper describes the results and discusses their implications.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Soil temperature, thermal conductivity, thermal diffusivity, soil heat flux.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Anandakumar" fname="K." isfellow="0">K. Anandakumar</author>
					<author lname="Venkatesan" fname="R." isfellow="0">R. Venkatesan</author>
					<author lname="Prabha" fname="Thara V." isfellow="0">Thara V. Prabha</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Influence of micrometeorological features on coastal boundary layer aerosol characteristics at the tropical station, Trivandrum</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0247-0265</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Characteristics of aerosols in the Atmospheric Boundary Layer (ABL) obtained from a bistatic CW lidar at Trivandrum for the last one decade are used to investigate the role of ABL micro- meteorological processes in controlling the altitude distribution and size spectrum. The altitude structure of number density shows three distinct zones depending on the prevailing boundary layer feature; viz, the well-mixed region, entertainment region and upper mixing region. In the lower altitudes vertical mixing is very strong (the well-mixed region) the upper limit of which is defined as aerosol-mixing height, is closely associated with the low level inversion. The aerosol mixing height generally lies in the range 150 to 400 m showing a strong dependence on the vertical eddy mixing processes in ABL. Above this altitude, the number density decreases almost exponentially with increase in altitude with a scale height of 0.5 --1.5 km. The aerosol mixing height is closely associated with the height of the Thermal Internal Boundary Layer (TIBL). Sea-spray aerosols generated as a result of the interaction of surface wind with sea surface forms an important component of mixing  region aerosols at this location. This component shows a non-linear dependence on wind speed. On an average, depending on the season, the mixing region contributes about 10--30% of the columnar aerosol optical depth (AOD) at $0.5 \mu m$ wavelength. A long term increasing trend ($\sim 2.8%$ per year) is observed in mixing region AOD from 1989 to 1997. A study on the development of the aerosols in the nocturnal mixing region shows that the convectively driven daytime altitude structure continues to persist for about 4--5 hrs. after the sunset and thereafter the altitude structure is governed by vertical structure of horizontal wind. Stratified aerosol layers associated with stratified turbulence is very common during the late night hours.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Boundary layer aerosols;mixing height;mixing region;turbulence;eddy transport;optical depth.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Parameswaran" fname="K." isfellow="0">K. Parameswaran</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="04" month="12" year="2001">
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Preface</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0267-0267</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Bhattacharya" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Bhattacharya</author>
					<author lname="Ganguly" fname="J." isfellow="0">J. Ganguly</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Earth support systems: Threatened? Why? What can we do?</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0269-0285</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The most important concept to emerge in the 20th century was the recognition that sustainability is threatened. A sustainable society is one that functions and lives in such harmony with earth systems that future generations will be able to function with equal or greater ease and the quality of life will in no way be diminished.</p>
					<p>Evidence of threats to sustainability is found in: global energy use; global climate change; availability of sufficient safe water; degradation of soil on agricultural lands; food production for a global population of 9,000 million by 2050; accelerated extinction rates and loss of biodiversity; human under- and over-nourishment; and the spread of diseases.</p>
					<p>Ignorance borne of alienation from nature deprives us of sensitivity to the threats human activities cause. Alienation may be traced to the agricultural revolution, but has become widespread and even inescapable for many with massive control of energy and the industrial revolution, dependence on machines, and urbanization. With the control of enough energy to dominate nature and the achievement of a high, but transient, level of wealth, a world view extolling growth - led by the highly industrialized nations, but now being emulated in the developing countries - has committed the world to an unsustainable path.</p>
					<p>Because of this, world societies must work to find practical "sustainability" world views to help guide our future choices. Wise choices will depend upon good scientiffic understanding and must be based upon a deep respect for the non-human world and a concern for the future. The environmental meaning of different world views, whether founded in the world religions or in non-religious philosophy, share a common concern to promote an equitable, harmonious, and sustainable relationship between humanity and nature. The similarities in pragmatic meaning in relation to nature of, e.g., Christian stewardship and Deep Ecology, illustrate this.</p>
					<p>Our attention must not be directed towards alternative symbolic or linguistic vocabularies, but toward the practical environmental commitments that different world views entail. Our problems have global reach and many of them are urgent, but they are not intrinsically unsolvable. We must seek ways to find and use common ground in the search for sustainability. We must work together, but remember that each of us contributes to the final outcome.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Earth systems;sustainability;world views;stewardship;Deep Ecology</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Reitan" fname="Paul H." isfellow="0">Paul H. Reitan</author>
					<author lname="Reitan" fname="Eric H." isfellow="0">Eric H. Reitan</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Partial melting of metavolcanics in amphibolite facies regional metamorphism</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0287-0291</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Metavolcanic rocks containing low-Ca amphiboles (gedrite, cummingtonite) and biotite can undergo substantial dehydration-melting. This is likely to be most prominent in Barrovian Facies Series (kyanite-sillimanite) and occurs at the same time as widespread metapelite dehydration- melting. In lower pressure facies series, metavolcanics will be represented by granulites rich in orthopyroxene when dehydration occurs at much lower temperatures than melting. In higher pressure facies series it is not well known whether metavolcanic rocks dehydrate or melt at temperatures lower or similar to that of metapelites.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Metavolcanics;gedrite;cummingtonite;biotite;dehydration-melting;granulites;orthopyroxene;experimental studies;amphibolite;Metapelite.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Thompson" fname="Alan Bruce" isfellow="0">Alan Bruce Thompson</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Some aspects of the role of intergranular fluids in the compositional evolution of metamorphic rocks</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0293-0303</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Minerals that react with each other during the progressive evolution of metamorphic terranes are not always in physical contact. As such, an "intergranular fluid" could play a major role in element transfer and chemical evolution. However, the nature of this uid and its specific role remains somewhat elusive. Recent experiments in our laboratory shed some light on the behavior of such a uid. Here we present a simple mathematical model which accounts for diffusion within crystals and fluid, solubility in the fluid and mass balance between the various reservoirs. The model elucidates the nature of element exchange between two minerals via the mediation of an intergranular fluid. It is shown that a coupling of thermodynamics and kinetics controls the evolution of the system and the concentration of an element in the intergranular fluid is a key parameter of interest.</p>
					<p>The results have important implications for standard tools of metamorphic petrology such as geothermometers and barometers, geospeedometry and the closure of isotopic systems. For example, homogeneity of mineral grains may be a poor criterion for equilibrium and the rim compositions of minerals showing diffusion zoning may be out of equilibrium with distant exchange partners, even in the presence of a uid in which transport is fast.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Intergranular fluid;metamorphism;diffusion;geothermometry;closure temperature.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chakraborty" fname="Sumit" isfellow="0">Sumit Chakraborty</author>
					<author lname="Dohmen" fname="Ralf" isfellow="0">Ralf Dohmen</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Reaction texture and Fe-Mg zoning in granulite garnet from S$\phi $strene Island, Antarctica: Modeling and constraint on the time scale of metamorphism during the Pan-African Collisional event</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0305-0312</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Garnets from the S$\phi $strene island, Antarctica, show reaction textures corresponding to two metamorphic episodes, one at c. 1000 Ma (M1) and the other at c. 500 Ma (M2). The latter is associated with a Pan-African tectono-metamorphic event that has been interpreted to represent a continent-continent collision followed by extensional collapse. Reaction-diffusion modeling of the compositional zoning of garnet associated with the development of reaction texture during M2 yields a time scale of $\sim $5--16 Myr for the duration of the peak of this overprinting metamorphism at $\sim 730\pm 20^\circ C$. The associated velocity of the reaction front is $\sim \sim 5.0--1.6 \mu m/Myr$. The inferred duration of peak metamorphism during the Pan-African event seems to be in good agreement with the available U-Pb SHRIMP ages of zircon and monazite that may be interpreted to have formed at the beginning and end stages of crystallization of granite during the metamorphic peak.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Time scale;tectono-metamorphism;diffusion;reaction</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ganguly" fname="J." isfellow="0">J. Ganguly</author>
					<author lname="Hensen" fname="B. J." isfellow="0">B. J. Hensen</author>
					<author lname="Cheng" fname="W." isfellow="0">W. Cheng</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Orogeny, migmatites and leucogranites: A review</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0313-0336</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The type of P-T-t path and availability of fluid ($H_2$O-rich metamorphic volatile phase or melt) are important variables in metamorphism. Collisional orogens are characterized by clockwise P-T evolution, which means that in the core, where temperatures exceed the wet solidus for common crustal rocks, melt may be present throughout a significant portion of the evolution. Field observations of eroded orogens show that lower crust is migmatitic, and geophysical observations have been interpreted to suggest the presence of melt in active orogens. A consequence of these results is that orogenic collapse in mature orogens may be controlled by a partially-molten layer that decouples weak crust from subducting lithosphere, and such a weak layer may enable exhumation of deeply buried crust. Migmatites provide a record of melt segregation in partially molten crustal materials and syn-anatectic deformation under natural conditions. Grain boundary ow and intra- and inter-grain fracture ow are the principal grain scale melt ow mechanisms. Field observations of migmatites in ancient orogens show that leucosomes occur oriented in the metamorphic fabrics or are located in dilational sites. These observations are interpreted to suggest that melt segregation and extraction are syntectonic processes, and that melt migration pathways commonly relate to rock fabrics and structures. Thus, leucosomes in depleted migmatites record the remnant permeability network, but evolution of permeability networks and amplification of anomalies are poorly understood. Deformation of partially molten rocks is accommodated by melt-enhanced granularow, and volumetric strain is accommodated by melt loss. Melt segregation and extraction may be cyclic or continuous, depending on the level of applied differential stress and rate of melt pressure buildup. During clockwise P-T evolution, $H_2$O is transferred from protolith to melt as rocks cross dehydration melting reactions, and $H_2$O may be evolved above the solidus at low P by crossing supra-solidus decompression-dehydration reactions if micas are still present in the depleted protolith. $H_2$O dissolved in melt is transported through the crust to be exsolved on crystallization. This recycled $H_2$O may promote wet melting at supra-solidus conditions and retrogression at sub-solidus conditions. The common growth of `late' muscovite over sillimanite in migmatite may be the result of this process, and in ux of exogenous $H_2$O may not be necessary. However, in general, metasomatism in the evolution of the crust remains a contentious issue. Processes in the lower-most crust may be inferred from studies of xenolith suites brought to the surface in lavas. Based on geochemical data, we can use statistical methods and modeling to evaluate whether migmatites are sources or feeder zones for granites, or simply segregated melt that was stagnant in residue, and to compare xenoliths of inferred lower crust with exposed deep crust. Upper-crustal granites are a necessary complement to melt-depleted granulites common in the lower crust, but the role of mafic magma in crustal melting remains uncertain. Plutons occur at various depths above and below the brittle-to-viscous transition in the crust and have a variety of 3-D shapes that may vary systematically with depth. The switch from ascent to emplacement may be caused by amplification of instabilities within (permeability, magma ow rate) or surrounding (strength or state of stress) the ascent column, or by the ascending magma intersecting some discontinuity in the crust that enables horizontal magma emplacement followed by thickening during pluton inflation. Feedback relations between rates of pluton filling, magma ascent and melt extraction maintain compatibility among these processes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Anatexis;granite emplacement;magma ascent;melt segregation;migmatite;orogeny;pluton</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Brown" fname="Michael" isfellow="0">Michael Brown</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Patchy charnockites from Jenapore, Eastern Ghats granulite belt, India: Structural and petrochemical evidences attesting to their relict nature</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0337-0350</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The charnockite patches that occur within leptynite host, in and around Jenapore, northern sector of the Eastern Ghats granulite belt, are disposed in a linear fashion and generally have sharp lithological contact with the host leptynite. Sometimes the patches and foliations of the host are cofolded. Also, the patches sometimes have the internal $S_1$ foliation, while the host leptynite records only $S_2$ foliation. Mineralogically and chemically patchy charnockites and host leptynites are distinct entities, and cannot be related by any prograde and retrograde reactions. Particularly important is the peraluminous granitic composition and high Rb/Sr ratios of the leptynites, presumably resulting from biotite-dehydration melting; as against metaluminous granodioritic to tonalitic composition and low Rb/Sr ratios of the patchy charnockites, presumably resulting from hornblende-dehydration melting. The charnockite patches here can be interpreted as caught up patches or xenolith within granitic melt (leptynite). Mg-rich rims of garnet in the charnockite patch were probably caused by heat from the crystallising melt or decompression during ascent of melt.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Patchy charnockite; leptynite; distinct entities; relict.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Kar" fname="Rajib" isfellow="0">Rajib Kar</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Evolution of the Bhandara-Balaghat granulite belt along the southern margin of the Sausar Mobile Belt of central India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0351-0368</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Bhandara-Balaghat granulite (BBG) belt occurs as a 190 km long, detached narrow, linear, NE{SW to ENE{WSW trending belt that is in tectonic contact on its northern margin with the Sausar Group of rocks and is bordered by the Sakoli fold belt in the south. The Bhandara part of the BBG belt is quite restricted, comprising a medium to coarse grained two-pyroxene granulite body that is of gabbroic composition and preserves relic igneous fabric. The main part of the belt in Arjuni-Balaghat section includes metasedimentary (quartzite, BIF, Al- and Mg-Al metapelites) and metaigneous (metaultramafic, amphibolite and two-pyroxene granulite) protoliths interbanded with charnockite and charnockitic gneiss. These rocks, occurring as small bands and enclaves within migmatitic and granitic gneisses, show polyphase deformation and metamorphism. Geochemically, basic compositions show tholeiitic trend without Fe-enrichment, non-komatitic nature, continental affinity and show evolved nature. Mineral parageneses and reaction textures in different rock compositions indicate early prograde, dehydration melt forming reactions followed by orthopyroxene stability with or without melt. Coronitic and symplectitic garnets have formed over earlier minerals indicating onset of retrograde IBC path. Evidences for high temperature ductile shearing are preserved at places. Retrogressive hydration events clearly post-date the above paths. The present study has shown that the BBG belt may form a part of the Bastar Craton and does not represent exhumed oceanic crust of the Bundelkhand Craton. It is further shown that rocks of the BBG belt have undergone an earlier high-grade granulite metamorphism at $2672 \pm 54 Ma$ (Sm-Nd age) and a post-peak granulite metamorphism at $1416 \pm 59 Ma$ (Sm-Nd age, $1380 \pm 28 Ma$ Rb-Sr age). These events were followed by deposition of the Sausar supracrustals and Neoproterozoic Sausar orogeny between $973 \pm 63 Ma$ and $800 \pm 16 Ma$ (Rb-Sr ages).</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Granulite;Sausar, Bhandara;Balaghat;tholeiite;migmatite;orogeny.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Ramachandra" fname="H. M." isfellow="0">H. M. Ramachandra</author>
					<author lname="Roy" fname="Abhinaba" isfellow="0">Abhinaba Roy</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>A reappraisal of polymetamorphism in the Eastern Ghats belt - A view from north of the Godavari rift</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0369-0383</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Evidence collated from different parts of the Eastern Ghats belt north of the Godavari rift (barring the "Western Charnockite Zone") indicates that this sector evolved through a series of compressive structures ($F_1$ to $F_3$), with prolific migmatization in quartzofeldspathic and metapelitic gneisses synchronous with $F_1$ shortening, as was the $syn- F_1$ emplacement of profuse megacrystic K-feldspar-bearing granitoid bodies. Thereafter, melt productivity of the rocks (synchronous with $F_2 - F_3$ folding) sharply decreased. Mineral parageneses stable in the $S_1, S_2$ and $S_3$ fabrics indicate persistence of granulite facies conditions. P-T estimates on orthopyroxene $+$ garnet $+$ plagioclase $+$ quartz assemblages anchored to recrystallized mosaic that overgrow all penetrative fabric elements in mafic granulites, granitoids and quartzofeldspathic gneisses are in the range of $900^\circ -950^\circ C$ and $P \cong 8-9$ kbar. This estimate is comparable to those retrieved from sapphirine-bearing paragenesis in Mg-Al metapelites that appear to be diachronous in relation to the fabric elements, and arguably disrupt the granoblastic mosaic. These facets in the northern sector of the orogenic belt are compatible with either a single cycle of tectonic events (i.e., $F_1, F_2$ and $F_3$ in continuum), or temporally-separate thermo-tectonic events, with the peak of earlier metamorphism (pre- to $syn- F_1$) at lower temperature (in the granulite facies) in comparison to the record of high $post-F_3-T_{max}$ values.</p>
					<p>It is suggested on the basis of the above evidence that the late Proterozoic/Pan-African granulites in the Eastern Ghats belt north of the Godavari rift, are unlikely to be reworked equivalents of any older granulitic crust, such as the $\sim 1.6$ Ga granulites south of the rift. Instead, the temporally disparate sectors may represent different crustal segments with unconnected pre-amalgamation tectonic history. However, if the $\sim 1.6$ Ga granulites of the Western Charnockite Zone continue northwards across the rift, as suggested by recent isotope data, there are serious doubts as to the validity of a north-south division within the Eastern Ghats belt.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Eastern Ghats orogenic belt;high-T proterozoic granulites;north-south divide;polyphase anatexis;crustal reworking.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Bhattacharya" fname="A." isfellow="0">A. Bhattacharya</author>
					<author lname="Gupta" fname="S." isfellow="0">S. Gupta</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>U-Pb age of the Diana Complex and Adirondack granulite petrogenesis</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0385-0395</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>U-Pb isotopic analyses of eight single and multi-grain zircon fractions separated from a syenite of the Diana Complex of the Adirondack Mountains do not define a single linear array, but a scatter along a chord that intersects the Concordia curve at $1145 \pm 29$ and $285 \pm 204$ Ma. For the most concordant analyses, the $^{207}Pb/ ^{206}Pb$ ages range between 1115 and 1150 Ma. Detailed petrographic studies revealed that most grains contained at least two phases of zircon growth, either primary magmatic cores enclosed by variable thickness of metamorphic overgrowths or magmatic portions enclosing presumably older xenocrystic zircon cores. The magmatic portions are characterized by typical dipyramidal prismatic zoning and numerous black inclusions that make them quite distinct from adjacent overgrowths or cores when observed in polarizing light microscopy and in back- scattered electron micrographs. Careful handpicking and analysis of the "best" magmatic grains, devoid of visible overgrowth of core material, produced two nearly concordant points that along with two of the multi-grain analyses yielded an upper-intercept age of $1118 \pm 2.8$ Ma and a lower- intercept age of $251 \pm 13$ Ma. The older age is interpreted as the crystallization age of the syenite and the younger one is consistent with late stage uplift of the Appalachian region. The 1118 Ma age for the Diana Complex, some 35 Ma younger than previously believed, is now approximately synchronous with the main Adirondack anorthosite intrusion, implying a cogenetic relationship among the various meta-igneous rocks of the Adirondacks. The retention of a high-temperature contact metamorphic aureole around Diana convincingly places the timing of Adirondack regional metamorphism as early as 1118 Ma. This result also implies that the sources of anomalous high- temperature during granulite metamorphism are the syn-metamorphic intrusions, such as the Diana Complex.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Granulites;geochronology;petrogenesis;Adirondacks;zircon age.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Basu" fname="Asish R." isfellow="0">Asish R. Basu</author>
					<author lname="Premo" fname="Wayne R." isfellow="0">Wayne R. Premo</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>The Rajahmundry Traps, Andhra Pradesh: Evaluation of their petrogenesis relative to the Deccan Traps</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0397-0407</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Geochemical and geochronological data for rocks from the Rajahmundry Traps, are evaluated for possible correlation with the main Deccan province. Lava flows are found on both banks of the Godavari River and contain an intertrappean sedimentary layer. Based on $^{40}Ar/ ^{39}Ar$ age data, rocks on the east bank are post K-T boundary, show normal magnetic polarity, and belong to chron 29N. Their chemistry is identical to lavas in the Mahabaleshwar Formation in the Western Ghats, $\sim 1000$ km away. It was suggested earlier that the genetic link between these geographically widely separated rocks resulted from lava owing down freshly incised river canyons at $\sim 64$ Ma. For the west bank rocks, recent paleomagnetic work indicates lava flows below and above the intertrappean (sedimentary) layer show reversed and normal magnetic polarity, respectively. The chemical composition of the west bank ow above the intertrappean layer is identical to rocks on the east bank. The west bank lava lying below the sedimentary layer, shows chemistry similar to Ambenali Formation lava ows in the western Deccan. $^{40}Ar/ ^{39}Ar$ dating and complete chemical characterization of this ow is required to elucidate its petrogenesis with respect to the main Deccan Province.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Flood-basalts;geochemistry; age;plumes;intracanyon flows;Rajahmundry;Deccan.</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Baksi" fname="Ajoy K." isfellow="0">Ajoy K. Baksi</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Generation of Deccan Trap magmas</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0409-0431</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Deccan Trap magmas may have erupted through multiple centers, the most prominent of which may have been a shield volcano-like structure in the Western Ghats area. The lavas are predominantly tholeiitic; alkalic mafic lavas and carbonatites are rare. Radioisotope dating, magnetic chronology, and age constraints from paleontology indicate that although the eruption started some 68 Ma, the bulk of lavas erupted at around 65-66 Ma. Paleomagnetic constraints indicate an uncertainty of $\pm 500,000$ years for peak volcanic activity at 65 m.y. in the type section of the Western Ghats. Maximum magma residence times were calculated in this study based on growth rates of   "giantplagioclase" crystals in lavas that marked the end phase of volcanic activity of different magma chambers. These calculations suggest that the &gt 1.7 km thick Western Ghats section might have erupted within a much shorter time interval of $\sim 55,000$ years, implying phenomenal eruption rates that are orders of magnitude larger than any present-day eruption rate from any tectonic environment. Other significant observations/conclusions are as follows: (1) Deccan lavas can be grouped into stratigraphic subdivisions based on their geochemistry; (2) While some formations are relatively uncontaminated others are strongly contaminated by the continental crust; (3) Deccan magmas were produced by 15-30% melting of a Fe-rich lherzolitic source at $\sim 3--2$ GPa; (4) Parent magmas of the relatively uncontaminated Ambenali formation had a primitive composition with 16% MgO, 47% $SiO_2$; (5) Deccan magmas were generated much deeper and by significantly more melting than other continental flood basalt provinces; (6) The erupted Deccan tholeiitic lavas underwent fractionation and magma mixing at $\sim 0.2$ GPa. The composition and origin of the crust and crust/mantle boundary beneath the Deccan are discussed with respect to the in uence of Deccan magmatic episode.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Deccan Trap;giant Plagioclase basalt;age;contamination;fractional crystallization;magma generation.</keywords>
				<allauthors> 
					<author lname="Sen" fname="Gautam" isfellow="0">Gautam Sen</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title>Petrology, geochemistry and tectonic settings of the mafic dikes and sills associated with the evolution of the Proterozoic Cuddapah Basin of south India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0433-0453</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this article we summarize the petrological, geochemical and tectonic processes involved in the evolution of the Proterozoic intracratonic Cuddapah basin. We use new and available ages of Cuddapah igneous rocks, together with field, stratigraphic, geophysical and other criteria, to arrive at a plausible model for the timing of these processes during basin evolution. We present petrological and geochronological evidence of dike emplacement along preferred lineament directions around the basin in response to stresses, which may have been responsible for the evolution of the basin itself. Basaltic dike intrusion started on the south Indian shield around 2400 Ma and continued throughout the Cuddapah basin evolution and sedimentation. A deep mantle perturbation, currently manifested by a lopolithic cupola-like intrusion under the southwestern part of the basin, may have occurred at the onset of basin evolution and played an important role in its development. Paleomagnetic, gravity and geochronological evidence indicates that it was a constant thermal source responsible for dike and sill emplacement between 1500 and 1200 Ma both inside and outside the basin. Lineament reactivation in the NW{SE and NE{SW directions, in response to the mantle perturbation, intensified between 1400 and 1200 Ma, leading to the emplacement of several cross cutting dikes.</p>
					<p>Fe-Mg partition coefficients of olivine and augite and Ca-Na partition coefficient of plagioclase, calculated from the composition of these minerals and bulk composition of their host rocks, indicate that the dikes outside the Cuddapah basin are cumulates. The contemporary dikes may be related by fractional crystallization as indicated by a positive correlation between their plagioclase Ca#(atomic Ca/[Ca$+$Na]) and augite Mg# (atomic Mg/[Mg$+$Fe]). A few NW--SE and NE--SW cross cutting dikes of the period between 1400 and 1200 Ma, preserve petrographic evidence of episodic magmatic intrusive activity along preferred directions. Petrological reasoning indicates that a magmatic liquid reacted with a set of cross cutting dikes, intruding into one that was already solidified and altering the composition of the magma that produced the other dike.</p>
					<p>The Cuddapah basin tholeiites may be related by fractional crystallization at 5 kb and $1019-1154^\circ C$, which occurred in the lopolithic cupola near the southwestern margin of the basin. Xenolith bearing picrites, which occur near the periphery of the cupola, originated by the accumulation of xenoliths in the tholeiites. This is indicated by the composition of the olivine in the xenoliths ($Fo_{78.7−81.9}$), which are closely similar to calculated olivine compositions ($Fo_{77.8−78.3}$) in equilibrium with the tholeiites under the same \textit {P-T} conditions. It is inferred that fractionation in the cupola resulted in crystals settling on its walls. Hence, the xenolith-bearing sills occur at the periphery of the lopolithic body.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Cuddapah;proterozoic;basalt;geochemistry;mafic dike;mafic sill;petrology</keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="Chatterjee" fname="Nilanjan" isfellow="0">Nilanjan Chatterjee</author>
					<author lname="Bhattacharji" fname="Somdev" isfellow="0">Somdev Bhattacharji</author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
			<entry issup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0457-0469</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<allauthors>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
					<author lname="" fname="" isfellow="0"></author>
				</allauthors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="111">
		<issue inum="01" month="03" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Simultaneous inversion of the aftershock data of the 1993 Killari earthquake in Peninsular India and its seismotectonic implications</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0015</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The aftershock sequence of the September 30th, 1993 Killari earthquake in the Latur district of Maharashtra state, India, recorded by 41 temporary seismograph stations are used for estimating 3-D velocity structure in the epicentral area. The local earthquake tomography (LET) method of Thurber (1983) is used. About 1500 \textit {P} and 1200 \textit {S} wave travel-times are inverted. The \textit {P} and \textit {S} wave velocities as well as $V_P /V_S$ ratio vary more rapidly in the vertical as well as in the horizontal directions in the source region compared to the adjacent areas. The main shock hypocentre is located at the junction of a high velocity and a low velocity zone, representing a fault zone at 6 - 7 km depth. The estimated average errors of \textit {P} velocity and $V_P / V_S$ ratio are $\pm 0.07 km/s$ and $\pm 0.016$, respectively. The best resolution of \textit {P} and \textit {S}-wave velocities is obtained in the aftershock zone. The 3-D velocity structure and precise locations of the aftershocks suggest a `stationary concept' of the Killari earthquake sequence.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Killari earthquake aftershocks;simultaneous inversion;stable continental region.</keywords>
				<authors> 
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Mukhopadhyay">S. Mukhopadhyay</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Earth Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology (formerly University of Roorkee), Roorkee, Uttaranchal 247 667, India</affiliation>
						<email>sagarfes@iitr.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. R." last="Kayal">J. R. Kayal</name>
						<affiliation>2Geological Survey of India, Central Geophysics Division, 27 J.L.N. Road, Kolkata 700 016, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. N." last="Khattri">K. N. Khattri</name>
						<affiliation>100 Rajendra Nagar, Dehra Dun, Uttaranchal 248 001, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. K." last="Pradhan">B. K. Pradhan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Earth Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology (formerly University of Roorkee), Roorkee, Uttaranchal 247 667, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-01-17</date>
					<date type="R">2001-07-15</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Formation of diapiric structure in the deformation zone, central Indian Ocean: A model from gravity and seismic reflection data</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0017-0028</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Analyses of bathymetry, gravity and seismic reflection data of the diffusive plate boundary in the central Indian Ocean reveal a new kind of deformed structure besides the well-reported structures of long-wavelength anticlinal basement rises and high-angle reverse faults. The structure (basement trough) has a length of about 150 km and deepens by up to 1 km from its regional trend (northward dipping). The basement trough includes a rise at its center with a height of about 1.5 km. The rise is about 10 km wide with rounded upper surface and bounded by vertical faults. A broad free-air gravity low of about 20 mGal and a local high of 8 mGal in its center are associated with the identified basement trough and rise structure respectively. Seismic results reveal that the horizontal crustal compression prevailing in the diffusive plate boundary might have formed the basement trough possibly in early Pliocene time. Differential loading stresses have been generated from unequal crust/sediment thickness on lower crustal and upper mantle rocks. A thin semi-ductile serpentinite layer existing near the base of the crust that is interpreted to have been formed at mid-ocean ridge and become part of the lithosphere, may have responded to the downward loading stresses generated by the sediments and crustal rocks to inject the serpentinites into the overlying strata to form a classic diapiric structure.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Diffusive plate boundary;deformation zone;diapiric structure;serpentinized peridotites;crustal structure;differential loading stresses.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Krishna">K. S. Krishna</name>
						<affiliation>National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email>krishna@csnio.ren.nic.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D. Gopala" last="Rao">D. Gopala Rao</name>
						<affiliation>National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yu P." last="Neprochnov">Yu P. Neprochnov</name>
						<affiliation>P.P. Shirshov Institute of Oceanology, 36 Nakhimovsky Prospect, Moscow 117851, Russia.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-07-01</date>
					<date type="R">2001-10-31</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Reflection of plane waves from free surface of a microstretch elastic solid</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0029-0037</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In the present investigation, it is shown that there exists five basic waves in a microstretch elastic solid half-space. The problem of reflection of plane waves from free surface of a microstretch elastic solid half-space is studied. The energy ratios for various reflected waves are obtained for aluminium- epoxy composite as a microstretch elastic solid half-space. The variations of the energy ratios with the angle of incidence are shown graphically. The microstretch effect is shown on various reflected waves.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Microstretch elastic solid;reflection;energy ratios;aluminium-epoxy composite.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Baljeet" last="Singh">Baljeet Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Jat College, Rohtak 124 001, Haryana, India.</affiliation>
						<email>baljeet−gill@hotmail.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1999-09-14</date>
					<date type="R">2001-10-07</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Records of climatic changes and volcanic events in an ice core from Central Dronning Maud Land (East Antarctica) during the past century</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0039-0049</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The depth profiles of electrical conductance, $\delta ^{18}O, ^{210}Pb$ and cosmogenic radio isotopes ${10}Be$ and $^{36}Cl$ have been measured in a 30 m ice core from east Antarctica near the Indian station, Dakshin Gangotri. Using $^{210}Pb$ and $\delta ^{18}O$, the mean annual accumulation rates have been calculated to be 20 and 21 cm of ice equivalent per year during the past $\sim 150$ years. Using these acumulation rates, the volcanic event that occurred in 1815 AD, has been identified based on electrical conductance measurements. Based on $\delta {18}O$ measurements, the mean annual surface air temperatures (MASAT) data observed during the last 150 years indicates that the beginning of the 19th century was cooler by about $2^\circ C$ than the recent past and the middle of 18th century. The fallout of cosmogenic radio isotope $^{10}Be$ compares reasonably well with those obtained on other stations ($73^circ S to 90^\circ S$) from Antarctica and higher latitudes beyond $77^\circ N$. The fallout of $^[36}Cl$ calculated based on the present work agrees well with the mean global production rate estimated earlier by Lal and Peters (1967) The bomb pulse of $^{36}Cl$ observed in Greenland is not observed in the present studies { a result which is puzzling and needs to be studied on neighbouring ice cores from the same region.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Antarctica;Electrical Conductivity Measurements (ECM);accumulation rates;climate;$^{10}Be$ and $^{36}Cl$.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="V. N." last="Nijampurkar">V. N. Nijampurkar</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D. K." last="Rao">D. K. Rao</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="H. B." last="Clausen">H. B. Clausen</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Geophysics, Niels Bohr Institute of Astronomy, Physics and Geophysics, DK 2200 Copenhagen O, Denmark</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. K." last="Kaul">M. K. Kaul</name>
						<affiliation>Geological Survey of India, Antarctica Division, Faridabad, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Chaturvedi">A. Chaturvedi</name>
						<affiliation>Geological Survey of India, Antarctica Division, Faridabad, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-04-20</date>
					<date type="R">2001-12-04</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Velocity of small-scale auroral ionospheric current systems over Indian Antarctic station Maitri</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0051-0062</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Indian Antarctic station Maitri (geog. $70^\circ 45/S, 11^\circ 45/E, geom. 66^\circ .03S, 53^\circ.21E$) occupies a sub-auroral location during magnetically quiet conditions ($\sigma Kp &lt; 10$), but attains an auroral position when the auroral oval shifts equatorwards with increasing strength of magnetic disturbance. At the latter times, triangulation with 3 uxgate magnetometers located at the vertices of a suitable triangle provides a means of monitoring mobile auroral ionospheric current systems over Maitri. The spacing between the magnetometers is typically kept at 75-200 km, keeping in mind the scale-sizes of $\sim 100$ km for these mobile current systems. This work reports the results of two triangulation experiments carried out around Maitri in January 1992 and January 1995, both during Antarctic summer. The velocities estimated for pulsations of the Pc4 and Pc5 type were about 0.59 km/sec in the direction $102^\circ .7$ east of due north, in the first case, and about 1-3 km/sec in the second case in the east-west direction.</p>
					<p>While several magnetometer arrays exist in the northern auroral regions (e.g., the Alberta array in Canada, the Alaskan array in the U.S. and the IMS Scandinavian array), there is no report in literature of triangulation through arrays in Antarctica, except for a one-day study by Neudegg \textit {et al} 1995 for ULF pulsations of the Pc1 and Pc2 type. The velocities obtained for the Pi3 type of irregular pulsations over Antarctica in the present study tally well with those obtained for northern auroral locations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Geomagnetic pulsations;mobile auroral current systems;field-aligned currents;Antarctica.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Girija" last="Rajaram">Girija Rajaram</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Geomagnetism, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. N." last="Hanchinal">A. N. Hanchinal</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Geomagnetism, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Kalra">R. Kalra</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Geomagnetism, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Unnikrishnan">K. Unnikrishnan</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Geomagnetism, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Jeeva">K. Jeeva</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Geomagnetism, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Sridharan">M. Sridharan</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Geomagnetism, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Dhar">A. Dhar</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Geomagnetism, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1999-07-30</date>
					<date type="R">2001-07-21</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Thermal Internal Boundary Layer characteristics at a tropical coastal site as observed by a mini-SODAR under varying synoptic conditions</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0063-0077</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Atmospheric boundary layer observations are conducted at a coastal site during a transition phase from winter to summer season over the Indian peninsula. Thermal Internal Boundary Layer (TIBL) characteristics in presence of an off-shore and a weakly in uenced on-shore synoptic wind are examined with the help of measurements carried out with a mini-SODAR (SOund Detection And Ranging), tethered balloon, and tower-based micrometeorological measurements. In uence of the changing synoptic scale conditions on turbulent characteristics of TIBL is discussed.</p>
					<p>Mini-SODAR data showed the development and decay of sea and land breeze. It is seen that the characteristics of TIBL over the coastal land after sea breeze onset are similar to that of a shallow convective boundary layer (CBL) commonly found over plain land. Inside the TIBL, a maximum wind speed was noted close to the surface due to the penetration of sea breeze. In the off-shore case, a distinct sea breeze circulation was observed unlike in the case of on-shore ow. In the presence of weak on-shore case, a `minor sea' breeze is noted before the establishment of sea breeze and a reduction in the momentum uxes gives rise to decrease in the turbulence intensity. Updraft in the sea breeze front was stronger during weak synoptic conditions. In uence of synoptic changes on the sea breeze-land breeze circulation such as onset, strength and duration of the sea-land breeze are also examined.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sea breeze;thermal internal boundary layer;turbulence;SODAR.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Thara V." last="Prabha">Thara V. Prabha</name>
						<affiliation>Crop and Soil Sciences, University of Georgia, GA, USA.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Venkatesan">R. Venkatesan</name>
						<affiliation>Health and Safety Division, SHINE Group, IGCAR, Kalpakkam, India 603 102.</affiliation>
						<email>rv@igcar.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Erich" last="Mursch-Radlgruber">Erich Mursch-Radlgruber</name>
						<affiliation>Boundary Layer Meteorology Division, Institut fuer Meteorologie und Physik (IMP-BOKU), Wien, Austria.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Rengarajan">G. Rengarajan</name>
						<affiliation>Boundary Layer Meteorology Division, Institut fuer Meteorologie und Physik (IMP-BOKU), Wien, Austria.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N." last="Jayanthi">N. Jayanthi</name>
						<affiliation>India Meteorological Department, Chennai, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-03-20</date>
					<date type="R">2001-10-16</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Temperature mapping, thermal diffusivity and subsoil heat flux at Kariavattom of Kerala</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0079-0085</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have studied the soil and air temperature characteristics over a period of one year at Kariavattom of Kerala. Thermal diffusivity (\textit {k_s}) of the soil has been calculated by range and lag methods and also from amplitudes and phase angles of first and second harmonics. The two methods lead to similar results. Diurnal soil heat ux and soil temperatures at different depths are modelled and found to be comparable with observations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Thermal wave;diffusivity;soil heat flux.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Tessy" last="Chacko P.">Tessy Chacko P.</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, University of Kerala, Kariavattom, Thiruvananthapuram, 695 581, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Renuka">G. Renuka</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics, University of Kerala, Kariavattom, Thiruvananthapuram, 695 581, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-05-25</date>
					<date type="R">2001-11-01</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="06" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Trace element and isotopic studies of Permo-Carboniferous carbonate nodules from Talchir sediments of peninsular India: Environmental and provenance implications</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0087-0101</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Syngenetic carbonate nodules constitute an interesting feature of the glaciogene sediments of various Talchir basins in peninsular India. Petrographic, cathodoluminescence and sedimentary results suggest that many of these nodules contain primary carbonate precipitates whose geochemical signatures can be used for determining environment of deposition and provenance of the sediments and drainage source. Several nodules were collected from Gondwana basins of east-central India and analyzed for stable carbon and oxygen isotope ratios, REE and trace element composition, and Sr isotope ratio. The mean $\delta ^{18}O$ and $\delta ^{13}C$ values of the calcites in the nodules are -- 19.5‰ and --9.7‰ (w.r.t. PDB) respectively suggesting a freshwater environment (probably lacustrine) for formation of these objects. Trace element ratios (Eu/Eu$^\ast$ and La/Yb) of the nodule samples show that the source of the sediments in the Damodar valley basin was the granites, gneisses and intrusives in the Chotanagpur region. The sediments in the Mahanadi valley were derived from granulites, charnockites and granites of the eastern ghat region. The Sr concentration of the carbonate phase of the nodules is low, ranging from 10--60 ng/g . The $^{87}Sr/^{86}Sr$ ratios of the samples from the west Bokaro basin and Ramgarh basin vary from 0.735 to 0.748 (mean: 0.739) and from 0.726 to 0.733 (mean: 0.730) respectively. These values are consistent with our proposition that water of these basins drained through the granitic rocks of the Chotanagpur region. In contrast, the $^{87}Sr/^{86}Sr$ ratios of the samples from the Talchir basin (Type area) of Mahanadi valley vary from 0.718 to 0.723 (mean: 0.719). These $^{87}Sr/^{86}Sr$ ratios are close to those of the granulites in the adjoining eastern ghat belt suggesting that area as the drainage source.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Talchir nodules;stable isotopes;REE and trace elements;provenance and environment.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Prosenjit" last="Ghosh">Prosenjit Ghosh</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. K." last="Bhattacharya">S. K. Bhattacharya</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. M." last="Dayal">A. M. Dayal</name>
						<affiliation>National Geophysical Research Institute, Hyderabad, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. R." last="Trivedi">J. R. Trivedi</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Ebihara">M. Ebihara</name>
						<affiliation>Tokyo Metropolitan University, Hachioji, Tokyo 192-0397, Japan.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. M." last="Sarin">M. M. Sarin</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Chakrabarti">A. Chakrabarti</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur 721 302, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-09-01</date>
					<date type="R">2002-03-14</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Electron spin resonance dating of fault gouge from Desamangalam, Kerala: Evidence for Quaternary movement in Palghat gap shear zone</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0103-0113</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The field investigations in the epicentral area of the 1994 Wadakkancheri (Desamangalam), Kerala, earthquake (M 4.3) indicate subtle, but clearly recognizable expressions of geologically recent fault zone, consisting of fracture sets showing brittle displacement and a gouge zone. The fracture zone confines to the crystalline basement, and is spatially coincident with the elongation of the isoseismals of the 1994 mainshock and a 10-km-long WNW-ESE trending topographic lineament. The preliminary results from the electron spin resonance (ESR) dating on the quartz grains from the fault gouge indicate that the last major faulting in this site occurred $430 \pm 43 ka$ ago. The experiments on different grain sizes of quartz from the gouge showed consistent decrease in age to a plateau of low values, indicating that ESR signals in finer grains were completely zeroed at the time of faulting due to frictional heat. The results show a relatively young age for displacement on the fault that occurs within a Precambrian shear zone. Discrete reactivated faults in such areas may be characterized by low degree of activity, but considering the ESR age of the last significant faulting event, the structure at Desamangalam may be categorized as a potentially active fault capable of generating moderate earthquakes, separated by very long periods of quiescence.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>ESR dating;fault gouge;neotectonism;paleoseismology;Palghat gap.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="T. K. Gundu" last="Rao">T. K. Gundu Rao</name>
						<affiliation>R.S.I.C., Indian Institute of Technology, Powai, Mumbai 400 076, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="C. P." last="Rajendran">C. P. Rajendran</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Earth Science Studies, Akkulam, Thiru</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="George" last="Mathew">George Mathew</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Geology, M.S. University of Baroda, Vadodara 390 002, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Biju" last="John">Biju John</name>
						<affiliation>Geological Survey of India, Northern Region, Lucknow 226 020, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-10-13</date>
					<date type="R">2002-02-28</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Age and duration of the Deccan Traps, India: A review of radiometric and paleomagnetic constraints</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0115-0123</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A review of the available radiometric and paleomagnetic data from the Deccan Flood Basalt Province (DFBP) suggests that the volcanism was episodic in nature and probably continued over an extended duration from 69Ma to 63Ma between 31R and 28N. It is likely that the most intense pulse of volcanism at $66.9 \pm 0.2Ma$ preceded the Cretaceous Tertiary Boundary (KTB, $65.2 \pm 0.2Ma$) events by $\sim 1.7Ma$. The magnetostratigraphic record in the Deccan lava pile is incomplete and it is therefore possible that the lava ows constituting the reverse polarity sequence were erupted in more than one reversed magnetic chron.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Deccan Volcanism;Cretaceous-Tertiary Boundary;geochronology;magneto-stratigraphy.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last="">Kanchan Pande</name>
						<affiliation>Earth Sciences and Solar System Division, Physical Research Laboratory, Navrangpura, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
						<email>kanchan@prl.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-01-23</date>
					<date type="R">2002-02-28</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Static deformation of two welded monoclinic elastic half-spaces due to a long inclined strike-slip fault</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0125-0131</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Static deformation of two monoclinic elastic half-spaces in welded contact due to a long inclined strike-slip fault situated in one of the half-spaces is studied analytically and numerically. Closedform algebraic expressions for the displacement at any point of the medium are obtained. The variation of the displacement at the interface with the horizontal distance from the fault is studied. The effect of anisotropy on the displacement field is examined. It is found that while the anisotropy of the source half-space has a significant effect on the displacement at the interface, the anisotropy of the other half-space has only a marginal effect.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Monoclinic elastic media;static deformation;strike-slip fault;welded half-spaces.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Anil" last="Kumar">Anil Kumar</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Maharshi Dayanand University, Rohtak 124 001, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sarvajit" last="Singh">Sarvajit Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Maharshi Dayanand University, Rohtak 124 001, India.</affiliation>
						<email>s_j_singh@yahoo.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jagdish" last="Singh">Jagdish Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Maharshi Dayanand University, Rohtak 124 001, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-09-25</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Mechanical sources in orthotropic micropolar continua</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0133-0141</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The present paper is concerned with the problem of an orthotropic micropolar half-space subjected to concentrated and distributed loads. The disturbance due to normal and tangential loads are investigated by employing eigen-value approach. The integral transforms have been inverted by using a numerical technique to obtain the normal displacement, normal force stress and tangential couple stress in the physical domain. The results of these quantities are given and illustrated graphically.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Micropolar;orthotropic;eigen-value;Fourier and Laplace transforms.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Rajneesh" last="Kumar">Rajneesh Kumar</name>
						<affiliation>Mathematics Department, Kurukshetra University, Kurukshetra 136 119, Haryana, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Suman" last="Choudhary">Suman Choudhary</name>
						<affiliation>Mathematics Department, Kurukshetra University, Kurukshetra 136 119, Haryana, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-11-05</date>
					<date type="R">2002-03-14</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Response of an anisotropic liquid-saturated porous medium due to two dimensional sources</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0143-0151</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Eigenvalue approach, following Laplace and Fourier transforms, has been employed to find the general solution to the field equations in an anisotropic liquid-saturated porous medium, in the transformed domain. The results of isotropic liquid-saturated porous medium can be derived as a special case. A numerical inversion technique has been applied to get the solutions in the physical domain. To illustrate the utility of the approach, an application of infinite space with impulsive force at the origin has been considered. The results in the form of displacement and stress components have been obtained and discussed graphically for a particular model.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Anisotropic;liquid-saturated porous;eigenvalue;Laplace and Fourier transforms.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Rajneesh" last="Kumar">Rajneesh Kumar</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Kurukshetra University, Kurukshetra 136 119, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Aseem" last="Miglani">Aseem Miglani</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, M.M. Engineering College, Mullana 133 203, Ambala, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. R." last="Garg">N. R. Garg</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Maharshi Dayanand University, Rohtak 124 001, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-09-24</date>
					<date type="R">2002-03-14</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Momentum transport of wave zero during March: A possible predictor for the Indian summer monsoon</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0153-0162</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Analysis of monthly momentum transport of zonal waves at 850 hPa for the period 1979 to 1993, between $30^\circ S$ and $30^\circ N$ for January to April, using zonal (\textit {u}) and meridional ($\upsilon $) components of wind taken from the ECMWF reanalysis field, shows a positive correlation (.1% level of significance) between the Indian summer monsoon rainfall (June through September) and the momentum transport of wave zero TM(0) over latitudinal belt between $25^\circ S$ and $5^\circ N$ (LB) during March. Northward (Southward) TM(0) observed in March over LB subsequently leads to a good (drought) monsoon season over India which is found to be true even when the year is marked with the El- Nino event. Similarly a strong westerly zone in the Indian Ocean during March, indicates a good monsoon season for the country, even if the year is marked with El-Nino. The study thus suggests two predictors, TM(0) over LB and the strength of westerly zone in the Indian Ocean during March.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Momentum transport;zonal waves;zone of westerlies;Indian monsoon rainfall.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. M." last="Bawiskar">S. M. Bawiskar</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Pune 411 008</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V. R." last="Mujumdar">V. R. Mujumdar</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Pune 411 008</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. S." last="Singh">S. S. Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Pune 411 008</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-03-27</date>
					<date type="R">2001-12-20</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Seasonal and interannual variability of phytoplankton pigment in the Laccadive (Lakshadweep) Sea as observed by the Coastal Zone Color Scanner</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0163-0185</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Based on Coastal Zone Color Scanner data from November 1978 through December 1981, the seasonal cycle of phytoplankton pigment in the upper part of the euphotic zone is established for the off shore Laccadive Sea. Year-round, the pigment content is low and the seasonal range is small, following the pattern of the nutrient-poor Arabian Sea to the west. Apparently, indigenous phytoplankton blooms are absent. July and August, however, were poorly studied because of cloud cover. Interannual differences during the northeast monsoon and the spring intermonsoon periods are minor. The abundant phytoplankton caused by the upwelling off India during the southwest monsoon remains essentially restricted to the shelf, but there are occasional large, zonal outbreaks into the Laccadive Sea, as well as others advected to the south of India. Visual inspection of the raw CZCS scenes for June through November 1982-1985, with almost no data until August or even September, shows such outbreaks of pigment-rich water to be common. Inspection of monthly SeaWiFS images for 1997 through part of 2001 confirms the absence of indigenous phytoplankton blooms.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Laccadive sea;Lakshadweep sea;CZCS;phytoplankton pigment;seasons;1979-1981.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Lisa Jade" last="Lierheimer">Lisa Jade Lierheimer</name>
						<affiliation>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Office of International Affairs, Division of Management Authority, 4401 North Fairfax Drive, Arlington, VA 22046</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Karl" last="Banse">Karl Banse</name>
						<affiliation>Corresponding author: School of Oceanography, Box 357940, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98195-7940, U.S.A.</affiliation>
						<email>banse@ocean.washington.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-02-22</date>
					<date type="R">2002-03-15</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="09" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Preface</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0187-0187</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="R">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="A">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="E">2014-09-30</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Retrieval of sea surface velocities using sequential Ocean Colour Monitor (OCM) data</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0189-0195</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Indian remote sensing satellite, IRS-P4 (Oceansat-I) launched on May 26th, 1999 carried two sensors on board, i.e., the Ocean Colour Monitor (OCM) and the Multi-frequency Scanning Microwave Radiometer (MSMR) dedicated for oceanographic research. Sequential data of IRS-P4 OCM has been analysed over parts of both east and west coast of India and a methodology to retrieve sea surface current velocities has been applied. The method is based on matching suspended sediment dispersion patterns, in sequential two time lapsed images. The pattern matching is performed on a pair of atmospherically corrected and geo-referenced sequential images by Maximum Cross-Correlation (MCC) technique. The MCC technique involves computing matrices of cross-correlation coe#cients and identifying correlation peaks. The movement of the pattern can be calculated knowing the displacement of windows required to match patterns in successive images. The technique provides actual flow during a specified period by integrating both tidal and wind influences. The current velocities retrieved were compared with synchronous data collected along  the east coast during the GSI cruise ST-133 of R.V. Samudra Kaustubh in January 2000. The current data were measured using the ocean current meter supplied by the Environmental Measurement and CONtrol (EMCON), Kochi available with the Geological Survey of India, Marine Wing. This current meter can measure direction and magnitude with an accuracy of $\pm 5^\circ $ and 2% respectively. The measurement accuracies with coefficient of determination ($R^2$) of 0.99, for both magnitude ($cm.s^{-1}$) and direction (deg.) were achieved.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>IRS-P4 OCM;suspended sediment concentration;advective velocity;maximum cross-correlation;coregistration.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. S." last="Prasad">J. S. Prasad</name>
						<affiliation>Presently at Applied Geophysical Laboratories, Department of Geophysics, University of Houston, Texas 77204, USA</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. S." last="Rajawat">A. S. Rajawat</name>
						<affiliation>Marine and Water Resources Group, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yaswant" last="Pradhan">Yaswant Pradhan</name>
						<affiliation>Marine and Water Resources Group, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="O. S." last="Chauhan">O. S. Chauhan</name>
						<affiliation>2Geological Oceanography Division, National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. R." last="Nayak">S. R. Nayak</name>
						<affiliation>Marine and Water Resources Group, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Estimation of colored dissolved organic matter and salinity fields in case 2 waters using SeaWiFS: Examples from Florida Bay and Florida Shelf</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0197-0207</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Estimates of water quality variables such as chlorophyll \textit {a} concentration (Chl), colored dissolved organic matter (CDOM), or salinity from satellite sensors are of great interest to resource managers monitoring coastal regions such as the Florida Bay and the Florida Shelf. However, accurate  stimates of these variables using standard ocean color algorithms have been di#cult due to the complex nature of the light field in these environments. In this study, we process SeaWiFS satellite  data using two recently developed algorithms; one for atmospheric correction and the other a semi-analytic bio-optical algorithm and compare the results with standard SeaWiFS algorithms. Overall, the two algorithms produced more realistic estimates of Chl and CDOM distributions in Florida Shelf and Bay waters. Estimates of surface salinity were obtained from the CDOM absorption field assuming a conservative mixing behavior of these waters. A comparison of SeaWiFS-derived Chl and CDOM absorption with field measurements in the Florida Bay indicated that although well correlated, CDOM was underestimated, while Chl was overestimated. Bottom reflectance appeared to affect these estimates at the shallow central Bay stations during the winter. These results demonstrate the need for new bio-optical algorithms or tuning of the parameters used in the bio-optical  algorithm for local conditions encountered in the Bay.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Remote sensing;SeaWiFS;atmospheric correction;chlorophyll \textit {a};CDOM;salinity</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="E. J." last="D'Sa">E. J. D'Sa</name>
						<affiliation>Present address: GB Tech, NASA Earth Science Applications Directorate, Bldg. 1100, Stennis Space Center, MS 39529, USA</affiliation>
						<email>ejdsa@ssc.nasa.gov</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="C." last="Hu">C. Hu</name>
						<email>hu@seas.marine.usf.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="F. E." last="Muller-Karger">F. E. Muller-Karger</name>
						<affiliation>College of Marine Science, University of South Florida, St. Petersburg, FL 33701, USA</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. L." last="Carder">K. L. Carder</name>
						<affiliation>College of Marine Science, University of South Florida, St. Petersburg, FL 33701, USA</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Primary production in the Sulu Sea</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0209-0213</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The Sulu Sea, located between Borneo and the Philippines, is separated from the surrounding ocean by two chains of islands. There are no passages below 500m depth and the basin, which at the deepest is 5,000 m, is filled with warm low oxygen water.</p>
					<p>The near surface chlorophyll concentration has been examined with the aid of ocean colour sensors on board satellites. Direct comparisons between a field observation of chlorophyll and its remotely sensed values from OCTS (Ocean Colour Temperature Scanner) are found to be in satisfactory agreement. An 8-month time series of chlorophyll near the centre of the Sulu Sea has been used to show that the chlorophyll level is significantly higher than the level in the adjacent South China Sea. This was most pronounced at the period of change between the monsoons. The greater primary productivity may provide the explanation for the higher deposition rate of carbon in the Sulu Sea.</p>
					<p>Although the Sulu Sea is more productive than the adjacent South China Sea, the central area can still be classified as a desert. Estimates of the new primary production in the central Sulu Sea seem to be just su#cient to support the current fishery.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oceanography;remote sensing;primary production;Sulu Sea.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Ian S. F." last="Jones">Ian S. F. Jones</name>
						<affiliation>Ocean Technology Group, J05 University of Sydney, NSW 2006, Australia</affiliation>
						<email>otg@otg.usyd.edu.au</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Seasonal and interannual variations in pigments in the Adriatic Sea</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0215-0225</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Spatial and temporal variability of pigments was studied from the CZCS satellite data and from \textit {in situ} chlorophyll and transparency for the period 1979--1985. The three Adriatic sites, Northern, Middle, and Southern Adriatic are differently in oceanographic parameters. The differences between seasonal \textit {in situ} chlorophyll and remotely sensed pigment concentrations (from CZCS satellite data) from the Adriatic are large in winter. Through the correlation analysis, pigments were compared to meteo-oceanographic and hydrological parameters from different Adriatic sites. The PCA (principal component analysis) was applied to the pigment data series and significant components were compared. Different correlations are obtained for warm and cold periods of the year pointing to seasonal differences in the underlying mechanism of pigment variability. The first PC is in more parameters seem to in field, than in the cold period. The pigments in the Adriatic are in good correlation to a number of hydrologic and meteo-oceanographic factors.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mediterranean;Adriatic Sea;CZCS;pigment concentrations;\textit {in situ} chlorophyll;transparency.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Mira" last="Morovic">Mira Morovi\acute{c}</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Oceanography and Fisheries, \breve{S}etali\breve{s}te I.Me\breve{s}trovi\acute{c}a 63, P.O.Box 500, 21000 Split, Croatia.</affiliation>
						<email>morovic@izor.hr</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Variability of photosynthetic pigments in the Colombian Pacific Ocean and its relationship with the wind field using ADEOS-I data</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0227-0236</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Variability of the oceanographic conditions in the Colombian Pacific Ocean, a part of the Panama Basin, is subjected to the variability of wind conditions in the equatorial part of the Pacific Ocean. Data of OCTS and NSCAT of ADEOS-I satellite provided as monthly averages for the period November 1996-- June 1997 by NASDA, were processed and manipulated. A meridional (N--S) component and a zonal (E--W) component were run in order to analyse the data variability and correlation. It is concluded that the variability of the oceanic surface chlorophyll and SST in the Colombian Pacific is a seasonal event related to the migration of the ITCZ and the generation of a wind jet at the Isthmus of Panama. Upwelling due to the wind rotor is present throughout the whole period, with variable spatial distribution and a tendency to be located towards the eastern part of the basin. In a similar way, high chlorophyll concentrations observed in March coincide with both the intensification of the vertical velocities during that month, and the maximal rise of the thermocline in the northern part of the Panama Basin. Picture series of surface chlorophyll, SST, wind stress and Ekman pumping are provided for the studied area.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Colombia;Pacific;chlorophyll;wind jet;ADEOS-I.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Efrain" last="Rodriguez-Rubio">Efrain Rodriguez-Rubio</name>
						<affiliation>University of Concepcion, Oceanography Department, Cabina 5, Concepci´on, Casilla 160-C, Chile.</affiliation>
						<email>erodrig@udec.cl</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jose" last="Stuardo">Jose Stuardo</name>
						<affiliation>University of Concepcion, Oceanography Department, Cabina 5, Concepci´on, Casilla 160-C, Chile.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Vertical diffuse attenuation coefficient ($K_d$) based optical classification of IRS-P3 MOS-B satellite ocean colour data</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0237-0245</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The optical classification of the different water types provides vital input for studies related to primary productivity, water clarity and determination of euphotic depth. Image data of the IRS- P3 MOS-B, for Path 90 of 27th February, 1998 was used for deriving vertical diffuse attenuation Coeffcient ($K_d$) and an optical classification based on $K_d$ values was performed. An atmospheric correction scheme was used for retrieving water leaving radiances in blue and green channels of 412, 443, 490 and 550 nm. The upwelling radiances from 443nm and 550nm spectral channels were used for computation of vertical diffuse attenuation coeffcient $K_d$ at 490 nm. The waters off the Gujarat coast were classified into different water types based on Jerlov classification scheme. The oceanic water type IA ($K_{d}$ range $0.035--0.040m^{-1}$), type IB ($0.042--0.065m^{-1}$), type II ($0.07--0.1m^{-1}$) and type III ($0.115--0.14m^{-1}$) were identified. For the coastal waters along Gujarat coast and Gulf of Kachchh, $K_d$(490) values ranged between $0.15m^{-1}$ and $0.35m^{-1}$. The depth of 1% of surface light for water type IA, IB, II and III corresponds to 88, 68, 58 and 34 meters respectively. Classifica- tion of oceanic and coastal waters based on $K_d$ is useful in understanding the light transmission characteristics for sub-marine navigation and under-water imaging.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Diffuse attenuation coefficient;optical classification;IRS-P3 MOS-B data.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Sarangi">R. K. Sarangi</name>
						<affiliation>Marine and Water Resources Group, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Prakash" last="Chauhan">Prakash Chauhan</name>
						<affiliation>Marine and Water Resources Group, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. R." last="Nayak">S. R. Nayak</name>
						<affiliation>Marine and Water Resources Group, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Intercomparison of IRS-P4-MSMR derived geophysical products with DMSP-SSM/I and TRMM-TMI finished products</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0247-0256</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this paper, MSMR geophysical products like Integrated Water Vapour (IWV), Ocean Surface Wind Speed (OWS) and Cloud Liquid Water (CLW) in different grids of 50, 75 and 150 kms are compared with similar products available from other satellites like DMSP-SSM/I and TRMM- TMI. MSMR derived IWV, OWS and CLW compare well with SSM/I and TMI finished products. Comparison of MSMR derived CLW with that derived from TMI and SSM/I is relatively in less agreement. This is possibly due to the use of 37 GHz in SSM/I and TMI that is highly sensitive to CLW, while 37 GHz channels are not available on MSMR. Monthly comparison of MSMR geo- physical products with those from TMI is all carried out for climatological purpose. The monthly comparisons were much better compared to instantaneous comparisons. In this paper, details of the data analysis and comparison results are presented. The usefulness of the MSMR vis-#a-vis other sensors is also discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>MSMR;TMI;SSM/I;geophysical products.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A. K." last="Varma">A. K. Varma</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India.</affiliation>
						<email>atul−varma@hotmail.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. M." last="Gairola">R. M. Gairola</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. K." last="Mathur">A. K. Mathur</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. S." last="Gohil">B. S. Gohil</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Vijay K." last="Agarwal">Vijay K. Agarwal</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Remote Sensing Applications Area, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Rain rate measurements over global oceans from IRS-P4 MSMR</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0257-0266</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this paper rain estimation capability of MSMR is explored. MSMR brightness temperature data of six channels corresponding to three frequencies of 10, 18 and 21 GHz are colocated with the TRMM Microwave Imager (TMI) derived rain rates to find a new empirical algorithm for rain rate by multiple regression. Multiple correlation analysis involving various combinations of channels in linear and non-linear forms and rain rate from TMI is carried out, and thus the best possible algorithm for rain rate measurement was identified which involved V and H polarized brightness temperature measurements at 10 and 18 GHz channels. This algorithm explained about 82 per cent correlation (\textit {r}) with rain rate, and $1.61 mm h^{-1}$ of error of estimation.</p>
					<p>Further, this algorithm is used for generating global average rain rate map for two contrasting months of August (2000) and January (2001) of northern and southern hemispheric summers, respectively. MSMR derived monthly averaged rain rates are compared with similar estimates from TRMM Precipitation Radar (PR), and it was found that MSMR derived rain rates match well, quantitatively and qualitatively, with that from PR.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>IRS-P4, MSMR, TRMM, TMI, PR.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A. K." last="Varma">A. K. Varma</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
						<email>atul−varma@hotmail.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. M." last="Gairola">R. M. Gairola</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Samir" last="Pokhrel">Samir Pokhrel</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. S." last="Gohil">B. S. Gohil</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. K." last="Mathur">A. K. Mathur</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Vijay K." last="Agarwal">Vijay K. Agarwal</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Wind-driven circulation in the subarctic north Pacific using altimeter data</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0267-0279</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Time-dependent wind-driven circulation in the subarctic north Pacific is investigated by using Topex/Poseidon (T/P) altimeter data and European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) wind data for about 6 years. The first empirical orthogonal function (EOF) of the T/P- derived sea level anomaly (SLA) without the variation related to the steric height change (SLA1) and the first EOF of the ECMWF-based wind stress curl fields represent basin-sized south-north oscillations and their time series agree well with a correlation of 0.49. They appear to express the spin-up and spin-down of the subarctic gyre. The third EOF of SLA (SLA3) and the second EOF of the wind stress curl are also related to the variation of the subarctic gyre. Though the correlation of their time series is 0.27, drastic changes in early winter coincide well. The two EOF pairs can be considered to mean that the SLA variation followed by the latitudinal migration of the Aleutian low is separated into two standing oscillation patterns, that is, the sea level variation combined with SLA1 and SLA3 expresses seasonal variations of the wind-driven circulation of the subarctic gyre. The interannual SLAs constructed by subtracting the SLA1 and SLA3 components clearly show trans-pacific westward propagation even in the high-latitudes. The time series of SLA1 is in agreement with that of \textit {in situ} SLAs measured with the tide gauge at Petropavlovsk (53-01N, 158-38E), which implies the possibility to monitor the subarctic circulation using tide gauge data.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Time-dependent wind-driven circulation;subarctic north Pacific;altimeter;EOF analyses.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Osamu" last="Isoguchi">Osamu Isoguchi</name>
						<affiliation>Remote Sensing Technology Center of Japan, Office Tower X 21F, Harumi Island Triton Square, 1-8-10 Harumi, Chuo-ku, Tokyo 104-6021, Japan</affiliation>
						<email>isoguchi@restec.or.jp</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Hiroshi" last="Kawamura">Hiroshi Kawamura</name>
						<affiliation>Center for Atmospheric and Oceanic Studies, Graduate School of Science, Tohoku University, Aoba, Sendai 980-8578, Japan</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Oceanic eddies in synthetic aperture radar images</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0281-0295</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Continuous observations since 1991 by using synthetic aperture radar (SAR) on board the Almaz-1, ERS-1/2, JERS-1, and RADARSAT satellites support the well-known fact that oceanic eddies are distributed worldwide in the ocean. The paper is devoted to an evaluation of the potential of SAR for detection of eddies and vortical motions in the ocean. The classification of typical vortical features in the ocean detected in remote sensing images (visible, infrared, and SAR) is presented as well as available information on their spatial and temporal scales. Examples of the Almaz-1 and ERS-1/2 SAR images showing different eddy types, such as rings, spiral eddies of the open ocean, eddies behind islands and in bays, spin-off eddies and mushroom-like structures (vortex dipoles) are given and discussed. It is shown that a common feature for most of the eddies detected in the SAR images is a broad spectrum of spatial scales, spiral shape and shear nature. It is concluded that the spaceborne SARs give valuable information on ocean eddies, especially in combination with visible and infrared satellite data.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oceanic eddies;vortical motions;synthetic aperture radar (SAR);SAR images.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Andrei Yu" last="Ivanov">Andrei Yu Ivanov</name>
						<affiliation>P P Shirshov Institute of Oceanology, Russian Academy of Sciences, Nakhimovsky prospect, 36, Moscow, 117851, Russia.</affiliation>
						<email>ivanoff@sio.rssi.ru</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Anna I." last="Ginzburg">Anna I. Ginzburg</name>
						<affiliation>P P Shirshov Institute of Oceanology, Russian Academy of Sciences, Nakhimovsky prospect, 36, Moscow, 117851, Russia.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Auto-correlation analysis of ocean surface wind vectors</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0297-0303</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The nature of the inherent temporal variability of surface winds is analyzed by comparison of winds obtained through different measurement methods. In this work, an auto-correlation analysis of a time series data of surface winds measured \textit {in situ} by a deep water buoy in the Indian Ocean has been carried out. Hourly time series data available for 240 hours in the month of May, 1999 were subjected to an auto-correlation analysis. The analysis indicates an exponential fall of the auto- correlation in the first few hours with a decorrelation time scale of about 6 hours. For a meaningful comparison between satellite derived products and \textit {in situ} data, satellite data acquired at different time intervals should be used with appropriate `weights', rather than treating the data as concurrent in time. This paper presents a scheme for temporal weighting using the auto-correlation analysis. These temporal `weights' can potentially improve the root mean square (rms) deviation between satellite and \textit {in situ} measurements. A case study using the TRMM Microwave Imager (TMI) and Indian Ocean buoy wind speed data resulted in an improvement of about 10%.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Surface wind speed;data buoy;time series;auto-correlation;microwave radiometer.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Abhijit" last="Sarkar">Abhijit Sarkar</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Meteorology and Oceanography Group, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad, India.</affiliation>
						<email>sarkar−abhi2000@yahoo.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sujit" last="Basu">Sujit Basu</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Meteorology and Oceanography Group, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. K." last="Varma">A. K. Varma</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Meteorology and Oceanography Group, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jignesh" last="Kshatriya">Jignesh Kshatriya</name>
						<affiliation>Oceanic Sciences Division, Meteorology and Oceanography Group, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Study of the relationship between non-dimensional roughness length and wave age, effected by wave directionality</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0305-0313</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Relationship between the non-dimensional roughness length and inverse of wave age has been discussed without consideration of wave directions, though wind wave field consists of various directional component waves. In this study we observe wave heights by an array of four wave gauges at the Hiratsuka Tower of (Independent Administrative Institution) National Research Institute for Earth Science and Disaster Prevention (NIED), Japan, and discuss the effect of wave directionality. As a result, the data sets were classified into two different groups according to the directional wave spectrum distribution. In case 1 only swell and wind waves exist and in case 2 there exist wave components from several directions. It is shown that the case of multiple- directional component waves (case 2) may affect the non-dimensional roughness length and friction velocity.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Wind wave;roughness length;wave age.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Naoya" last="Suzuki">Naoya Suzuki</name>
						<affiliation>Center for Environmental Remote Sensing (CEReS), Chiba University, 1-33 Yayoi Inage Chiba, 263-8522 Japan.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Naoto" last="Ebuchi">Naoto Ebuchi</name>
						<affiliation>Center for Atmospheric and Oceanic Studies, Graduate School of Science, Tohoku University, Aoba, Sendai 980-8578, Japan.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Chaofang" last="Zhao">Chaofang Zhao</name>
						<affiliation>Center for Environmental Remote Sensing (CEReS), Chiba University, 1-33 Yayoi Inage Chiba, 263-8522 Japan, Ocean Remote Sensing Laboratory, Ocean University of Qingdao, China.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Isao" last="Watabe">Isao Watabe</name>
						<affiliation>National Research Institute for Earth Science and Disaster Prevention, Science and Technology Agency, 9-2 Nijigahama, Hiratsuka, Kanagawa, 254-0823 Japan.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yasuhiro" last="Sugimori">Yasuhiro Sugimori</name>
						<affiliation>Center for Environmental Remote Sensing (CEReS), Chiba University, 1-33 Yayoi Inage Chiba, 263-8522 Japan.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Oceanic whitecaps: Sea surface features detectable via satellite that are indicators of the magnitude of the air-sea gas transfer coefficient</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0315-0319</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Stage A whitecaps (spilling wave crests) have a microwave emissivity of close to 1. Thus if even a small fraction of the sea surface is covered by these features there will be a detectable enhancement in the apparent microwave brightness temperature of that surface as determined by satellite-borne microwave radiometers. This increase in the apparent microwave brightness temperature can as a consequence be routinely used to estimate the fraction of the sea surface covered by stage A whitecaps. For all but the very lowest wind speeds it has been shown in a series of controlled experiments that the air-sea gas transfer coeffcient for each of a wide range of gases, including carbon dioxide and oxygen, is directly proportional to the fraction of the sea surface covered by these stage A whitecaps.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Whitecaps;air-sea exchange;gas transfer coefficient;breaking waves;microwave brightness temperature;microwave emissivity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="E. C." last="Monahan">E. C. Monahan</name>
						<affiliation>University of Connecticut at Avery Point, Groton, Connecticut, 06340-6097, USA</affiliation>
						<email>edward.monahan@uconn.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Mesoscale modeling study of the oceanographic conditions off the southwest coast of India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0321-0337</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A high resolution model, using the Miami Isopycnic Coordinate Ocean Model (MICOM), has been implemented for the first time to study the seasonal circulation and coastal upwelling off the southwest Indian coast during 1974. This model is part of a model and data assimilation system capable of describing the ocean circulation and variability in the Indian Ocean and its predictability in response to the monsoon system.</p>
					<p>Along the southwest coast of India the dominant coastal current is the reversing West Indian Coastal Current which is well simulated and described, in addition to the weaker undercurrent of the opposite direction. Upwelling of cold water, $4^\circ C$ lower than offshore temperatures appear in April. The upwelling intensifies with the southwest monsoon and is simulated in accordance with \textit {in situ} observations. Upwelling appears to be strongest off Cochin and Quilon, and the upwelling of cold water is seen together with a decrease in salinity in the model simulation.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mesoscale modeling;coastal upwelling;India.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Vibeke E." last="Haugen">Vibeke E. Haugen</name>
						<affiliation>Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center, Edvard Griegs Vei 3a, N-5059 Solheimsviken, Norway.</affiliation>
						<email>Vibeke.Haugen@nrsc.no</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ola M." last="Johannessen">Ola M. Johannessen</name>
						<affiliation>Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center, Edvard Griegs Vei 3a, N-5059 Solheimsviken, Norway.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Geir" last="Evensen">Geir Evensen</name>
						<affiliation>Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center, Edvard Griegs Vei 3a, N-5059 Solheimsviken, Norway.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Chlorophyll modulation of mixed layer thermodynamics in a mixed-layer isopycnal General Circulation Model - An example from Arabian Sea and equatorial Pacific</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0339-0349</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Western tropical Indian Ocean, Arabian Sea, and the equatorial Pacific are known as regions of intense bio-chemical-physical interactions: the Arabian Sea has the largest phytoplankton bloom with seasonal signal, while the equatorial Pacific bloom is perennial with quasi-permanent upwelling. Here, we studied three dimensional ocean thermodynamics comparing recent ocean observation with ocean general circulation model (OPYC) experiment combined with remotely sensed chlorophyll pigment concentrations from the Coastal Zone Color Scanner (CZCS). Using solar radiation parameterization representing observations that a higher abundance of chlorophyll increases absorption of solar irradiance and heating rate in the upper ocean, we showed that the mixed layer thickness decreases more than they would be under clear water conditions. These changes in the model mixed layer were consistent with Joint Global Ocean Flux Study (JGOFS) observations during the 1994--1995 Arabian Sea experiment and epi-fluorescence microscopy (EFM) on samples collected during Equatorial Pacific Ocean Climate Study (EPOCS) in November, 1988. In the Arabian Sea, as the chlorophyll concentrations peak in October ($3mg/m^3$) after the summer plankton bloom induced by coastal upwelling, the chlorophyll induced biological heating enhanced the sea surface temperature (SST) by as much as $0.6^\circ C$ and sub-layer temperature decreases and sub-layer thickness increases. In the equatorial Pacific, modest concentrations of chlorophyll less than $0.3mg/m^3$ is enough to introduce a meridional differential heating, which results in reducing the equatorial mixed layer thickness to more than 20 m. The anomalous meridional tilting of the mixed layer bottom enhances off equatorial westward geostrophic currents. Consequently, the equatorial undercurrent transports more water from west to east. We proposed that these numerical model experiments with use of satellite and \textit {in situ} ocean observations are consistent under three dimensional ocean circulation theory combined with solar radiation transfer process.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Mixed-layer;isopycnal model;phytoplankton bloom;radiation-transfer;equatorial Pacific;Arabian Sea;JGOFS;geostrophic current.</keywords>
				<authors>
						<name first="S." last="Nakamoto">S. Nakamoto</name>
						<affiliation>Earth Science and Technology Organization, Bussan bldg Annex, 1-2-1 Nshi-shinbashi, Minatoku, Tokyo 105 Japan.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. Prasanna" last="Kumar">S. Prasanna Kumar</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Oceanography Division, National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. M." last="Oberhuber">J. M. Oberhuber</name>
						<affiliation>DKRZ, Bundesstrasse 55, D-20146 Hamburg, Germany.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="H." last="Saito">H. Saito</name>
						<affiliation>Japan Marine Science & Technology Center, 2-15 Natsushima, Yokosuka 237-0004 Japan.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Muneyama">K. Muneyama</name>
						<affiliation>Marine Works Japan, 2-15 Natsushima, Yokosuka 237-0004 Japan.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Frouin">R. Frouin</name>
						<affiliation>Scripps Institution of Oceanography, UCSD, La Jolla, CA, 92093-0221, USA.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Assimilation of IRS-P4 (MSMR) meteorological data in the NCMRWF global data assimilation system</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0351-0364</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Oceansat-1 was successfully launched by India in 1999, with two payloads, namely Multi-frequency Scanning Microwave Radiometer (MSMR) and Ocean Color Monitor (OCM) to study the biological and physical parameters of the ocean. The MSMR sensor is configured as an eight-channel radiometer using four frequencies with dual polarization. The MSMR data at 75km resolution from the Oceansat-I have been assimilated in the National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting (NCMRWF) data assimilation forecast system. The operational analysis and forecast system at NCMRWF is based on a T80L18 global spectral model and Spectral Statistical Inter-polation (SSI) scheme for data analysis. The impact of the MSMR data is seen globally, however it is significant over the oceanic region where conventional data are rare. The dry-nature of the control analyses have been removed by utilizing the MSMR data. Therefore, the total precipitable water data from MSMR has been identified as a very crucial parameter in this study. The impact of surface wind speed from MSMR is to increase easterlies over the tropical Indian Ocean. Shifting of the positions of westerly troughs and ridges in the south Indian Ocean has contributed to reduction of temperature to around $30^\circ S$.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>MSMR data;wind speed;total precipitable water content;GDAS;impact.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Rupa" last="Kamineni">Rupa Kamineni</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, I.I.T., New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. R. H." last="Rizvi">S. R. H. Rizvi</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting (NCMRWF), Mausam Bhavan, Lodi Road, New Delhi 110 003, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. C." last="Kar">S. C. Kar</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting (NCMRWF), Mausam Bhavan, Lodi Road, New Delhi 110 003, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="U. C." last="Mohanty">U. C. Mohanty</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, I.I.T., New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Paliwal">R. K. Paliwal</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting (NCMRWF), Mausam Bhavan, Lodi Road, New Delhi 110 003, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Meteorological fields variability over the Indian seas in pre and summer monsoon months during extreme monsoon seasons</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0365-0378</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this study, the possible linkage between summer monsoon rainfall over India and surface meteorological fields (basic fields and heat budget components) over monsoon region ($30^\circ E--120^\circ E, 30^\circ S--30^\circ N$) during the pre-monsoon month of May and summer monsoon season (June to September) are examined. For this purpose, monthly surface meteorological fields anomaly are analyzed for 42 years (1958--1999) using reanalysis data of NCEP/NCAR (National Center for Environmental Prediction/National Center for Atmospheric Research). The statistical significance of the anomaly (difference) between the surplus and deficient monsoon years in the surface meteorological fields are also examined by Student's t-test at 95% confidence level.</p>
					<p>Significant negative anomalies of mean sea level pressure are observed over India, Arabian Sea and Arabian Peninsular in the pre-monsoon month of May and monsoon season. Significant positive anomalies in the zonal and meridional wind (at 2m) in the month of May are observed in the west Arabian Sea off Somali coast and for monsoon season it is in the central Arabian Sea that extends up to Somalia. Significant positive anomalies of the surface temperature and air temperature (at 2m) in the month of May are observed over north India and adjoining Pakistan and Afghanistan region. During monsoon season this region is replaced by significant negative anomalies. In the month of May, significant positive anomalies of cloud amount are observed over Somali coast, north Bay of Bengal and adjoining West Bengal and Bangladesh. During monsoon season, cloud amount shows positive anomalies over NW India and north Arabian Sea.</p>
					<p>There is overall reduction in the incoming shortwave radiation flux during surplus monsoon years. A higher magnitude of latent heat flux is also found in surplus monsoon years for the month of May as well as the monsoon season. The significant positive anomaly of latent heat flux in May, observed over southwest Arabian Sea, may be considered as an advance indicator of the possible behavior of the subsequent monsoon season. The distribution of net heat flux is predominantly negative over eastern Arabian Sea, Bay of Bengal and Indian Ocean. Anomaly between the two extreme monsoon years in post 1980 (i.e., 1988 and 1987) shows that shortwave flux, latent heat flux and net heat flux indicate reversal in sign, particularly in south Indian Ocean. Variations of the heat budget components over four smaller sectors of Indian seas, namely Arabian Sea, Bay of Bengal and west Indian Ocean and east Indian Ocean show that a small sector of Arabian Sea is most dominant during May and other sectors showing reversal in sign of latent heat flux during monsoon season.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Summer monsoon;heat budget components;NCEP reanalysis;Student’s t-test.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="U. C." last="Mohanty">U. C. Mohanty</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology-Delhi, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
						<email>mohanty@cas.iitd.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Bhatla">R. Bhatla</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology-Delhi, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P. V. S." last="Raju">P. V. S. Raju</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology-Delhi, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="O. P." last="Madan">O. P. Madan</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology-Delhi, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Sarkar">A. Sarkar</name>
						<affiliation>Modi College of Engineering and Technology, Lakshamangarh, Sikar, Rajasthan, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="04" month="12" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Isotopic and sedimentological clues to productivity change in Late Riphean Sea: A case study from two intracratonic basins of India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0379-0390</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Enriched $^{13}C/^{12}C$ ratios with $\delta ^{13} C \sim 3‰$ (w.r.t PDB) of two Late Riphean ($\sim 700--610Ma$) intracratonic carbonate successions viz., Bhander Limestone of Vindhyan Basin and Raipur Limestone of Chattisgarh Basin suggest higher organic productivity during this period. This view is supported by sedimentological evidence of higher biohermal growth and consequent increase in depositional relief in the low gradient ramp settings inferred for these basins. Oxygen isotope analysis of these carbonates show distinct segregation between enriched deeper water carbonate mudstone and depleted shallow water stromatolite facies that received fresh water influx. This shows that facies-specific analyses can be useful in understanding the depositional setting of these sediments.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>$\delta ^{13}C$;Late Riphean;intracratonic;organic productivity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P. P." last="Chakraborty">P. P. Chakraborty</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Applied Geology, Indian School of Mines, Dhanbad 826 004, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Sarkar">A. Sarkar</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Geology and Geophysics, Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur 721 302, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. K." last="Bhattacharya">S. K. Bhattacharya</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Sanyal">P. Sanyal</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-01-07</date>
					<date type="R">2002-08-18</date
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Grenvillian thermal event and remnant charnockite: Isotopic evidence from the Chilka Lake granulite-migmatite suite in the Eastern Ghats belt, India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0391-0399</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Spectacular exposures of granulite-migmatite occur in the Chilka Lake area of the Eastern Ghats belt. The garnetiferous granite gneiss of peraluminous granitic composition, often contains restitic metapelite inclusions and is demonstrably a product of biotite-dehydration melting in pelitic rocks. On the other hand, older layers and bands of charnockitic rocks frequently occur as dismembered patches within the peraluminous granite, thus imparting a measled appearance of the granite exposures.</p>
					<p>The partial melting and emplacement of the peraluminous granite represent the Grenvillian thermal event, as evidenced by Rb-Sr whole rock and Pb-Pb zircon dating. On the other hand, minor patches of charnockite represent migmatized relict, as evidenced by some older zircons, in addition to those of Grenvillian age.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Granite-migmatite;Grenvillian event;zircon population;remnant charnockite.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Bhattacharya">S. Bhattacharya</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T.Road, Calcutta 700 035, India.</affiliation>
						<email>samar@isical.ac.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. P." last="Deomurari">M. P. Deomurari</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="W." last="Teixeira">W. Teixeira</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Geosciences, Sao Paulo University, Brazil.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-04-02</date>
					<date type="R">2002-07-30</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Reflection of \textit {P} and \textit {SV} waves at the free surface of a monoclinic elastic half-space</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0401-0412</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The propagation of plane waves in an anisotropic elastic medium possessing monoclinic symmetry is discussed. The expressions for the phase velocity of \textit {qP} and \textit {qSV} waves propagating in the plane of elastic symmetry are obtained in terms of the direction cosines of the propagation vector. It is shown that, in general, \textit {qP} waves are not longitudinal and \textit {qSV} waves are not transverse. Pure longitudinal and pure transverse waves can propagate only in certain specific directions. Closed-form expressions for the reflection coefficients of \textit {qP} and \textit {qSV} waves incident at the free surface of a homogeneous monoclinic elastic half-space are obtained. These expressions are used for studying numerically the variation of the reflection coefficients with the angle of incidence. The present analysis corrects some fundamental errors appearing in recent papers on the subject.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Anisotropic medium;elastic waves;monoclinic half-space;reflection coefficients.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Sarva Jit" last="Singh">Sarva Jit Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Maharshi Dayanand University, Rohtak 124 001, India.</affiliation>
						<email>s−j−singh@yahoo.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sandhya" last="Khurana">Sandhya Khurana</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Maharshi Dayanand University, Rohtak 124 001, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-06-17</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Characteristics of low frequency oscillations of the atmosphere-ocean coupling</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0413-0423</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The low frequency oscillation of latent heat flux over the tropical oceans has been studied. The NCEP reanalyzed fields of wind and humidity alongwith Reynolds SST are used to compute the instantaneous as well as monthly mean surface latent heat fluxes (LHF) for the year 1999. The procedure of LHF computation is based on bulk method. Spectral analysis shows that significant energy is contained in Madden Julian Oscillation band in the winds, SST, moisture and in  the latent heat flux. The global distribution of wind, humidity, SST and LHF oscillation on the time scale of 30-50 days are analyzed. Maximum amplitude of oscillation on this time scale in all the above mentioned parameters were found over the Indian Ocean. The fluctuation of surface wind speed and moisture controls the latent heat flux on this time scale. The fluctuation of SST on this time scale does not seem to be important over most of the oceans.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>NCEP (National Center for Environmental Prediction);COADS (Comprehensive Ocean Atmosphere Data Set);LHF (Surface Latent Heat Flux);MJO (Madden Julian Oscillation);FFT (Fast Fourier Transformation).</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Randhir" last="Singh">Randhir Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Atmospheric Sciences Division, Meteorology & Oceanography Group, Space Applications Centre (SAC), ISRO, Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B." last="Simon">B. Simon</name>
						<affiliation>Atmospheric Sciences Division, Meteorology & Oceanography Group, Space Applications Centre (SAC), ISRO, Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P. C." last="Joshi">P. C. Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Atmospheric Sciences Division, Meteorology & Oceanography Group, Space Applications Centre (SAC), ISRO, Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-10-31</date>
					<date type="R">2002-03-26</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Detection of marine aerosols with IRS P4-Ocean Colour Monitor</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0425-0435</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The atmospheric correction bands 7 and 8 (765nm and 865nm respectively) of the Indian Remote Sensing Satellite IRS P4-OCM (Ocean Colour Monitor) can be used for deriving aerosol optical depth (AOD) over the oceans. A retrieval algorithm has been developed which computes the AOD using band 7 data by treating the ocean surface as a dark background after removing the Rayleigh path radiance in the sensor-detected radiances. This algorithm has been used to detect marine aerosol distributions at different coastal and offshore locations around India.</p>
					<p>A comparison between OCM derived AOD and the NOAA operational AOD shows a correlation $\sim 0.92$ while that between OCM derived AOD and the ground-based sun photometer measurements near the coast of Trivandrum shows a correlation of $\sim 0.90$.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>IRS P4-OCM;Ocean Colour Monitor;aerosol optical depth;marine aerosols;aerosol plumes.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Indrani" last="Das">Indrani Das</name>
						<affiliation>Marine Science and Coastal Environment Division, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
						<email>dindrani@rediffmail.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Mohan">M. Mohan</name>
						<affiliation>Marine Science and Coastal Environment Division, Space Applications Centre (ISRO), Ahmedabad 380 015, India</affiliation>
						<email>mannilmohan@yahoo.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Krishnamoorthy">K. Krishnamoorthy</name>
						<affiliation>Space Physics Laboratory, Vikram Sarabhai Space Centre (ISRO), Trivandrum 695 022, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-08-02</date>
					<date type="R">2002-03-05</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Study on the sensitivity of the vertical cooling (heat sink) on the displacements of the mid-tropospheric ridge using a linear model</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0437-0451</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A linear model of the response of a stratified atmosphere to isolated heat sources in spherical coordinates is used to study the maintenance of the mean position of the mid tropospheric ridge and its displacement. It is well known that the performance of the southwest Indian monsoon is related to the latitudinal position of the April 500 hPa ridge along $75^\circ E$. It was demonstrated that an anomalous cooling associated with the increased snow cover in Eurasia can result in moderate southward displacement of the mid-tropospheric ridge. The results of this study indicate that the vertically integrated cooling rate (strength of heat sink) has more effect on the southward displacement of the ridge when the sink is closer to the ridge.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Eurasian snow cover;mid-tropospheric ridge;southwest Indian monsoon;normal modes;heat sources and heat sinks.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Chandrasekar">A. Chandrasekar</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Physics and Meteorology, Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur 721 302, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1998-06-04</date>
					<date type="R">2000-05-29</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Characteristics of monsoon low level jet (MLLJ) as an index of monsoon activity</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0453-0457</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Temperature and wind data are used to describe variation in the strength of the Monsoon Low Level Jet (MLLJ) from an active phase of the monsoon to a break phase. Also estimated are the characteristics of turbulence above and below MLLJ.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Monsoon Low Level Jet (MLLJ);turbulence;wind shear.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. V." last="Sam">N. V. Sam</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India</affiliation>
						<email>nelson@cas.iitd.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. P. R. Vittal" last="Murty">K. P. R. Vittal Murty</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Meteorology and Oceanography, Andhra University, Visakhapatnam 530 003, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">1997-04-28</date>
					<date type="R">2002-06-05</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Multidimensional scaling technique for analysis of magnetic storms at Indian observatories</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0459-0465</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Multidimensional scaling is a powerful technique for analysis of data. The latitudinal dependenceof geomagnetic field variation in horizontal component (H) during magnetic storms is analysed in this paper by employing this technique.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Multidimensional scaling;covering distance;storm time range.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Sridharan">M. Sridharan</name>
						<affiliation>IIG Magnetic Observatory, Pondicherry 605 014, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. M. S." last="Ramasamy">A. M. S. Ramasamy</name>
						<affiliation>Professor of Mathematics, Pondicherry University, Pondicherry 605 014, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-08-02</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Magnetic rock properties of the gabbros from the ODP Drill Hole 1105 A of the Atlantis Bank, Southwest Indian Ridge</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0467-0481</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Laboratory studies of 30 samples from 158m long drill core of the Hole 1105A (ODP Leg 179) of the Atlantis Bank, Southwest Indian Ridge have revealed magnetic properties of the gabbros, olivine gabbros, oxide gabbros and olivine oxide gabbros down the core. Comparison of modal proportions of the oxides, grain sizes and magnetization parameters of the rocks has confirmed that most coarse-grained oxide mineral bearing rocks record low Koenigsberger ratio (2 to 5) and median destructive fields (5 to 7 mT). Average natural remanent magnetization (\textit {J_{nrm}}) and stable remanent magnetization (\textit {J_{st}}) of the core samples are 5.8A/m and 1.9 A/m, respectively. Their mean stable magnetic inclination is $66^\circ \pm 4^\circ $, about $14^\circ $ steeper than the expected dipole inclination of the area similar to the one reported at Hole 735 B. The excess inclination perhaps marks a tectonic block rotation of the reversely magnetized rocks of the bank. We interpret that gabbros and serpentinites devoid of basaltic carapace significantly contribute to seafloor spreading anomalies of the bank.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Southwest Indian Ridge;Atlantis Bank;ODP Drill Hole 1105 A;gabbros;serpentinites.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D. Gopala" last="Rao">D. Gopala Rao</name>
						<affiliation>National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
						<email>gopalrao@csnio.ren.nic.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Krishna">K. S. Krishna</name>
						<affiliation>National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-02-18</date>
					<date type="R">2002-07-24</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Comments on ‘Generation of Deccan Trap magmas’ by Gautam Sen</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0483-0485</page>
				<abstract></abstract>
				<keywords>Volcanism;eruption;basalt;lava;Deccan.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="H. C." last="Sheth">H. C. Sheth</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Geology & Geophysics, School of Ocean & Earth Science & Technology (SOEST), University of Hawaii at Manoa, Honolulu HI 96822 U.S.A.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-04-26</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Giant Plagioclase Basalts, eruption rate versus time: Response to Sheth’s comments and some additional thoughts</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0487-0488</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Deccan Trap;Giant Plagioclase Basalts;eruption duration.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Gautam" last="Sen">Gautam Sen</name>
						<affiliation>Florida Center for Electron Microscopy, Florida International University, University Park, Miami, FL 33199.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-06-27</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Comments on ‘No K/T boundary at Anjar, Gujarat, India: Evidence from magnetic susceptibility and carbon isotopes’ by H J Hansen, D M Mohabey and P Toft</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0489-0491</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A. D." last="Shukla">A. D. Shukla</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India</affiliation>
						<email>anilds@prl.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P. N." last="Shukla">P. N. Shukla</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-12-04</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Reply to the comments by A D Shukla and P N Shukla</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0493-0497</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Iridium;rhyolites, paleomagnetics;Deccan;Lameta.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="H. J." last="Hansen">H. J. Hansen</name>
						<affiliation>Geological Institute, Oster Voldgade 10, DK-1350, Denmark.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D. M." last="Mohabey">D. M. Mohabey</name>
						<affiliation>Geological Survey of India, Seminary Hills, Nagpur 440 006, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Toft">P. Toft</name>
						<affiliation>Geological Institute, Oster Voldgade 10, DK-1350, Denmark.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-04-22</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="112">
		<issue inum="01" month="03" year="2003">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Late Quaternary sea level and environmental changes from relic carbonate deposits of the western margin of India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0025</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Relic carbonate deposits along the western margin of India occur as dolomite crusts, aragonite sands (pelletal / oolitic) and aragonite-cemented limestones, oyster shells, corals, encrusted coralline algal and foraminiferal-dominated nodules. The petrology and mineralogy of the deposits indicate that except for aragonite sands and foraminiferal nodules, the others were formed in shallow marine conditions and serve as sea level indicators. Radiocarbon dates were measured for 62 relic deposits covering the entire margin. The age of these deposits on the continental shelf off Cape Comorin and Mangalore, between 110 and 18m depth, ranges between 12, 610 $^{14}C$ yr BP and 6,390 $^{14}C$ yr BP. On the northwestern margin of India, especially on the carbonate platform (between 64 and 100 m), the age ranges from 17,250 to 6,730 $^{14}C$ yr BP. The relic deposits of the Gulf of Kachchh at depths between 35 and 25m are dated at 12,550--9,630 $^{14}C$ yr BP. The age vs. depth plot of the relic deposits further indicates that the Gulf of Kachchh was inundated much early, atleast by 15 ka, after the Last Glacial Maximum, and was subjected to uplift and subsidence during the Holocene. The carbonate platform subsided during the early Holocene. Some of the relic deposits between Cape Comorin and Mangalore plot on or, closely follow the glacio-eustatic sea level curve. Despite abundant siliciclastic flux discharged by the Narmada and Tapti during the early Holocene, the platform off these rivers is largely devoid of this flux and carbonate sedimentation continued until 6,700 $^{14}C$ yr BP. We suggest that the river-derived ediment flux diverted southwards under the influence of the SW monsoon current and, thereby, increased the turbidity on the shelf and slope southeast of the carbonate platform and facilitated the formation of deeper water foraminiferal nodules off Vengurla-Goa.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Late Quaternary sea level;western margin of India;subsidence;uplift;depositional environment.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="V. Purnachandra" last="Rao">V. Purnachandra Rao</name>
						<affiliation>National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Rajagopalan">G. Rajagopalan</name>
						<affiliation>Birbal Sahni Institute of Palaeobotany, 53 University Road, Lucknow, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. H." last="Vora">K. H. Vora</name>
						<affiliation>National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="F." last="Almeida">F. Almeida</name>
						<affiliation>National Institute of Oceanography, Dona Paula, Goa 403 004, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-04-22</date>
					<date type="R">2002-09-30</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Effects of galvanic distortions on magnetotelluric data: Interpretation and its correction using deep electrical data</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0027-0036</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The non-inductive galvanic disturbances due to surficial bodies, lying smaller than high frequency skin depth, cause serious interpretational errors in magnetotelluric data. These frequency independent distortions result in a quasi-static shift between the apparent resistivity curves known as static shift. Two-dimensional modelling studies, for the effects of surficial bodies on magnetotelluric interpretation, show that the transverse electric (TE) mode apparent resistivity curves are hardly affected compared to the transverse magnetic (TM) mode curves, facilitating the correction by using a curve shifting method to match low frequency asymptotes. But in the case of field data the problem is rather complicated because of the random distribution of geometry and conductivity of near surface inhomogeneities. Here we present the use of deep resistivity sounding (DRS) data to constrain MT static shift. Direct current sensitivity studies show that the behaviour of MT static shift can be estimated using DC resistivity measurements close to the MT sounding station to appreciable depths. The distorted data set is corrected using the MT response for DRS model and further subject to joint inversion with DRS data. Joint inversion leads to better estimation of MT parameters compared to the separate inversion of data sets.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Magnetotelluric;deep resistivity sounding;galvanic distortion;static shift;joint inversion.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Jimmy" last="Stephen">Jimmy Stephen</name>
						<affiliation>National Geophysical Research Institute, # 66, Hyderabad 500 007, India. e-mail: jimmy@ngri.res.in</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. G." last="Gokarn">S. G. Gokarn</name>
						<affiliation>Indian Institute of Geomagnetism, Colaba, Mumbai 400 005, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="C." last="Manoj">C. Manoj</name>
						<affiliation>National Geophysical Research Institute, # 66, Hyderabad 500 007, India. e-mail: jimmy@ngri.res.in</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. B." last="Singh">S. B. Singh</name>
						<affiliation>National Geophysical Research Institute, # 66, Hyderabad 500 007, India. e-mail: jimmy@ngri.res.in</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-12-04</date>
					<date type="R">2002-08-10</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>2D Stabilised analytic signal method in DC pole-pole potential data interpretation</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0037-0049</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Using analytic signal method, interpretation of pole-pole secondary electric potentials due to 2D conductive/resistive prisms is presented. The estimated parameters are the location, lateral extent or width and depth to top surface of the prism. Forward modelling is attempted by 2D-Finite Difference method. The proposed stabilised analytic signal algorithm (RES2AS) uses Tikhonov's regularization scheme and FFT routines. The algorithm is tested on three theoretical examples and field data from the campus of Roorkee University. The stability of RES2AS is also tested on synthetic error prone secondary pole-pole potential data.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Analytic signal;regularisation;secondary electric potentials.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Paras R." last="Pujari">Paras R. Pujari</name>
						<affiliation>Scientist, National Environmental Engineering Research Institute (NEERI), Nehru Marg, Nagpur 440 020, India</affiliation>
						<email>prpujari@nagpur.dot.net.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Rambhatla G." last="Sastry">Rambhatla G. Sastry</name>
						<affiliation>Associate Professor, Department of Earth Sciences, IIT, Roorkee 247 667, India</affiliation>
						<email>rgss1fes@rurkiu.ernet.in</email>
						<email>rgssastry@yahoo.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-10-31</date>
					<date type="R">2002-08-20</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Dissolved helium and TDS in groundwater from Bhavnagar in Gujarat: Unrelated to seismic events between August 2000 and January 2001</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0051-0060</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Temporal variations have been observed in both dissolved helium and TDS in the form of increase in basaltic and decrease in alluvial aquifers. The increase in basaltic aquifers has been explained by enhanced pumping of old groundwater with relatively higher concentration of dissolved helium and salt, whereas the decrease in alluvial aquifers has been explained by dilution from the post monsoon groundwater recharge. Therefore, the observed temporal variations cannot be ascribed to the contemporary enhanced seismic activity in this region since August-September 2000.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Groundwater;Helium;TDS;Bhavnagar;seismicity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. K." last="Gupta">S. K. Gupta</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. D." last="Deshpande">R. D. Deshpande</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Research Laboratory, P.O. Box 4218, Navrangpura, Ahmedabad 380 009, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-01-01</date>
					<date type="R">2002-08-30</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Indian Ocean surface winds from NCMRWF analysis as compared to QuikSCAT and moored buoy winds</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0061-0077</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The quality of the surface wind analysis at the National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasts (NCMRWF), New Delhi over the tropical Indian Ocean and its improvement in 2001 are examined by comparing it with \textit {in situ} buoy measurements and satellite derived surface winds from NASA QuikSCAT satellite (QSCT) during 1999, 2000 and 2001. The NCMRWF surface winds su ered from easterly bias of $1.0--1.5 ms^{-1}$ in the equatorial Indian Ocean (IO) and northerly bias of $2.0--3.0 ms^{-1}$ in the south equatorial IO during 1999 and 2000 compared to QSCT winds. The amplitude of daily variability was also underestimated compared to that in QSCT. In particular, the amplitude of daily variability of NCMRWF winds in the eastern equatorial IO was only about 60% of that of QSCT during 1999 and 2000. The NCMRWF surface winds during 2001 have significantly improved with the bias of the mean analyzed winds considerably reduced everywhere bringing it to within $0.5 ms^{-1}$ of QSCT winds in the equatorial IO. The amplitude and phase of daily and intraseasonal variability are very close to that in QSCT almost everywhere during 2001. It is shown that the weakness in the surface wind analysis during 1999 and 2000 and its improvement in 2001 are related to the weakness in simulation of precipitation by the forecast model in the equatorial IO and its improvement in 2001. </p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Equatorial Indian Ocean;ocean surface forcing;NCMRWF analysed winds;scatterometer winds.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="B. N." last="Goswami">B. N. Goswami</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="E. N." last="Rajagopal">E. N. Rajagopal</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting, Department of Science and Technology, Mausam Bhavan, Lodi Road, New Delhi 110 003, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-08-12</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Impact of horizontal resolution on prediction of tropical cyclones over Bay of Bengal using a regional weather prediction model</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0079-0093</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The present study is carried out to examine the performance of a regional atmospheric model in forecasting tropical cyclones over the Bay of Bengal and its sensitivity to horizontal resolution. Two cyclones, which formed over the Bay of Bengal during the years 1995 and 1997, are simulated using a regional weather prediction model with two horizontal resolutions of 165km and 55 km. The model is found to perform reasonably well towards simulation of the storms. The structure, intensity and track of the cyclones are found to be better simulated by finer resolution of the model as compared to the coarse resolution. Rainfall amount and its distribution are also found to be sensitive to the model horizontal resolution. Other important fields, viz., vertical velocity, horizontal divergence and horizontal moisture flux are also found to be sensitive to model horizontal resolution and are better simulated by the model with finer horizontal grids.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Tropical cyclone;resolution;track;regional model.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Mandal">M. Mandal</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="U. C." last="Mohanty">U. C. Mohanty</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. V. J." last="Potty">K. V. J. Potty</name>
						<affiliation>Alfred Wegener Institute for Polar and Marine Research, Bremerhaven, Germany.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Sarkar">A. Sarkar</name>
						<affiliation>Modi College of Engineering and Technology, Lakshmangarh, Sikar, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-01-25</date>
					<date type="R">2002-04-02</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Indian summer monsoon as revealed by NCMRWF system</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0095-0111</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In this study, we present the mean seasonal features of the Indian summer monsoon circulation in the National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting (NCMRWF) global data assimilation and forecast system. The large-scale budgets of heat and moisture are examined in the analyzed and model atmosphere. The daily operational analyses and forecasts (day 1 through day 5) produced for the summer seasons comprising June, July and August of 1995 and 1993 have been considered for the purpose. The principal aim of the study is two-fold. Primarily, to comprehend the influence of the systematic errors over the Indian summer monsoon, secondarily, to analyze the performance of the model in capturing the interseasonal variability.</p>
					<p>The heat and moisture balances show reduction in the influx of heat and moisture in the model forecasts compared to the analyzed atmosphere over the monsoon domain. Consequently, the diabatic heating also indicates reducing trend with increase in the forecast period. In effect, the strength of Indian summer monsoon, which essentially depends on these parameters, weakens considerably in the model forecasts. Despite producing feeble monsoon circulation, the model captures interseasonal variability realistically. Although, 1995 and 1993 are fairly normal monsoon seasons, the former received more rainfall compared to the latter in certain pockets of the monsoon domain. This is clearly indicated by the analyzed and model atmosphere in terms of energetics.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Summer monsoon;energy budgets;systematic errors;interseasonal variability.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P. L. S." last="Rao">P. L. S. Rao</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="U. C." last="Mohanty">U. C. Mohanty</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P. V. S." last="Raju">P. V. S. Raju</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Gopal" last="Iyengar">Gopal Iyengar</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting, Mausam Bhavan Complex, Lodi Road, New Delhi 110 003, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-04-30</date>
					<date type="R">2002-04-22</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Laser microprobe for the study of noble gases and nitrogen in single grains: A case study of individual chondrules from the Dhajala meteorite</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0113-0127</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A laser microprobe capable of analysing nitrogen and noble gases in individual grains with masses less than a milligram is described. It can be used in both continuous wave (CW) mode, useful for stepwise heating of an individual grain, as well as in pulsed mode, useful for ablating material from a small selected area of a sample, for gas extraction. We could achieve low blanks (in ccSTP units) for $^{4}He(4.8 \times 10^{-12}),^{22}Ne(1.0 \times 10^{-12}),^{36}Ar(1.0 \times 10^{-13}),^{84}Kr(2.9 \times 10^{-14}),^{132}Xe(2.6 \times 10^{-14})$, and N (87 pg), using this system. Preliminary data for individual chondrules from the Dhajala meteorite show that noble gases and nitrogen from grains as small as 170 microgram can be analysed using the present laser microprobe setup. The amount of trapped neon in Dhajala chondrules is very small, and nitrogen in the chondrules is isotopically heavier as compared to the bulk meteorite.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Laser;mass spectrometer;noble gases;nitrogen;chondrule;meteorite.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R. R." last="Mahajan">R. R. Mahajan</name>
						<affiliation>Planetary and Geosciences Division, Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. V. S." last="Murty">S. V. S. Murty</name>
						<affiliation>Planetary and Geosciences Division, Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad 380 009, India</affiliation>
						<email>murty@prl.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-06-27</date>
					<date type="R">2002-10-30</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="06" year="2003">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Preface</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0129-0129</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="D. R." last="Sikka">D. R. Sikka</name>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="R">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="A">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="E">2014-09-30</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Some salient features of the atmosphere observed over the north Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0131-0146</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>This paper describes the near surface characteristics and vertical variations based on the observations made at $17.5^\circ N$ and $89^\circ E$ from ORV Sagar Kanya in the north Bay of Bengal during the Bay of Bengal Monsoon Experiment (BOBMEX) carried out in July--August 1999. BOBMEX captured both the active and weak phases of convection. SST remained above the convection threshold  throughout the BOBMEX. While the response of the SST to atmospheric forcing was clearly observed, the response of the atmosphere to SST changes was not clear. SST decreased during periods of large scale precipitation, and increased during a weak phase of convection. It is shown that the latent heat flux at comparable wind speeds was about 25--50% lower over the Bay during BOBMEX compared to that over the Indian Ocean during other seasons and tropical west Pacific. On the other hand, the largest variations in the surface daily net heat flux are observed over the Bay during BOBMEX. SST predicted using observed surface fluxes showed that 1-D heat balance model works sometime but not always, and horizontal advection is important. The high resolution Vaisala radiosondes launched during BOBMEX could clearly bring out the changes in the vertical structure of the atmosphere between active and weak phases of convection. Convective Available Potential Energy of the surface air decreased by 2--3 kJ $kg^{−1}$ following convection, and recovered  in a time period of one or two days. The mid tropospheric relative humidity and water vapor content, and wind direction show the major changes between the active and weak phases of convection.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Monsoon;air-sea coupling;tropical convection;boundary layer.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="G. S." last="Bhat">G. S. Bhat</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India.</affiliation>
						<email>bhat@caos.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A study on the structure of the convective atmosphere over the Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX-99</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0147-0163</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Convective activity is one of the major processes in the atmosphere influencing the local and large scale weather in the tropics. The latent heat released by the cumulus cloud is known to drive monsoon circulation, which on the other hand supplies the moisture that maintains the cumulus clouds. An investigation is carried out on the convective structure of the atmosphere during active and suppressed periods of convection using data sets obtained from the Bay of Bengal and Monsoon Experiment (BOBMEX). The cumulus convection though being a small-scale phenomenon, still influences its embedding environment by interaction through various scales. This study shows the variation in the kinematic and convective parameters during the transition from suppressed to active periods of convection. Convergence in the lower levels and strong upward vertical velocity, significant during active convection are associated with the formation of monsoon depressions. The apparent heat source due to latent heat release and the vertical transport of the eddy heat by cumulus convection, and the apparent moisture sink due to net condensation and vertical divergence of the eddy transport of moisture, are estimated through residuals of the thermodynamic equation and examined in relation to monsoon activity during BOBMEX.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Convection;monsoon depression;Bay of Bengal;BOBMEX.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="U. C." last="Mohanty">U. C. Mohanty</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi, New Delhi, India.</affiliation>
						<email>mohanty@cas.iitd.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. V." last="Sam">N. V. Sam</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi, New Delhi, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Das">S. Das</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting, Lodhi Road, New Delhi, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. N. V." last="Satyanarayana">A. N. V. Satyanarayana</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi, New Delhi, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Circulation characteristics of a monsoon depression during BOBMEX-99 using high-resolution analysis</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0165-0184</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The skill and efficiency of a numerical model mostly varies with the quality of initial values, accuracy on parameterization of physical processes and horizontal and vertical resolution of the model. Commonly used low-resolution reanalyses are hardly able to capture the prominent features associated with organized convective processes in a monsoon depression. The objective is to prepare improved high-resolution analysis by the use of MM5 modelling system developed by the Pennsyl- vania State University/National Center for Atmospheric Research (PSU/NCAR). It requires the objective comparison of high and low-resolution analysis datasets in assessing the specific convective features of a monsoon depression. For this purpose, reanalysis datasets of NCAR/NCEP (National Center for Atmospheric Research/National Centers for Environmental Prediction) at a horizontal resolution of $2.5^\circ $ (latitude/longitude) have been used as first guess in the objective analysis scheme. The additional asynoptic datasets obtained during BOBMEX-99 are utilized within the assimilation process. Cloud Motion Wind (CMW) data of METEOSAT satellite and SSM/I surface wind data are included for the improvement of derived analysis. The multiquadric (MQD) interpolation technique is selected and applied for meteorological objective analysis at a horizontal resolution of 30 km. After a successful inclusion of additional data, the resulting reanalysis is able to produce the structure of convective organization as well as prominent synoptic features associated with monsoon depression. Comparison and error verifications have been done with the help of available upper-air station data. The objective verification reveals the efficiency of the analysis scheme.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>BOBMEX;high-resolution analysis;monsoon depression;MM5.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Ananda K." last="Das">Ananda K. Das</name>
						<affiliation>Center for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="U. C." last="Mohanty">U. C. Mohanty</name>
						<affiliation>Center for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Someshwar" last="Das">Someshwar Das</name>
						<affiliation>National Center for Medium Range Weather Forecasting, Mausam Bhavan, Lodhi Road, New Delhi 110 003.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Mandal">M. Mandal</name>
						<affiliation>Center for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. R." last="Kalsi">S. R. Kalsi</name>
						<affiliation>India Meteorological Department, Mausam Bhavan, Lodhi Road, New Delhi 110 003.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Simulation of Marine Boundary Layer characteristics using a 1-D PBL model over the Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX-99</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0185-0204</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The characteristic features of the marine boundary layer (MBL) over the Bay of Bengal during the southwest monsoon and the factors influencing it are investigated. The Bay of Bengal and Monsoon Experiment (BOBMEX) carried out during July--August 1999 is the first observational experiment under the Indian Climate Research Programme (ICRP). A very high-resolution data in the vertical was obtained during this experiment, which was used to study the MBL characteristics off the east coast of India in the north and south Bay of Bengal. Spells of active and suppressed convection over the Bay were observed, of which, three representative convective episodes were considered for the study. For this purpose a one-dimensional multi-level PBL model with a TKE$-\varepsilon $ closure scheme was used. The soundings, viz., the vertical profiles of temperature, humidity, zonal and meridional component of wind, obtained onboard ORV Sagar Kanya and from coastal stations along the east coast are used for the study. The temporal evolution of turbulent kinetic energy, marine boundary layer height (MBLH), sensible and latent heat fluxes and drag coefficient of momentum are simulated for different epochs of monsoon and monsoon depressions during BOBMEX-99.The model also generates the vertical profiles of potential temperature, specific humidity, zonal and meridional wind. These simulated values compared reasonably well with the observations available from BOBMEX.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sensible and latent heat fluxes;marine boundary layer;turbulent kinetic energy.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. V." last="Sam">N. V. Sam</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="U. C." last="Mohanty">U. C. Mohanty</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
						<email>mohanty@cas.iitd.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. N. V." last="Satyanarayana">A. N. V. Satyanarayana</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology, Hauz Khas, New Delhi 110 016, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Study of total column atmospheric aerosol optical depth, ozone and precipitable water content over Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX-99</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0205-0221</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The spatial and temporal variations in aerosols and precursor gases over oceanic regions have special importance in the estimation of radiative forcing parameters and thereby in the refinement of general circulation models. Extensive observations of the columnar aerosol optical depth (AOD), total column ozone (TCO) and precipitable water content (PWC) have been carried out using the on-line, multi-band solar radiometers onboard ORV Sagar Kanya (Cruise # SK 147B) over Bay of Bengal during 11th--28th August 1999. Aerosol optical and physical properties (optical depth and angstrom parameter) have been estimated at six wavelengths covering from UV to NIR (380--1020 nm) while TCO and PWC have been determined using the UV band around 300nm and NIR band around 940 nm, respectively. Added, concurrent meteorological and satellite observations during this field phase of BOBMEX-99 have been utilized to investigate spectral-temporal variations of AOD, TCO and PWC in marine environment.</p>
					<p>The results indicate lower AODs (around 0.4 at characteristic wavelength of 500 nm) and size distributions with abundance of coarse-mode particles as compared to those aerosols of typical land origin. An interesting result that is found in the present study is the significant reduction in AOD at all wavelengths from initial to later part of observation period due to cloud-scavenging and rain-washout effects as well as signature of coastal aerosol loading. The clear-sky daytime diurnal variation of TCO shows gradual increase during post-sunrise hours, broad maximum during afternoon hours and gradual decrease during pre-sunset hours, which is considered to be due to photochemical reactions. The diurnal variation curve of PWC showed maximum ($\sim 4cm$) during morning hours and gradual decrease ($\sim 3.5cm$) towards evening hours, which are found to be greater as compared to typical values over land. Another interesting feature observed is that although the PWC values are very high, there was no proportionate or appreciable enhancement in AOD--a feature that can be utilized to infer composition of aerosols over the study region.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Bay of Bengal;total column aerosol optical depth;size distribution; ozone;precipitable water content;ship;TOMS;satellite.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. K." last="Dani">K. K. Dani</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Meteorology and Aerology Division, Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Dr. Homi Bhabha Marg, Pune 411 008, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. S." last="Maheskumar">R. S. Maheskumar</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Meteorology and Aerology Division, Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Dr. Homi Bhabha Marg, Pune 411 008, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P. C. S." last="Devara">P. C. S. Devara</name>
						<affiliation>Physical Meteorology and Aerology Division, Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Dr. Homi Bhabha Marg, Pune 411 008, India.</affiliation>
						<email>devara@tropmet.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Observed daily large-scale rainfall patterns during BOBMEX-1999</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0223-0232</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A daily rainfall dataset and the corresponding rainfall maps have been produced by objective analysis of rainfall data. The satellite estimate of rainfall and the raingauge values are merged to form the final analysis. Associated with epochs of monsoon these rainfall maps are able to show the rainfall activities over India and the Bay of Bengal region during the BOBMEX period. The intra-seasonal variations of rainfall during BOBMEX are also seen using these data. This dataset over the oceanic region compares well with other available popular datasets like GPCP and CMAP. Over land this dataset brings out the features of monsoon in more detail due to the availability of more local raingauge stations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>BOBMEX;rainfall analysis;monsoon;Bay of Bengal;convection.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A. K." last="Mitra">A. K. Mitra</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting, Mausam Bhavan Complex, Lodi Road, New Delhi 3, India.</affiliation>
						<email>akm@ncmrwf.gov.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. Das" last="Gupta">M. Das Gupta</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting, Mausam Bhavan Complex, Lodi Road, New Delhi 3, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Paliwal">R. K. Paliwal</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting, Mausam Bhavan Complex, Lodi Road, New Delhi 3, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. V." last="Singh">S. V. Singh</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Medium Range Weather Forecasting, Mausam Bhavan Complex, Lodi Road, New Delhi 3, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Thermohaline features of the subsurface cyclonic eddy in the south central Bay of Bengal during August 1999</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0233-0237</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Analysis of the spatial data collected along two sections of temperature and salinity from Chennai to $13^\circ N$ and $87^\circ E$ and back to Chennai onboard INS Sagardhwani during the Bay of Bengal  Monsoon Experiment (BOBMEX) from 10th to 20th August 1999 revealed the presence of a prominent cyclonic eddy centered around 280km away from the coast. Analysis of the dissipation rate of the cyclonic eddy from transect one to transect two and from the analysis of the TOPEX data, it may be inferred that the cyclonic eddy is possibly due to the presence of westward propagating Rossby waves in the Bay of Bengal.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Sagardhwani;BOBMEX;cyclonic eddy;TOPEX;Rossby wave</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Madhusoodanan">P. Madhusoodanan</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Physical and Oceanographic Laboratory, Kochi 682 021, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V. V." last="James">V. V. James</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Physical and Oceanographic Laboratory, Kochi 682 021, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Synoptic weather conditions during BOBMEX</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0239-0253</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We document the flow features, which are associated with the important synoptic systems that affected the Bay of Bengal (BoB) and its neighbourhood and controlled the convective activity there during BOBMEX. The monsoon during July and August, 1999 was subdued. It was slightly more active in the initial phase of BOBMEX that commenced on 15th July 1999 and continued up to first week of August 1999 but weakened during the second half of August. The convection was accordingly affected, reducing the rainfall over India. There were several active and weak spells of convection over the Bay of Bengal that manifested in five low pressure systems, of which twobecame depressions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>BOBMEX;monsoon depression;OLR;intraseasonal oscillation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. R." last="Kalsi">S. R. Kalsi</name>
						<affiliation>India Meteorological Department, Lodi Road, New Delhi 110 003, India.</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Observations of wind and waves in the central Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX-99 and their effect on mixed layer depth variability due to forced mixing</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0255-0266</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Time-series wind and wave measurements were carried out onboard INS Sagardhwani in the central Bay of Bengal during BOBMEX-99. Various other marine meteorological and oceanographic measurements relevant to monsoon studies were also collected simultaneously. The observed variations of wind and waves and the associated mixed layer depth (MLD) variability based on both temperature and density criteria at 3 hourly intervals are presented in this paper as a case study. At the time-series location ($13^\circ N, 87^\circ E$) wind varied between 6 and 16 m/s and the predominant direction was southwesterly. The significant wave height and period varied from 1.9 to 3.7m and 8 to 13 s respectively. Some of the available statistical predictive methods for the determination of MLD by forced mixing are utilized to test the extent of mechanical mixing within the top layer of water by the local wind and wave activity. The same is extended to formulate a new empirical relation for gross estimation of effective depth within which the sound energy is generally trapped during its transmission in the surface duct. The present analysis aiming for estimation of observed MLD variability (35 to 75 m) using the suggested simple empirical relation reveals that, the mixed layer variability observed during the experiment depends on both local ocean variability as well as remote forcing as reported earlier.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Wind, waves and MLD;forced mixing;MLD variability;prediction of MLD;BOBMEX-99.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J." last="Swain">J. Swain</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Physical and Oceanographic Laboratory, Thrikakkara, Kochi 682 021, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Shukla">R. K. Shukla</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Physical and Oceanographic Laboratory, Thrikakkara, Kochi 682 021, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. Raghunadha" last="Rao">A. Raghunadha Rao</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Physical and Oceanographic Laboratory, Thrikakkara, Kochi 682 021, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J. K." last="Panigrahi">J. K. Panigrahi</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Physical and Oceanographic Laboratory, Thrikakkara, Kochi 682 021, India</affiliation>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. R." last="Venkitachalam">N. R. Venkitachalam</name>
						<affiliation>Naval Physical and Oceanographic Laboratory, Thrikakkara, Kochi 682 021, India</affiliation>
					</author>
				</authors>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>000-000</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="R">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="A">2014-09-30</date>
					<date type="E">2014-09-30</date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			
		
		
					
			
</jess>
	
