<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cs SYSTEM "jg.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>

<journal title="Journal of Genetics" short="J. Genet." mnemonic="jg">
	<volume vnum="079">
		<issue inum="01" month="04" year="2000">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Stationary-State Mutagenesis in \textit{Escherichia coli}: a Model</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0007</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Stationary-phase mutagenesis in nondividing \textit{E. coli} cells exposed to a nonlethal stress was, a few years ago, claimed to be a likely case of a Lamarckian mechanism capable of producing exclusively useful mutations in a directed manner. After a heated debate over the last decade it now appears to involve a Darwinian mechanism that generates a transient state of hypermutagenesis, operating on a large number of sites spread over the entire genome, at least in a proportion of the resting cells. Most of the studies that clarified this position were on the reversion of a frameshift mutation present in a \textit{lacI -- lacZ} fusion in \textit{E. coli} strain FC40. Several groups have extensively examined both the sequence changes associated with these reversions and the underlying genetic requirements. On the basis of our studies on the genomic sequence analysis, we recently proposed a model to explain the specific changes associated with the reversion hotspots. Here we propose a more detailed version of this model that also takes into account the observed genetic requirements of stationary-state mutagenesis. Briefly, G:T/U mismatches produced at methylatable cytosines are preferentially repaired in nondividing cells by the very short patch mismatch repair (VSPMR) mechanism which is itself mutagenic and can produce mutations in very short stretches located in the immediate vicinity of these cytosine methylation sites. This mechanism requires a homologous or homeologous strand invasion step and an error-prone DNA synthesis step and is dependent on RecA, RecBCD and a DNA polymerase. The process is initiated near sequences recognized by Dcm and Vsr enzymes and further stimulated if these sequences are a part of CHI or CHI-like sequences, but a double-strand-break-dependent recombination mediated by the RecBCD pathways proposed by others seems to be nonessential. The strand transfer step is proposed to depend on RecA, RuvA, RuvB and RuvC and is opposed by RecG and MutS. The model also gives interesting insights into the evolution of the \textit{E. coli} genome.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>stationary-phase mutagenesis;genome evolution;adaptive mutagenesis;mismatch repair;CHI sequence;\textit{E. coli};cytosine methylation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="S. K." last="Mahajan">S. K. Mahajan</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Agriculture Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email>skmaha@magnum.barc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. V. S. S." last="Narayana Rao">A. V. S. S. Narayana Rao</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Agriculture Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. K." last="Bhattacharjee">S. K. Bhattacharjee</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Agriculture Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-03-29</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Conditions for the Trivers-Willard Hypothesis to be Valid: a Minimal Population-Genetic Model</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0009-0015</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The very insightful Trivers-Willard hypothesis, proposed in the early 1970s, states that females in good physiological condition are more likely to produce male offspring when the variance of reproductive success among males is high. The hypothesis has inspired a number of studies over the last three decades aimed at its experimental verification, and many of them have found adequate supportive evidence in its favour. Theoretical investigations, on the other hand, have been few, perhaps because formulating a population-genetic model for describing the Trivers±Willard hypothesis turns out to be surprisingly complex. The present study is aimed at using a minimal population-genetic model to explore one specific scenario, namely how is the preference for a male offspring by females in good condition altered when $g$, the proportion of such females in the population, changes from a low to a high value. As expected, when the proportion of such females in good condition is low in the population, i.e. for low values of $g$, the Trivers-Willard (TW) strategy goes to fixation against the equal investment strategy. This holds true up to $g_\mathrm{max}$, a critical value of $g$, above which the two strategies coexist, but the proportion of the TW strategy steadily decreases as $g$ increases to unity. Similarly, when the effect of well-endowed males attaining disproportionately high number of matings is more pronounced, the TW strategy is more likely to go to fixation. Interestingly, the success of the TW strategy has a complex dependence on the variance of the physiological condition of females. If the difference in the two types of conditions is not large, TW strategy is favoured, and its success is more likely as the difference increases. However, beyond a critical value of the difference, the TW strategy is found to be less and less likely to succeed as the difference becomes larger. Possible reasons for these effects are discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Trivers-Willard hypothesis;maternal investment;sex ratio theory;optimal resource allocation;mathematical modelling.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. V." last="Joshi">N. V. Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Ecological Sciences, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>nvjoshi@ces.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-03-30</date>
					<date type="R">2000-04-28</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>sY116, a human $Y$-linked polymorphic STS</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0017-0020</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>During a study of deletions of Y-chromosomal DNA in infertile males, sY116, a Y-linked STS, showed different electrophoretic mobilities in three males, two infertile and one fertile. A study of this STS among 35 other normal males showed that this locus is polymorphic. sY116 has a poly A-rich stretch whose instability appears to be the most likely cause of this polymorphism. The possible usefulness of sY116 polymorphism in the detection of subtle genome-wide instabilities in some types of cancer is discussed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>male infertility;polymorphism;Y chromosome;mitotic instability.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="G. Mustafa" last="Saifi">G. Mustafa Saifi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>saifi@mcbl.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Reiner" last="Veitia">Reiner Veitia</name>
						<affiliation>Immunogénétique Humaine, Institut Pasteur, 75724 Paris, Cedex 15, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Houssein Khodjet El" last="Khil">Houssein Khodjet El Khil</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratoire d'Immunogénétique, Faculté de Sciences de Tunis, Tunis, Tunisia</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sandrine" last="Barbaux">Sandrine Barbaux</name>
						<affiliation>Immunogénétique Humaine, Institut Pasteur, 75724 Paris, Cedex 15, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Preetha" last="Tilak">Preetha Tilak</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Anatomy, St John's Medical College, Bangalore 560 034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="I. Manorama" last="Thomas">I. Manorama Thomas</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Anatomy, St John's Medical College, Bangalore 560 034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Marc" last="Fellous">Marc Fellous</name>
						<affiliation>Immunogénétique Humaine, Institut Pasteur, 75724 Paris, Cedex 15, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-03-31</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Darwin's Spectre: Evolutionary Biology in the Modern World, by Michael R. Rose</title>
				<feature>Book Review</feature>
				<page>0021-0023</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="08" year="2000">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A spectrum of genes expressed during early stages of rice panicle and flower development</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0025-0032</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>To unravel gene expression patterns during rice inflorescence development, particularly at early stages of panicle and floral organ specification, we have characterized random cloned cDNAs from developmental-stage-specific libraries. cDNA libraries were constructed from rice panicles at the stage of branching and flower primordia specification or from panicles undergoing floral organogenesis. Partial sequence analysis and expression patterns of some of these random cDNA clones from these two rice panicle libraries are presented. Sequence comparisons with known DNA sequences in databases reveal that approximately sixtyeight per cent of these expressed rice genes show varying degrees of similarity to genes in other species with assigned functions. In contrast, thirtytwo per cent represent uncharacterized genes. cDNAs reported here code for potential rice homologues of housekeeping molecules, regulators of gene expression, and signal transduction molecules. They comprise both single-copy and multicopy genes, and genes expressed differentially, both spatially and temporally, during rice plant development. New rice cDNAs requiring specific mention are those with similarity to <i>COP1</i>, a regulator of photomorphogenesis in <i>Arabidopsis</i>; sequence-specific DNA binding plant proteins like <i>AP2</i>-domain-containing factors; genes that specify positional information in shoot meristems like leucine-rich-repeat-containing receptor kinases; regulators of chromatin structure like Polycomb domain protein; and also proteins induced by abiotic stresses.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>cDNA clones;rice panicles;floral development;rice.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Kumuda M." last="Kushalappa">Kumuda M. Kushalappa</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Botany, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC V6T124, Canada</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Autar K." last="Mattoo">Autar K. Mattoo</name>
						<affiliation>USDA Vegetable Lab, Building 010A, ARS/PSI/BARC- West, 10300 Baltimore Avenue, Beltsville, MD 20705-2350, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Usha" last="Vijayraghavan">Usha Vijayraghavan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>uvr@mcbl.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-17</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The <i>p10</i> gene of <i>Bombyx mori</i> nucleopolyhedrosis virus encodes a 7.5-kDa protein and is hypertranscribed from a TAAG motif</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0033-0040</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In baculovirus-based high-level expression of cloned foreign genes, the viral very late gene promoters of <i>polyhedrin (polh)</i> and <i>p10</i> are extensively exploited. Here we report the cloning and characterization of the <i>p10</i> gene from a local isolate of <i>Bombyx mori</i> nucleopolyhedrosis virus (BmNPV). The gene harbours a 213-bp open reading frame encoding a protein of 70 amino acids with a predicted molecular mass of 7.5 kDa. The BmNPV <i>p10</i> showed deletion of a single A at +210 nucleotide compared to the prototype baculovirus, <i>Autographa californica</i> multinucleocapsid nucleopolyhedrosis virus (AcMNPV), <i>p10</i> gene, resulting in a translational frameshift to generate a termination codon and consequently a truncated polypeptide instead of the 10-kDa protein. This protein P7.5 from BmNPV has a putative leucine zipper dimerization motif towards the N-terminal end and the central nuclear disintegration domain but the carboxy-terminal domain implicated in protein association for fibrillar structure formation is absent. Phylogenetic analysis revealed that <i>p10</i> is highly conserved among baculoviruses and the BmNPV strains are more closely related to AcMNPV than other baculoviruses. The transcription of <i>p10</i> is regulated in a temporal manner, reaching maximal levels by 72 h post-infection. RNAase protection and primer extension analysis mapped the transcription start sites at $-70$ and $-71$ nt with respect to the ATG, within the conserved baculovirus late gene motif T\underline{AA}G. The upstream region showed complete homology to the strong promoter of the AcMNPV <i>p10</i>, suggesting that this promoter from BmNPV could also be exploited for high-level expression of cloned foreign genes in silkworm cells or larvae.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>baculovirus;<i>Bombyx mori</i>;BmNPV;late gene expression;<i>p10</i> gene;transcriptional regulation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Vikas B." last="Palhan">Vikas B. Palhan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Karumathil P." last="Gopinathan">Karumathil P. Gopinathan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>kpg@mcbl.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-18</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Congruence of genomic and ethnolinguistic affinities among five tribal populations of Madhya Pradesh (India)</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0041-0046</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The central Indian state of Madhya Pradesh is home to a large number of tribal populations of diverse linguistic and ethnic backgrounds. With a view to examining how well genomic affinities among tribal populations of this state correspond with their ethnic and linguistic affinities, we analysed DNA samples of individuals drawn from five tribes with diverse, but reasonably well-documented, ethnohistorical and linguistic backgrounds. Each DNA sample was scored at 16 biallelic DNA marker loci. On the basis of these data, genomic affinities among these populations were estimated. We have found an extremely good correspondence between the genomic and ethnolinguistic affinities.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>DNA polymorphism;ethnic group;language family.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Namita" last="Mukherjee">Namita Mukherjee</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology and Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T. Road, Calcutta 700 035, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Mitashree" last="Mitra">Mitashree Mitra</name>
						<affiliation>School of Studies in Anthropology, Pandit Ravishankar Shukla University, Raipur 492 010, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Madan" last="Chakraborty">Madan Chakraborty</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology and Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T. Road, Calcutta 700 035, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Partha P." last="Majumder">Partha P. Majumder</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology and Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T. Road, Calcutta 700 035, India</affiliation>
						<email>ppm@isical.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-07</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>An improved procedure of mapping a quantitative trait locus via the EM algorithm using posterior probabilities</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0047-0053</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Mapping a locus controlling a quantitative genetic trait (e.g. blood pressure) to a specific genomic region is of considerable contemporary interest. Data on the quantitative trait under consideration and several codominant genetic markers with known genomic locations are collected from members of families and statistically analysed to estimate the recombination fraction, $\theta$, between the putative quantitative trait locus and a genetic marker. One of the major complications in estimating $\theta$ for a quantitative trait in humans is the lack of haplotype information on members of families. We have devised a computationally simple two-stage method of estimation of $\theta$ in the absence of haplotypic information using the expectation-maximization (EM) algorithm. In the first stage, parameters of the quantitative trait locus (QTL) are estimated on the basis of data of a sample of unrelated individuals and a Bayes's rule is used to classify each parent into a QTL genotypic class. In the second stage, we have proposed an EM algorithm for obtaining the maximum-likelihood estimate of $\theta$ based on data of informative families (which are identified upon inferring parental QTL genotypes performed in the first stage). The purpose of this paper is to investigate whether, instead of using genotypically `classified' data of parents, the use of posterior probabilities of QT genotypes of parents at the second stage yields better estimators. We show, using simulated data, that the proposed procedure using posterior probabilities is statistically more efficient than our earlier classification procedure, although it is computationally heavier.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>recombination fraction;linkage;maximum likelihood estimation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Saurabh" last="Ghosh">Saurabh Ghosh</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology and Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T. Road, Calcutta 700 035, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Partha P." last="Majumder">Partha P. Majumder</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology and Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T. Road, Calcutta 700 035, India</affiliation>
						<email>ppm@isical.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-07</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Modulation of allele leakiness and adaptive mutability in <i>Escherichia coli</i></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0055-0060</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>It is shown that partial phenotypic suppression of two ochre mutations (<i>argE3</i> and <i>lacZU118</i>) and an amber mutation (in <i>argE</i>) by sublethal concentrations of streptomycin in an <i>rpsL$^{+}$</i> (streptomycin-sensitive) derivative of the <i>Escherichia coli</i> strain AB1157 greatly enhances their adaptive mutability under selection. Streptomycin also increases adaptive mutability brought about by the <i>ppm</i> mutation described earlier. Inactivation of <i>recA</i> affects neither phenotypic suppression by streptomycin nor replication-associated mutagenesis but abolishes adaptive mutagenesis. These results indicate a causal relationship between allele leakiness and adaptive mutability.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Escherichia coli;phenotypic suppression;adaptive mutagenesis;allele leakiness;streptomycin.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Jayaraman">R. Jayaraman</name>
						<affiliation>School of Biological Sciences, Madurai Kamaraj University, Madurai 625 021, India</affiliation>
						<email>ram.jayaraman@usa.net</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-17</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Negative regulation of <i>Ultrabithorax</i> expression by <i>engrailed</i> is required for proper specification of wing development in <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0061-0070</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In both vertebrates and invertebrates, homeotic selector genes confer morphological differences along the antero-posterior axis. However, insect wing development is independent of all homeotic gene functions, reflecting the ground plan of an ancestral pterygote, which bore wings on all segments. Dipteran insects such as <i>Drosophila</i> are characterized by a pair of wings in the mesothoracic segment. In all other segments, wing development is essentially repressed by different homeotic genes, although in the metathorax they are modified into a pair of halteres. This necessitates that during development all homeotic genes are to be maintained in a repressed state in wing imaginal discs. In this report we show that</p> 
					<ol type="roman">
						<li>the function of the segment polarity <i>gene engrailed</i> (en) is critical to keep the homeotic selector gene <i>Ultrabithorax</i> (<i>Ubx</i>) repressed in wing imaginal discs,</li>
						<li>normal levels of En in the posterior compartment of haltere discs, however, are not enough to completely repress <i>Ubx</i>, and</li>
						<li>the repression of <i>Ubx</i> by <i>en</i> is independent of Hedgehog signalling through which the long-range signalling of <i>en</i> is mediated during wing development.</li> 
					</ol>
					<p>Finally we provide evidence for a possible mechanism by which en represses <i>Ubx</i>. On the basis of these results we propose that <i>en</i> has acquired two independent functions during the evolution of dorsal appendages. In addition to its well-known function of conferring posterior fate and inducing long-range signalling to pattern the developing appendages, it maintains wing fate by keeping <i>Ubx</i> repressed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>homeosis;<i>Drosophila</i>;wing;haltere;<i>Ultrabithorax</i>;<i>engrailed</i>;<i>hedgehog.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="B. Starling" last="Emerald">B. Starling Emerald</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad, India 500 007</affiliation>
						<affiliation>European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="L. S." last="Shashidhara">L. S. Shashidhara</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad, India 500 007</affiliation>
						<email>shashi@ccmb.ap.nic.in;shashi@gene.ccmbindia.org</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-17</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Inheritance and segregation of exogenous genes in transgenic cotton</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0071-0075</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Three transgenic cotton varieties (lines) were chosen for the study of inheritance and segregation of foreign Bt (<i>Bacillus thuringiensis</i> toxin) and <i>tfdA</i> genes in cotton. The transformed cotton varieties CCRI 30 and NewCott 33B expressing the Bt <i>cryIA</i> gene, and cotton line TFD expressing the <i>tfdA</i> gene were crossed with CCRI 19, CCRI 12 and Lumian 6. The results confirm inheritance and segregation of</p>
					<ol type="roman">
						<li>the exogenous Bt gene in transgenic CCRI 30 and NewCott 33B, governing resistance to bollworm, and</li>
						<li>the exogenous <i>tfdA</i> gene in transgenic TFD, governing resistance to the herbicide 2,4-D.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Both resistance characters were governed by a single dominant nuclear gene, and were not affected by cytoplasm. Our data support the conclusion that foreign traits encoded by single genes are inherited and expressed in Mendelian fashion in cotton. Our results also indicate that a practical backcross breeding program could be used to develop cotton cultivars combining one or more resistance traits from foreign and native gene sources.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>transgenic cotton;Bt gene;<i>tfdA</i> gene;inheritance;dominant gene.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Bao-Hong" last="Zhang">Bao-Hong Zhang</name>
						<affiliation>Key Laboratory of Cotton Genetic Improvement of the Ministry of Agriculture, Cotton Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Anyang Henan 455 112, People's Republic of China</affiliation>
						<affiliation>1632 West 6th Street Apt F, Austin, TX 78703, USA.</affiliation>
						<email>zbh68@hotmail.com;zbh68@yahoo.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Teng-Long" last="Guo">Teng-Long Guo</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Heze Agricultural Sciences, Heze, Shandong 273 000, People's Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Qing-Lian" last="Wang">Qing-Lian Wang</name>
						<affiliation>Henan Vocational Technical Teacher's College, Xinxiang Henan 453 003, People's Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-03-08</date>
					<date type="R">2000-06-14</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Expression of the gene for large subunit of m-calpain is elevated in skeletal muscle from Duchenne muscular dystrophy patients</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0077-0080</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Calpain is an intracellular nonlysosomal protease involved in essential regulatory or processing functions of the cell, mediated by physiological concentrations of Ca$^{2+}$. However, in an environment of abnormal intracellular calcium, such as that seen in Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD), calpain is suggested to cause degeneration of muscle owing to enhanced activity. To test whether the reported increase in calpain activity in DMD results from <i>de novo</i> synthesis of the protease, we have assessed the quantitative changes in mRNA specific for m-calpain. mRNA isolated from DMD and control muscle was analysed by dot blot hybridization using a cDNA probe for the large subunit of m-calpain. Compared to control a four-fold increase in specific mRNAwas observed in dystrophic muscle. This enhanced expression of the m-calpain gene in dystrophic condition suggests that the reported increase in m-calpain activity results from <i>de novo</i> synthesis of protease and underlines the important role of m-calpain in DMD.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>m-calpain;Duchenne muscular dystrophy;muscle tissue;RNA dot blot;calpain genetics.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Tajamul" last="Hussain">Tajamul Hussain</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Genetics, Begumpet, Hyderabad 500 016, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Centre for DNA Fingerprinting and Diagnostics, Nacharam, Hyderabad 500 076, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Harleen" last="Mangath">Harleen Mangath</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Genetics, Begumpet, Hyderabad 500 016, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="C." last="Sundaram">C. Sundaram</name>
						<affiliation>Nizam's Institute of Medical Sciences, Punjagutta, Hyderabad 500 082, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. P. J. S." last="Anandaraj">M. P. J. S. Anandaraj</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Genetics, Begumpet, Hyderabad 500 016, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-05</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Gene therapy in inflammatory diseases</title>
				<feature>Book Review</feature>
				<page>0081-0081</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Apurva" last="Sarin">Apurva Sarin</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="00" year="2000">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Identification of four genes involved in suppression of the pre-mRNA splicing defect in the <i>sng1-1/rhp6$^{-}$</i> mutant of fission yeast</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0083-0090</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Apart from the global regulators of silencing in the fission yeast <i>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</i>, namely <i>swi6, clr1, clr2, clr3, clr4</i> and <i>rik1</i>, the DNA repair gene <i>rhp6</i> plays a unique role in mating-type silencing. Recently, we showed that <i>sng1-1</i>, a mutation in the $5'$ splice junction of the second intron of the <i>rhp6</i> gene, leads to derepression of both the silent loci <i>mat2</i> and <i>mat3</i> in switching background. To address the mechanism of <i>rhp6</i> in silencing, we have isolated several extragenic suppressors of the <i>sng1-1/rhp6$^{-}$</i> mutation. These suppressors fall into four complementation groups and are referred to as suppressor of <i>rhp6: sur1, sur2, sur3</i> and <i>sur4</i>. Interestingly, reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction analysis of the <i>rhp6</i> transcript shows that in contrast to about $\gt 50\%$ level of unspliced <i>rhp6</i> pre-mRNA in the <i>sng1-1/rhp6$^{-}$</i> mutant, there is a restoration of normal splicing to varying degrees in the suppressors. The <i>sur2</i> gene belongs to the AAA-ATPase family of proteins, with maximum homology to the SIN1-associated protein SAP1 of <i>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</i>. We propose that <i>sur2</i>, along with <i>sur1, sur3</i> and <i>sur4</i>, may play an as yet uncharacterized role in pre-mRNA splicing.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>pre-mRNA splicing;suppressors;<i>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</i>.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Alpana" last="Naresh">Alpana Naresh</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Microbial Technology, Sector 39A, Chandigarh 160 036, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jagmohan" last="Singh">Jagmohan Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Microbial Technology, Sector 39A, Chandigarh 160 036, India</affiliation>
						<email>jag@imtech.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-09-05</date>
					<date type="R">2000-11-25</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Isolation of a <i>cdc28</i> mutation that abrogates the dependence of S phase on completion of M phase of the budding yeast cell cycle</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0091-0096</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have isolated a mutation in the budding yeast <i>Saccharomyces cerevisisae CDC28</i> gene that allows <i>cdc13</i> cells, carrying damaged DNA, to continue with the cell division cycle. While <i>cdc13</i> mutant cells are arrested as large-budded cells at the nonpermissive temperature 37$^{\circ}$C, the <i>cdc13 cdc28</i> double mutant culture showed cells with one or more buds, most of which showed apical growth. The additional buds emerged without the intervening steps of nuclear division and cell separation. We suggest that the <i>cdc28</i> mutation abrogates a checkpoint function and allows cells with damaged or incompletely replicated DNA an entry to another round of cell cycle and bypasses the mitotic phase of the cell cycle.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>yeast;Cdc28 kinase;checkpoint;cell cycle.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Santanu Kumar" last="Ghosh">Santanu Kumar Ghosh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Bose Institute, Calcutta 700 054, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Pratima" last="Sinha">Pratima Sinha</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Bose Institute, Calcutta 700 054, India</affiliation>
						<email>pratima@bic.boseinst.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-11-29</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Induced mutation to monocotyledony in periwinkle, <i>Catharanthus roseus</i>, and suppression of mutant phenotype by kinetin</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0097-0104</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A recessive EMS-induced mutation inherited in Mendelian fashion caused monocotyledonous embryo formation and seed germination on high salt medium in <i>Catharanthus roseus</i>. Availability during embryo development of exogenously supplied cytokinin kinetin suppressed the mutant phenotype. These observations suggest that, in <i>C. roseus</i>,</p>
					<ol type="roman">
						<li>insufficiency in endogenous kinetin may lead to monocotyledonous embryo patterning and</li> 
						<li>dicotyledonous embryo formation requires a critical amount of kinetin in certain cells of early embryos.</li>
					</ol>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>cimap@satyam.net.in</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Shashi Pandey" last="Rai">Shashi Pandey Rai</name>
						<affiliation>Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants, P.O. CIMAP, Lucknow 226 015, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sushil" last="Kumar">Sushil Kumar</name>
						<affiliation>Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants, P.O. CIMAP, Lucknow 226 015, India</affiliation>
						<email>cimap@satyam.net.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-11-24</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Meiosis and speciation: a study in a speciating <i>Mus terricolor</i> complex</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0105-0111</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The three chromosomal species of the <i>Mus terricolor</i> complex possess $2n = 40$ chromosomes. We show that their karyotypes differ in stable heterochromatin variations fixed in homozygous condition as prominent short arms in auto-somes 1, 3 and 6. The three chromosomal species exhibit a high incidence of polymorphisms for Robertsonian fusions and pericentric inversions. Breeding experiments and histological analysis of testis show that heterozygosity for pericentric inversions and Robertsonian fusions had no effect on fertility. Meiotic analysis shows normal overall progression of meiosis in the heterozygotes, which is consistent with their normal gametogenesis. Nevertheless, both the inversion and fusion heterozygotes had undergone some alterations in the regular process of homologous synapsis, and it appeared that certain features of the meiotic system circumvented the potential negative effects of these polymorphic chromosomal rearrangements. The results indicate that the attributes of the meiotic system in a given organism could modulate the potential of a chromosomal rearrangement as reproductive barrier. The meiotic modulation hypothesis offers an explanation for the contradictory effects of the similar kinds of chromosomal mutations reported in different species.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>inversion;Robertsonian fusion;heterochromatin;chromosomal polymorphism;meiosis;speciation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Bardhan">A. Bardhan</name>
						<affiliation>Cytogenetics Laboratory, Department of Zoology, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi 221 005, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="T." last="Sharma">T. Sharma</name>
						<affiliation>Cytogenetics Laboratory, Department of Zoology, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi 221 005, India</affiliation>
						<email>tsharma@banaras.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-07</date>
					<date type="R">2000-12-27</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Characterization of newly established colorectal cancer cell lines: correlation between cytogenetic abnormalities and allelic deletions associated with multistep tumorigenesis</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0113-0123</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have established a series of 20 colorectal cancer cell lines and performed cytogenetic and RFLP analyses to show that the recurrent genetic abnormalities of chromosomes 1, 5, 17 and 18 associated with multistep tumorigenesis in colorectal cancer, and frequently detected as recurrent abnormalities in primary tumours, are also retained in long-term established cell lines. Earlier studies by us and other investigators showed that allelic losses of chromosomes 1 and 17 in primary colorectal cancers predicted poorer survival for the patients $(P = 0.03)$. We utilized the cell lines to identify specific chromosomal sites or gene(s) on chromosomes 1 and 17 which confer more aggressive phenotype. Cytogenetic deletions of chromosome 1p were detected in 14 out of the 20 (70\%) cell lines, whereas allelic deletions for 1p using polymorphic markers were detected in 13 out of 18 (72\%) informative cell lines for at least one polymorphic marker. We have performed Northern blotting, immunohistochemical staining (p53 mRNA, protein) and RFLP analysis using several probes including p53 and nm23. RFLP analysis using a total of seven polymorphic markers located on 17p and 17q arms showed allelic losses around the <i>p53</i> locus in 16 out of the 20 cell lines (80\%), four of which were losses of the <i>p53</i> locus itself. In addition, seven cell lines (out of nine informative cases) also showed losses of the <i>nm23</i> gene, four with concurrent losses of the <i>p53</i> locus, while the remaining three were homozygous. In addition, five out of seven cell lines with <i>nm23</i> deletions were derived from hepatic metastatic tumours, and one cell line was obtained from recurrent tumour. A comparison between allelic deletions of 1p and functional loss of <i>nm23</i> gene revealed a close association between these two events in cell lines derived from hepatic metastasis. Following immunohistochemical staining, nine out of the twenty cell lines showed high levels (25–80\%) of mutant p53, four showed intermediate levels $(\lt 20\%)$, and seven had undetectable levels of the protein. Of these seven, four showed complete absence of mRNA. Of the remaining three cell lines one showed aberrant mRNA due to germline rearrangement of the <i>p53</i> gene, whereas in two cell lines normal levels of mRNA were present. Nineteen of the 20 cell lines had normal germline configurations for the <i>p53</i> gene, while one showed a rearrangement. These data suggest that functional loss of <i>p53</i> and <i>nm23</i> genes accomplished by a variety of mechanisms may be associated with poor prognosis and survival. In addition, concurrent deletions of chromosome regions 17p, 17q and 1p were closely associated with high-stage hepatic metastatic disease. These cell lines with well-characterized genetic alterations and known clinical history provide an invaluable source of material for various biological and clinical studies relating to multistep colorectal tumorigenesis.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>colorectal cancer;cell line;tumorigenesis;allelic deletion;chromosomal aberration.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Hans" last="Gerdes">Hans Gerdes</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratory of Solid Tumor Genetics, Department of Human Genetics, and Gastroenterology Service, Department of Medicine, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1275 York Avenue, New York, NY 10021, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Abul" last="Elahi">Abul Elahi</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratory of Solid Tumor Genetics, Department of Human Genetics, and Gastroenterology Service, Department of Medicine, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1275 York Avenue, New York, NY 10021, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Quanguang" last="Chen">Quanguang Chen</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratory of Solid Tumor Genetics, Department of Human Genetics, and Gastroenterology Service, Department of Medicine, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1275 York Avenue, New York, NY 10021, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Suresh C." last="Jhanwar">Suresh C. Jhanwar</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratory of Solid Tumor Genetics, Department of Human Genetics, and Gastroenterology Service, Department of Medicine, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1275 York Avenue, New York, NY 10021, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-12-19</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Understanding protein–protein interactions by genetic suppression</title>
				<feature>Review article</feature>
				<page>0125-0129</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Protein–protein interactions influence many cellular processes and it is increasingly being felt that even a weak and remote interplay between two subunits of a protein or between two proteins in a complex may govern the fate of a particular biochemical pathway. In a bacterial system where the complete genome sequence is available, it is an arduous task to assign function to a large number of proteins. It is possible that many of them are peripherally associated with a cellular event and it is very difficult to probe such interaction. However, mutations in the genes that encode such proteins (primary mutations) are useful in these studies. Isolation of a suppressor or a second-site mutation that restores the phenotype abolished by the primary mutation could be an elegant yet simple way to follow a set of interacting proteins. Such a reversion site need not necessarily be geometrically close to the primary mutation site.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>genetic suppression;protein–protein interaction;allele specificity;long-range interaction.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Sitaraman" last="Sujatha">Sitaraman Sujatha</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biophysics Unit, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Dipankar" last="Chatterji">Dipankar Chatterji</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biophysics Unit, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>dipankar@mbu.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The genetics of sheep</title>
				<feature>Book review</feature>
				<page>0131-0132</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. H." last="Edwards">J. H. Edwards</name>
						<affiliation>Emeritus Professor of Genetics, Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, South Parks Road, Oxford OX1 3QU, UK.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Evolutionary genetics: from molecules to morphology</title>
				<feature>Book review</feature>
				<page>0133-0134</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. V." last="Joshi">N. V. Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Ecological Sciences, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="080">
		<issue inum="01" month="04" year="2001">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Evolution of faster development does not lead to greater fluctuating asymmetry of sternopleural bristle number in <i>Drosophila</i></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0007</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Both strong directional selection and faster development are thought to destabilize development, giving rise to greater fluctuating asymmetry (FA), although there is no strong empirical evidence supporting this assertion. We compared FA in sternopleural bristle number in four populations of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> successfully selected for faster development from egg to adult, and in four control populations. The fraction of perfectly symmetric individuals was higher in the selected populations, whereas the FA levels did not differ significantly between selected and control populations, clearly indicating that directional selection for faster development has not led to increased FA in sternopleural bristle number in these populations. This may be because:</p>
					<ol type="roman">
						<li>development time and FA are uncorrelated,</li> 
						<li>faster development does result in FA, but selection has favoured developmentally stable individuals that can develop fast and still be symmetrical, or</li>
						<li>the increased fraction of symmetric individuals in the selected populations is an artifact of reduced body size.</li> 
					</ol>
					<p>Although we cannot discriminate among these explanations, our results suggest that the relationship between development time, FA and fitness may be far more subtle than often thought.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>sternopleural bristle; developmental stability; evolution; canalization; fluctuating asymmetry; <i>Drosophila melanogaster.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Mallikarjun" last="Shakarad">Mallikarjun Shakarad</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Poornaprajna Institute of Scientific Research, 4, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. G." last="Prasad">N. G. Prasad</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Rajamani">M. Rajamani</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-01-15</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>An automated annotation tool for genomic DNA sequences using GeneScan and BLAST</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0009-0016</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Genomic sequence data are often available well before the annotated sequence is published. We present a method for analysis of genomic DNA to identify coding sequences using the GeneScan algorithm and characterize these resultant sequences by BLAST. The routines are used to develop a system for automated annotation of genome DNA sequences.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>GeneScan;BLAST;genome annotation;DNA sequence;computational genomics;Fourier analysis.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Andrew M." last="Lynn">Andrew M. Lynn</name>
						<affiliation>Bioinformatics Centre, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Chakresh Kumar" last="Jain">Chakresh Kumar Jain</name>
						<affiliation>Bioinformatics Centre, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Kosalai">K. Kosalai</name>
						<affiliation>Bioinformatics Centre, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Pranjan" last="Barman">Pranjan Barman</name>
						<affiliation>Bioinformatics Centre, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Nupur" last="Thakur">Nupur Thakur</name>
						<affiliation>Bioinformatics Centre, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Harish" last="Batra">Harish Batra</name>
						<affiliation>Bioinformatics Centre, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Alok" last="Bhattacharya">Alok Bhattacharya</name>
						<affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email>alok@jnuniv.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-02-26</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Accelerated molecular evolution of insect orthologues of <i>ERG28/C14orf1</i>: a link with ecdysteroid metabolism?</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0017-0021</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have analysed the evolution of <i>ERG28/C14orf1</i>, a gene coding for a protein involved in sterol biosynthesis. While primary sequence of the protein is well conserved in all organisms able to synthesize sterols <i>de novo</i>, strong divergence is noticed in insects, which are cholesterol auxotrophs. In spite of this virtual acceleration, our analysis suggests that the insect orthologues are evolving today at rates similar to those of the remaining members of the family. A plausible way to explain this acceleration and subsequent stabilization is that Erg28 plays a role in at least two different pathways. Discontinuation of the cholesterogenesis pathway in insects allowed the protein to evolve as much as the function in the other pathway was not compromised.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>ergosterol;cholesterol;steroids;ecdysteroids;Erg28;C14orf1.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Reiner A." last="Veitia">Reiner A. Veitia</name>
						<affiliation>Unité d’Immunogénétique Humaine/Université Denis Diderot – Paris VII, Institut Pasteur, 25 rue du Dr Roux, 75015 Paris, France</affiliation>
						<email>rveitia@pasteur.fr</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Laurence D." last="Hurst">Laurence D. Hurst</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biology and Biochemistry, University of Bath, Claverton Down, Bath, Somerset BA2 7AY, UK</affiliation>
						<email>l.d.hurst@bath.ac.uk</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-03-28</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Genetic variation at minisatellite loci D1S7, D4S139, D5S110 and D17S79 among three population groups of eastern India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0023-0030</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Genetic variation at four minisatellite loci D1S7, D4S139, D5S110 and D17S79 in three predominant population groups of eastern India, namely Brahmin, Kayastha and Garo, are reported in this study. The Brahmin and Kayastha are of Indo-Caucasoid origin while the Garo community represents the Indo-Mongoloid ethnic group. The methodology employed comprised generation of <i>Hae</i>III-restricted fragments of isolated DNA, Southern blotting, and hybridization using chemiluminescent probes MS1, pH30, LH1 and V1 for the four loci. All four loci were highly polymorphic in the population groups. Heterozygosity values for the four loci ranged between 0.68 and 0.95. Neither departure from Hardy–Weinberg expectations nor evidence of any association across alleles among the selected loci was observed. The gene differentiation value among the loci is moderate $(G_{\text{ST}} = 0.027)$. A neighbour-joining tree constructed on the basis of the generated data shows very low genetic distance between the Brahmin and Kayastha communities in relation to the Garo. Our results based on genetic distance analysis are consistent with results of earlier studies based on serological markers and linguistic as well as morphological affiliations of these populations and their Indo-Caucasoid and Indo-Mongoloid origin. The minisatellite loci studied here were found to be not only useful in showing significant genetic variation between the populations but also to be suitable for human identity testing among eastern Indian populations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>RFLP;D1S7;D4S139;D5S110;D17S79;genetic variation;minisatellite;Indian populations.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Ranjan" last="Dutta">Ranjan Dutta</name>
						<affiliation>DNA Typing Unit, Central Forensic Science Laboratory, Bureau of Police Research and Development, 30 Gorachand Road, Kolkata 700 014, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V. K." last="Kashyap">V. K. Kashyap</name>
						<affiliation>DNA Typing Unit, Central Forensic Science Laboratory, Bureau of Police Research and Development, 30 Gorachand Road, Kolkata 700 014, India</affiliation>
						<email>dtubprd@giascl01.vsnl.net.in;vkk2k@hotmail.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-08-14</date>
					<date type="R">2000-12-12;2001-04-20</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Isolation and characterization of stable mutants of <i>Streptomyces peucetius</i> defective in daunorubicin biosynthesis</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0031-0038</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Daunorubicin and its derivative doxorubicin are antitumour anthracycline antibiotics produced by <i>Streptomyces peucetius</i>. In this study we report isolation of stable mutants of <i>S. peucetius</i> blocked in different steps of the daunorubicin biosynthesis pathway. Mutants were screened on the basis of colony colour since producer strains are distinctively coloured on agar plates. Different mutants showed accumulation of aklaviketone, $\epsilon$-rhodomycinone, maggiemycin or 13-dihydrocarminomycin in their culture filtrates. These results indicate that the mutations in these isolates affect steps catalysed by <i>dnrE</i> (mutants SPAK and SPMAG), <i>dnrS</i> (SPFS and SPRHO) and <i>doxA</i> (SPDHC) gene products.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Streptomyces peucetius;daunorubicin;$\epsilon$-rhodomycinone;NTG mutagenesis.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. S." last="Vetrivel">K. S. Vetrivel</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetic Engineering, School of Biotechnology, Madurai Kamaraj University, Madurai 625 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Dharmalingam">K. Dharmalingam</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetic Engineering, School of Biotechnology, Madurai Kamaraj University, Madurai 625 021, India</affiliation>
						<email>kdharmalingam@vsnl.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-04-06</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Testing quantum dynamics in genetic information processing</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0039-0043</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Does quantum dynamics play a role in DNA replication? What type of tests would reveal that? Some statistical checks that distinguish classical and quantum dynamics in DNA replication are proposed.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>assembly;computation;database search;DNA replication;genetic information;nucleotide base;polymerase enzyme;quantum coherence;quantum mechanics;quantum superposition.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Apoorva" last="Patel">Apoorva Patel</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Theoretical Studies, and Supercomputer Education and Research Centre, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>adpatel@cts.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-01-24</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Darkness in El Dorado: human genetics on trial</title>
				<feature>Commentary</feature>
				<page>0045-0052</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Newton E." last="Morton">Newton E. Morton</name>
						<affiliation>Human Genetics Research Division, University of Southampton, Southampton SO16 6YD, UK</affiliation>
						<email>nem@soton.ac.uk</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Neurospora compendium: chromosomal loci</title>
				<feature>Book Review</feature>
				<page>0053-0054</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Durgadas P." last="Kasbekar">Durgadas P. Kasbekar</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad 500 007, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="08" year="2001">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Evidence for dominant suppression of repeat-induced point mutation (RIP) in crosses with the wild-isolated <i>Neurospora crassa</i> strains Sugartown and Adiopodoume-7</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0055-0061</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A convenient assay to score repeat-induced point mutation (RIP) in <i>Neurospora</i> employs the <i>erg-3</i> locus as a mutagenesis target. Using this assay we screened 132 wild-isolated <i>Neurospora crassa</i> strains for ability to dominantly suppress RIP. RIP was exceptionally inefficient in crosses with the wild isolates Sugartown (P0854) and Adiopodoume-7 (P4305), thereby suggesting the presence of dominant RIP suppressors in these strains. In other experiments, we found no evidence for dominant RIP suppression by the <i>Spore killer</i> haplotypes <i>Sk-2</i> and <i>Sk-3</i>.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Spore killer;meiotic drive;Neurospora crassa;RIP.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Felicite K." last="Noubissi">Felicite K. Noubissi</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Hyderabad 500 007, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Aparna">K. Aparna</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Hyderabad 500 007, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Kevin" last="McCluskey">Kevin McCluskey</name>
						<affiliation>Fungal Genetics Stock Center, Department of Microbiology, University of Kansas Medical Center, Kansas City, KS 66103, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Durgadas P." last="Kasbekar">Durgadas P. Kasbekar</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Hyderabad 500 007, India</affiliation>
						<email>kas@ccmb.ap.nic.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-08-07</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>$K$-selection, $\alpha$-selection, effectiveness, and tolerance in competition: density-dependent selection revisited</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0063-0075</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In the <i>Drosophila</i> literature, selection for faster development and selection for adapting to high density are often confounded, leading, for example, to the expectation that selection for faster development should also lead to higher competitive ability. At the same time, results from experimental studies on evolution at high density do not agree with many of the predictions from classical density-dependent selection theory. We put together a number of theoretical and empirical results from the literature, and some new experimental results on <i>Drosophila</i> populations successfully subjected to selection for faster development, to argue for a broader interpretation of density-dependent selection. We show that incorporating notions of $\alpha$-selection, and the division of competitive ability into effectiveness and tolerance components, into the concept of density-dependent selection yields a formulation that allows for a better understanding of the empirical results. We also use this broader formulation to predict that selection for faster development in <i>Drosophila</i> should, in fact, lead to the correlated evolution of decreased competitive ability, even though it does lead to the evolution of greater efficiency and higher population growth rates at high density when in monotypic culture.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>density-dependent selection;competition;development time;urea tolerance;feeding rate;<i>Drosophila melanogaster.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box No. 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. G." last="Prasad">N. G. Prasad</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box No. 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Mallikarjun" last="Shakarad">Mallikarjun Shakarad</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box No. 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Poornaprajna Institute of Scientific Research, 4 Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-06-18</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Body size and mating success in <i>Drosophila willistoni</i> are uncorrelated under laboratory conditions</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0077-0081</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Mating activity and wing length were investigated in the F$_{1}$ progeny of <i>Drosophila willistoni</i> females collected in the field to examine any possible relationship between body size and mating success. The flies were observed in a mating chamber under laboratory conditions. No significant differences in wing length were observed between copulating and noncopulating flies, and there was no significant correlation between wing length and copulation latency for both males and females. These results therefore suggest that the commonly accepted view that large body size is positively correlated with mating success in <i>Drosophila</i> does not always hold true. The results support the view that the extent of environmentally induced variation in body size may be an important factor in determining whether an association between body size and mating success is observed in <i>Drosophila</i> species.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>Drosophila willistoni</i>;mating success;sexual behaviour;body size.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="L. Basso Da" last="Silva">L. Basso Da Silva</name>
						<affiliation>Departamento de Genética, Instituto de Biociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Caixa Postal 15053, 91501-970 Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V. L. S." last="Valente">V. L. S. Valente</name>
						<affiliation>Departamento de Genética, Instituto de Biociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Caixa Postal 15053, 91501-970 Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil</affiliation>
						<email>vera.gaiesky@ufrgs.br</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-01-03</date>
					<date type="R">2001-07-10</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Effects of mutations at the <i>stambh A</i> locus of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0083-0095</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report novel findings on the cytogenetic location, functional complexity and maternal and germline roles of the <i>stambh A</i> locus of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>. <i>stmA</i> is localized to polytene bands 44D1.2 on 2R. <i>stmA</i> mutations are of two types: temperature-sensitive (ts) adult and larval paralytic or unconditional embryonic or larval lethal. Twelve alleles reported in this study fall into two intragenic complementing groups suggesting that <i>stmA</i> is a complex locus with more than one functional domain. Some unconditional embryonic lethal alleles show a ‘neurogenic’ phenotype of cuticle loss accompanied by neural hypertrophy. It is shown that embryos of ts paralytic alleles also show mild neural hypertrophy at permissive temperatures while short exposure to heat induces severe cuticle loss in these embryos. <i>stmA</i> exerts a maternal influence over heat-induced cuticle loss. Unconditional embryonic lethal alleles of <i>stmA</i> are also germline lethal.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Drosophila melanogaster;stambh A;maternal effect;cuticle loss.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Kumar">M. Kumar</name>
						<affiliation>Division of Genetics, Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi 110 012, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Minu" last="Joseph">Minu Joseph</name>
						<affiliation>Division of Genetics, Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi 110 012, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shanti" last="Chandrashekaran">Shanti Chandrashekaran</name>
						<affiliation>Division of Genetics, Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi 110 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>shantic@vsnl.net</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-05-23</date>
					<date type="R">2001-08-31</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Male sterility associated with overexpression of the noncoding $hsr\omega$ gene in cyst cells of testis of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0097-0110</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Of the several noncoding transcripts produced by the $hsr\omega$ gene of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>, the nucleus-limited $\gt 10$-kb hsr$\omega$-n transcript colocalizes with heterogeneous nuclear RNA binding proteins (hnRNPs) to form fine nucleoplasmic omega speckles. Our earlier studies suggested that the noncoding hsr$\omega$-n transcripts dynamically regulate the distribution of hnRNPs in active (chromatin bound) and inactive (in omega speckles) compartments. Here we show that a P transposon insertion in this gene’s promoter (at – 130 bp) in the $hsr\omega^{05241}$ enhancer-trap line had no effect on viability or phenotype of males or females, but the insertion-homozygous males were sterile. Testes of $hsr\omega^{05241}$ homozygous flies contained nonmotile sperms while their seminal vesicles were empty. RNA : RNA <i>in situ</i> hybridization showed that the somatic cyst cells in testes of the mutant male flies contained significantly higher amounts of hsr$\omega$-n transcripts, and unlike the characteristic fine omega speckles in other cell types they displayed large clusters of omega speckles as typically seen after heat shock. Two of the hnRNPs, viz. HRB87F and Hrp57A, which are expressed in cyst cells, also formed large clusters in these cells in parallel with the hsr$\omega$-n transcripts. A complete excision of the P transposon insertion restored male fertility as well as the fine-speckled pattern of omega speckles in the cyst cells. The <i>in situ</i> distribution patterns of these two hnRNPs and several other RNA-binding proteins (Hrp40, Hrb57A, S5, Sxl, SRp55 and Rb97D) were not affected by $hsr\omega$ mutation in any of the meiotic stages in adult testes. The present studies, however, revealed an unexpected presence (in wild-type as well as mutant) of the functional form of Sxl in primary spermatocytes and an unusual distribution of HRB87F along the retracting spindle during anaphase-telophase of the first meiotic division. It appears that the P transposon insertion in the promoter region causes a misregulated overexpression of $hsr\omega$ in cyst cells, which in turn results in excessive sequestration of hnRNPs and formation of large clusters of omega speckles in these cell nuclei. The consequent limiting availability of hnRNPs is likely to <i>trans</i>-dominantly affect processing of other pre-mRNAs in cyst cells. We suggest that a compromise in the activity of cyst cells due to the aberrant hnRNP distribution is responsible for the failure of individualization of sperms in $hsr\omega^{05241}$ mutant testes. These results further support a significant role of the noncoding hsr$\omega$-n transcripts in basic cellular activities, namely regulation of the availability of hnRNPs in active (chromatin bound) and inactive (in omega speckles) compartments.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>heat shock;93D;hnRNP;omega speckles;spermatogenesis;sperm individualization.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="T. K." last="Rajendra">T. K. Rajendra</name>
						<affiliation>Cytogenetics Laboratory, Department of Zoology, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi 221 005, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K. V." last="Prasanth">K. V. Prasanth</name>
						<affiliation>Cytogenetics Laboratory, Department of Zoology, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi 221 005, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. C." last="Lakhotia">S. C. Lakhotia</name>
						<affiliation>Cytogenetics Laboratory, Department of Zoology, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi 221 005, India</affiliation>
						<email>lakhotia@banaras.ernet.in;sclakhotia@yahoo.co.in.</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-01-27</date>
					<date type="R">2001-05-08</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Mutation analysis of codons 345 and 347 of rhodopsin gene in Indian retinitis pigmentosa patients</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0111-0116</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>More than 100 mutations have been reported till date in the rhodopsin gene in patients with retinitis pigmentosa. The present study was undertaken to detect the reported rhodopsin gene point mutations in Indian retinitis pigmentosa patients. We looked for presence or absence of codon 345 and 347 mutations in exon 5 of the gene using the technique of allele-specific polymerase chain reaction by designing primers for each mutation. We have examined 100 patients from 76 families irrespective of genetic categories. Surprisingly, in our sample the very widely reported highly frequent mutations of codon 347 (P $\to$ S/A/R/Q/L/T) were absent while the codon 345 mutation V $\to$ M was seen in three cases in one family (autosomal dominant form) and in one sporadic case (total two families). This is the first report on codon 345 and 347 mutation in Indian retinitis pigmentosa subjects.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>retinitis pigmentosa;rhodopsin gene;allele-specific polymerase chain reaction.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Madhurima" last="Dikshit">Madhurima Dikshit</name>
						<affiliation>Division of Biochemistry, Department of Chemistry, University of Pune, Pune 411 007, India</affiliation>
						<email>mdikshit@chem.unipune.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Rakhi" last="Agarwal">Rakhi Agarwal</name>
						<affiliation>Division of Biochemistry, Department of Chemistry, University of Pune, Pune 411 007, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-01-20</date>
					<date type="R">2001-05-22</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>1. Molecular epidemiology of bacterial infectious disease in an age of rapid DNA sequencing and the Internet &mdash; 2. Phage therapy: bacteriophage as natural, self-replicating and self-limiting antibiotics</title>
				<feature>Book Review</feature>
				<page>0117-0118</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J." last="Gowrishankar">J. Gowrishankar</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for DNA Fingerprinting and Diagnostics, Nacharam, Hyderabad 500 076, India.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="12" year="2001">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Axial distortion as a sensor of supercoil changes: a molecular model for the homeostatic regulation of DNA gyrase</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0119-0124</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Negative supercoiling stimulates transcription of many genes. In contrast, transcription of the genes coding for DNA gyrase is subject to a novel mechanism of autoregulation, wherein relaxation of the template DNA stimulates their transcription. Since DNA gyrase is the sole supercoiling activity in the eubacterial cell, relaxation-stimulated transcription (RST) could reflect an autoregulatory mechanism to maintain supercoil levels within the cell. Extensive deletion and mutational analyses of <i>Escherichia coli gyrA</i> promoter have shown that the $-10$ region is essential for RST; however, a molecular model has proved to be elusive. We find a strong bend centre immediately downstream of the $-10$ region in the <i>gyrA</i> promoter. On the basis of analysis of various mutants in the $-10$ region, we propose a model where axial distortion acts as a sensor of topological changes in DNA. Our model is consistent with earlier data with <i>E. coli gyrA</i> and <i>gyrB</i> promoters. We also extrapolate the model to explain the phenomenon of RST of <i>gyr</i> promoters in other organisms and contrast it with promoters induced by supercoiling.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>DNA curvature;supercoiling;DNA topology;gyrase;relaxation-stimulated transcription.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Shyam" last="Unniraman">Shyam Unniraman</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Valakunja" last="Nagaraja">Valakunja Nagaraja</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>vraj@mcbl.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-12-14</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>High-resolution analysis of Y-chromosomal polymorphisms reveals signatures of population movements from Central Asia and West Asia into India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0125-0135</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Linguistic evidence suggests that West Asia and Central Asia have been the two major geographical sources of genes in the contemporary Indian gene pool. To test the nature and extent of similarities in the gene pools of these regions we have collected DNA samples from four ethnic populations of northern India, and have screened these samples for a set of 18 Y-chromosome polymorphic markers (12 unique event polymorphisms and six short tandem repeats). These data from Indian populations have been analysed in conjunction with published data from several West Asian and Central Asian populations. Our analyses have revealed traces of population movement from Central Asia and West Asia into India. Two haplogroups, HG-3 and HG-9, which are known to have arisen in the Central Asian region, are found in reasonably high frequencies (41.7\%\ and 14.3\%\ respectively) in the study populations. The ages estimated for these two haplogroups are less in the Indian populations than those estimated from data on Middle Eastern populations. A neighbour-joining tree based on Y-haplogroup frequencies shows that the North Indians are genetically placed between the West Asian and Central Asian populations. This is consistent with gene flow from West Asia and Central Asia into India.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>unique event polymorphism;short tandem repeat;haplotype;haplogroup;genome diversity.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Namita" last="Mukherjee">Namita Mukherjee</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology and Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, B.T. Road, Kolkata 700 108, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Almut" last="Nebel">Almut Nebel</name>
						<affiliation>Hebrew University–Hadassah Medical School, Jerusalem, Israel 91120</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ariella" last="Oppenheim">Ariella Oppenheim</name>
						<affiliation>Hebrew University–Hadassah Medical School, Jerusalem, Israel 91120</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Partha P." last="Majumder">Partha P. Majumder</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology and Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, B.T. Road, Kolkata 700 108, India</affiliation>
						<email>ppm@isical.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-12-12</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Distribution of HIV-1 resistance-conferring polymorphic alleles <i>SDF-1-3$'$A, CCR2-64I</i> and <i>CCR5-$\Delta$32</i> in diverse populations of Andhra Pradesh, South India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0137-0140</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Polymorphic allelic variants of chemokine receptors CCR2 and CCR5, as well as of stromal-derived factor-1 SDF-1, the ligand for the chemokine receptor CXCR4, are known to have protective effects against HIV-1 infection and to be involved with delay in disease progression. We have studied the DNA polymorphisms at the loci that encode these proteins in 525 healthy individuals without any history of HIV-1 infection from 11 diverse populations of Andhra Pradesh, South India. The two protective alleles <i>SDF-1-3$'$A</i> and <i>CCR2-64I</i> at the SDF-1 and CCR2 loci, respectively, are present in all populations studied, although their frequencies differ considerably across populations (from 17\%\ to 35\%\ for the <i>SDF-1-3$'$A</i> allele, and from 3\%\ to 17\%\ for <i>CCR2-64I</i>). In contrast the <i>CCR5-$\Delta$32</i> allele is observed only in three populations (Yamani, Pathan and Kamma), all in low frequencies (i.e. 1\%\ to 3\%). The mean number of mutant alleles (for the three loci together) carried by each individual varies from 0.475 (in Vizag Brahmins) to 0.959 (in Bohra Muslims). The estimated relative hazard values for the populations, computed from the three-locus genotype data, are comparable to those from Africa and Southeast Asia, where AIDS is known to be widespread.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>HIV-1 resistance polymorphism;chemokine receptor;stromal-derived factor-1;Andhra Pradesh;AIDS.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="G. V." last="Ramana">G. V. Ramana</name>
						<affiliation>Human Genetics Center, School of Public Health, University of Texas, P.O. Box 20186, Houston, TX 77225, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Vasanthi">A. Vasanthi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics, Owaisi Medical and Research Centre, Deccan College of Medical Sciences and Allied Hospitals, Kanchan Bagh, Santosh Nagar, Hyderabad 500 058, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Khaja">M. Khaja</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics, Owaisi Medical and Research Centre, Deccan College of Medical Sciences and Allied Hospitals, Kanchan Bagh, Santosh Nagar, Hyderabad 500 058, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B." last="Su">B. Su</name>
						<affiliation>Human Genetics Center, School of Public Health, University of Texas, P.O. Box 20186, Houston, TX 77225, USA</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Center for Genome Information, Department of Environmental Health, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, OH 46267, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V." last="Govindaiah">V. Govindaiah</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for DNA Fingerprinting and Diagnostics, 4-87/1 ECIL Road, Nacharam, Hyderabad 500 076, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="L." last="Jin">L. Jin</name>
						<affiliation>Human Genetics Center, School of Public Health, University of Texas, P.O. Box 20186, Houston, TX 77225, USA</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Center for Genome Information, Department of Environmental Health, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, OH 46267, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="L." last="Singh">L. Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad 500 007, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Chakraborty"></name>
						<affiliation>Human Genetics Center, School of Public Health, University of Texas, P.O. Box 20186, Houston, TX 77225, USA</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Center for Genome Information, Department of Environmental Health, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, OH 46267, USA</affiliation>
						<email>ranajit.chakraborty@uc.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-09-03</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Genetic variation and population structure in <i>Oryza malampuzhaensis</i> Krish. <i>et</i> Chand. endemic to Western Ghats, South India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0141-0148</page>
				<abstract>
					<p><i>Oryza malampuzhaensis</i> Krish. <i>et</i> Chand. ($2n = 4x = 48$; Poaceae, <i>Oryza</i>) is endemic to Western Ghats, South India, and shows a highly localized distribution over a small geographical area in this region. This is the most poorly understood taxon in genus <i>Oryza</i> and is often misidentified as <i>O. officinalis</i> owing to their close morphology. We assessed the nature and distribution of genetic variation among 11 populations of <i>O. malampuzhaensis</i> using random amplified polymorphic DNA markers. The analysis revealed low genetic variation in <i>O. malampuzhaensis.</i> Cluster analysis of pairwise genetic distances of populations revealed three distinct clusters and the grouping of populations largely corresponded to their geographical proximity. Restricted gene flow and a geography-dependent differentiation were evident among populations. The altitude-influenced differences in ecological factors among the natural habitats of the populations seem to be the cause of the geography-dependent differentiation. Genetically isolated smaller populations and a narrow genetic base in <i>O. malampuzhaensis</i> point to its vulnerability to genetic drift and genetic depauperation. Thus <i>O. malampuzhaensis</i> appears to be under the threat of extinction and needs to be conserved by use of suitable methods. The present study also identified molecular markers diagnostic for <i>O. malampuzhaensis</i>.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Oryza malampuzhaensis;genetic diversity;population structure;RAPD.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="George" last="Thomas">George Thomas</name>
						<affiliation>Plant Genomics Group, Rajiv Gandhi Centre for Biotechnology, Thiruvananthapuram 695 014, India</affiliation>
						<email>gtpulikunnel@yahoo.com.</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="" last="Sreejayan">Sreejayan</name>
						<affiliation>Plant Genomics Group, Rajiv Gandhi Centre for Biotechnology, Thiruvananthapuram 695 014, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Latha" last="Joseph">Latha Joseph</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Botany, University of Kerala, Thiruvananthapuram 695 581, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Philomena" last="Kuriachan">Philomena Kuriachan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Botany, University of Kerala, Thiruvananthapuram 695 581, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-05-21</date>
					<date type="R">2001-10-16</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Evaluation of the genetic variability of 13 microsatellite markers in native Indian pigs</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0149-0153</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We analysed polymorphism of 13 microsatellites in two Indian domesticated pig types (North Indian and Northeast Indian). Heterozygosity, polymorphism information content, and probability of identity of two random individuals were calculated for all microsatellites in both types. The number of alleles observed at a locus varied between five and 12. The evaluated microsatellites exhibited a very high heterozygosity and polymorphism information content. The probability of identity of two random individuals from different populations taking into account all the 13 microsatellites was as low as $3.51 \times 10^{-19}$. On the basis of these results, we propose that these microsatellite markers may be used with reliability for studying the genetic diversity and for identification of individuals in Indian pig types.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>microsatellite;genetic variability;Indian pig.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Rajeev" last="Kaul">Rajeev Kaul</name>
						<affiliation>Animal Genetics Division, National Bureau of Animal Genetic Resources, P.O. Box 129, Karnal 132 001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Atar" last="Singh">Atar Singh</name>
						<affiliation>Animal Genetics Division, National Bureau of Animal Genetic Resources, P.O. Box 129, Karnal 132 001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. K." last="Vijh">R. K. Vijh</name>
						<affiliation>Animal Genetics Division, National Bureau of Animal Genetic Resources, P.O. Box 129, Karnal 132 001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="M. S." last="Tantia">M. S. Tantia</name>
						<affiliation>Animal Genetics Division, National Bureau of Animal Genetic Resources, P.O. Box 129, Karnal 132 001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Rahul" last="Behl">Rahul Behl</name>
						<affiliation>Animal Genetics Division, National Bureau of Animal Genetic Resources, P.O. Box 129, Karnal 132 001, India</affiliation>
						<email>rahul@nbagr.hry.nic.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-05-08</date>
					<date type="R">2001-10-08</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The genetics of cattle</title>
				<feature>Book Review</feature>
				<page>0155-0158</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. H." last="Edwards">J. H. Edwards</name>
						<affiliation>Emeritus Professor of Genetics, Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, South Parks Road, Oxford OX1 3QU, UK.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The genetics of the horse</title>
				<feature>Book Review</feature>
				<page>0159-0161</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. H." last="Edwards">J. H. Edwards</name>
						<affiliation>Emeritus Professor of Genetics, Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, South Parks Road, Oxford OX1 3QU, UK.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Subject Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0163-0168</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="081">
		<issue inum="01" month="04" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Epigenetics comes of age in the twentyfirst century</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0001-0004</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Robin" last="Holliday">Robin Holliday</name>
						<affiliation>12 Roma Court, West Pennant Hills, N.S.W. 2125, Australia</affiliation>
						<email>RandL.Holliday@bigpond.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Cloning and characterization of an insecticidal crystal protein gene from <i>Bacillus thuringiensis</i> subspecies <i>kenyae</i></title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0005-0011</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A sporulating culture of <i>Bacillus thuringiensis</i> subsp. <i>kenyae</i> strain HD549 is toxic to larvae of lepidopteran insect species such as <i>Spodoptera litura, Helicoverpa armigera</i> and <i>Phthorimaea operculella</i>, and a dipteran insect, <i>Culex fatigans</i>. A 1.9-kb DNA fragment, PCR-amplified from HD549 using <i>cryII</i>-gene-specific primers, was cloned and expressed in <i>E. coli</i>. The recombinant protein produced 92\%\ mortality in first-instar larvae of <i>Spodoptera litura</i> and 86\%\ inhibition of adult emergence in <i>Phthorimaea operculella</i>, but showed very low toxicity against <i>Helicoverpa armigera</i>, and lower mortality against third-instar larvae of dipteran insects <i>Culex fatigans, Anopheles stephensi</i> and <i>Aedes aegypti</i>. The sequence of the cloned crystal protein gene showed almost complete homology with a mosquitocidal toxin gene from <i>Bacillus thuringiensis</i> var. <i>kurstaki</i>, with only five mutations scattered in different regions. Amino acid alignment with different insecticidal crystal proteins using the MUTALIN program suggested presence of the conserved block 3 region in the sequence of this protein. A mutation in codon 409 of this gene that changes a highly conserved phenylalanine residue to serine lies in this block.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>insecticidal protein;dipteran;Bacillus thuringiensis var. kenyae.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Hari S." last="Misra">Hari S. Misra</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Agriculture Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email>hsmisra@magnum.barc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Nivedita P." last="Khairnar">Nivedita P. Khairnar</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Agriculture Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Manjula" last="Mathur">Manjula Mathur</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Agriculture Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N." last="Vijayalakshmi">N. Vijayalakshmi</name>
						<affiliation>Nuclear Agriculture and Biotechnology Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ramesh S." last="Hire">Remesh S. Hire</name>
						<affiliation>Nuclear Agriculture and Biotechnology Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="T. K." last="Dongre">T. K. Dongre</name>
						<affiliation>Nuclear Agriculture and Biotechnology Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. K." last="Mahajan">S. K. Mahajan</name>
						<affiliation>Nuclear Agriculture and Biotechnology Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai 400 085, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-10-29</date>
					<date type="R">2002-03-05</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Cloning, chromosome localization and features of a novel human gene, <i>MATH2</i></title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0013-0017</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We report cloning and some features of a novel human gene, <i>MATH2</i>, which encodes a protein of 337 amino acid residues with a basic helix–loop–helix domain and exhibits 98\%\ similarity to mouse <i>Math2</i>. Results of Northern blot analysis revealed two transcripts of the <i>MATH2</i> gene of 1.7 kb and 2.4 kb in human brain. We localized <i>MATH2</i> to chromosome 7 at 7p14–15 by matching with the Human Genome Sequence Database. Human <i>MATH2</i> and mouse <i>Math2</i> may have the same functions in the nervous system.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>MATH2;transcription factor;bHLH;novel human gene.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Lingchen" last="Guo">Lingchen Guo</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Min" last="Jiang">Min Jiang</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yushu" last="Ma">Yushu Ma</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Haipeng" last="Cheng">Haipeng Cheng</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Xiaohua" last="Ni">Xiaohua Ni</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yangsheng" last="Jin">Yangsheng Jin</name>
						<affiliation>United Gene Holdings, Ltd, Shanghai 200092, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yi" last="Xie">Yi Xie</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>ymmao@fudan.edu.cn</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yumin" last="Mao">Yumin Mao</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>ymmao@fudan.edu.cn</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2001-12-14</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title><i>RPE65</i> gene: multiplex PCR and mutation screening in patients from India with retinal degenerative diseases</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0019-0023</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We used multiplex PCR followed by sequencing to screen for mutations in the 14 exons of the <i>RPE65</i> gene in early-childhood-onset autosomal recessive retinitis pigmentosa (arRP) and Leber’s congenital amaurosis (LCA) patients. The RPE65 protein is believed to play an important role in the metabolism of vitamin A in the visual cycle and mutations identified in the gene could have implications for vitamin A-based therapeutic intervention. We were able to identify a homozygous mutation (AAT $\to$ AAG) in exon 9 in an arRP patient and a heterozygous missense transversion (AAT $\to$ AAG) also in exon 9 of an LCA patient. We also identified a polymorphism in exon 10 (GAG $\to$ GAA) in an arRP as well as an LCA patient. Mutation screening would be greatly facilitated by multiplex PCR which could cut down costs, labour and time involved. The nucleotide changes observed in this study could be <i>de novo</i>. Though a larger study has been undertaken, from the preliminary results it appears that in India the <i>RPE65</i> gene seems to be less involved in causation of LCA.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>RPE65</i>;multiplex PCR;retinal degenerative disease.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Biju" last="Joseph">Biju Joseph</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Medical and Vision Research Foundations, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Anuradha" last="Srinivasan">Anuradha Srinivasan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Medical and Vision Research Foundations, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Nagasamy" last="Soumittra">Nagasamy Soumittra</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Medical and Vision Research Foundations, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Authiappan" last="Vidhya">Authiappan Vidhya</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Medical and Vision Research Foundations, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Nitin Shridhara" last="Shetty">Nitin Shridhara Shetty</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Medical Retina, Medical and Vision Research Foundations, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Satagopan" last="Uthra">Satagopan Uthra</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Medical and Vision Research Foundations, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Govindasamy" last="Kumaramanickavel">Govindasamy Kumaramanickavel</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Medical and Vision Research Foundations, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email>drgkm@sankaranethralaya.org</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-03-26</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Annotation and BAC/PAC localization of nonredundant ESTs from drought-stressed seedlings of an <i>indica</i> rice</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0025-0044</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>To decipher the genes associated with drought stress response and to identify novel genes in rice, we utilized 1540 high-quality expressed sequence tags (ESTs) for functional annotation and mapping to rice genomic sequences. These ESTs were generated earlier by $3'$-end single-pass sequencing of 2000 cDNA clones from normalized cDNA libraries constructed from drought-stressed seedlings of an <i>indica</i> rice. A rice UniGene set of 1025 transcripts was constructed from this collection through the BLASTN algorithm. Putative functions of 559 nonredundant ESTs were identified by BLAST similarity search against public databases. Putative functions were assigned at a stringency E value of $10^{-6}$ in BLASTN and BLASTX algorithms. To understand the gene structure and function further, we have utilized the publicly available finished and unfinished rice BAC/PAC (BAC, bacterial artificial chromosome; PAC, P1 artificial chromosome) sequences for similarity search using the BLASTN algorithm. Further, 603 nonredundant ESTs have been mapped to BAC/PAC clones. BAC clones were assigned by a homology of above 95\%\ identity along 90\%\ of EST sequence length in the aligned region. In all, 700 ESTs showed rice EST hits in GenBank. Of the 325 novel ESTs, 128 were localized to BAC clones. In addition, 127 ESTs with identified putative functions but with no homology in IRGSP (International Rice Genome Sequencing Program) BAC/PAC sequences were mapped to the Chinese WGS (whole genome shotgun contigs) draft sequence of the rice genome. Functional annotation uncovered about a hundred candidate ESTs associated with abiotic stress in rice and <i>Arabidopsis</i> that were previously reported based on microarray analysis and other studies. This study is a major effort in identifying genes associated with drought stress response and will serve as a resource to rice geneticists and molecular biologists.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>ESTs;annotation;<i>Oryza sativa</i>;<i>indica</i> rice;cDNA libraries;rice genome;drought tolerance.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P. Ravindra" last="Babu">P. Ravindra Babu</name>
						<affiliation>Plant Molecular Genetics and Functional Genomics Laboratory, Department of Plant Sciences, School of Life Sciences, University of Hyderabad, Hyderabad 500 046, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. Chandra" last="Sekhar">A. Chandra Sekhar</name>
						<affiliation>Plant Molecular Genetics and Functional Genomics Laboratory, Department of Plant Sciences, School of Life Sciences, University of Hyderabad, Hyderabad 500 046, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Nagabhushana" last="Ithal">Nagabhushana Ithal</name>
						<affiliation>Plant Molecular Genetics and Functional Genomics Laboratory, Department of Plant Sciences, School of Life Sciences, University of Hyderabad, Hyderabad 500 046, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G." last="Markandeya">G. Markandeya</name>
						<affiliation>Plant Molecular Genetics and Functional Genomics Laboratory, Department of Plant Sciences, School of Life Sciences, University of Hyderabad, Hyderabad 500 046, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Arjula R." last="Reddy">Arjula R. Reddy</name>
						<affiliation>Plant Molecular Genetics and Functional Genomics Laboratory, Department of Plant Sciences, School of Life Sciences, University of Hyderabad, Hyderabad 500 046, India</affiliation>
						<email>arjulsl@uohyd.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-04-25</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The genetics of the dog</title>
				<feature>Book review</feature>
				<page>0045-0047</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. H." last="Edwards">J. H. Edwards</name>
						<affiliation>Emeritus Professor of Genetics, Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, South Parks Road, Oxford OX1 3QU, UK.</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="08" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>William Bateson: a biologist ahead of his time</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0049-0058</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Patrick" last="Bateson">Patrick Bateson</name>
						<affiliation>Sub-Department of Animal Behaviour, University of Cambridge, Madingley, Cambridge CB3 8AA, UK</affiliation>
						<affiliation>The Provost’s Lodge, King’s College, Cambridge CB2 1ST, UK.</affiliation>
						<email>ppgb@cam.ac.uk</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Screening for homozygosity by descent in families with autosomal recessive retinitis pigmentosa</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0059-0063</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Retinitis pigmentosa (RP) is a genetically heterogeneous disease and an important cause of blindness in the state of Andhra Pradesh in India. In an attempt to identify the disease locus in families with the recessive form of the disease, we used the approach of screening for homozygosity by descent in offspring of consanguineous and nonconsanguineous families with RP. Microsatellite markers closely flanking 21 known candidate genes for RP were genotyped in parents and affected offspring to determine whether there was homozygosity at these loci that was shared by affected individuals of a family. This screening approach may be a rapid preliminary method to test known loci for possible cosegregation with disease.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>retinitis pigmentosa;candidate gene;homozygosity screening.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Kota" last="Lalitha">Kota Lalitha</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Genetics, Prof. Brien Holden Eye Research Centre and Hyderabad Eye Research Foundation, L. V. Prasad Marg, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad 500 034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Subhadra" last="Jalali">Subhadra Jalali</name>
						<affiliation>Smt. Kannuri Santhamma Retina-Vitreous Services, L. V. Prasad Eye Institute, L. V. Prasad Marg, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad 500 034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Tejas" last="Kadakia">Tejas Kadakia</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Genetics, Prof. Brien Holden Eye Research Centre and Hyderabad Eye Research Foundation, L. V. Prasad Marg, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad 500 034, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Chitra" last="Kannabiran">Chitra Kannabiran</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Genetics, Prof. Brien Holden Eye Research Centre and Hyderabad Eye Research Foundation, L. V. Prasad Marg, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad 500 034, India</affiliation>
						<email>chitra@lvpeye.stph.net</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-07-06</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Candidate gene polymorphisms among North Indians and their association with schizophrenia in a case–control study</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0065-0071</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Knowledge of candidate gene polymorphisms in a population is useful for a variety of gene–disease association studies, particularly for some complex traits. A number of candidate genes, a majority of them from the monoaminergic pathway in the brain, have been very popular in association studies with schizophrenia, a neuropsychiatric disorder. In this study diallelic/multiallelic polymorphisms in some dopaminergic, serotonergic and membrane-phospholipid-related genes have been evaluated in a control population recruited from North India. Association, if any, of these allelic variants with schizopherenia has been tested using a case–control approach. The case data have been taken from our published family-based association studies in schizophrenia. Of the eight genes tested in this study, association with schizophrenia was observed for only two gene polymorphisms, one in the promoter region of the serotonin 2A receptor gene and the other in the tryptophan hydroxylase gene. One new allele for the dopamine transporter gene (with eight repeats, 570-bp size), not reported in any population so far, has been identified in one individual in our sample. The data generated in this study, besides providing a normative background for various disease association studies, are a significant contribution to the population-specific genome database, a currently growing requirement.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>candidate gene;gene polymorphism;allele frequency;schizophrenia;case–control study;North Indian population.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Prachi" last="Semwal">Prachi Semwal</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Suman" last="Prasad">Suman Prasad</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Panchami G." last="Varma">Panchami G. Varma</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. M." last="Bhagwat">A. M. Bhagwat</name>
						<affiliation>C. B. Patel Research Centre for Chemistry and Biological Sciences, 3rd floor, Bhaidas Hall Building, Vile Parle (West), Mumbai 400 056, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. N." last="Deshpande">S. N. Deshpande</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Dr Ram Manohar Lohia Hospital, New Delhi 110 001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. K." last="Thelma">B. K. Thelma</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email>humgen@del3.vsnl.net.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-08-03</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Mobile genetic elements in protozoan parasites</title>
				<feature>Review Article</feature>
				<page>0073-0086</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Mobile genetic elements, by virtue of their ability to move to new chromosomal locations, are considered important in shaping the evolutionary course of the genome. They are widespread in the biological kingdom. Among the protozoan parasites several types of transposable elements are encountered. The largest variety is seen in the trypanosomatids—<i>Trypanosoma brucei, Trypanosoma cruzi</i> and <i>Crithidia fasciculata</i>. They contain elements that insert site-specifically in the spliced-leader RNA genes, and others that are dispersed in a variety of genomic locations. <i>Giardia lamblia</i> contains three families of transposable elements. Two of these are subtelomeric in location while one is chromosome-internal. <i>Entamoeba histolytica</i> has an abundant retrotransposon dispersed in the genome. Nucleotide sequence analysis of all the elements shows that they are all retrotransposons, and, with the exception of one class of elements in <i>T. cruzi</i>, all of them are non-long-terminal-repeat retrotransposons. Although most copies have accumulated mutations, they can potentially encode reverse transcriptase, endonuclease and nucleic-acid-binding activities. Functionally and phylogenetically they do not belong to a single lineage, showing that retrotransposons were acquired early in the evolution of protozoan parasites. Many of the potentially autonomous elements that encode their own transposition functions have nonautonomous counterparts that probably utilize the functions in trans. In this respect these elements are similar to the mammalian LINEs and SINEs (long and short interspersed DNA elements), showing a common theme in the evolution of retrotransposons. So far there is no report of a DNA transposon in any protozoan parasite. The genome projects that are under way for most of these organisms will help understand the evolution and possible function of these genetic elements.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>protozoan parasites;autonomous and nonautonomous mobile elements;non-LTR retrotransposons.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Sudha" last="Bhattacharya">Sudha Bhattacharya</name>
						<affiliation>School of Environmental Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email>sb@mail.jnu.ac.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Abhijeet" last="Bakre">Abhijeet Bakre</name>
						<affiliation>School of Environmental Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Alok" last="Bhattacharya">Alok Bhattacharya</name>
						<affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi 110 067, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Thinking about evolution: historical, philosophical, and political perspectives</title>
				<feature>Book Review</feature>
				<page>0087-0089</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. V." last="Joshi">N. V. Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Ecological Sciences, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India.</affiliation>
						<email>nvjoshi@ces.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="11" year="2002">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Endogamy, consanguinity and community genetics</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0091-0098</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A. H." last="Bittles">A. H. Bittles</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Human Genetics, Edith Cowan University, 100 Joondalup Drive, Perth, WA 6027, Australia</affiliation>
						<email>a.bittles@ecu.edu.au</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The power and statistical behaviour of allele-sharing statistics when applied to models with two disease loci</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0099-0103</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have evaluated the power for detecting a common trait determined by two loci, using seven statistics, of which five are implemented in the computer program SimWalk2, and two are implemented in GENEHUNTER. Unlike most previous reports which involve evaluations of the power of allele-sharing statistics for a single disease locus, we have used a simulated data set of general pedigrees in which a two-locus disease is segregating and evaluated several non-parametric linkage statistics implemented in the two programs. We found that the power for detecting linkage using the $S_{\text{all}}$ statistic in GENEHUNTER (GH, version 2.1), implemented as statistic $E$ in SimWalk2 (version 2.82), is different in the two. The $P$ values associated with statistic $E$ output by SimWalk2 are consistently more conservative than those from GENEHUNTER except when the underlying model includes heterogeneity at a level of 50\%\ where the $P$ values output are very comparable. On the other hand, when the thresholds are determined empirically under the null hypothesis, $S_{\text{all}}$ in GENEHUNTER and statistic $E$ have similar power.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>mapping complex traits;power calculation;allele-sharing statistics.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Yin Y." last="Shugart">Yin Y. Shugart</name>
						<affiliation>Epidemiology Department, Bloomberg School of Public Health, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Center for Inherited Disease Research, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Bing-Jian" last="Feng">Bing-Jian Feng</name>
						<affiliation>Epidemiology Department, Bloomberg School of Public Health, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Andrew" last="Collins">Andrew Collins</name>
						<affiliation>Human Genetics Division, School of Medicine, University of Southampton, Southampton SO16 6YD, UK</affiliation>
						<email>arc@soton.ac.uk</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-11-20</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>An orphan <i>gyrB</i> in the <i>Mycobacterium smegmatis</i> genome uncovered by comparative genomics</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0105-0110</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>DNA gyrase is an essential topoisomerase found in all bacteria. It is encoded by <i>gyrB</i> and <i>gyrA</i> genes. These genes are organized differently in different bacteria. Direct comparison of <i>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</i> and <i>Mycobacterium smegmatis</i> genomes reveals presence of an additional <i>gyrB</i> in <i>M. smegmatis</i> flanked by novel genes. Analysis of the amino acid sequence of GyrB from different organisms suggests that the orphan GyrB in <i>M. smegmatis</i> may have an important cellular role.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>Mycobacterium smegmatis</i>;<i>gyr</i> genes;DNA gyrase;topoisomerase;comparative genomics.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Jain">P. Jain</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V." last="Nagaraja">V. Nagaraja</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>vraj@mcbl.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-12-13</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The social biology of Ropalidia marginata: towards understanding the evolution of eusociality</title>
				<feature>Book Review</feature>
				<page>0111-0112</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Oliver" last="Mayo">Oliver Mayo</name>
						<affiliation>CSIRO Livestock Industries, Kintore Avenue, Adelaide, SA 5000, Australia.</affiliation>
						<email>oliver.mayo@csiro.au</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Subject Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0113-0115</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Author Index</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0116-0117</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="082">
		<issue inum="01-02" month="04-08" year="2003">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Extreme nuclear disproportion and constancy of enzyme activity in a heterokaryon of <i>Neurospora crassa</i></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0006</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Heterokaryons of <i>Neurospora crassa</i> were generated by transformation of multinucleate conidia of a <i>histidine-3</i> auxotroph with <i>his-3$^{+}$</i> plasmid. In one of the transformants, propagated on a medium with histidine supplementation, a gradual but drastic reduction occurred in the proportion of prototrophic nuclei that contained an ectopically integrated <i>his-3$^{+}$</i> allele. This response was specific to histidine. The reduction in prototrophic nuclei was confirmed by several criteria: inoculum size test, hyphal tip analysis, genomic Southern analysis, and by visual change in colour of the transformant incorporating genetic colour markers. Construction and analyses of three-component heterokaryons revealed that the change in nuclear ratio resulted from interaction of auxotrophic nucleus with prototrophic nucleus that contained an ectopically integrated <i>his-3$^{+}$</i> gene, but not with prototrophic nucleus that contained <i>his-3$^{+}$</i> gene at the normal chromosomal location. The growth rate of heterokaryons and the activity of histidinol dehydrogenase—the protein encoded by the <i>his-3$^{+}$</i> gene—remained unchanged despite prototrophic nuclei becoming very scarce. The results suggest that not all nuclei in the coenocytic fungal mycelium may be active simultaneously, the rare active nuclei being sufficient to confer the wild-type phenotype.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>Neurospora crassa</i>;heterokaryon;nuclear ratio;histidinol dehydrogenase;transformation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Kandasamy" last="Pitchaimani">Kandasamy Pitchaimani</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ramesh" last="Maheshwari">Ramesh Maheshwari</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>fungi@biochem.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-07-28</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A comparison of two popular statistical methods for estimating the time to most recent common ancestor (TMRCA) from a sample of DNA sequences</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0007-0012</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have compared two statistical methods of estimating the time to most recent common ancestor (TMRCA) from a sample of DNA sequences, which have been proposed by Templeton (1993) and Bandelt <i>et al.</i> (1995). Monte-Carlo simulations were used for generating DNA sequence data. Different evolutionary scenarios were simulated and the estimation procedures were evaluated. We have found that for both methods</p>
					<ol type="roman">
						<li>the estimates are insensitive to demographic parameters and</li>
						<li>the standard deviations of the estimates are too high for these methods to be reliably used in practice.</li>
					</ol>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>coalescence;Monte-Carlo simulation;evolution.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Analabha" last="Basu">Analabha Basu</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology &amp; Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T. Road, Kolkata 700 108, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Partha P." last="Majumder">Partha P. Majumder</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology &amp; Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T. Road, Kolkata 700 108, India</affiliation>
						<email>ppm@isical.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-04-29</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The inactive X chromosome in the human female is enriched in 5-methylcytosine to an unusual degree and appears to contain more of this modified nucleotide than the remainder of the genome</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0013-0016</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>By employing a procedure that combines ELISA and photoacoustic spectroscopy, we have examined the content of 5-methylcytosine (m$^{5}$C) in DNA of individuals who differed from one another in the number of X chromosomes in their genomes. The results show that the human inactive X chromosome (Xi) contains very high amounts of this modified nucleotide. We estimate that in the 46,XX female there is more m$^{5}$C in Xi ($\sim 3.6 \times 10^{7}$) than in all the remaining chromosomes put together ($\sim 2.1 \times 10^{7}$). Our results also suggest that nearly one-fifth of all cytosines in Xi are methylated and that, in addition to CpG methylation, there is extensive non-CpG methylation as well.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>5-methylcytosine;X inactivation;human X chromosome;methylation;photoacoustic spectroscopy.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Deepti D." last="Deobagkar">Deepti D. Deobagkar</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Zoology, University of Pune, Pune 411 007, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>dddeo@unipune.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="H. Sharat" last="Chandra">H. Sharat Chandra</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Human Genetics, G-04, ITPL, Whitefield, Bangalore 560 066, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Cell Biology, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>sharat@mcbl.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-07-19</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Absence of <i>GABRA1</i> Ala322Asp mutation in juvenile myoclonic epilepsy families from India</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0017-0021</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>An Ala322Asp mutation in the <i>GABRA1</i> gene was recently reported to be responsible for causing the autosomal dominant (AD) form of juvenile myoclonic epilepsy (JME) in a French-Canadian family. To study if JME families from India exhibiting the AD mode of inheritance carry the Ala322Asp mutation, we examined 35 unrelated JME-affected individuals from such families for the Ala322Asp mutation in <i>GABRA1</i>. Ala322Asp mutation was not observed in any of these JME-affected individuals, suggesting that this mutation is unlikely to be a predominant mutation involved in causation of epilepsy. To evaluate the possibility of other mutation(s) in and around <i>GABRA1</i> that may predispose to JME, we compared the allele frequencies at two marker loci, D5S2118 and D5S422, flanking <i>GABRA1</i>, in probands and 100 matched population controls. One of the allele frequencies at D5S422 shows a significant difference between the cases and controls ($\chi^{2} = 11.44$, d.f. = 1, $P = 0.0007$), suggesting genetic association between JME and genes located in the proximity of the DNA marker.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>GABRA1</i>;juvenile myoclonic epilepsy;DNA sequencing;Indian families.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Kapoor">A. Kapoor</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Genetics Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J." last="Vijai">J. Vijai</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Neurology, Sree Chitra Tirunal Institute for Medical Sciences and Technology, Thiruvananthapuram 695 011, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="H. M." last="Ravishankar">H. M. Ravishankar</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Genetics Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Satishchandra">P. Satishchandra</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Neurology, National Institute of Mental Health and Neurosciences, Hosur Road, Bangalore 560 029, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Radhakrishnan">K. Radhakrishnan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Neurology, Sree Chitra Tirunal Institute for Medical Sciences and Technology, Thiruvananthapuram 695 011, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A." last="Anand">A. Anand</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Genetics Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>anand@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-03-29</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Assignment of human <i>sprouty 4</i> gene to chromosome segment 5q32$\sim$33 and analysis of its pattern of expression</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0023-0026</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The human <i>sprouty 4</i> (<i>SPYR4</i>) gene was localized to chromosome band 5q32$\sim$33 by screening the Stanford radiation hybrid G3 panel using a <i>SPRY4</i>-specific primer pair for PCR. Northern blot analysis revealed two different mRNAs (5 kb and 2 kb) in liver, skeletal muscle, heart, lung, kidney, spleen, placenta and small intestine. Reverse transcriptase-PCR analysis showed that <i>SPYR4</i> was expressed in all tested tissues to different levels.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>SPRY4</i>;radioactive hybridization (RH);expression pattern.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Hua" last="Liu">Hua Liu</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jin-Zhong" last="Chen">Jin-Zhong Chen</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shao-Hua" last="Gu">Shao-Hua Gu</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jian-Liang" last="Dai">Jian-Liang Dai</name>
						<affiliation>United Gene Holdings, Ltd., Shanghai 200092, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="En-Pang" last="Zhao">En-Pang Zhao</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Lu" last="Huang">Lu Huang</name>
						<affiliation>United Gene Holdings, Ltd., Shanghai 200092, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Wang-Xiang" last="Xu">Wang-Xiang Xu</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yi" last="Xie">Yi Xie</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>ymmao@fudan.edu.cn</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yu-Min" last="Mao">Yu-Min Mao</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>ymmao@fudan.edu.cn</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-10-31</date>
					<date type="R">2003-03-05</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Molecular cloning and characterization of a novel human kinase gene, <i>PDIK1L</i></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0027-0032</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We isolated a 4301-bp cDNA from a human foetal brain cDNA library by high-throughput cDNA sequencing. It encodes a protein of 341 amino acids, which shows 69\%\ identity with the human kinase CLIK1 (AAL99353), which was suggested to be the CLP-36 interacting kinase. Bioinformatics analysis suggests that the putative kinase may interact with PDZ and LIM domain proteins. Therefore the protein and its cDNA were named ‘PDLIM1 interacting kinase 1 like’ (PDIK1L; nomenclature approved by the HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee). Ensembl Genome Browser located <i>PDIK1L</i> to human chromosome 1p35.3. It spans about 13.7 kb and consists of four exons and three introns. Multiple-tissue cDNA panel PCR revealed that the gene is expressed widely in human tissues: liver, kidney, pancreas, spleen, thymus and prostate. The protein appears to be localized to the nucleus.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>PDIK1L</i>;protein kinase;human;expression.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Lingchen" last="Guo">Lingchen Guo</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Chaoneng" last="Ji">Chaoneng Ji</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shaohua" last="Gu">Shaohua Gu</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Kang" last="Ying"></name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Haipeng" last="Cheng">Haipeng Cheng</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Xiaoghua" last="Ni">Xiaoghua Ni</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jianping" last="Liu">Jianping Liu</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yi" last="Xie">Yi Xie</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yumin" last="Mao">Yumin Mao</name>
						<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering, Institute of Genetics, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai 200433, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>ymmao@fudan.edu.cn</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-01-13</date>
					<date type="R">2003-05-19</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Ethnic variations of a retinoblastoma susceptibility gene (<i>RB1</i>) polymorphism in eight Asian populations</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0033-0037</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>An A $\to$ G single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) at nucleotide 153,104 in the retinoblastoma susceptibility locus (<i>RB1</i>) at 13q14 was previously reported to be present only in Asians. In this study, we determined the distribution of this SNP in normal Southeast Asian populations (Chinese, Malay, Javanese, Thai, Filipino), in South Asian populations (Bangladeshi, Pakistani Pushtun and Indian) and in Chinese retinoblastoma cases and control subjects. The <i>RB1</i> SNP was present in all populations at an overall frequency of $\leq 0.18$. Heterozygosity was higher in the Southeast Asian groups (0.14–0.34) than in the South Asian groups (Bangladeshi and Indian) (0.04–0.06). Significant differences in allele frequencies were found between the two population groups. Interestingly, our Pakistani population comprised of ethnic Pushtuns from northwest Pakistan was significantly different from the neighbouring Bangladeshi and Indian populations. No significant difference was found between Chinese case patients and control subjects. This <i>RB1</i> SNP appears to be an ethnic variant prevalent in Southeast Asian populations and may be useful for studying <i>RB1</i> inheritance by pedigree analysis.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>retinoblastoma susceptibility gene (<i>RB1</i>);single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP);allele frequency;Asian.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Priya" last="Kadam-Pai">Priya Kadam-Pai</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, National University of Singapore, Lower Kent Ridge Road, Singapore 119074</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Xin-Yi" last="Su">Xin-Yi Su</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, National University of Singapore, Lower Kent Ridge Road, Singapore 119074</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jasmin Jiji" last="Miranda">Jasmin Jiji Miranda</name>
						<affiliation>National Neuroscience Institute, Singapore 308433</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Agustinus" last="Soemantri">Agustinus Soemantri</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, University Diponegoro, Indonesia 50241</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Nilmani" last="Saha">Nilmani Saha</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Human Genetics, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA 15261, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Chew-Kiat" last="Heng">Chew-Kiat Heng</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, National University of Singapore, Lower Kent Ridge Road, Singapore 119074</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Poh-San" last="Lai">Poh-San Lai</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, National University of Singapore, Lower Kent Ridge Road, Singapore 119074</affiliation>
						<email>paelaips@nus.edu.sg</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-12-11</date>
					<date type="R">2003-05-27</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Molecular-genetic analysis of two cases with retinoblastoma: benefits for disease management</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0039-0044</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Effective counselling and management of retinoblastoma families using genetic information is presently practised in many parts of the world. We studied histopathological, chromosomal and molecular-genetic data of two retinoblastoma patients from India. The two patients, one with bilateral and the other with unilateral retinoblastoma, underwent complete ophthalmic examination, cytogenetic study, retinoblastoma gene (<i>RB1</i>) mutational analysis and <i>RB1</i> promoter region methylation screening. In the bilateral retinoblastoma patient deletion of chromosome region 13q14 in peripheral blood lymphocytes and a hemizygous novel 8-bp deletion in exon 4 of <i>RB1</i> in tumour sample were observed. In the unilaterally affected patient CGA to TGA transition protein truncation mutations were observed in exons 8 and 14 of <i>RB1</i>.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>DNA sequencing;gene methylation;<i>RB1</i> gene;retinoblastoma.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Govindasamy" last="Kumaramanickavel">Govindasamy Kumaramanickavel</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Vision Research Foundation, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email>drgkm@sankaranethralaya.org</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Biju" last="Joseph">Biju Joseph</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Vision Research Foundation, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Komaravelly" last="Narayana">Komaravelly Narayana</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Vision Research Foundation, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sribhargava" last="Natesh">Sribhargava Natesh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Vitreo-Retinal Surgery, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Gandra" last="Mamatha">Gandra Mamatha</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Vision Research Foundation, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Mahesh P." last="Shanmugam">Mahesh P. Shanmugam</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Vitreo-Retinal Surgery, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Anuradha" last="Elamparathi">Anuradha Elamparathi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Vision Research Foundation, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jyotirmay" last="Biswas">Jyotirmay Biswas</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Pathology, Medical Research Foundation, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-02-07</date>
					<date type="R">2003-03-14</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>What have two decades of laboratory life-history evolution studies on <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> taught us?</title>
				<feature>Review Article</feature>
				<page>0045-0076</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A series of laboratory selection experiments on <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> over the past two decades has provided insights into the specifics of life-history tradeoffs in the species and greatly refined our understanding of how ecology and genetics interact in life-history evolution. Much of what has been learnt from these studies about the subtlety of the microevolutionary process also has significant implications for experimental design and inference in organismal biology beyond life-history evolution, as well as for studies of evolution in the wild. Here we review work on the ecology and evolution of life-histories in laboratory populations of <i>D. melanogaster</i>, emphasizing how environmental effects on life-history-related traits can influence evolutionary change. We discuss life-history tradeoffs—many unexpected—revealed by selection experiments, and also highlight recent work that underscores the importance to life-history evolution of cross-generation and cross-life-stage effects and interactions, sexual antagonism and sexual dimorphism, population dynamics, and the possible role of biological clocks in timing life-history events. Finally, we discuss some of the limitations of typical selection experiments, and how these limitations might be transcended in the future by a combination of more elaborate and realistic selection experiments, developmental evolutionary biology, and the emerging discipline of phenomics.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>laboratory selection;experimental evolution;lifespan;development time;competitive ability;genetic architecture</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. G." last="Prasad">N. G. Prasad</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P. O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P. O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-00-00</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="12" year="2003">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Preface : Evolutionary genetics: the <i>Drosophila</i> model</title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0077-0078</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Genetic variability of sexual size dimorphism in a natural population of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>: an isofemale-line approach</title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0079-0088</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Most animal species exhibit sexual size dimorphism (SSD). SSD is a trait difficult to quantify for genetical purposes since it must be simultaneously measured on two kinds of individuals, and it is generally expressed either as a difference or as a ratio between sexes. Here we ask two related questions: What is the best way to describe SSD, and is it possible to conveniently demonstrate its genetic variability in a natural population? We show that a simple experimental design, the isofemale-line technique (full-sib families), may provide an estimate of genetic variability, using the coefficient of intraclass correlation. We consider two SSD indices, the female–male difference and the female/male ratio. For two size-related traits, wing and thorax length, we found that both SSD indices were normally distributed. Within each family, the variability of SSD was estimated by considering individual values in one sex (the female) with respect to the mean value in the other sex (the male). In a homogeneous sample of 30 lines of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>, both indices provided similar intraclass correlations, on average 0.21, significantly greater than zero but lower than those for the traits themselves: 0.50 and 0.36 for wing and thorax length respectively. Wing and thorax length were strongly positively correlated within each sex. SSD indices of wing and thorax length were also positively correlated, but to a lesser degree than for the traits themselves. For comparative evolutionary studies, the ratio between sexes seems a better index of SSD since it avoids scaling effects among populations or species, permits comparisons between different traits, and has an unambiguous biological significance. In the case of <i>D. melanogaster</i> grown at 25$^{\circ}$C, the average female/male ratios are very similar for the wing (1.16) and the thorax (1.15), and indicate that, on average, these size traits are 15–16\%\ longer in females.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>sexual size dimorphism;female–male difference;female/male ratio;intraclass correlation;evolvability;isofemale lines.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Jean R." last="David">Jean R. David</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Populations, Génétique et Evolution, 91198 – Gif sur Yvette Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email>david@pge.cnrs-gif.fr</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Patricia" last="Gibert">Patricia Gibert</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Biométrie, Biologie Evolutive, Université de Lyon I 69622 – Villeurbanne Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sandrine" last="Mignon-Grasteau">Sandrine Mignon-Grasteau</name>
						<affiliation>INRA, Station de Recherches Avicoles 37380 – Nouzilly, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Hélène" last="Legout">Hélène Legout</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Populations, Génétique et Evolution, 91198 – Gif sur Yvette Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Georges" last="Pétavy">Georges Pétavy</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Populations, Génétique et Evolution, 91198 – Gif sur Yvette Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Catherine" last="Beaumont">Catherine Beaumont</name>
						<affiliation>INRA, Station de Recherches Avicoles 37380 – Nouzilly, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Brigitte" last="Moreteau">Brigitte Moreteau</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Populations, Génétique et Evolution, 91198 – Gif sur Yvette Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-00-00</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0000-0000</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Mild heat stress at a young age in <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> leads to increased Hsp70 synthesis after stress exposure later in life</title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0089-0094</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In a number of animal species it has been shown that exposure to low levels of stress at a young age has a positive effect on stress resistance later in life, and on longevity. The positive effects have been attributed to the activation of defence/cleaning systems (heat shock proteins (Hsps), antioxidases, DNA repair) or to effects of a changed metabolic rate, or both. We investigated the effect of mild stress exposures early in life on Hsp70 synthesis after a harder stress exposure later in life in five isofemale lines of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>. Female flies were either exposed to repeated bouts of mild heat stress (3 h at 34$^{\circ}$°C) at a young age (days 2, 4 and 6 post-eclosion) or held under standard laboratory conditions. At 16 and 32 days of adult age, respectively, flies were exposed to a high temperature treatment known to induce Hsp70 in the investigated species (1 h at 37$^{\circ}$ºC). Thereafter, the inducible Hsp70 levels were measured. Our data show a tendency towards increased Hsp70 synthesis with increased age for both ‘mild stress’ and ‘no stress’ flies. Moreover, the results show that flies exposed to mild stress at a young age synthesized more Hsp70 upon induction, compared to control flies, and that this difference was accentuated at 32 days compared to 16 days of age. Thus, bouts of mild heat stress at a young age impact on the physiological stress response system later in life. This may be caused by an increased ability to react to future stresses. Alternatively, the mild stress exposure at a young age may actually have caused cellular damages increasing the need for Hsp70 levels after stress exposure later in life. The importance of an Hsp70 upregulation (throughout life) in explaining the phenomenon of hormesis is discussed, together with alternative hypotheses, and suggestions for further studies.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>ageing;<i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>;isofemale lines;hormesis;Hsp70;mild heat stress;molecular chaperones.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Torsten Nygaard" last="Kristensen">Torsten Nygaard Kristensen</name>
						<affiliation>Aarhus Centre for Environmental Stress Research (ACES), Department of Ecology and Genetics, University of Aarhus, Building 540, Ny Munkegade, DK-8000 Aarhus C, Denmark</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Animal Breeding and Genetics, Danish Institute of Agricultural Sciences, P.O. Box 50, DK-8830 Tjele, Denmark</affiliation>
						<email>torsten.kristensen@biology.au.dk</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jesper Givskov" last="Sørensen">Jesper Givskov Sørensen</name>
						<affiliation>Aarhus Centre for Environmental Stress Research (ACES), Department of Ecology and Genetics, University of Aarhus, Building 540, Ny Munkegade, DK-8000 Aarhus C, Denmark</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Volker" last="Loeschcke">Volker Loeschcke</name>
						<affiliation>Aarhus Centre for Environmental Stress Research (ACES), Department of Ecology and Genetics, University of Aarhus, Building 540, Ny Munkegade, DK-8000 Aarhus C, Denmark</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Quantitative-genetic analysis of wing form and bilateral asymmetry in isochromosomal lines of <i>Drosophila subobscura</i> using Procrustes methods</title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0095-0113</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Fluctuating asymmetry (FA) is often used as a measure of underlying developmental instability (DI), motivated by the idea that morphological variance is maladaptive. Whether or not DI has evolutionary potential is a highly disputed topic, marred by methodological problems and fuzzy prejudices. We report here some results from an ongoing study of the effects of karyotype, homozygosity and temperature on wing form and bilateral asymmetry using isochromosomal lines of <i>Drosophila subobscura</i>. Our approach uses the recently developed methodologies in geometric morphometrics to analyse shape configurations of landmarks within the standard statistical framework employed in studies of bilateral asymmetries, and we have extended these methods to partition the individual variation and the variation in asymmetries into genetic and environmental causal components. The analyses revealed temperature-dependent expression of genetic variation for wing size and wing shape, directional asymmetry (DA) of wing size, increased asymmetries at suboptimal temperature, and a transition from FA to DA in males as a result of increase in the rearing temperature. No genetic variation was generally detected for FA in our samples, but these are preliminary results because no crosses between lines were carried out and, therefore, the contribution of dominance was not taken into account. In addition, only a subset of the standing genetic variation was represented in the experiments.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>directional asymmetry;<i>Drosophila subobscura</i>;fluctuating asymmetry;geometric morphometrics;isochromosomal lines;Procrustes analysis;wing shape; wing size.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Pedro Fernández" last="Iriarte">Pedro Fernández Iriarte</name>
						<affiliation>Grup de Biologia Evolutiva (GBE), Departament de Genètica i de Microbiologia, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, 08193 Bellaterra (Barcelona), Spain</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Walkiria" last="Céspedes">Walkiria Céspedes</name>
						<affiliation>Grup de Biologia Evolutiva (GBE), Departament de Genètica i de Microbiologia, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, 08193 Bellaterra (Barcelona), Spain</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Mauro" last="Santos">Mauro Santos</name>
						<affiliation>Grup de Biologia Evolutiva (GBE), Departament de Genètica i de Microbiologia, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, 08193 Bellaterra (Barcelona), Spain</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Molecular population genetics of the $\beta$-<i>esterase</i> gene cluster of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i></title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0115-0131</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have investigated nucleotide polymorphism at the $\beta$-<i>esterase</i> gene cluster including the <i>Est-6</i> gene and $\psi$<i>Est-6</i> putative pseudogene in four samples of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> derived from natural populations of southern Africa (Zimbabwe), Europe (Spain), North America (USA: California), and South America (Venezuela). A complex haplo-type structure is revealed in both <i>Est-6</i> and $\psi$<i>Est-6</i>. Total nucleotide diversity is twice in $\psi$<i>Est-6</i> as in <i>Est-6</i>; diversity is higher in the African sample than in the non-African ones. Strong linkage disequilibrium occurs within the $\beta$-<i>esterase</i> gene cluster in non-African samples, but not in the African one. Intragenic gene conversion events are detected within <i>Est-6</i> and, to a much greater extent, within $\psi$<i>Est-6</i>; intergenic gene conversion events are rare. Tests of neutrality with recombination are significant for the $\beta$-<i>esterase</i> gene cluster in the non-African samples but not significant in the African one. We suggest that the demographic history (bottleneck and admixture of genetically differentiated populations) is the major factor shaping the pattern of nucleotide polymorphism in the $\beta$-<i>esterase</i> gene cluster. However there are some ‘footprints’ of directional and balancing selection shaping specific distribution of nucleotide polymorphism within the cluster. Intergenic epistatic selection between <i>Est-6</i> and $\psi$<i>Est-6</i> may play an important role in the evolution of the $\beta$-<i>esterase</i> gene cluster preserving the putative pseudogene from degenerative destruction and reflecting possible functional interaction between the functional gene and the putative pseudogene. <i>Est-6</i> and $\psi$<i>Est-6</i> may represent an indivisible intergenic complex (‘intergene’) in which each single component (<i>Est-6</i> or $\psi$<i>Est-6</i>) cannot separately carry out the full functional role.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>DNA polymorphism;<i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>;<i>Est-6</i>;$\psi$<i>Est-6</i>;<i>Drosophila</i> colonization;positive selection;epistatic selection;intergene;potogene.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Evgeniy S." last="Balakirev">Evgeniy S. Balakirev</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Institute of Marine Biology, Vladivostok 690041, Russia, and Academy of Ecology, Marine Biology, and Biotechnology, Far Eastern State University, Vladivostok 690600, Russia</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Francisco J." last="Ayala">Francisco J. Ayala</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<email>fjayala@uci.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The devil in the details of life-history evolution: instability and reversal of genetic correlations during selection on <i>Drosophila</i> development</title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0133-0145</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The evolutionary relationships between three major components of Darwinian fitness, development rate, growth rate and preadult survival, were estimated using a comparison of 55 distinct populations of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> variously selected for age-specific fertility, environmental-stress tolerance and accelerated development. Development rate displayed a strong net negative evolutionary correlation with weight at eclosion across all selection treatments, consistent with the existence of a size-versus-time tradeoff between these characters. However, within the data set, the magnitude of the evolutionary correlation depended upon the particular selection treatments contrasted. A previously proposed tradeoff between preadult viability and growth rate was apparent only under weak selection for juvenile fitness components. Direct selection for rapid development led to sharp reductions in both growth rates and viability. These data add to the mounting results from experimental evolution that illustrate the sensitivity of evolutionary correlations to</p>
					<ol type="roman">
						<li>genotype-by-environment (G $\times$ E) interaction,</li>
						<li>complex functional-trait interactions, and</li>
						<li>character definition.</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Instability, disappearance and reversal of patterns of genetic covariation often occur over short evolutionary time frames and as the direct product of selection, rather than some stochastic process. We suggest that the functional architecture of fitness is a rapidly evolving matrix with reticulate properties, a matrix that we understand only poorly.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>evolution;life history;genetic correlation;experimental evolution;growth rate;<i>Drosophila melanogaster.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Adam K." last="Chippindale">Adam K. Chippindale</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biology, Queen’s University, Kingston, ON K7L 3N6, Canada</affiliation>
						<email>chippind@biology.queensu.ca</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Anh L." last="Ngo">Anh L. Ngo</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Michael R." last="Rose">Michael R. Rose</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The contribution of ancestry, chance, and past and ongoing selection to adaptive evolution</title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0147-0162</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The relative contributions of ancestry, chance, and past and ongoing selection to variation in one adaptive (larval feeding rate) and one seemingly nonadaptive (pupation height) trait were determined in populations of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> adapting to either low or high larval densities in the laboratory. Larval feeding rates increased rapidly in response to high density, and the effects of ancestry, past selection and chance were ameliorated by ongoing selection within 15–20 generations. Similarly, in populations previously kept at high larval density, and then switched to low larval density, the decline of larval feeding rate to ancestral levels was rapid (15–20 generations) and complete, providing support for a previously stated hypothesis regarding the costs of faster feeding in <i>Drosophila</i> larvae. Variation among individuals was the major contributor to variation in pupation height, a trait that would superficially appear to be nonadaptive in the environmental context of the populations used in this study because it did not diverge between sets of populations kept at low versus high larval density for many generations. However, the degree of divergence among populations ($F_{\text{ST}}$) for pupation height was significantly less than expected for a selectively neutral trait, and we integrate results from previous studies to suggest that the variation for pupation height among populations is constrained by stabilizing selection, with a flat, plateau-like fitness function that, consequently, allows for substantial phenotypic variation within populations. Our results support the view that the genetic imprints of history (ancestry and past selection) in outbreeding sexual populations are typically likely to be transient in the face of ongoing selection and recombination. The results also illustrate the heuristic point that different forms of selection—for example directional versus stabilizing selection—acting on a trait in different populations may often not be due to differently shaped fitness functions, but rather due to differences in how the fitness function maps onto the actual distribution of phenotypes in a given population. We discuss these results in the light of previous work on reverse evolution, and the role of ancestry, chance, and past and ongoing selection in adaptive evolution.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>density-dependent selection;reverse evolution;larval feeding rate;pupation height;fitness functions;directional selection;stabilizing selection;<i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Robinson B." last="Castillo">Robinson B. Castillo</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Laurence D." last="Mueller">Laurence D. Mueller</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Hybridization, transgressive segregation and evolution of new genetic systems in <i>Drosophila</i></title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0163-0177</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Introgressive hybridization facilitates incorporation of genes from one species into the gene pool of another. Studies on long-term effects of introgressive hybridization in animal systems are sparse. <i>Drosophila nasuta</i> ($2n = 8$) and <i>D. albomicans</i> ($2n = 6$)—a pair of allopatric, morphologically almost identical, cross-fertile members of the <i>nasuta</i> subgroup of the <i>immigrans</i> species group—constitute an excellent system to analyse the impact of hybridization followed by transgressive segregation of parental characters in the hybrid progeny. Hybrid populations of <i>D. nasuta</i> and <i>D. albomicans</i> maintained for over 500 generations in the laboratory constitute new recombinant hybrid genomes, here termed cytoraces. The impact of hybridization, followed by introgression and transgressive segregation, on chromosomal constitution and karyotypes, some fitness parameters, isozymes, components of mating behaviour and mating preference reveals a complex pattern of interracial divergence among parental species and cytoraces. This assemblage of characters in different combinations in a laboratory hybrid zone allows us to study the emergence of new genetic systems. Here, we summarize results from our ongoing studies comparing these hybrid cytoraces with the parental species, and discuss the implications of these findings for our understanding of the evolution of new genetic systems.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>Drosophila nasuta</i>;<i>Drosophila albomicans</i>;hybridization;cytoraces;new genetic systems.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="H. A." last="Ranganath">H. A. Ranganath</name>
						<affiliation>Drosophila Stock Centre, Department of Studies in Zoology, University of Mysore, Manasagangotri, Mysore 570 006, India</affiliation>
						<email>drosrang@sancharnet.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Aruna">S. Aruna</name>
						<affiliation>Drosophila Stock Centre, Department of Studies in Zoology, University of Mysore, Manasagangotri, Mysore 570 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Thermal adaptation in <i>Drosophila serrata</i> under conditions linked to its southern border: unexpected patterns from laboratory selection suggest limited evolutionary potential</title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0179-0189</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>To investigate the ability of <i>Drosophila serrata</i> to adapt to thermal conditions over winter at the species southern border, replicate lines from three source locations were held as discrete generations over three years at either 19$^{\circ}$C (40 generations) or temperatures fluctuating between 7$^{\circ}$C and 18$^{\circ}$C (20 generations). Populations in the fluctuating environment were maintained either with an adult 0$^{\circ}$C cold shock or without a shock. These conditions were expected to result in temperature-specific directional selection for increased viability and productivity under both temperature regimes, and reduced development time under the fluctuating-temperature regime. Selection responses of all lines were tested under both temperature regimes after controlling for carry-over effects by rearing lines in these environments for two generations. When tested in the 19$^{\circ}$C environment, lines evolving at 19$^{\circ}$C showed a faster development time and a lower productivity relative to the other lines, while cold shock reduced development time and productivity of all lines. When tested in the fluctuating environment, productivity of the 7–18$^{\circ}$C lines selected with a cold shock was relatively lower than that of lines selected without a shock, but this pattern was not observed in the other populations. Viability and body size as measured by wing length were not altered by selection or cold shock, although there were consistent effects of source population on wing length. These results provide little evidence for temperature-specific adaptation in <i>D. serrata</i>—although the lines had diverged for some traits, these changes were not consistent with a priori predictions. In particular, there was no evidence for life-history changes reflecting adaptation to winter conditions at the southern border. The potential for <i>D. serrata</i> to adapt to winter conditions may therefore be limited.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>species borders;central and marginal populations;cold shock;selection;thermal adaptation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Andréa" last="Magiafoglou">Andréa Magiafoglou</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Environmental Stress and Adaptation Research, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Victoria 3086, Australia</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ary" last="Hoffmann">Ary Hoffmann</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Environmental Stress and Adaptation Research, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Victoria 3086, Australia</affiliation>
						<email>a.hoffmann@latrobe.edu.au</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Variation in adult life history and stress resistance across five species of <i>Drosophila</i></title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0191-0205</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Dry weight at eclosion, adult lifespan, lifetime fecundity, lipid and carbohydrate content at eclosion, and starvation and desiccation resistance at eclosion were assayed on a long-term laboratory population of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>, and one recently wild-caught population each of four other species of <i>Drosophila</i>, two from the <i>melanogaster</i> and two from the <i>immigrans</i> species group. The relationships among trait means across the five species did not conform to expectations based on correlations among these traits inferred from selection studies on <i>D. melanogaster</i>. In particular, the expected positive relationships between fecundity and size/lipid content, lipid content and starvation resistance, carbohydrate (glycogen) content and desiccation resistance, and the expected negative relationship between lifespan and fecundity were not observed. Most traits were strongly positively correlated between sexes across species, except for fractional lipid content and starvation resistance per microgram lipid. For most traits, there was evidence for significant sexual dimorphism but the degree of dimorphism did not vary across species except in the case of adult lifespan, starvation resistance per microgram lipid, and desiccation resistance per microgram carbohydrate. Overall, <i>D. nasuta nasuta</i> and <i>D. sulfurigaster neonasuta</i> (<i>immigrans</i> group) were heavier at eclosion than the <i>melanogaster</i> group species, and tended to have somewhat higher absolute lipid content and starvation resistance. Yet, these two <i>immigrans</i> group species were shorter-lived and had lower average daily fecundity than the <i>melanogaster</i> group species. The smallest species, <i>D. malerkotliana</i> (<i>melanogaster</i> group), had relatively high daily fecundity, intermediate lifespan and high fractional lipid content, especially in females. <i>D. ananassae</i> (<i>melanogaster</i> group) had the highest absolute and fractional carbohydrate content, but its desiccation resistance per microgram carbohydrate was the lowest among the five species. In terms of overall performance, the laboratory population of <i>D. melanogaster</i> was clearly superior, under laboratory conditions, to the other four species if adult lifespan, lifetime fecundity, average daily fecundity, and absolute starvation and desiccation resistance are considered. This finding is contrary to several recent reports of substantially higher adult lifespan and stress resistance in recently wild-caught flies, relative to flies maintained for a long time in discrete-generation laboratory cultures. Possible explanations for these apparent anomalies are discussed in the context of the differing selection pressures likely to be experienced by <i>Drosophila</i> populations in laboratory versus wild environments.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>life-history evolution;lifespan;fecundity;starvation;desiccation;lipid;glycogen;sexual dimorphism;laboratory adaptation;<i>Drosophila</i>.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. Sharmila" last="Bharathi">N. Sharmila Bharathi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. G." last="Prasad">N. G. Prasad</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Present address: Department of Biology, Queen’s University, Kingston ON K7L 3N6, Canada</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Mallikarjun" last="Shakarad">Mallikarjun Shakarad</name>
						<affiliation>Behaviour, Ecology and Evolution Laboratory, Department of Biology, Poornaprajna Institute of Scientific Research, 4, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Latitudinal clines in <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>: body size, allozyme frequencies, inversion frequencies, and the insulin-signalling pathway</title>
				<feature>Special issue - Evolutionary genetics: the Drosophila model</feature>
				<page>0207-0223</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Many latitudinal clines exist in <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>: in adult body size, in allele frequency at allozyme loci, and in frequencies of common cosmopolitan inversions. The question is raised whether these latitudinal clines are causally related. This review aims to connect data from two very different fields of study, evolutionary biology and cell biology, in explaining such natural genetic variation in <i>D. melanogaster</i> body size and development time. It is argued that adult body size clines, inversion frequency clines, and clines in allele frequency at loci involved in glycolysis and glycogen storage are part of the same adaptive strategy. Selection pressure is expected to differ at opposite ends of the clines. At high latitudes, selection on <i>D. melanogaster</i> would favour high larval growth rate at low temperatures, and resource storage in adults to survive winter. At low latitudes selection would favour lower larval critical size to survive crowding, and increased male activity leading to high male reproductive success. Studies of the insulin-signalling pathway in <i>D. melanogaster</i> point to the involvement of this pathway in metabolism and adult body size. The genes involved in the insulin-signalling pathway are associated with common cosmopolitan inversions that show latitudinal clines. Each chromosome region connected with a large common cosmopolitan inversion possesses a gene of the insulin transmembrane complex, a gene of the intermediate pathway and a gene of the TOR branch. The hypothesis is presented that temperate <i>D. melanogaster</i> populations have a higher frequency of a ‘thrifty’ genotype corresponding to high insulin level or high signal level, while tropical populations possess a more ‘spendthrift’ genotype corresponding to low insulin or low signal level.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>Drosophila;insulin;body size;latitudinal cline;inversion polymorphism.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Gerdien" last="De Jong">Gerdien De Jong</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Population Biology, Utrecht University, Padualaan 8, NL-3584 CH Utrecht, Netherlands</affiliation>
						<email>g.dejong@bio.uu.nl</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Zoltán" last="Bochdanovits">Zoltán Bochdanovits</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Population Biology, Utrecht University, Padualaan 8, NL-3584 CH Utrecht, Netherlands</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="083">
		<issue inum="01" month="04" year="2004">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Editorial</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0002</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. Vijay" last="Raghavan">K. Vijay Raghavan</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Genetic correlations: transient truths of adaptive evolution</title>
				<feature>Research commentary</feature>
				<page>0003-0006</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>genetic architecture;life history;experimental evolution;genetic correlations;genotype $\times$ environment interaction;stress resistance;<i>Drosophila melanogaster.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="N. G." last="Prasad">N. G. Prasad</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biology, Queen’s University, Kingston, Ontario K7L 3N6, Canada</affiliation>
						<email>prasad@biology.queensu.ca</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Mallikarjun N." last="Shakarad">Mallikarjun N. Shakarad</name>
						<affiliation>Behaviour, Ecology and Evolution Laboratory, Biology Department, Poornaprajna Institute of Scientific Research, 4, Sadashivanagar, Bangalore 560 080, India</affiliation>
						<email>mallik99@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Immunocompetence in <i>Drosophila</i>: linking genetic to phenotypic variation</title>
				<feature>Research commentary</feature>
				<page>0007-0008</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords><i>Drosophila</i> immunity;immunocompetence;polymorphism;genetic variation;phenotypic variation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Shampa" last="Ghosh">Shampa Ghosh</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>shampa@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="N. Sharmila" last="Bharathi">Sharmila Bharathi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>sharmila@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>On the genetic basis of temperature compensation of circadian clocks</title>
				<feature>Hypothesis</feature>
				<page>0009-0011</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>circadian;biological clocks;temperature compensation;<i>period</i> gene;<i>frequency</i> gene.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Vijay Kumar" last="Sharma">Vijay Kumar Sharma</name>
						<affiliation>Chronobiology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>vsharma@jncasr.ac.in;vksharmas@yahoo.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-03-26</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Are bigger flies always better: the role of genes and environment</title>
				<feature>Commentary on <i>J. Genet.</i> classic</feature>
				<page>0013-0015</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>life-history evolution;tradeoff;fecundity;development time;mating success;body size;stabilizing selection;<i>Drosophila melanogaster.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Studies in Quantitative Inheritance XI. Genetic and Environmental Correlation Between Body Size and Egg Production in <i>Drosophila Melanogaster</i></title>
				<feature><i>J. Genet. classic</i></feature>
				<page>0017-0032</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Forbes W." last="Robertson">Forbes W. Robertson</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Animal Genetics, Edinburgh</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Member of the Scientific Staff of the Agricultural Research Council</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Engineered <i>Xcm</i>I cassette-containing vector for PCR-based phylogenetic analyses</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0033-0034</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>T-vector;direct cloning;<i>Xcm</i>I cassette;sequencing;PCR;marine population genetics.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Futoshi" last="Aranishi">Futoshi Aranishi</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology Division, National Institute of Fisheries Science, Yokohama 236-8648, Japan</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, Mirjazaki University, Mirjazaki 889-2192, Japan</affiliation>
						<email>aranishi@affrc.go.jp</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Takane" last="Okimoto">Takane Okimoto</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology Division, National Institute of Fisheries Science, Yokohama 236-8648, Japan</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Graduate School of Science and Technology, Nagasaki University, Nagasaki 852-8521, Japan</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-09-18</date>
					<date type="M">2004-02-23</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Refinement of the locus for non-syndromic sensorineural deafness (DFN2)</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0035-0038</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Non-syndromic X-linked deafness is a rare form of genetic deafness in humans accounting for a small proportion of all hereditary hearing loss. Different clinical forms of non-syndromic X-linked deafness have been described, and most of these have been mapped. Here, we report a Chinese family affected by a congenital profound sensorineural hearing loss. All phenotypes of this family are clinically compatible with non-syndromic sensorineural deafness (DFN2). A maximum two-point Lod score of 2.32 was obtained at marker <i>DXS6797</i> ($\theta = 0.00$). Recombinants define a region of 4.3 cm flanked by markers <i>DXS6799</i> and <i>GATA172D05</i>. This region overlaps the previously reported DFN2 region by 2.0 cm.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>non-syndromic sensorineural deafness (DFN2);profound congenital sensorineural deafness;linkage;X chromosome.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Bin" last="Cui">Bin Cui</name>
						<affiliation>Health Science Center, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences and Shanghai Second Medical University, 225 South Chong Qing Road, Shanghai 200025, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Shenyang Pharmaceutical University, 103 Wenhua Road, Shenyang 110016, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Haibing" last="Zhang">Haibing Zhang</name>
						<affiliation>Health Science Center, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences and Shanghai Second Medical University, 225 South Chong Qing Road, Shanghai 200025, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yongzhong" last="Lu">Yongzhong Lu</name>
						<affiliation>Qingdao Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital, Qingdao Medical College, Qingdao 266003, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Wei" last="Zhong">Wei Zhong</name>
						<affiliation>Health Science Center, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences and Shanghai Second Medical University, 225 South Chong Qing Road, Shanghai 200025, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Gang" last="Pei">Gang Pei</name>
						<affiliation>Health Science Center, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences and Shanghai Second Medical University, 225 South Chong Qing Road, Shanghai 200025, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Shenyang Pharmaceutical University, 103 Wenhua Road, Shenyang 110016, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Xiangyin" last="Kong">Xiangyin Kong</name>
						<affiliation>Health Science Center, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences and Shanghai Second Medical University, 225 South Chong Qing Road, Shanghai 200025, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Landian" last="Hu">Landian Hu</name>
						<affiliation>Health Science Center, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences and Shanghai Second Medical University, 225 South Chong Qing Road, Shanghai 200025, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>ldhu@sibs.ac.cn</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-11-20</date>
					<date type="R">2004-04-05</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Mitochondrial DNA sequence variation in the Anatolian Peninsula (Turkey)</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0039-0047</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Throughout human history, the region known today as the Anatolian peninsula (Turkey) has served as a junction connecting the Middle East, Europe and Central Asia, and, thus, has been subject to major population movements. The present study is undertaken to obtain information about the distribution of the existing mitochondrial D-loop sequence variations in the Turkish population of Anatolia. A few studies have previously reported mtDNA sequences in Turks. We attempted to extend these results by analysing a cohort that is not only larger, but also more representative of the Turkish population living in Anatolia. In order to obtain a descriptive picture for the phylogenetic distribution of the mitochondrial genome within Turkey, we analysed mitochondrial D-loop region sequence variations in 75 individuals from different parts of Anatolia by direct sequencing. Analysis of the two hypervariable segments within the noncoding region of the mitochondrial genome revealed the existence of 81 nucleotide mutations at 79 sites. The neighbour-joining tree of Kimura’s distance matrix has revealed the presence of six main clusters, of which H and U are the most common. The data obtained are also compared with several European and Turkic Central Asian populations.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>mtDNA;Anatolian peninsula;sequence variation;hypervariable segments;Turkish population.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Hatice" last="Mergen">Hatice Mergen</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Molecular Biology, Hacettepe University, 06532 Beytepe, Ankara, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Reyhan" last="Öner">Reyhan Öner</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Faculty of Science, Hacettepe University, 06532 Beytepe, Ankara, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Cihan" last="Öner">Cihan Öner</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Molecular Biology, Hacettepe University, 06532 Beytepe, Ankara, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email>coner@hacettepe.edu.tr</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-06-24</date>
					<date type="R">2003-11-04</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Deciphering diversity in populations of various linguistic and ethnic affiliations of different geographical regions of India: analysis based on 15 microsatellite markers</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0049-0063</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>The extent of genetic polymorphism at fifteen autosomal microsatellite markers in 54 ethnically, linguistically and geographically diverse human populations of India was studied to decipher intrapopulation diversity. The parameters used to quantify intrapopulation diversity were average allele diversity, average heterozygosity, allele range (base pairs), and number of alleles. Multilocus genotype frequencies calculated for selected populations were utilized for testing conformity with the assumption of Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium. The exact test values, after Bonferroni correction, showed significant deviation amongst Gowda (vWA, Penta E); Dhangar, Satnami and Gounder (D8S1179); Hmar (FGA); Kuki and Balti (vWA) groups. Relatively low number of alleles and allelic diversity (base-pairs size) had been observed in populations of central India as compared with southern and northern regions of the country. The communities of Indo-Caucasoid ethnic origin and Indo-European linguistic family (Kshatriya of Uttar Pradesh) showed highest allelic diversity, as well as rare alleles, not reported in any other Indian populations. Analysis based on average heterozygosity was also found to be lowest among the populations of central India (0.729) and highest among the populations from north (0.777) and west (0.784) regions of the country, having Indo-Caucasoid ethnic origin and Austro-Asiatic linguistic affiliation. The maximum power of discrimination (85\%–89\%) had been observed at loci FGA, Penta E, D18S51 and D21S11, suggested high intrapopulation diversity in India. Genetic diversity revealed by STR markers was consistent with the known demographic histories of populations. Thus, the present study clearly demonstrated that the intrapopulation diversity is not only present at the national level, but also within smaller geographical regions of the country. This is the first attempt to understand the extent of diversity within populations of India at such a large scale at genomic level.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>microsatellites;Indian populations;heterozygosity;power of discrimination;Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="V. K." last="Kashyap">V. K. Kashyap</name>
						<affiliation>DNA Typing Unit, Central Forensic Science Laboratory, 30 Gorachand Road, Kolkata 700 014, India</affiliation>
						<email>vkk2k@hotmail.com;dtubprd@giascl01.vsnl.net.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Richa" last="Ashma">Richa Ashma</name>
						<affiliation>DNA Typing Unit, Central Forensic Science Laboratory, 30 Gorachand Road, Kolkata 700 014, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sonali" last="Gaikwad">Sonali Gaikwad</name>
						<affiliation>DNA Typing Unit, Central Forensic Science Laboratory, 30 Gorachand Road, Kolkata 700 014, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. N." last="Sarkar">B. N. Sarkar</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropological Survey of India, 27 Jawaharlal Nehru Road, Kolkata 700 016, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R." last="Trivedi">R. Trivedi</name>
						<affiliation>DNA Typing Unit, Central Forensic Science Laboratory, 30 Gorachand Road, Kolkata 700 014, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2002-10-22</date>
					<date type="R">2003-11-19</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Allelic structure and distribution of 103 STR loci in a Southern Tunisian population</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0065-0071</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Genotypes of 103 short tandem repeat (STR) markers distributed at an average of 40 cM intervals throughout the genome were determined for 40 individuals from the village of BirEl Hfai (BEH). This village of approximately 31.000 individuals is localized in the south-west of Tunisia. The allele frequency distributions in BEH were compared with those obtained for individuals in the CEPH (Centre d’Etude du Polymorphisme Humain) data using a Kolmogorov–Smirnov two-sample test. Fourteen out of the 103 markers (13.2%) showed significant differences ($P\lt 0.05$) in distribution between the two populations. Population heterogeneity in BEH was indicated by an excess of observed homozygosity deviations from Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium at 3 loci ($P\lt 0.0005$). No evidence for genotypic disequilibrium was found for any of the marker pairs. This demonstrated that in spite of a high inbreeding level in the population, few markers showed evidence for a different pattern of allelic distribution compared to CEPH.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>microsatellite markers;polymorphism;allele frequency;population studies;disequilibrium.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Abdellatif" last="Maalej">Abdellatif Maalej</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratoire de Génétique Moléculaire Humaine, Faculté de Médecine, Avenue Majida Boulila, 3029 Sfax, Tunisia</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ahmed" last="Rebai">Ahmed Rebai</name>
						<affiliation>Unité de bio-informatique, Centre de Biotechnologie de Sfax, B.P. ‘K’, 3038 Sfax,Tunisia</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Adnen" last="Ayadi">Adnen Ayadi</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratoire de Génétique Moléculaire Humaine, Faculté de Médecine, Avenue Majida Boulila, 3029 Sfax, Tunisia</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jomaa" last="Jouida">Jomaa Jouida</name>
						<affiliation>Dispensaire de Bir ElHfai, Sidi Bouzid, Tunisia</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Hafedh" last="Makni">Hafedh Makni</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratoire de Génétique Moléculaire Humaine, Faculté de Médecine, Avenue Majida Boulila, 3029 Sfax, Tunisia</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Hammadi" last="Ayadi">Hammadi Ayadi</name>
						<affiliation>Laboratoire de Génétique Moléculaire Humaine, Faculté de Médecine, Avenue Majida Boulila, 3029 Sfax, Tunisia</affiliation>
						<email>hammadi.ayadi@fmsf.rnu.tn</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-06-09</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Circadian clocks and life-history related traits: is pupation height affected by circadian organization in <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>?</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0073-0077</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>In <i>D. melanogaster</i>, the observation of greater pupation height under constant darkness than under constant light has been explained by the hypothesis that light has an inhibitory effect on larval wandering behaviour, preventing larvae from crawling higher up the walls of culture vials prior to pupation. If this is the only role of light in affecting pupation height, then various light : dark regimes would be predicted to yield pupation heights intermediate between those seen in constant light and constant darkness. We tested this hypothesis by measuring pupation height under various light : dark regimes in four laboratory populations of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>. Pupation height was the greatest in constant darkness, intermediate in constant light, and the least in a light / dark regime of LD 14:14 h. The results clearly suggest that there is more to light regime effects on pupation height than mere behavioural inhibition of wandering larvae, and that circadian organization may play some role in determining pupation height, although the details of this role are not yet clear. We briefly discuss these results in the context of the possible involvement of circadian clocks in life-history evolution.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>pupation height;pupariation;life-history evolution;circadian clocks;circadian organization;<i>Drosophila melanogaster.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Dhanashree A." last="Paranjpe">Dhanashree A. Paranjpe</name>
						<affiliation>Chronobiology Laboratory, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D." last="Anitha">D. Anitha</name>
						<affiliation>Chronobiology Laboratory, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Vijay Kumar" last="Sharma">Vijay Kumar Sharma</name>
						<affiliation>Chronobiology Laboratory, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-09-26</date>
					<date type="R">2004-03-20</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Structural and functional analysis of rice genome</title>
				<feature>Review article</feature>
				<page>0079-0099</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Rice is an excellent system for plant genomics as it represents a modest size genome of 430 Mb. It feeds more than half the population of the world. Draft sequences of the rice genome, derived by whole-genome shotgun approach at relatively low coverage (4–6 X), were published and the International Rice Genome Sequencing Project (IRGSP) declared high quality ($\gt 10$ X), genetically anchored, phase 2 level sequence in 2002. In addition, phase 3 level finished sequence of chromosomes 1, 4 and 10 (out of 12 chromosomes of rice) has already been reported by scientists from IRGSP consortium. Various estimates of genes in rice place the number at $\gt 50,000$. Already, over 28,000 full-length cDNAs have been sequenced, most of which map to genetically anchored genome sequence. Such information is very useful in revealing novel features of macro- and micro-level synteny of rice genome with other cereals. Microarray analysis is unraveling the identity of rice genes expressing in temporal and spatial manner and should help target candidate genes useful for improving traits of agronomic importance. Simultaneously, functional analysis of rice genome has been initiated by marker-based characterization of useful genes and employing functional knock-outs created by mutation or gene tagging. Integration of this enormous information is expected to catalyze tremendous activity on basic and applied aspects of rice genomics.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>annotation;comparative genomics;functional genomics;genetic mapping;genome sequencing;physical mapping;rice.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Akhilesh K." last="Tyagi">Akhilesh K. Tyagi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email>akhilesh@genomeindia.org</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jitendra P." last="Khurana">Jitendra P. Khurana</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Paramjit" last="Khurana">Paramjit Khurana</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Saurabh" last="Raghuvanshi">Saurabh Raghuvanshi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Anupama" last="Gaur">Anupama Gaur</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Anita" last="Kapur">Anita Kapur</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Vikrant" last="Gupta">Vikrant Gupta</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Dibyendu" last="Kumar">Dibyendu Kumar</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="V." last="Ravi">V. Ravi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shubha" last="Vij">Shubha Vij</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Parul" last="Khurana">Parul Khurana</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sulabha" last="Sharma">Sulabha Sharma</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Plant Molecular Biology, University of Delhi South Campus, Benito Juarez Road, New Delhi 110 021, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>C. C. Li (1912–2003): his science and his spirit</title>
				<feature>Obituary</feature>
				<page>0101-0105</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Partha P." last="Majumder">Partha P. Majumder</name>
						<affiliation>Anthropology and Human Genetics Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, 203 B.T. Road, Kolkata 700 108, India</affiliation>
						<email>ppm@isical.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>John Maynard Smith (6 January 1920 – 19 April 2004)</title>
				<feature>Obituary</feature>
				<page>0107-0108</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary &amp; Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box. 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="08" year="2004">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Genetically engineered monogamy in voles lends credence to the <i>modus operandi</i> of behavioural ecology</title>
				<feature>Research Commentary</feature>
				<page>0109-0111</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>voles;monogamy;behavioural ecology;genetics of behaviour;vasopressin;<p>Microtus.</p></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Raghavendra" last="Gadagkar">Raghavendra Gadagkar</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Ecological Sciences, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, P.O. Box 6436, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ragh@ces.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Benefits of being biased!</title>
				<feature>Research Commentary</feature>
				<page>0113-0115</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>codon bias;alcohol dehydrogenase;Darwinian fitness;<i>Drosophila melanogaster.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Sutirth" last="Dey">Sutirth Dey</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary &amp; Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur P.O. Box 6436, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>dey@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Chance in our strands?</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0117-0119</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Quasar Saleem" last="Padiath">Quasar Saleem Padiath</name>
						<affiliation>Dept. of Neurology, University of California, 505 Parnassus Ave., Box 0114, San Francisco, Ca., 94143-0114, USA</affiliation>
						<email>qpadiath@itsa.ucsf.edu</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="B. Jagadeeshwara" last="Rao">B. Jagadeeshwara Rao</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, Mumbai 400 005, India</affiliation>
						<email>bjrao@tifr.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Sex determining signal in <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i></title>
				<feature>Commentary on <i>J. Genet.</i> Classic</feature>
				<page>0121-0123</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords><i>Drosophila</i>;sex determination;X/A ratio;Sex-lethal.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Anuranjan" last="Anand">Anuranjan Anand</name>
						<affiliation>Molecular Biology and Genetics Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P.O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>anand@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Distribution of Sex-Factors in the X-Chromosome of <i>Drosophila Melanogaster</i></title>
				<feature><i>J. Genet. classic</i></feature>
				<page>0125-0162</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Th." last="Dobzhansky">Th. Dobzhansky</name>
						<affiliation>W. G. Kerckhoff Laboratories of the Biological Sciences, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jack" last="Schultz">Jack Schultz</name>
						<affiliation>W. G. Kerckhoff Laboratories of the Biological Sciences, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Carnegie Institution of Washington</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>REML estimates of genetic parameters of sexual dimorphism for wing and thorax length in <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i></title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0163-0170</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Restricted maximum likelihood was used to estimate genetic parameters of male and female wing and thorax length in isofemale lines of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i>, and results compared to estimates obtained earlier with the classical analysis of variance approach. As parents within an isofemale line were unknown, a total of 500 parental pedigrees were simulated and mean estimates computed. Full and half sibs were distinguished, in contrast to usual isofemale studies in which animals were all treated as half sibs and hence heritability was overestimated. Heritability was thus estimated at 0.33, 0.38, 0.30 and 0.33 for male and female wing length and male and female thorax length, respectively, whereas corresponding estimates obtained using analysis of variance were 0.46, 0.54, 0.35 and 0.38. Genetic correlations between male and female traits were 0.85 and 0.62 for wing and thorax length, respectively. Sexual dimorphism and the ratio of female to male traits were moderately heritable (0.30 and 0.23 for wing length, 0.38 and 0.23 for thorax length). Both were moderately and positively correlated with female traits, and weakly and negatively correlated with male traits. Such heritabilities confirmed that sexual dimorphism might be a fast evolving trait in <i>Drosophila.</i></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>sexual dimorphism;genetic parameters;body size;restricted maximum likelihood (REML);<i>Drosophila.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Sandrine" last="Mignon-Grasteau"></name>
						<affiliation>Station de Recherches Avicoles, Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique, 37380 Nouzilly, France</affiliation>
						<email>grasteau@tours.inra.fr</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jean" last="David">Jean David</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Populations, Génétique et Evolution, 91198 Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Patricia" last="Gibert">Patricia Gibert</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Biométrie, Biologie Evolutive, Université de Lyon I, 69622 Villeurbanne Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Hélène" last="Legout">Hélène Legout</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Populations, Génétique et Evolution, 91198 Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Georges" last="Pétavy">Georges Pétavy</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Populations, Génétique et Evolution, 91198 Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Brigitte" last="Moreteau">Brigitte Moreteau</name>
						<affiliation>CNRS, Laboratoire Populations, Génétique et Evolution, 91198 Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Catherine" last="Beaumont">Catherine Beaumont</name>
						<affiliation>Station de Recherches Avicoles, Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique, 37380 Nouzilly, France</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-02-10</date>
					<date type="R">2004-06-25</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Genetic and genotype $\times$ environment interaction effects for the content of seven essential amino acids in <i>indica</i> rice</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0171-0178</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>It is necessary for rice breeders to understand the genetic basis of nutrient quality traits of rice. Essential amino acids are most important in determining the nutrient quality of rice grain and can affect the health of people who depend on rice as a staple food. In view of the paucity of genetic information available on essential amino acids in <i>indica</i> rice, we estimated the genetic main effects and genotype $\times$ environment (G $\times$ E) interaction effects on the content of essential amino acids. Nine cytoplasmic male sterile lines as females and five restorer lines as males were introduced in a North Carolina II design across environments. Estimates of the content of the essential amino acids valine, methionine, leucine and phenylalanine showed that they were mainly controlled by genetic main effects, while the contents of threonine, cysteine and isoleucine were mainly affected by G $\times$ E effects. In the case of genetic main effects, both cytoplasmic and maternal genetic effects were predominant for all essential amino acids, indicating that selection for improving essential amino acid content based on maternal performance would be more effective than that based on seeds. The total narrow-sense heritabilities were high and ranged from 0.72 to 0.83. Since general heritabilities for these essential amino acids (except for cysteine) were found to be much larger than G $\times$ E interaction heritability, the improvement of content of most essential amino acids under selection would be expected under various environments. Rice varieties such as Zhenan 3, Yinchao 1, T49, 26715, 102 and 1391 should be selected as optimal parents for increasing the content of most essential amino acids, while the total genetic effects from Zhexie 2, Xieqingzao, Gangchao 1, V20, Zuo 5 and Zhenshan 97 were mainly negative and these parents could decrease the contents of most essential amino acids.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>plant breeding;rice (<i>Oryza sativa</i> L.);nutrient quality;essential amino acid;genetic effect;genotype $\times$ environment interaction.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. G." last="Wu">J. G. Wu</name>
						<affiliation>Agronomy Department, College of Agriculture and Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310029, People's Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>jgwu@zju.edu.cn</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="C. H." last="Shi">C. H. Shi</name>
						<affiliation>Agronomy Department, College of Agriculture and Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310029, People's Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="X. M." last="Zhang">X. M. Zhang</name>
						<affiliation>Agronomy Department, College of Agriculture and Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310029, People's Republic of China</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Crop Research and Atomic Energy Utilization Institute, Zhejiang Academy of Agricultural Science, Hangzhou 310021, People's Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="T." last="Katsura">T. Katsura</name>
						<affiliation>Fukui Agricultural Experiment Station, Fukui 918-8215, Japan</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-02-02</date>
					<date type="R">2004-06-04</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Variation in the relative magnitude of intraspecific and interspecific competitive effects in novel versus familiar environments in two <p>Drosophila</p> species</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0179-0188</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Models of competitor coevolution, especially the genetic feedback hypothesis, suggest that a negative correlation between intraspecific and interspecific competitive effects may be important in sustaining competitor coexistence, and can give rise to oscillatory dynamics with repeated reversals of competitive superiority. I reanalyzed previously published census data from an experiment in which populations of <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> and <i>D. simulans</i> underwent competitive coevolution in one familiar and two novel environments, to specifically look for any evidence of a negative relationship between intraspecific and interspecific competitive effects on population growth rates, and for any indication of short period cycling in the relative magnitude of intraspecific and interspecific competitive effects. While there was considerable variation in the relative magnitude of intraspecific and interspecific competitive effects over generations, among both populations and environments, there was no clear evidence supporting the genetic feedback hypothesis. Intraspecific and interspecific competitive effects on population growth rates were strongly positively correlated in novel environments, and uncorrelated in the familiar environment. Data from the familiar environment indicated that indices of competition of populations of the initially superior competitor, <i>D. melanogaster</i>, might be showing some cyclic behaviour, but I argue that this is likely to be transient, and not suggestive of sustained oscillatory dynamics predicted by the genetic feedback model. I discuss the results in the context of the importance of the genetic architecture of intraspecific and interspecific competitive abilities in determining the coevolutionary trajectory of competitive interactions.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>intraspecific competition;interspecific competition;competitor coevolution;index of competition;competition coefficient;<i>Drosophila.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, P. O. Box 6436, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-07-04</date>
					<date type="R">2004-07-26</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Cytochrome P450c17$\alpha$ 5$'$-untranslated region *T/C polymorphism in endometriosis</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0189-0192</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Estrogen plays a role in the pathogenesis of endometriosis. The CYP17 gene codes for the cytochrome P450c17$\alpha$ enzyme that is involved in the estrogen biosynthesis. We aimed to investigate if CYP17 polymorphism could be used as marker to predict the susceptibility of endometriosis. Women were divided into two groups:</p>
					<ol type="arabic">
						<li>severe endometriosis (n=119);</li>
						<li>non-endometriosis groups (n=128).</li>
					</lo>
					<p>A 169-bp fragment encompassing the T/C polymorphic site in 5$'$-untranslated promoter region ($5'$-UTR) of the CYP17 was amplified by the polymerase chain reaction, treated with restriction enzyme MspA1I, and electrophoresis. The polymorphism was divided into restriction- enzyme indigestible (T homozygote), T/C heterozygote, and digestible (C homozygote). Genotypes and allelic frequencies for this polymorphism in both groups were compared. We observed a higher but non-significant percentage of T homozygote in the endometriosis women compared with the non-endometriosis women. Proportions of T homozygote/heterozygote/C homozygote for CYP17 in both groups were:</p>
					<ol type="arabic">
						<li>26.1/46.2/27.7\%\ and</li> 
						<li>17.2/45.3/37.5\%\ (p- value=0.131).</li>
					</ol>
					<p>T allele was related with higher susceptibility of endometriosis. T and C allele frequencies in both groups were:</p>
					<ol type="arabic">
						<li>49.2/50.8\%;</li>
						<li>39.8/60.2\% (p- value=0.046).</li>
					</ol>
					<p>Despite the CYP17* T allele appearing to be asscoiatd with a trend of increased risk of endometriosis, CYP17 $5'$-UTR gene polymorphism might not be a useful marker for prediction of endometriosis susceptibility.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>cytochrome P450c17 CYP17;endometriosis;single nucleotide polymorphism.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Yao-Yuan" last="Hsieh">Yao-Yuan Hsieh</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, China Medical University Hospital, No.2 Yuh-Der Road, Taichung, Taiwan</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Biological Science and Technology, National Chiao Tung University, Hsinchu, Taiwan</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Chi-Chen" last="Chang">Chi-Chen Chang</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, China Medical University Hospital, No.2 Yuh-Der Road, Taichung, Taiwan</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Fuu-Jen" last="Tsai">Fuu-Jen Tsai</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Pediatrics and Medical Genetics, China Medical University Hospital, No.2 Yuh-Der Road, Taichung, Taiwan</affiliation>
						<email>d0704@www.cmuh.org.tw</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Cheng-Chieh" last="Lin">Cheng-Chieh Lin</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Family Medicine, China Medical University Hospital, Taichung, Taiwan</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Chang-Hai" last="Tsai">Chang-Hai Tsai</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Pediatrics and Medical Genetics, China Medical University Hospital, No.2 Yuh-Der Road, Taichung, Taiwan</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Taichung Health Care and Management University, Taichung, Taiwan</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-07-14</date>
					<date type="R">2004-07-05</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>PCR-based detection of allergenic mackerel ingredients in seafood</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0193-0195</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Scomber mackerel;allergy;seafood;PCR;genus identification.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Futoshi" last="Aranishi">Futoshi Aranishi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, Miyazaki University, Miyazaki 889-2192, Japan</affiliation>
						<email>aranishi@cc.miyazaki-u.ac.jp</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Takane" last="Okimoto">Takane Okimoto</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, Miyazaki University, Miyazaki 889-2192, Japan</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Graduate School of Science and Technology, Nagasaki University, Nagasaki 852-8521, Japan</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-05-06</date>
					<date type="R">2004-05-17</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Short tandem repeat (STR) polymorphisms in Turkish population</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0197-0199</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>forensic science;population genetics;short tandem repeat;polymorphism;human genetics;Turkey.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Üner" last="Ülküer">Üner Ülküer</name>
						<affiliation>General Directory of Security, Criminal Police Laboratories, Biyoloji Bölümü, Aniteppe, Ankara, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email>unerulkuer@hotmail.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Melahat" last="Kurtuluş-Ülküer">Melahat Kurtuluş-Ülküer</name>
						<affiliation>Gazi University, Kirşehir Education Faculty, Kirşehir, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Cüneyt" last="Elma">Cüneyt Elma</name>
						<affiliation>General Directory of Security, Criminal Police Laboratories, Biyoloji Bölümü, Aniteppe, Ankara, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Tahsin" last="Kesici">Tahsin Kesici</name>
						<affiliation>Ankara University, Faculty of Agriculture, Biometry-Genetics Unit, Ankara, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Sevda" last="Menevşe">Sevda Menevşe</name>
						<affiliation>Gazi University, Faculty of Medicine, Department of Medical Biology and Genetics, Ankara, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2003-06-26</date>
					<date type="R">2004-04-30</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>From fruit flies to fallout: Ed Lewis and his science</title>
				<feature>Special Feature</feature>
				<page>0201-0218</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Howard D." last="Lipshitz">Howard D. Lipshitz</name>
						<affiliation>Program in Developmental Biology, Research Institute, The Hospital for Sick Children, Department of Molecular and Medical Genetics, University of Toronto, 555 University Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M5G 1X8, Canada</affiliation>
						<email>lipshitz@sickkids.ca</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Edward B Lewis (1918–2004)</title>
				<feature>Obituary</feature>
				<page>0219-0219</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="L. S." last="Shashidhara">L. S. Shashidhara</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Hyderabad, 500 007, India</affiliation>
						<email>shashi@ccmb.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Francis Crick (1916–2004)</title>
				<feature>Obituary</feature>
				<page>0221-0221</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Graeme" last="Mitchison">Graeme Mitchison</name>
						<affiliation>MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Hills Road, Cambridge, CB2 2QH, UK</affiliation>
						<email>gjm@mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="12" year="2004">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Discrimination in partnership: compartment-specific interactions of Hox proteins</title>
				<feature>Research Commentary</feature>
				<page>0223-0226</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>Hox proteins;segmentation genes;<i>cis</i>-elements;binding domain;repressor;gene regulation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="K. G." last="Guruharsha">K. G. Guruharsha</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Biological Sciences, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, GKVK PO, Bangalore 560 065, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Department of Studies in Zoology, University of Mysore, Manasagangotri, Mysore 570 006, India</affiliation>
						<email>gharsha@ncbs.res.in</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="K." last="Vijayraghavan">K. Vijayraghavan</name>
						<affiliation>National Centre for Biological Sciences, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, GKVK PO, Bangalore 560 065, India</affiliation>
						<email>vijay@ncbs.res.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Brain clocks for morning and evening behaviour</title>
				<feature>Research Commentary</feature>
				<page>0227-0230</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>circadian;locomotor activity;morning and evening oscillators;<i>Drosophila.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Vijay Kumar" last="Sharma">Vijay Kumar Sharma</name>
						<affiliation>Chronobiology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>vsharma@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Haldane and the first estimates of the human mutation rate</title>
				<feature>Commentary on <i>J. Genet.</i> Classic</feature>
				<page>0231-0233</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>mutation;haemophilia;mutation–selection balance.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Michael W." last="Nachman">Michael W. Nachman</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, P.O. Box 210088, Biosciences West Bldg, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85721, USA</affiliation>
						<email>nachman@u.arizona.edu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>The Rate of Spontaneous Mutation of a Human Gene.</title>
				<feature><i>J. Gent. classic</i></feature>
				<page>0235-0244</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. B. S." last="Haldane">J. B. S. Haldane</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>DNA marker mining of ILSTS035 microsatellite locus on chromosome 6 of Hanwoo cattle</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0245-0250</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We describe tests for detecting and locating quantitative trait loci (QTL) for traits in Hanwoo cattle. From results of a permutation test to detect QTL for marbling, we selected the microsatellite locus ILSTS035 on chromosome 6 for further analysis. $K$-means clustering analysis applied to five traits and nine DNA markers in ILSTS035 resulted in three cluster groups. Finally we employed the bootstrap test method to calculate confidence intervals using the resampling method to find major DNA markers. We conclude that the major markers of ILSTS035 locus on chromosome 6 of Hanwoo cattle are markers 235 bp and 266 bp.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>LOD score;QTL;permutation test;$K$-means clustering;bootstrap method.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Jung-Sou" last="Yeo">Jung-Sou Yeo</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Animal Science, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongbuk 712-749, Korea</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Institute of Biotechnology, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongbuk 712-749, Korea</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jea-Young" last="Lee">Jea-Young Lee</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Statistics, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongbuk 712-749, Korea</affiliation>
						<email>jlee@yu.ac.kr</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Jae-Woo" last="Kim">Jae-Woo Kim</name>
						<affiliation>Institute of Biotechnology, Yeungnam University, Gyeongsan, Gyeongbuk 712-749, Korea</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-04-30</date>
					<date type="R">2004-10-04</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Excess of counterclockwise scalp hair-whorl rotation in homosexual men</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0251-0255</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>While most men prefer women as their sexual partners, some are bisexual and others are homosexuals. It has been debated for a long time whether a person’s sexual preference is innate, learned, or due to a combination of both causes. It was recently discovered that the human right-versus-left-hand use preference and the direction of scalp hair-whorl rotation develop from a common genetic mechanism. Such a mechanism controls functional specialization of brain hemispheres. Whether the same mechanism specifying mental makeup influences sexual preference was determined here by comparing hair-whorl rotation in groups enriched with homosexual men with that in males at large. Only a minority of 8.2\%\ ($n = 207$) unselected ‘control’ group of males had counterclockwise rotation. In contrast, all three samples enriched with homosexual men exhibited highly significant ($P \lt 0.0001$), 3.6-fold excess (29.8\%, $n = 272$) counterclockwise rotation. These results suggest that sexual preference may be influenced in a significant proportion of homosexual men by a biological/genetic factor that also controls direction of hair-whorl rotation.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>sexual orientation;homosexuality;human behaviour;hair-whorl orientation;behaviour biology.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amar J. S." last="Klar">Amar J. S. Klar</name>
						<affiliation>Ijamsville, MD 21754, USA</affiliation>
						<email>amar.klar@gmail.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-08-02</date>
					<date type="R">2004-09-30</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Cloning of a novel gene, <i>Cymg1</i>, related to family 2 cystatins and expressed at specific stages of mouse testis development</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0257-0263</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>We have cloned a novel gene, <i>Cymg1</i> (GenBank accession number AY600990), from a mouse testis cDNA library. <i>Cymg1</i> is located in 2G3 of mouse chromosome 2. The cDNA includes an open reading frame that encodes 141 amino acid residues. The encoded polypeptide has a cysteine protease inhibitor domain found in the family 2 cystatins but lacks critical consensus sites important for cysteine protease inhibition. These characteristics are seen in the proteins of the CRES subfamily of the family 2 cystatins which are expressed specifically in the reproductive tract. CYMG1 protein shows 44\%\ identity with mouse CRES and 30\%\ identity with mouse cystatin C. Northern blot analysis showed that the <i>Cymg1</i> gene was specifically expressed in adult mouse testis. RT-PCR also showed that <i>Cymg1</i> was expressed in testis and spermatogonial cells. <i>Cymg1</i> expression level varied in the different developmental stages of mouse testis, and were coincidental with spermatogenesis and sex maturation. These results indicate that <i>Cymg1</i> may play important roles in mouse spermatogenesis and sex maturation</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>cystatins;gene cloning;testis;spermatogenesis;sex maturation.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Y." last="Xiang">Y. Xiang</name>
						<affiliation>Human Reproductive and Stem Cell Engineering Institute, Central South University, Changsha 410078, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D. S." last="Nie">D. S. Nie</name>
						<affiliation>Human Reproductive and Stem Cell Engineering Institute, Central South University, Changsha 410078, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="G. X." last="Lu">G. X. Lu</name>
						<affiliation>Human Reproductive and Stem Cell Engineering Institute, Central South University, Changsha 410078, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>lgxdirector@sina.com.cn;lgxdirector@yahoo.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-08-27</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Quantitative genetics of functional characters in <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> populations subjected to laboratory selection</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0265-0277</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>What are the genetics of phenotypes other than fitness, in outbred populations? To answer this question, the quantitative-genetic basis of divergence was characterized for outbred <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> populations that had previously undergone selection to enhance characters related to fitness. Line-cross analysis using first-generation and second-generation hybrids from reciprocal crosses was conducted for two types of cross, each replicated fivefold. One type of cross was between representatives of the ancestral population, a set of five populations maintained for several hundred generations on a two-week discrete-generation life cycle and a set of five populations adapted to starvation stress. The other type of cross was between the same set of ancestral-representative populations and another set of five populations selected for accelerated development from egg to egg. Developmental time from egg to eclosion, starvation resistance, dry body weight and fecundity at day 14 from egg were fit to regression models estimating single-locus additive and dominant effects, maternal and paternal effects, and digenic additive and dominance epistatic effects. Additive genetic variation explained most of the differences between populations, with additive maternal and cytoplasmic effects also commonly found. Both within-locus and between-locus dominance effects were inferred in some cases, as well as one instance of additive epistasis. Some of these effects may have been caused by linkage disequilibrium. We conclude with a brief discussion concerning the relationship of the genetics of population differentiation to adaptation.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>line-cross analysis;epistasis;dominance;adaptation;experimental evolution;reverse evolution;life-history evolution;quantitative genetics;<i>Drosophila.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Henrique" last="Teotónio">Henrique Teotónio</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Present address: Centro de Biologia do Desenvolvimento, Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência, Rua da Quinta Grande 6, 2780-156 Oeiras, Portugal</affiliation>
						<email>teotonio@igc.gulbenkian.pt</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Margarida" last="Matos">Margarida Matos</name>
						<affiliation>Centro de Biologia Ambiental, Dep. Biologia Animal, Faculdade de Ciências da Universidade de Lisboa, 1749-016 Campo Grande Lisboa, Portugal</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Michael R." last="Rose">Michael R. Rose</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Irvine, CA 92697-2525, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-10-11</date>
					<date type="R">2004-11-02</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Abnormal pollen mitoses (PM I and PM II) in an interspecific hybrid of <i>Brachiaria ruziziensis</i> and <i>Brachiaria decumbens</i> (Gramineae)</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0279-0283</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords><i>Brachiaria decumbens</i>;<i>Brachiaria ruziziensis</i>;interspecific hybrid;pollen mitosis;pollen sterility.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Andréa Beatriz" last="Mendes-Bonato">Andréa Beatriz Mendes-Bonato</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Cell Biology and Genetics, State University of Maringá, 87020-900 Maringá PR, Brazil</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Maria Suely" last="Pagliarini">Maria Suely Pagliarini</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Cell Biology and Genetics, State University of Maringá, 87020-900 Maringá PR, Brazil</affiliation>
						<email>mspagliarini@uem.br</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Cacilda Borges Do" last="Valle">Cacilda Borges Do Valle</name>
						<affiliation>Embrapa Beef Cattle, P.O. Box 154, 79002-970 Campo Grande MS, Brazil</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Liana" last="Jank">Liana Jank</name>
						<affiliation>Embrapa Beef Cattle, P.O. Box 154, 79002-970 Campo Grande MS, Brazil</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-04-08</date>
					<date type="R">2004-10-06</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0285-0289</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords><p>Klebsiella</p>;$\beta$-glucosides;EMS mutagenesis;phenyl $\beta$-D-glucopyranoside.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Tirumalai R." last="Raghunand">Tirumalai R. Raghunand</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Molecular Reproduction, Development and Genetics, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Center for TB Research, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, 1503 E Jefferson Street, Baltimore, MD 21231-1001, USA</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Mahadevan">S. Mahadevan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Molecular Reproduction, Development and Genetics, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation>
						<email>mahi@mrdg.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-07-18</date>
					<date type="R">2004-10-05</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Genetic characterization of Indian Spiti horses</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0291-0295</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>microsatellite;genetic variability;Spiti horse.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Mamta" last="Chauhan">Mamta Chauhan</name>
						<affiliation>National Research Centre on Equines, Sirsa Road, Hisar 125 001, India</affiliation>
						<email>mamtachauhan@scientist.com</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. K." last="Gupta">A. K. Gupta</name>
						<affiliation>National Research Centre on Equines, Sirsa Road, Hisar 125 001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Dhillon">S. Dhillon</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Chaudhary Charan Singh Haryana Agriculture University, Hisar 125 001, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-09-13</date>
					<date type="R">2004-10-27</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="084">
		<issue inum="01" month="04" year="2005">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Editorial</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0001-0001</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>A family tree in every gene</title>
				<feature>Invited Editorial</feature>
				<page>0003-0006</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Armand Marie" last="Leroi">Armand Marie Leroi</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Strategic analysis in evolutionary genetics and the theory of games</title>
				<feature>Perspectives</feature>
				<page>0007-0012</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>John Maynard Smith;game theory;evolutionarily stable strategy;population genetics;genetic constraint;phenotypic evolution.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Peter" last="Hammerstein">Peter Hammerstein</name>
						<affiliation>Institute for Theoretical Biology, Humboldt University Berlin, Invalidenstrasse 43, D-10115 Berlin, Germany</affiliation>
						<email>p.hammerstein@biologie.hu-berlin.de</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Inbreeding and sex: canalization, plasticity and sexual selection</title>
				<feature>Commentary on <i>J. Genet.</i> Classic</feature>
				<page>0013-0015</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>canalization;adaptive plasticity;inbreeding;courtship;fertility;fecundity;mate choice;<i>Drosophila subobscura.</i></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Fertility, Mating Behaviour and Sexual Selection in <i>Drosophila Subobscura</i></title>
				<feature><i>J. Genet. classic</i></feature>
				<page>0017-0035</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. Maynard" last="Smith">J. Maynard Smith</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Zoology, University College London</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Acclimatization to High Temperatures in Inbred and Outbred <i>Drosophila Subobscura</i></title>
				<feature><i>J. Genet. classic</i></feature>
				<page>0037-0045</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. Maynard" last="Smith"></name>
						<affiliation>Department of Zoology, University College London</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Coincident natural selection of CCR5$\Delta$32 and C282Y in Europe: to be or not to be?</title>
				<feature>Hypothesis</feature>
				<page>0047-0048</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>CCR5$\Delta$32;C282Y;natural selection;Black Death;plague.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Marjan" last="Gharagozloo">Marjan Gharagozloo</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Immunology, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, P.O. Box 71345 1798, Shiraz, Iran</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Abbas" last="Ghaderi">Abbas Ghaderi</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Immunology, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, P.O. Box 71345 1798, Shiraz, Iran</affiliation>
						<email>gharagozlo@sums.ac.ir;ghaderia@sums.ac.ir</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-11-30</date>
					<date type="R">2005-02-09</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Exact Tandem Repeats Analyzer (E-TRA): A new program for DNA sequence mining</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0049-0054</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Exact Tandem Repeats Analyzer 1.0 (E-TRA) combines sequence motif searches with keywords such as ‘organs’, ‘tissues’, ‘cell lines’ and ‘development stages’ for finding simple exact tandem repeats as well as non-simple repeats. E-TRA has several advanced repeat search parameters/options compared to other repeat finder programs as it not only accepts GenBank, FASTA and expressed sequence tags (EST) sequence files, but also does analysis of multiple files with multiple sequences. The minimum and maximum tandem repeat motif lengths that E-TRA finds vary from one to one thousand. Advanced user defined parameters/options let the researchers use different minimum motif repeats search criteria for varying motif lengths simultaneously. One of the most interesting features of genomes is the presence of relatively short tandem repeats (TRs). These repeated DNA sequences are found in both prokaryotes and eukaryotes, distributed almost at random throughout the genome. Some of the tandem repeats play important roles in the regulation of gene expression whereas others do not have any known biological function as yet. Nevertheless, they have proven to be very beneficial in DNA profiling and genetic linkage analysis studies. To demonstrate the use of E-TRA, we used 5,465,605 human EST sequences derived from 18,814,550 GenBank EST sequences. Our results indicated that 12.44\%\ (679,800) of the human EST sequences contained simple and non-simple repeat string patterns varying from one to 126 nucleotides in length. The results also revealed that human organs, tissues, cell lines and different developmental stages differed in number of repeats as well as repeat composition, indicating that the distribution of expressed tandem repeats among tissues or organs are not random, thus differing from the un-transcribed repeats found in genomes.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>expressed sequence tag (EST);motifs;simple sequence repeats (SSR);bioinformatics;Exact Tandem Repeats Analyzer.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Mehmet" last="Karaca">Mehmet Karaca</name>
						<affiliation>Akdeniz University, Faculty of Agriculture, 07059 Antalya, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email>mkaraca@akdeniz.edu.tr</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Mehmet" last="Bilgen">Mehmet Bilgen</name>
						<affiliation>Akdeniz University, Faculty of Agriculture, 07059 Antalya, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="A. Naci" last="Onus">A. Naci Onus</name>
						<affiliation>Akdeniz University, Faculty of Agriculture, 07059 Antalya, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Ayse Gul" last="Ince">Ayse Gul Ince</name>
						<affiliation>Akdeniz University, Faculty of Agriculture, 07059 Antalya, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Safinaz Y." last="Elmasulu">Safinaz Y. Elmasulu</name>
						<affiliation>Akdeniz University, Faculty of Agriculture, 07059 Antalya, Turkey</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-09-25</date>
					<date type="R">2005-01-12</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Comparative studies on codon usage pattern of chloroplasts and their host nuclear genes in four plant species</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0055-0062</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>A detailed comparison was made of codon usage of chloroplast genes with their host (nuclear) genes in the four angiosperm species <i>Oryza sativa, Zea mays, Triticum aestivum</i> and <i>Arabidopsis thaliana</i>. The average GC content of the entire genes, and at the three codon positions individually, was higher in nuclear than in chloroplast genes, suggesting different genomic organization and mutation pressures in nuclear and chloroplast genes. The results of Nc-plots and neutrality plots suggested that nucleotide compositional constraint had a large contribution to codon usage bias of nuclear genes in <i>O. sativa, Z. mays,</i> and <i>T. aestivum</i>, whereas natural selection was likely to be playing a large role in codon usage bias in chloroplast genomes. Correspondence analysis and chi-test showed that regardless of the genomic environment (species) of the host, the codon usage pattern of chloroplast genes differed from nuclear genes of their host species by their AU-richness. All the chloroplast genomes have predominantly A- and/or U-ending codons, whereas nuclear genomes have G-, C- or U-ending codons as their optimal codons. These findings suggest that the chloroplast genome might display particular characteristics of codon usage that are different from its host nuclear genome. However, one feature common to both chloroplast and nuclear genomes in this study was that pyrimidines were found more frequently than purines at the synonymous codon position of optimal codons.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords>codon usage;bioinformatics;chloroplast;plant;genome.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Qingpo" last="Liu">Qingpo Liu</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Agronomy, College of Agriculture and Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, 310 029, Hangzhou, China</affiliation>
						<email>liuqp@genomics.org.cn</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Qingzhong" last="Xue">Qingzhong Xue</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Agronomy, College of Agriculture and Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, 310 029, Hangzhou, China</affiliation>
						<email>qzhxue@hotmail.com</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-09-06</date>
					<date type="R">2005-01-11</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Mutational analysis of the <i>BRCA1</i> gene in 30 Czech ovarian cancer patients</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0063-0067</page>
				<abstract>
					<p>Ovarian cancer is one of the most severe of oncological diseases. Inherited mutations in cancer susceptibility genes play a causal role in 5–10\%\ of newly diagnosed tumours. <i>BRCA1</i> and <i>BRCA2</i> gene alterations are found in the majority of these cases. The aim of this study was to analyse the <i>BRCA1</i> gene in the ovarian cancer risk group to characterize the spectrum of its mutations in the Czech Republic. Five overlapping fragments amplified on both genomic DNA and cDNA were used to screen for the whole protein-coding sequence of the <i>BRCA1</i> gene. These fragments were analysed by the protein truncation test (PTT) and direct sequencing. Three inactivating mutations were identified in the group of 30 Czech ovarian cancer patients: the 5382insC mutation in two unrelated patients and a deletion of exons 21 and 22 in another patient. In addition, we have found an alternatively spliced product lacking exon 5 in two other unrelated patients. The 5382insC is the most frequent alteration of the <i>BRCA1</i> gene in Central and Eastern Europe. The deletion of exons 21 and 22 affects the BRCT functional domain of the BRCA1 protein. Although large genomic rearragements are known to be relatively frequent in Western European populations, no analyses have been performed in our region yet.</p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords><i>BRCA1</i> gene;ovarian cancer;mutational analysis;protein truncation test;direct sequencing.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Zikan">M. Zikan</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Experimental Oncology, 1st Faculty of Medicine, Charles University, U Nemocnice 5, 12853 Prague 2, Czech Republic</affiliation>
						<email>michal.zikan@lf1.cuni.cz</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="P." last="Pohlreich">P. Pohlreich</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Experimental Oncology, 1st Faculty of Medicine, Charles University, U Nemocnice 5, 12853 Prague 2, Czech Republic</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="J." last="Stribrna">J. Stribrna</name>
						<affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Experimental Oncology, 1st Faculty of Medicine, Charles University, U Nemocnice 5, 12853 Prague 2, Czech Republic</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-02-20</date>
					<date type="R">2004-12-17</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title><i>JP-3</i> gene polymorphism in a healthy population of Serbia and Montenegro</title>
				<feature>Research Article</feature>
				<page>0069-0071</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>junctophilin-3;polymorphism;HD-like phenotype;DNA analyses.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="M." last="Keckarević">M. Keckarević</name>
						<affiliation>Faculty of Biology, University of Belgrade, Studentski trg 16, P.O. Box 52, Belgrade 11000, Serbia and Montenegro</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="D." last="Savić">D. Savić</name>
						<affiliation>Faculty of Biology, University of Belgrade, Studentski trg 16, P.O. Box 52, Belgrade 11000, Serbia and Montenegro</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S." last="Romac">S. Romac</name>
						<affiliation>Faculty of Biology, University of Belgrade, Studentski trg 16, P.O. Box 52, Belgrade 11000, Serbia and Montenegro</affiliation>
						<email>stanka@bf.bio.bg.ac.yu</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-03-08</date>
					<date type="R">2004-12-09</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Chromosomal localization of autosomal mutations in <i>Drosophila nasuta nasuta</i> and <i>Drosophila nasuta albomicans</i></title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0073-0076</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords><i>Drosophila nasuta nasuta</i>;<i>D. n. albomicans</i>;autosomal mutations;chromosomal localization.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. S." last="Ashadevi">J. S. Ashadevi</name>
						<affiliation>Drosophila Stock Centre, Department of Studies in Zoology, University of Mysore, Manasagangotri, Mysore 570 006, India</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="S. R." last="Ramesh">S. R. Ramesh</name>
						<affiliation>Drosophila Stock Centre, Department of Studies in Zoology, University of Mysore, Manasagangotri, Mysore 570 006, India</affiliation>
						<email>srramesh2000@yahoo.com;srramesh54@rediffmail.com.</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="W.-E." last="Kalisch">W.-E. Kalisch</name>
						<affiliation>Institut für Genetik, Ruhr Universität Bochum, D-44780 Bochum 1, Germany</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-07-12</date>
					<date type="R">2005-01-03</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Genetic diversity analysis of five cattle breeds native to China using microsatellites</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0077-0080</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords>China native cattle;genetic diversity;microsatellite markers;population genetics.</keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Guo Li" last="Zhou">Guo Li Zhou</name>
						<affiliation>College of life Science, Liaocheng University, Liaocheng 252 059, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email>glzhou@lctu.edu.cn</email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Hai Guo" last="Jin">Hai Guo Jin</name>
						<affiliation>Branch of Animal Husbandry, Jilin Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Gongzhuling 136 100, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Qi" last="Zhu">Qi Zhu</name>
						<affiliation>College of life Science, Liaocheng University, Liaocheng 252 059, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Shan Li" last="Guo">Shan Li Guo</name>
						<affiliation>College of life Science, Liaocheng University, Liaocheng 252 059, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="Yu Hou" last="Wu">Yu Hou Wu</name>
						<affiliation>College of life Science, Liaocheng University, Liaocheng 252 059, People’s Republic of China</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-12-07</date>
					<date type="R">2005-01-05</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Orchid flower evolution</title>
				<feature>Research Note</feature>
				<page>0081-0084</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="J. D." last="Rajkumari">J. D. Rajkumari</name>
						<affiliation>AVRC, Manipur University, Canchipur 795 003, Manipur</affiliation>
						<affiliation>Life Sciences Department, Manipur University, Canchipur 795 003, Manipur</affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
					<author>
						<name first="R. S." last="Longjam">R. S. Longjam</name>
						<affiliation>AVRC, Manipur University, Canchipur 795 003, Manipur</affiliation>
						<email>rslongj@sancharnet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2004-10-20</date>
					<date type="R">2004-12-29</date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Hampton Lawrence Carson (5 November 1914 – 13 December 2004)</title>
				<feature>Obituary</feature>
				<page>0085-0086</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Amitabh" last="Joshi">Amitabh Joshi</name>
						<affiliation>Evolutionary Biology Laboratory, Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India.</affiliation>
						<email>ajoshi@jncasr.ac.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Ernst Mayr (1904–2005)</title>
				<feature>Obituary</feature>
				<page>0087-0089</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Raghavendra" last="Gadagkar">Raghavendra Gadagkar</name>
						<affiliation>Centre for Ecological Sciences, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 560 012, India</affiliation> 
						<affiliation>Evolutionary and Organismal Biology Unit, Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Jakkur, Bangalore 560 064, India.</affiliation>
						<email>ragh@ces.iisc.ernet.in</email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>80 years of watching the evolutionary scenery</title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0091-0093</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="Ernst" last="Mayr">Ernst Mayr</name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title>Erratum</title>
				<feature>Erratum</feature>
				<page>0094-0094</page>
				<abstract />
				<keywords />
				<authors />
				<dates>
					<date type="M"></date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="02" month="08" year="2005">%raghu, vol 84
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0000-0000</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-00-00</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
		<issue inum="03" month="12" year="2005">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0000-0000</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-00-00</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
	<volume vnum="085">
		<issue inum="00" month="00" year="2000">
			<entry hassup="0">
				<title></title>
				<feature></feature>
				<page>0000-0000</page>
				<abstract>
					<p></p>
				</abstract>
				<keywords></keywords>
				<authors>
					<author>
						<name first="" last=""></name>
						<affiliation></affiliation>
						<email></email>
					</author>
				</authors>
				<dates>
					<date type="M">2000-00-00</date>
					<date type="R"></date>
					<date type="A"></date>
					<date type="E"></date>
				</dates>
			</entry>
		</issue>
	</volume>
</journal>
